<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27i15a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, September 15, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27i15a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003, 2014</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, September 15, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-09-15</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27i15aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1727-09-15"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27i15a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, September 15, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Liverpool merchant John Pemberton, September 15, 1727, to inform him that he is unable to handle the sale of the slaves on Pemberton's ship, the <hi rend="italics">Leopard,</hi> because the terms Pemberton has set forth are too rigid. The captain apparently has arranged with John Tayloe to handle the sale. He reports the arrival of the governor and the proclamation of King George II, and that he is assisting Captain Christian of the <hi rend="italics">Rose</hi> in the sale of his cargo of slaves. Captain Denton of  the <hi rend="italics">John and Betty</hi> sold a slave to a man named Killby whom Carter is sure will not be able to pay and he expects Denton to reimburse him.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="JP">John Pemberton</note>, September 15, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Added to Mr. Pemberton's last Letter<lb/><lb/>
&mdash;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-09-15">Sepr. the 15th. 1727</date><lb/>

</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>



<p>After <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Hayes in the <name type="ship">Leopard</name> had bin in York <lb/>river to meet with <note target="n1">Mr. Nelson</note> who is <sic corr="gone">gon</sic> for England and find<lb/>ing no Orders for him there he came into <note target="n2">this rive</note>r to me, up<lb/>on Seeing the Strictness of your Orders I told him I could not meddle <lb/>with his Slaves it being impossible in my Esteem at this Season <lb/>of the Year to bring them out at your Peremptory <sic corr="terms">termes</sic> so I <lb/>let him go he immedately goes up the river to <note target="n3">Colonel Tayloe</note> wt. <lb/><sic corr="their">there</sic> Agreement may be I dont yet know the Ship is <sic corr="gone">gon</sic> up <lb/>the Bay to <note target="n4">Petuckson</note> and Tayloe meets her there;</p>

<p>Our <note n="WG"><abbr expan="Governor">Govr:</abbr></note> arrived into James river the 7th <abbr expan="Instant">Instt:</abbr> <lb/>I went from home to wait upon him the 9th: the 11th the <note target="n5">King</note> <lb/>was <sic corr="proclaimed">proclaimd</sic> I got home last night at one <sic corr="o'clock">a Clock</sic> <note target="n6"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> <lb/>Christain</note> came about from York into this river the 10th: is now <lb/>in <note target="n7">Corotoman</note> and I am going aboard him I shall do you the <lb/>best Service I can in the Sale of the Slaves but I fear that will not <lb/>be very good I <add resp="editor">[do not]</add> doubt I must <add resp="editor">[be]</add> forced to Stay for a great many bills <lb/><sic corr="until April">till Aprill</sic> and Cash I am afraid will be very plenty the ship <lb/>I am in hopes <sic corr="we">wee</sic> may get a freight for the number of the Slaves <lb/>are One hundred and Nineteen, of these but 38 men the rest women <lb/>and a great many boys and Girls,</p>

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
	<p>The three Sick Slaves I <sic corr="fetched">fetch'd</sic> home immediately <lb/>after <note target="n8"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Dentons</note> sailing and took the best care of them I could <lb/>one of them is Since Dead of whom I had hopes to make the most <lb/>money,</p>

<p>One morning in my Absence before I got aboard <lb/>the Ship <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Denton Sells a woman to one Killby an Acquain<lb/>tance of his, for &pound;20. &pound;17 a bill of Exchange on <note target="n9">Mr. Stark</note> of Glasgow <lb/>and takes a <sic corr="note">noat</sic> of him for &pound;3 to be paid in Cash in my name <lb/>he is a sort of a <note target="n10">Pilate</note> <sic corr="has">hath</sic> bin Several times by my house <lb/>but <sic corr="has">hath</sic> not yet brought me his money and his bills I am told <lb/>are not worth a <note target="n10">groat,</note> I shall Expect Mr. Denton Shall make good <lb/>this loss to me pray be Expeditious in returning me the protests <lb/>Particularly this rascals for I Expect no other but to See it again <lb/>I have time to add no more but that I am</p> 

<closer>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sir<lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Yor: very hum<add place="supralinear">ble</add> Servt:&mdash;</closer>




</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>Although this letter is headed in the letter book, "Added to Mr. Pemberton's last Letter," it has not been possible to determine which letter Carter meant. The last letter to Pemberton of which the editor has a copy was August 23,  1727, and is marked "per the Carter." According to Carter's diary, the <hi rend="italics">Carter</hi> sailed the next day. Accordingly, this letter must stand alone.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Thomas Nelson (1667-1745), a resident of Yorktown, was a merchant and was sheriff of York County in 1722 and 1723. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:12,34,184;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B30">Greene. <title>The Diary of Colonel Landon Carter. . . .</title>, p. 96.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] The Rappahannock</note>

<note id="n3">[3] John Tayloe (1687-1747) of Mt. Airy, Richmond County, who served as justice, burgess, colonel of militia, and as a member of the Council after 1732. (<cit><bibl n="B31">Ryland. <title>Richmond County Virginia. . . . </title> pp. 115-16.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Carter may mean the river in Maryland spelled "Petuckson" in his day, but now spelled "Patuxent."</note>

<note id="n5">5] King George II (1683-1760) reigned from 1727 until 1760. (<cit><bibl>George II [r. 1727-1760] "The Official <xref to="http://www.royal.gov.uk/HistoryoftheMonarchy/KingsandQueensoftheUnitedKingdom/TheHanoverians/GeorgeII.aspx">Website of the British Monarchy.</xref>"</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] James Christian was captain of the <hi rend="italics">Rose,</hi> a vessel owned by merchant Pemberton. (See <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C30d15a.html">Carter to Pemberton,</xref> April 15, 1730.)  </note>

<note id="n7">[7] Corotoman Creek runs in front of Carter's home of the same name in Lancaster County.</note>

<note id="n8">[8] The <hi rend="italics">John &amp; Betty</hi> was a Liverpool ship often carrying slaves owned by merchant John Pemberton. In 1726 the captain was John Gale, and in the next year, she was commanded by a Captain William Denton. The ship would be lost in 1729. (<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 18, n. 23;</bibl></cit> <cit><bibl><xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C30d15c.html">Carter to Pemberton,</xref> April 15;  1730,</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl><xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27f28c.html">Carter to William Dawkins,</xref> June 28, July 26, and August 22, 1727, for Denton's first name.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n9">[9] John Stark (b. 1685) was a  prominent Glasgow merchant in the sugar trade.  "John Stark, another Revolutioner provost, was born in 1685, the son of a merchant, and was admitted a burgess by right of his father in 1706. He was brought into the magistracy in 1724 as dean of guild and then chosen as provost in 1725. Stark's election as provost was quite unusual, because, while all the provosts from the Union until 1724 had experience of serving as merchant-baillie, he had none. This probably indicates that Stark represented a new force of 
urban politics which came into the council in 1724. . . . " He served as as baillie and provost (mayor) from 1725-1727. (<cit><bibl>Hisashi Kuboyama. "The Politics of the People in Glasgow and the West of Scotland, 1707-c. 1785." [Ph.D. thesis, University of Edinborough, 2012.], p. 66.</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl>"Provosts of Glasgow" at <xref to="https://www.glasgow.gov.uk/index.aspx?articleid=3052">"Welcome to Glasgow."</xref></bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n10">[10] Carter meant that Kilby was "a person likened in some way to Pontius Pilate; esp. (in early use) a corrupt or lax person; (in later use) a person who evades responsibility."  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary</title> online.</bibl></cit>) </note>

<note id="n11">[11] A groat is "an old British coin worth four pennies." (Merriam Webster <xref to="http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/groat"><title>Dictionary</title></xref>.)</note>


<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2003, was revised April 11, 2014,  to strengthen the footnotes and modern language version text.</hi></note>



</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>