<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C24d05b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to [Mann Page, April 5, 1724]</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C24d05b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to ]</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1724-04-04</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C24d05bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1724-04-04"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C24d05b.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to [Mann Page, April 5, 1724]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to an unidentified correspondent, probably his son-in-law, Mann Page, [April 5, 1724], informing him of the death of Daniel McCarty and soliciting his support for George Eskridge for the post of collector of Potomac River, an opening created by McCarty's death.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to [<note n="MP1">Mann Page,</note> April 5, 1724]</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1724-04-04"></date><lb/>

</dateline>
<salute>Hon<hi rend="underline">ble: Sr</hi></salute>

</opener>

<p>This is a hasty Errand occasioned by a Lettr: to <lb/>me at Church this Day which gives me an Accot of <note n="DM"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr>
 McCartys</note> <lb/>Death last night, <note n="GE">Eskridge</note> is gone to Stafford but in Expecta<lb/>tion of his Neighbours Death every <sic corr="minute">Minuite</sic> leaves this Lettr: <lb/>to be <sic corr="dispatched">dispatch'd</sic> away to me Earnestly pressing me to write to <lb/>the <note n="HD">Governour</note> in his favour for McCartys place our friend<lb/>ship hath been so long and strong I cannot deny him Accord<lb/>ingly my Coach man comes post with my Express now my <lb/>desire to you is that you will let your Man ned who is better <lb/>Acquainted with the Town carry this Express and Charles <lb/>will Supply his room <sic corr="until">till</sic> he comes he may go over to new <lb/><abbr expan="Quarter">Qr:</abbr> and there take a horse to Town by your Order I have <lb/>writ a line to the Commissary knowing he is alwayes at <lb/>hand</p>

<p>you know the Maxim <note target="n1">Vis unita fortior </note><lb/>whether you will think it proper to say a word in <lb/>Eskridges favour I shal submit Intirely to you I pur<lb/>pose by my man that is come for my Children <lb/>to write Severall Lettrs: to <abbr expan="Williamsburg">Wmsburgh</abbr> have onely time <lb/>at prsent to bid you all hail from</p>


<closer><seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>Sunday 4 of the Clock<lb/>
If there by any hopes of a Answer from the Governour it will <lb/>be very proper ned waits for it</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1723 June 16-1724 April 23, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>The name of Carter's home, the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note>

<note>Because Carter's son-in-law, Mann Page lived in Gloucester County, just across the York River from Williamsburg, and because of the  affectionate tone of this letter, the editor believes that it was sent to Page, also a member of the Council.</note>


<note>Most references cite the date of Daniel McCarty's death as 1724 <hi rend="italics">May</hi> 4, and cite his tombstone inscription: "Here lyeth the body of Daniel McCarty, who departed this life the fourth of May 1724 in the forty fifth year of his age. He was endowed with many virtues and qualifications, but the actions proceeding therefrom bespeak their praise."  (See, for instance, <cit><bibl n="B1">Kukla. <title>Speakers and Clerks. . . .</title> p. 100.</bibl></cit> The inscription is quoted from an email, 2002 July 30, William M. McCarty to the editor. Dr. McCarty has been working on a book on the McCarty family for some sixty years.)</note>

<note>There is no indication in the minutes of the Council that Eskridge was given the post that Carter sought for him. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739].</bibl></cit>)</note>



<note id="n1">[1] Vis unita fortior means strength united is stronger.</note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>