<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="Cbiodir">


<teiHeader type="aacr2"> 
                          
<fileDesc> 
<titleStmt> 
     <title type="245">NOTES ON OFTEN-CITED PERSONS, PLACES, AND THINGS</title> 
     <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title> 
     <respStmt> 
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp> 
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name> 
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp> 
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr., and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name> 
     </respStmt> 
</titleStmt> 
 
<extent>ca. 35 kilobytes </extent> 
 
<publicationStmt> 
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher> 
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace> 
     <idno type="ETC"></idno> 
     <availability> 
     <p>Publicly accessible</p> 
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/modeng.browse.html</p> 
         </availability> 
 
</publicationStmt> 
 
<sourceDesc> 
     <biblFull> 
     <titleStmt> 
     <title>NOTES ON OFTEN-CITED PERSONS, PLACES, AND THINGS</title> 
      <author>Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</author>
     </titleStmt> 
    <extent>10 p.</extent> 
<publicationStmt> 
     <date>2001</date> 
     <idno type="callNo">Cbiodir</idno> 
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull> 
</sourceDesc> 
 
</fileDesc> 
     <encodingDesc> 
     <projectDesc> 
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p> 
     </projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl> 
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p> 
</editorialDecl> 
 
<classDecl> 
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
     <bibl> 
     <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
     </bibl> 
     </taxonomy> 
</classDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
 
<profileDesc> 
     <creation> 
     <date>2000 </date> 
     </creation> 
     <langUsage> 
     <language id="eng"></language> 
     </langUsage> 
     <textClass> 
     <keywords> 
     <term>non-fiction</term> 
     <term>prose</term> 
     </keywords> 
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term> 
     </keywords> 
     </textClass> 
</profileDesc> 
 
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="Cbiodir.xmlT"> 

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AD</abbr>
<extent>10 pp.</extent>
<date value="2001"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">Cbiodir.xml</idno>
<title>NOTES ON OFTEN-CITED PERSONS, PLACES, AND THINGS</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>This text contains brief notes, with sources as necessary, identifying persons with whom Robert Carter frequently corresponds, or on places and things that he mentions often in his diary and letters.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>


<body> 
 
<div1 type="document" n="1"> 
 
<head>BRIEF NOTES ON OFTEN-CITED <lb/>PERSONS, PLACES, AND THINGS IN <lb/>ROBERT CARTER'S DIARY AND LETTERS</head><lb/> 
 
<opener> 
 
<dateline> 
 
<date value="2001"></date> 
</dateline> 
                                                             
</opener> 
 
 
 <p>


<name id="AP">ANDERSON'S PILLS,</name> or <q>Anderson's Scots Pills, a product of the 1630's</q> had been invented by <name type="person">Patrick Anderson,</name> a Scot, who wrote in a book published in 1635 that he had learned the secret of the pills in Venice. He passed the formula to his daughter Katherine who in turn passed it to a doctor named <name type="person">Thomas Weir</name> in 1686. Weir obtained letters patent on the formula from James II in 1687. (<cit><bibl>George B. Griffenhagen and James Harvey Young. "Old English Patent Medicines in America." <title>Contributions From the Museum of History and Technology. </title> Washington, D.C.: Smithsonian Institution, 1959, paper 10, 156-183.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="HA" type="person">ARMISTEAD, HENRY,</name> (d. <hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1739), second son of Colonel <name type="person">John Armistead.</name> He lived at <q><name type="house">Hesse,</name></q> <name type="county">Gloucester County,</name> with his wife, <name type="person">Martha Burwell</name>. His sister, <name n="JAC" type="person">Judith Armistead</name>, was RC's first wife, and another sister,  <name type="person">Elizabeth Armistead</name>, was <name type="person">Ralph Wormeley</name>'s wife. (<cit><bibl n="A1">"Armistead Family". <title>Virginia Magazine. . . .</title></bibl></cit> )<lb/><lb/>

<name type="person">ARMISTEAD, JUDITH</name> <hi rend="italics"> see</hi><name n="JAC"> Carter, Judith (Armistead)</name> <lb/><lb/>

<name id="EA" type="person">ATHAWES, EDWARD,</name> <name type="city">London</name> merchant, partner to <name n="WD" type="person">William Dawkins</name>. <lb/><lb/>

<name id="AB1">BAILEY, ARTHUR ,</name>(d. 1683), <name type="city">London</name> merchant and  a former ship's captain who had been in Virginia. He apparently was an old friend of Robert Carter's father, <name n="JC" type="person">John Carter I,</name> who may have been an apprentice under Bailey; he was known to <name n="JC1" type="person">John Carter II</name> as well, for Bailey is mentioned in their wills. <name type="person">Alan Simpson</name> has discovered that Bailey probably lived in the <name type="place">Mile-End district</name> of London where his son later lived. RC seems to have lived in this house while attending school.  (<cit><bibl n="A3">Simpson, "Robert Carter's Schooldays."</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="AB2" type="person">BAILEY, ARTHUR, </name> (d. <hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1714), <name type="city">London</name> merchant, owned a number of ships that traded with Virginia, and was active in presenting the affairs of the merchants and trade in general to the government. He wrote in 1708 a pamphlet titled <title>A Short State of the Virginia Trade in a Letter Occasioned by a Bill Proposed to the House of Commons for Commuting Tobacco for French Wines</title>. His daughter, <name type="person">Katherine Bailey</name>, married <name n="RB2" type="person">Robert Bristow,</name> another merchant involved in the Virginia trade. (<cit><bibl n="A4">Egerton MS921, British Library, cited in  Olson, <title>The Virginia Merchants of <lb/>London. . . .</title></bibl></cit> )<lb/><lb/>

<name id="WB" type="person">BALL, WILLIAM,</name> (1686-1745),  of <q><name type="house">Millenbeck,</name></q>  <name type="county">Lancaster County,</name> not far from <q><name type="house">Corotoman,</name></q>  a close friend of RC's, a justice, burgess, and wealthy and powerful man. (<cit><bibl n="A2"> Mann. "William Ball. . . ."</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="JB" type="person">BELFIELD, JOSEPH,</name> (d. 1738), of Devon, <name type="country">England,</name> had been a surgeon in the British navy before coming to Virginia. He settled in <name type="county">Richmond County,</name> was a justice in 1721, sheriff in 1726-1728, and married <name type="person">Frances Wright.</name> (<cit><bibl n="B31">Ryland. <title>Richmond County Virginia. . . . </title> pp. 195, 500, 504.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JB4">BELL, DR. JOHN,</name> was the minister of Christ Church Parish, <name type="county">Lancaster County.</name><lb/><lb/>

<name id="EB" type="person">BERKELEY, EDMUND,</name> (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1665-1718), of Petsworth Parish, <name type="county">Gloucester County,</name> and, after 1713, of <q><name type="house">Barn Elms,</name></q> <name type="county">Middlesex County</name>; he was appointed to the Council in the same year. He married in 1703 <name type="person">Lucy Burwell</name>, daughter of <name n="LB" type="person">Lewis Burwell</name>.  (<cit><bibl>Edmund Berkeley, Jr., "Berkeley, Edmund,"  in <title>Dictionary of Virginia Biography</title>. Richmond: Library of Virginia, 1998. I, pp. 448-49.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="PB" type="person">BEVERLEY, PETER,</name> (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1668-1728), of <name type="county">Gloucester County</name> was <q>Speaker of the House of Burgesses at four of the first five assemblies of the eighteenth century,</q> and had been clerk of the House earlier. He was clerk of <name type="county">Gloucester County</name> from 1695 until 1714, treasurer of the colony from 1712 until 1723, and was elevated to the Council in 1719. (<cit><bibl n="B1">Kukla. <title>Speakers and Clerks. . . .</title> pp 103-105.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JB1" type="person">BLAIR, JAMES,</name>(<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1655-1743), a Scot and a Presbyterian minister, represented the Anglican bishop of <name type="city">London</name> in Virginia (to which he emigrated in 1685) as commissary from 1690 until his death. Often at odds with the governors of the colony, and especially Francis Nicholson, he was a formidable opponent. The founder of the <name type="organization">College of William and Mary</name> and its first president, he was a member of the Council, and, as president of the Council, served briefly as governor in 1740-1741. (<cit><bibl n="B2">Rouse.  <title>James Blair.</title></bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="B27">Billings. <hi rend="italics">et al. </hi> <title>Colonial Virginia: A History, </title> esp. Chapter 7, "The Era of the Council."</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="MCB" type="person">BRAXTON, MARY (CARTER),</name> (1712-1736), Robert Carter's thirteenth child. She married <name type="person">George Braxton II</name> (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1705-1749) of <q><name type="house">Newington,</name></q> <name type="county">King and Queen County.</name> Her son, <name type="person">Carter Braxton</name>, was a Signer of the Declaration of Independence. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carlton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 429-430.</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="BT" type="place">BRENT TOWN</name> was a speculative land development put together by <name type="person">Nicholas Hayward</name> (d. <hi rend="italics">ante</hi> 1697) of London, a notary public, merchant, and speculator. Hayward assembled a syndicate composed of London merchants <name type="person" n="RB">Robert Bristow</name> (1643-1707)  and <name type="person">Richard Foote</name> (his brother-in-law), and <name type="person">George Brent</name> of <q>Woodstock,</q> <name type="county">Stafford County. </name>The syndicate purchased on January 10, 1686/87, from Lord Culpeper, by then the sole owner of the Northern Neck Proprietary, 30,006 acres in Stafford County <q>Between the Courses of the said Two Rivers, Rappahannock and Potowmack  . . . upon and Between the Southwest and Northeast Branches of Ocaquant Creek. . . .</q> Hayward obtained a dispensation from King James II that would allow the Hugenots that he hoped to settle on the land to have the <q>full exercise  of their Religion.</q> The town that Hayward hoped to build on the tract was called Brenton, <q>but this was corrupted by local [Virginia] usage into Brent Town, and that came to be the designation of the whole tract.</q> Hayward was not successful in persuading Hugenots to move to the lands, and, after flirting with other possibilities, the tract remained unsettled and unsurveyed at the time of his death about 1697. The members of the syndicate and their heirs bequeathed and sold their rights in the Brenton tract for generations. RC was to have considerable trouble over the tract after becoming agent of the proprietors  again in 1721. He was pressed to grant lands in the area of Brenton, but it was very difficult to do so because the tract had not been surveyed&mdash;and was not to be until 1737-1738.  Fairfax Harrison, in a chapter entitled <q>Brent Town, Ravensworth and the Hugenots,</q> in his <title>Landmarks of Old Prince William</title> (from which all quotations used here are taken) tells the story of Brent Town  extremely well.  (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> pp. 177-198.</bibl></cit> See also <cit><bibl n="B5">Davis,  <title>William Fitzhugh. . . .</title> p. 191, fn 2</bibl></cit>, and other sources.)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="BHQ" type="farm">BRICK HOUSE QUARTER</name></q>  was located in <name type="county">Lancaster County</name> and had originally belonged to Mrs. <name type="person" n="MJS">Mary Swan,</name> RC's sister-in-law; in the 1732 inventory of RC's estate, there were 20 slaves, 63 sheep, 45 hogs, and 46 cattle on the place. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . "</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="RB" type="person">BRISTOW, ROBERT,</name>  (1643-1707), "emigrated to Virginia about 1660 and established himself in <name type="county">Gloucester County</name>." He became 
a burgess, supported the government during Bacon's Rebellion, and was captured by the rebels and lost much property. He is usually referred to as <q>Major Bristow,</q> probably because of his service at this time. Returning to England in 1677, he became a member of the <name type="organization">Grocer's Company</name>, a successful merchant in the Virginia trade, and an alderman of <name type="city">London</name>. His daughter was married to <name n="AB2" type="person">Arthur Bailey</name>. Bristow was one of the four partners in the Brenton  land speculation in Virginia; see the letter of January 1, 1715, Hooper to Robert Carter, for more information. (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 191.</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="RB1" type="person">BRISTOW, ROBERT,</name> (d. 1706), son of Major <name 
n="RB">Robert Bristow</name>; his will states that he was of the parish of 
Gabriel, Fenchurch Street, <name type="city">London</name>, and that he was a merchant. (<cit><bibl n="A27">"Bristow Wills. . . ." </bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="RB2" type="person">BRISTOW, ROBERT,</name> (1688-1737), grandson of Major <note n="RB" type="person">Robert Bristow</note> ; Robert Carter turned down an opportunity to be his Virginia agent, and, in 1709, Bristow gave a power of attorney to <name type="person">Thomas Booth</name> of <name type="county">York County</name> for that purpose. In 1772, a Thomas Booth was still the Bristow family's agent, but their lands were confiscated during the American Revolution. Bristow was a Member of <name type="organization">Parliament</name> for <name type="city">Winchelsea</name>, 1708-1737, and a director of the <name type="organization"> Bank of England</name>. (<cit><bibl n="A5">Tyler. "Inscriptions on Old Tombs in Gloucester Co., Virginia."</bibl></cit>, and <cit><bibl n="B6">Sedgwick. <title>Parliament.</title> I, 488.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JB2" type="person">BURFORD, JOHN,</name> commanded the <name type="ship"><hi rend="italics">Elizabeth and Mary,</hi></name> a <name type="city">London</name> ship of 20 men and 10 guns, built at <name type="city">Ipswich</name> in 1697, and of 250 tons. She was owned by <note n="JG">John Goodwin</note> and <note n="JM">Jonathan Mathews,</note> <name type="person">Samuel Landford</name>, <name type="person">Nicholas Goodwin</name>, <name type="person">William Holditch</name>, and <name type="person">Job Mathews</name>.  This ship sank during a voyage to Virginia in the winter of 1701-1702; Burford later commanded the <hi rend="italics">Mansfield</hi> by which RC sent tobacco to London. (<cit><bibl n="A23">"List of Ships . . . 1705."</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="M3">Naval officer's return for Rappahannock River, 1700. . . . ff. 13.</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="BH" type="farm">BURNT HOUSE</name></q> was a farm in <name type="county">Richmond County,</name> <q>apparently in the vicinity of Cat Point Bridge.</q> (<cit><bibl n="B29">Miller, Mary R. <title>Place-Names of the Northern Neck. . . .</title>,  19.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JB3" type="person">BURRIDGE, JOHN,</name> (1681?-1753), brother of <name 
n="RB3">Robert Burridge</name>, a merchant in <name type="city">London</name> trading primarily "to 
Guinea and the West Indies." In 1717, John Burridge's estate 
was seized by the Crown for non-payment of duties  on wine. John Burridge represented Lyme Regis in <name type="organization">Parliament</name> from 1710-1728. (<cit><bibl n="B6">Sedgwick. <title>The History of Pariament . . . Commons.</title></bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/> 

<name id="RB3" type="person">BURRIDGE, ROBERT,</name> (1683-1752),  a merchant of <name type="city">Lyme Regis,</name> Dorset, who came from an ancient <name type="county">Somerset</name> family. He was mayor of Lyme in 1710 
and 1721. His brother John  was a London merchant who represented Lyme in Parliament. In 
RC's letter to Robert Burridge of July 13, 1720, he mentions "Mr. <name type="person">Joseph 
Paise </name> Yor. Partner." (<cit><bibl>George Roberts. <title>History and Antiquities of the Borough of Lyme Regis and Charmworth. </title> London, 1834. pp. 383-4, 209, 286, 295, </bibl></cit> and other sources. )<lb/><lb/>

<name id="LB" type="person">BURWELL, LEWIS,</name> (    -1710), of <q><name type="place">Carter's Creek</name>,
</q><name type="county">Gloucester County</name>, and later of <name type="house">"King's Creek,"</name> <name type="county">York County</name>. He was a member of the Council, 1702-1710. <lb/><lb/>

<name id="NB" type="person">BURWELL, NATHANIEL,</name> (1680-1721), of <q><name type="house">Carter's Creek</name></q> (later called <q><name type="house">Fairfield</name></q>), <name type="county">Gloucester County</name>, a justice, burgess, and 
Council member. He married Robert Carter's daughter 
<name type="person">Elizabeth Carter</name> (1692-1734) in 1709. RC managed the Burwell estates until his own death. <lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="BQ" type="farm">BURWELL'S QUARTER</name></q> probably had belonged to RC's son-in-law, Nathaniel Burwell, who died in 1721. The profits from this farm went to Burwell's widow, Elizabeth, and RC acquired title to it at some point because he bequeathed it to one of Elizabeth's sons.<lb/><lb/>

<name id="WB1" type="person">BYRD, WILLIAM,</name> (1652-1704), first of that name in Virginia, 
arrived  <q>before 1670 . . . to live with his maternal uncle, <name type="person">Thomas Stegge</name>, auditor general of the colony.</q> From Stegge, Byrd learned of the lucrative fur trade in which he subsequently prospered. He served as a burgess, was appointed to the Council in 1682, and in 1687 won <q>the office his uncle had held of duputy auditor and receiver general of the revenues.</q> (<cit><bibl n="B7">Tinling, <title>The Correspondence of the Three William Byrds. . . .</title>, 3-6</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="WC" type="person">CAGE, WILLIAM,</name> of <name type="place">Milgate</name>, <name type="county">County Kent</name>, 
England, was related to the Fairfax family, and became trustee for Lady Fairfax after the fifth baron's death. He sought the advice of <note n="MP">Micajah</note> and Richard Perry in finding a replacement for <name type="person">Edmund Jenings</name> as Virginia agent for the Northern Neck proprietary, and Robert Carter obtained a lease for it in 1721. The trusteeship ended in 1727. (<hi rend="italics">See</hi> various references in <cit><bibl n="B8">Brown. <title>Virginia Baron. . . .</title></bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="EWC" type="person">CARTER, ELIZABETH (LANDON) WILLIS,</name> (1684-1719) Robert Carter's second wife by whom he had ten children, the last, George, being born in 1718. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 2.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="GC" type="person">CARTER, GEORGE,</name> (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1718-c.1741/42), Robert Carter's fifteenth child. He attended <name type ="organization">William &amp; Mary</name>, and was sent to London by his older brother,<name n="JC1" type="person"> John Carter</name>, after RC's death. He studied law there, 
and remained in <name type="city">London</name> until his death. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carlton, <title>A Genealogy . . .</title>457</bibl> </cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JC2" type="person">CARTER, JAMES,</name> (1684-1743), of <name type="county">Stafford County</name>, was the younger brother of Carter's dear friend and associate, Captain <name type="person">Thomas Carter</name> of <name type="county">Lancaster County</name>, and was one of RC's chief managers. (<cit><bibl>Joseph Lyon Miller, "Captain Thomas Carter and His Descendants," <title>William and Mary Quarterly</title> 1st. ser., 17(1908-09): 275-285.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JC" type="person">CARTER, JOHN,</name> (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi>1648-1690), older brother of Robert, justice, militia officer, and prominent citizen of <name type="county">Lancaster County</name>. He inherited the bulk of his father's estate, and managed it well, while adhering both to the specifics and intent of his father's will with regard to the education of his younger brother. John 
Carter II married twice, first to <name type="person">Elizabeth Hull</name>, daugher of John and Elizabeth Hull, by whom he had his only child, <name n="ECL" type="person">Elizabeth Carter</name>. Carter married his second wife, <name type="person">Elizabeth Travers</name>, in 1684; she married <name type="person">Christopher 
Wormeley</name> after Carter's death, and died herself in 1693. (<cit><bibl>Thomas Allen Glenn. <title>Some Colonial Mansions and Those Who Lived in Them, With Genealogies of the Various Families Mentioned.</title> Philadelphia: H. T. Coates &amp; Company, 1899.  pp. 244 ff.</bibl></cit>;  <cit><bibl>review of <title>The Ancestry of Benjamin Harrison, President of the United States of America, 1889-1893</title> in <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography</title>, 2 (Oct. 1894): p. 236, with notes on the Carter family; and other sources.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JC1" type="person">CARTER, JOHN,</name> (<hi  rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1689-1742), oldest child of Robert, studied at <name>Trinity College, Cambridge</name>, and then at the <name>Middle Temple</name>; was called to the bar in 1720. <name type="person">Alexander 
Spotswood</name> appointed John Carter agent for Virginia in England, but he resigned this post when he was appointed Secretary of State for the colony in 1722. He returned to Virginia in 1723, and had a distinguished career. He married <name type="person">Elizabeth Hill</name> of <q><name type="house">Shirley,</name></q> and had four children. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 3.</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl>"Virginia Council Journals," <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography.</title> 32 (1924): 48.</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="JAC" type="person">CARTER, JUDITH (ARMISTEAD),</name> (1665-1699), Robert Carter's first wife, mother of:<name n="JC1" type="person"> John Carter (1689/90-1742)</name>, <name type="person">Elizabeth Carter (1692-1734)</name>; <name type="person">Judith Carter(c. 1693, d. in infancy)</name>; <name type="person">Sarah Carter (c. 1694, d. in infancy)</name>; and a second <name n="JCP" type="person">Judith Carter (1695-c. 1750)</name> (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 2.</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

CARTER, LUCY <hi rend="italics"> see</hi> <name n="LCF" type="person"> Fitzhugh, Lucy (Carter)</name> <lb/><lb/>

CARTER, MARY <hi rend="italics"> see</hi> <name n="MCB" type="person"> Braxton, Mary (Carter)</name> <lb/><lb/>

<name id="TC1" type="person">CARTER, THOMAS,</name>  (1672-1733) was the second of that name in <name type="county">Lancaster County</name>, and may have been RC's first cousin as there is evidence that their fathers were brothers. He lived at <q><name type="house">Barford</name></q> in the northern part of the county. (<cit><bibl>Catherine Adams Jones. <title>The Early Thomas Carters of Lancaster County, Virginia.</title> Lancaster, Virginia: Mary Ball Washington Museum &amp; Library, 1982.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="CS" type="ship">CARTER</name> (SHIP) A vessel named the <hi rend="italics">Carter</hi> traded to Virginia for many years; she is most often referred to as the <hi rend="italics">Carter Frigatt</hi>. The captain in 1706 was <name type="person">Thomas Graves</name> who is mentioned in the <name type="county">Lancaster County </name>Court Orders Book for judgements against him obtained by RC. Later, the <hi rend="italics">Carter</hi> would be commanded by <name type="person">Baily Kent,</name> 1718-1721, <name type="person">Thomas Dove,</name> and by <name type="person">Benjamin Graves.</name> She was owned by RC and <note n="WD">William Dawkins</note> in 1720. (<cit><bibl>Survey report 6800 for Adm. 68/194-5, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert H. Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</bibl></cit>; and Lancaster County Court Orders Book 5, 1702-13, p. 187, as abstracted in <cit><bibl n="B28">Jones, <title>Orders Book Entries . . . Referring to "Robert Carter. . . . " </title></bibl></cit> )

<q><name id="CC" type="house">CARTER'S CREEK</name>,</q> the Burwell home, was in <name type="county">Gloucester County</name> about two miles up the stream of this name from <q><name type="house">Rosewell.</name></q> 

<q><name id="CR" type="farm">CARTER'S RANGE</name></q> probably was the farm in <name type="county">Prince William County</name> called <q>Range Quarter</q> in the 1732 inventory of RC's estate. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . "</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="RC" type="person">CARY, ROBERT,</name> (1685-1751),  <name type="city">London</name> merchant, second of the name, a partner in a firm that was involved in the Virginia tobacco trade for over 100 years.  Robert Carter mentions in his will that he had purchased lands in <name type="county">Richmond</name>, <name type="county">Westmoreland</name>, and <name 
type="county">King George</name> counties from Cary. 
(<cit><bibl n="A16">Robert Carter's will</bibl></cit>, and <cit><bibl n="A6">Jacob M. Price, "Who Was John Norton? A Note on the Historical Character of Some Eighteenth-Century London Virginia Firms," <title>William and Mary Quarterly</title>, 3rd. ser.,19(July 1962):400-407.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="CF" type="farm">CHANGLINS</name></q> was a farm owned by RC located in <name type="county">Lancaster County</name> relatively close to <name type="house">Corotoman.</name><lb/><lb/>

<name id="RC1" type="person">CHICHESTER, RICHARD,</name> (1657-1734) came to Virginia in 1702. He married <name type="person">Anne Fox Chinn</name>, and settled in <name type="county">Lancaster County</name>. (<cit><bibl>"Virginia Gleanings in England," <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography</title>, 21 (1913): 249-253.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="AC" type="person">CHURCHILL, ARMISTEAD,</name> (1704-1763) was the son of William Churchill of <q><name type="house">Bushy Park,</name></q> <name type="county">Middlesex County.</name> (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison, <title>Landmarks of Old Prince William</title>, p. 346.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="WC1" type="person">CHURCHILL, WILLIAM,</name> (1649/50-1710), of <name type="house">"Bushy Park,"</name> <name type="county">Middlesex County</name>, served in various posts before being appointed to the Council on August 15, 1705. His daughter, <name type="person">Priscilla Churchill</name>, 
married RC's son Robert. (<cit><bibl n="B23">Tinling. <title>The Secret Diary of William Byrd. . . . </title></bibl></cit>, 264, for death date 
(28.XI.1710); and <cit><bibl><title>William and Mary Quarterly</title>, 1st. ser., 8(1900): 39, 47-50 for genealogy of the Churchills.</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="JC3" type="person">CLAYTON, JOHN,</name> (1665-1737), an attorney educated at Eton, Cambridge, and the <name type="organization">Inner Temple</name>, came to Virginia about 1705, and served as secretary to Governor <name type="person">Edward Nott</name>.  He practiced law, held various legal posts in the colony, and was appointed Attorney General in 1713. (<cit><bibl n="B26">Berkeley and Berkeley. <title>John Clayton</title>.</bibl></cit>.)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="CF1" type="farm">COLEMAN'S</name></q>  was a farm apparently in <name type="county">Lancaster County</name> close to <q><note n="BHQ">Brick House</note></q> and <q>Pursells.</q><lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="CP" type="farm">COLE'S POINT</name></q>  was a farm in <name type="county">Westmoreland County</name> <q>in <name type="place">Coles Neck</name> just east of Lower Machodoc Creek on the Potomac</q> Mary R. Miller notes. The property, of some 1,350 acres, descended to Robert Carter III, according to Louis Morton. (<cit><bibl n="B29">Miller, <title>Place-Names of the Northern Neck. . . .</title>p. 32.</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="B32"> Morton,<title> Robert Carter. . . . </title> 70.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="GC1" type="person">CORBIN, GAWIN,</name> (d. 1744), of <name type="house">"Buckingham,"</name> <name type="county">Middlesex County</name>, and later of <q><name type="house">Laneville,</name></q> <name type="county">King and Queen County</name>, was a justice of the 
peace, burgess, collector, and naval officer of the Rappahannock; he owned extensive tracts of land in many counties. (<cit><bibl n="A7">"The Corbin Family of Virginia," 244</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl><title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography,</title>85 (Jan.77): 28, fn. 50.</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="TC" type="person">CORBIN, THOMAS,</name> (d. <hi rend="italics">post</hi> 1732), a fellow trustee with RC of <note n="RW"><name type="person">Ralph Wormeley's</name></note> estate, was born in Virginia but became a <name type="city">London</name> merchant, perhaps in the firm run by his father's brother, <name type="person">Gawin Corbin</name> (d. 1709), who was <q>for a number of years financial agent for Virginia in England. . . .</q> (<cit><bibl n="A7">"The Corbin Family of Virginia," 244.</bibl></cit>)  <lb/><lb/>

<q><name type="farm">COROTOMAN</name></q>  or <q><name type="farm">Buckles</name>,</q> was a property very close to RC's home, also called <q><name type="house">Corotoman.</name></q> But this property was under the direction of an overseer named <name type="person">John Buckles,</name> and RC frequently refers to it as <q>Buckles.</q><lb/><lb/>

<name id="AC1" type="person">COSBY, AMY,</name>  seems to have been an important house servant, probably the housekeeper for RC, then a widower, and is mentioned a number of times in the diary.<lb/><lb/>

<name id="WD" type="person">DAWKINS, WILLIAM,</name> a <name type="county">London</name> merchant, who began his career as an apprentice to <note n="AB1"><name type="person">Arthur Bailey,</name></note> and succeeded to the firm. He later brought <note n="EA"><name type="person">Edward Athawes</name></note>  into his business. Dawkins was one of Robert Carter's most frequent correspondents. <lb/><lb/>

<name id="HD" type="person">DRYSDALE, HUGH,</name>  (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1670-1726), was lieutenant governor under the Earl of Orkney, the titular governor who never came to Virginia. Drysdale arrived in Virginia in September 1722 and  ruled the colony until his death in July 1726. RC, then ranking member of the Council, succeeded him. (<cit><bibl n ="B36">Raimo. <title>Directory of American Colonial . . . Governors 1607-1789.</title></bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="ES">ESCHEAT</name> is the reversion of land to the lord of the manor (usually in these documents, to the proprietors of the Northern Neck) because of the death without heirs of the holder of the lands. Anyone wishing to patent escheated lands had to pay a fee to RC as the agent of the proprietors.<lb/><lb/>

<name id="GE" type="person">ESKRIDGE, GEORGE,</name>  (1660-1735), of <q><name type="house">"Sandy Point,"</name></q> <name type="county">Westmoreland County,</name> was a burgess and perhaps the most prominent man in the county at this time. He was the guardian for <name type="person">Mary Ball,</name> mother of <name type="person">George Washington,</name> and the latter's namesake. (<cit><bibl>Lucy Brown Beale, "Colonel George Eskridge," <title>Northern Neck of Virginia Historical Magazine</title>, 3(Dec. 1953): 233-236</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl>Charles Willard Hoskins Warner, "George Eskridge of Westmoreland: His Age and Political Career," <title>Northern Neck of Virginia Historical Magazine</title>, 16(Dec. 1966): 1450-1467.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="WE" type="person">EUSTACE, WILLIAM,</name> (d. <hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1740), was sheriff of <name type="county">Northumberland County</name> in 1729, and had a large estate. He petitioned the <name type="county">Lancaster County</name> court for an acre of land <q>to build a Water Mill on the land lately belonging to Thomas Purrcell on Norris Bridge swamp. . . .</q> (<cit><bibl><title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography</title> 34(1926): 201, 346, 347</bibl></cit>; and Lancaster County Order Book 7, 1721-1729,  pp. 66 and 69, as abstracted in <bibl n="B28">Jones, <title>Orders Book Entries . . . Referring to "Robert Carter. . . ."</title></bibl>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="TE" type="person">EVANS, THOMAS,</name> a <name type="city">London</name> merchant. <lb/><lb/>

<name id="TF" type="person">FAIRFAX, THOMAS,</name> (1693-1781), sixth Lord Fairfax,  inherited the Northern Neck proprietary in Virginia upon his mother's death in 1719. Her will established a trust that extended to <q>1728 [when] Robert Fairfax reached the age of 21, and this event terminated Lady Fairfax's testamentary trust,</q> relieving <note n="WC"><name type="person">William Cage,</name></note> and giving Thomas Fairfax full control of his estates. Because of his concern over RC's management of them, he came to Virginia in 1735 to administer them himself. His relationship with <name type="person">George Washington</name> is well known. (<cit><bibl n="B8">Brown. <title>Virginia Baron. . . .</title>; p. 39 for quotation.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="FQ" type="farm">FALLS QUARTER</name></q>  was located in <name type="county">King George County,</name> and had twenty-four slaves, three horses, and thirty-eight cattle in the 1732 inventory of RC's estate; it lay on lands patented in March 1704 by <name type="person">James Innes</name> for RC. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison, <title>Landmarks of Old Prince William</title>. p. 198.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="FT" type="town">FALMOUTH</name> was a new town created by the Assembly in February 1727. RC, <name type="person">Mann Page,</name> <name type="person">Nicholas Smith,</name> <name type="person">William Thornton,</name> <name type="person">John Fitzhugh,</name> <name type="person">Charles Carter,</name> and <name type="person">Henry Fitzhugh</name> the younger were the <q>directors and trustees.</q> The land chosen for the site lay in <name type="county">King George County,</name> and deeds were recorded in its court records. (<cit><bibl>William Waller Hening, <title>The Statutes at Large; Being a Collection of the Laws of Virginia . . . .</title> [Richmond, 1820. reprint, 1969], IV, pp. 234-39</bibl></cit>).<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="FP" type="farm">FIELDING'S PLANTATION</name></q> was located in Fielding Neck, <name type="county">Northumberland County,</name>and comprised some 1800 to 2000 acres. In the 1732 inventory of RC's estate, it had six slaves, twenty-four sheep, twenty-five hogs, thirty-three cattle, and a horse. It passed to Robert Carter III. (<cit><bibl n="B32">Morton, <title>Robert Carter of Nomini Hall.</title></bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>.)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="LCF" type="person">FITZHUGH, LUCY (CARTER),</name> (1715-1763), Robert Carter's fourteenth child. She married <name type="person">Henry Fitzhugh</name> (1706-1742) of <q><name type="house">Eagle's Nest,</name></q> <name type="county">Stafford County,</name> in 1730, and had four children; after Fitzhugh's death, she married <note n="NH"><name type="person">Nathaniel Harrison</name></note> (1713-1791). (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 451.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="FB">FLEET'S BAY</name>  is at the east end of <name type="county">Northumberland County</name> not far from Corotoman.<lb/><lb/>

<name id="RF" type="person">FOOTE, RICHARD,</name> (1666-1724), of <name type="county">Stafford County,</name> nephew of <name type="person">Nicholas Hayward,</name> developer of the Brent Town speculation in the Northern Neck Proprietary. Foote's father was one of Hayward's partners, and a successful merchant in London.  The son lived in the Brent Town tract, and represented the owners in Virginia.<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JF" type="person">FRANKLIN, JOSHUA,</name>  a merchant of <name type="city">Bristol,</name> very active in the <name type="organization">Merchant Venturers' Company</name>. He began 
his career as an apprentice to <name type="person">Richard Franklin</name>, who may have been his cousin, in 1693. His brother <name type="person">Henry Franklin</name> was also apprenticed to Richard some years earlier. (<cit><bibl n="B34">McGrath. <title>Records Relating to the Society of Merchant Venturers . . .  of Bristol.</title> p.38.</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl id ="B35">McGrath. <title>The Merchants Venturers of Bristol: A History. . . .</title> p. 151.</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="JG1" type="person">GIBSON, JONATHAN,</name>  (d. 1729), <q>established Gibson's Tobacco Warehouse on the Rappahannock river on the dower land of his wife, <name type="person">Elizabeth (Thornton) Conway Gibson</name></q>; it was located <q>immediately opposite <name type="town">Port Royal</name> in <name type="county">Caroline County.</name></q> (<cit><bibl><title>King George County Virginia Will Book A-1 1721-1752 And Miscellaneous Notes</title>. [Fredericksburg, Va.: Privately Printed, 1978], 237.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JG" type="person">GOODWIN, JOHN,</name> presumed to be <note n="JM"><name type="person">Jonathan Mathews'</name></note> partner in a <name type="city">London</name> firm as RC usually addressed them jointly. He may have been a kinsman of <name type="person">William Churchill</name> who named Nicholas and John 
Goodwin of London as two of his executors. RC 
was "agent" for the London merchants <name type="person">James Waye</name> and <name type="person">Nicholas Goodwin</name> in August 1709 when he obtained a court order on their behalf.  (<cit><bibl><title>William and Mary Quarterly</title>, 1st.ser.,17(1909): 167.</bibl></cit>; and   <cit><bibl n="B28">Jones, <title>Orders Book Entries . . . referring to "Robert Carter".</title>, 218.</bibl> </cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="GS" type="house">GREEN SPRINGS</name></q>  was located in <name type="county">James City County</name> about eight miles from <name type="town">Williamsburg,</name> and five from <name type="town">Jamestown.</name> Originally, it was the home of <name type="person">Sir William Berkeley,</name> and passed into the Ludwell family when <note n="PL1"><name type="person">Philip Ludwell</name></note> (1638-1717) married Berkeley's widow.<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JG2" type="person">GRYMES, JOHN,</name> (1692-1748) of  <q><name type="house">Brandon,</name></q> <name type="county">Middlesex County,</name> served as deputy auditor of the colony and  was appointed to the Council in 1725.<lb/><lb/>

<name id="GH" type="person">HAMILTON, GEORGE,</name> (1666-1737), Earl of Orkney, was appointed governor of Virginia, February 10, 1710, but never came to the colony during his tenure which extended to his death. He was a distinguished soldier and Privy Councillor. (<cit><bibl><title>Dictionary of National Biography</title></bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="ACH">HARRISON, ANNE (CARTER),</name>  (1702-<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1743), RC's daughter, married in 1722 <name type="person">Benjamin Harrison IV</name> of <q><name type="house">Bromley,</name></q> <name type="county">Charles City County.</name><lb/><lb/>

<name id="BH1">HARRISON, BENJAMIN,</name>(1695-1745), of <q>Bromley,</q> (later the builder of <q><name type="house">Berkeley,</name></q>) both in <name type="county">Charles City County,</name> a prominent citizen and frequently a burgess, married RC's daughter Anne in 1722. (<cit><bibl>"Harrison of James River," <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography. </title> 32(1924): 97.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="NH" type="person">HARRISON, NATHANIEL,</name> (1697-1727), of <name type="house">"Wakefield,"</name> <name type="county">Surry County</name>, justice, burgess, naval officer, and receiver of duties, was appointed to the Council in 1713. (<cit><bibl n="B9">Tyler, <title>Encyclopedia of Virginia Biography,</title> I, 152;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 3(1721-1739): 523-527.</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="NH1" type="person">HEDGEMAN, NATHANIEL,</name> (d. 1721),  settled his family at <q>Accokeek</q> on Potomac Creek, <name type="county">Stafford County,</name> a property he bought from <name type="person">George Mason</name> (1629-1686). He was one of RC's senior overseers, or managers, and his accidental death caused problems for RC. (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison, <title>Landmarks of Old Prince William</title>, pp. 198 203.</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl>Robert A. Rutland, <title>The Papers of George Mason</title>. [Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1970], l, x.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="HT" type="farm">HICKORY THICKET</name></q>  was located in <name type="county">Richmond County</name>  <q>northeast of Warsaw.</q> (<cit><bibl n="B29">Miller,  <title>Place-Names of the Northern Neck . . . .</title>, p. 66.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="HQ" type="farm">HILLS QUARTER</name></q> was a farm owned by RC located in <name type="county">Lancaster County </name>relatively close to <q>Corotoman.</q><lb/><lb/>

<name id="JH" type="person">HOLLOWAY, JOHN,</name> (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1666-1734), an English-born lawyer who emigrated first to <name type="state">Maryland</name>, and then to Virginia at the beginning of the eighteenth century. He represented <name type="county">King and Queen County</name> in the <name type="organization">House of Burgesses</name> in 1710, and was elected Speaker in the sessions of 1720-1722, 1723-1726, and 1728-1734.  He was at first a strong supporter of Lieutnant Governor <name type="person">Alexander Spotswood</name>, but  later broke with him. He did legal work for Robert Carter from time to time. (<bibl n="B1">Kukla. <title>Speakers and Clerks. . . .</title> pp. 113-118.</bibl>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="TH">HOOPER, THOMAS,</name>  was appointed sheriff of <name type="county">Stafford County</name> in 1719. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 3 (1721-1739): p. xl.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JH1" type="person">HUST (or Hurst), JOHN,</name>  was the overseer of <q><name type="farm">Hamstead Quarter,</name></q> <name type="county">Stafford County,</name> in the 1732 inventory of RC's estate, supervising  sixteen slaves with the assistance of one horse. Hust apparently was a carpenter because Carter mentions his doing carpentry work in various letters. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JH2">HYDE, JOHN,</name>,usually referred to as <q>Captain,</q>  was a London merchant with whom RC dealt. His firm owned the <hi rend="italics">Providence</hi>.<lb/><lb/>

<name id="IP" type="farm">INNIS,</name> a <name type="county">Richmond County</name> property acquired by RC toward the end of 1728. <name type="person">Enoch Innis</name> inherited it from his father, James, who died in 1709. (<cit><bibl>Lucy Jane Brent Palmer, "Charles Brent of Stafford County and Some of His Descendants," <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography</title>, 34(1926): 280-85 and 378-84</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl>"Abstracts From Records of Richmond County, Virginia," <title>William and Mary Quarterly</title>, (1)17(1908-09): 176-177,</bibl></cit> which cites records of Richmond County concerning this will, probated 25 December 1709, as from Will Book 3).<lb/><lb/>

<name id="EJ" type="person">JENINGS, EDMUND,</name>  (1659-1727), was born in <name type="country">England</name>, trained as a lawyer, and 
practiced that profession in Virginia where he was Attorney General and 
Secretary of State as well as a member of the Council and holder of many lesser offices. He succeeded RC as agent for the proprietors of the Northern Neck in 1711, and, due to his poor health, left the records in a considerable muddle as Carter found upon resuming the agency in 1721. Jenings accrued many debts, especially to <name type="city">London</name> merchant <note n="MP"><name type="person">Micajah Perry,</name></note> and RC eventually took a mortgage on Jenings' estate, <name type="house">"Ripon Hall,"</name> taking 
it over when Jenings could not make the payments. Because of poor health Jenings was suspended from the Council in 1726 when Lieutenant Governor <name type="person">Hugh Drysdale</name> was planning a trip to England for his health. RC thus became first member of the Council, and acting governor upon Drysdale's sudden death on July 22, 1726. (<cit><bibl n="B8">Brown. <title>Virginia Baron. . . .</title></bibl></cit> and a variety of other sources.)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JJ" type="person">JOHNSON, JOHN,</name> replaced <name type="person" n="NH1">Nathaniel Hedgeman</name> as Carter's <q>general overseer</q> in late spring 1721 after Nathaniel Hedgeman's accidental death. Johnson, Carter wrote Captain <name type="person">Thomas Hooper</name> on June 22, 1721, <q>hath lived under me for several Years and I hope will prove a diligent honest man . . . although he is unlettered.</q> (<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright, <title>Letters of Robert Carter 1720-1727.</title>, 103.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="CJ" type="person">JONES, CHARLES,</name>, a long-time overseer for RC at <q><name type="farm">Hills Quarter</name></q> in <name type="county">Lancaster County.</name> RC wrote to him there in 1727, and he appears in RC's will as the overseer on that property. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="RJ" type="person">JONES, ROBERT,</name>, resident of <name type="county">Prince William County</name> where he was a justice and 
sheriff 1731-1732. He probably sold Robert Carter a plantation in <name type="county">Northumberland County</name> that is mentioned in RC's will. In 1727, Jones seems to have been Robert Carter's chief overseer in the upper country; see the lengthy letter to him of 10 October 1727. (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p.339.</bibl></cit>, and <cit><bibl n="A8">Berkeley. "Robert Carter as Agricultural Administrator: . . .", 
273-295.</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="JK" type="person">KING, JOHN,</name> (d. 1734),  
<name type="city">Bristol</name> merchant, and a prominent citizen who served as a member of the corporation, 1716-1734, sheriff, 1719-1720, and as mayor in 1732-1734. 
He was involved in the trade of both tobacco and iron.  (<cit><bibl id="B33">Minchinton. <title>Politics and the Port of Bristol in the Eighteenth Century. . . . </title> pp. 23, 31, 147</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl>Alfred B. Bevan, <title>Bristol Lists: Municipal and Miscellaneous.</title> p. 298.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="KC" type="house">KINGS CREEK</name></q> was the home of <note n="LB"><name type="person">Lewis Burwell</name></note> (d. 1710) in 
<name type="county">York County.</name>
 He was a member of Council and the father of <note n="NB">Nathaniel</note> (1680-1721) who  married RC's daughter, Elizabeth, in 1708.<lb/><lb/>

<name id="FL" type="person">LEE, FRANCIS,</name> (1648-1714), third son of <name type="person">Richard Lee,</name> the emigrant, inherited considerable property in Virginia when his father died in 1664.  But he had probably already served a "commercial apprenticeship in London with Griffith and Lockey" before returning to Virginia about 1670. He settled in <name type="county">Northumberland County</name>, became a justice, and 
prospered. The call of merchant life took him back to <name type="country">London</name> where he kept offices first in Buttolfe Lane, and later in <name type="house">St. Dionis, Backchurch</name>. (<cit><bibl id="A9">Montague. "Richard Lee, the Emigrant 1613 (?)-1664."
     <title>Virginia Magazine. . . . </title></bibl></cit>
 and <cit><bibl id="B7">Tinling. <title>The Correspondence of the Three William Byrds. . . .</title></bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="RL" type="person">LEE, RICHARD,</name> (1691-1740), of <name type="house">"Ditchley,"</name> <name type="county">Northumberland County</name>, a justice and long-time (1716-1735) clerk of the county court. 
He was the son of <name type="person">Hancock Lee</name> (d. 1709), an intimate friend of Robert Carter who was named in Lee's will as "a good friend," and appointed one of the trustees of his children. (<cit><bibl n="B11">Cazenove G. Lee, <title>Lee Chronicle . . .</title> pp. 33-35</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 28</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="ECL" type="person">LLOYD, ELIZABETH (CARTER),</name> (1675-1693) only child of Robert Carter's brother. Elizabeth married <name type="person">John Lloyd</name> in 1691, and was dead by November 1693 of measles. John appointed managers of the estate in 1699 in <name type="county">Essex County</name>, and returned to England the next year as he had inherited land there. Elizabeth inherited from her mother, <name>Elizabeth Hull,</name> also an only child, all of her grandfather <name>John Hull's</name> property.  (<cit><bibl>"Abstracts of Richmond County, Virginia" [from Order Book 1], <title>William and Mary Quarterly</title>, 1st. ser. 18(Oct. 1908): 73-85</bibl></cit>; <hi rend="italics">see also</hi> <cit><bibl> Carl F. Cannon, Jr., "Robert ("King") Carter of "Corotoman." Unpublished doctoral dissertation, Duke University, 1956, p. 25.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="LL" type="farm">LLOYD'S,</name> a plantation lying up the Rappahannock near the falls as RC always sent his sloop for its tobacco. RC was involved with the Lloyd property which was that of <name type="person">John Lloyd,</name> widower of RC's niece <note n="ECL">Elizabeth</note>. The estate's tobacco mark was the double arrowhead or double <q>L</q> which RC uses in his diary to refer to it. He undertook to buy the Lloyd estate in the later years of his life, and finally acquired it about 1730. Richard Meeks was the overseer.<lb/><lb/>
*
<name id="JL" type="person">LOMAX, JOHN,</name> (1675-1729), born in <name type="house">North Shields</name>, <name type="county">Northumberland</name>, <name  type="country">England,</name> came to Virginia in 1701, and married <name type="person">Betty Wormeley</name>, daughter of <name n="RW" type="person">Ralph Wormeley</name>, two years later. Through her, he acquired <name type="house">"Portobogo,"</name> <name type="county">Essex</name> (later, <name type="county">Caroline) County</name>. He was a justice of the peace. (<cit><bibl n="M6">Lomax Family Bible.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="PL" type="person">LUDWELL, PHILLIP,</name> (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1638-1717?), emigrated from <name type="country">England</name> about 1660, rising to Council membership in 1675. He supported 
Governor Sir <name type="person">William Berkeley</name> during Bacon's Rebellion, and married Berkeley's widow, Frances, in 1677. He was a stormy character, fighting with governors, losing and winning back his Council seat on two occasions. He returned to England where he represented the <name type="organization">House of Burgesses</name>, later served as governor of Northern Carolina and of North and <name type="place">South Carolina</name>, returning to England in 1700 where he lived seventeen more years. (<cit><bibl n="A10">"Ludwell Family"</bibl></cit>;  <cit><bibl>"Philip Ludwell's Account," <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography</title>, 1(1893-1894): 174-186</bibl></cit>; and the <cit><bibl><title>Dictionary of American Biography.</title></bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="PL1" type="person">LUDWELL, PHILLIP</name> (1672-1727), 
auditor, member of and president of the Council, and rector of the <name type="organization">College of William and Mary.</name> (<cit><bibl n="A10">"Ludwell Family." </bibl></cit>)  <lb/><lb/>

<name id="DM" type="person">McCARTY, DANIEL</name> (1679-1724), son of <name type="person">Dennis McCarty</name> (d. 1694) of <name 
type="county">Richmond County</name>, an attorney, sheriff 
(1710-1712), and longtime burgess from <name
type="county">Westmoreland County</name> (1705-1724), Speaker of the House of Burgesses in 1715 and 1718. He married <name type="person">Ann Lee</name>, daughter of the second <name type="person">Richard Lee</name>, and widow of the second <name type="person">William Fitzhugh</name>. (<cit><bibl n="B1">Kukla. <title>Speakers and Clerks. . . .</title> pp. 113-118.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="MF" type="farm">MANGORITE</name></q> (or Mangorike) was a farm in <name type="county">Richmond County</name> <q>in the vicinity of present Downing Bridge spanning the Rappahannock and present-day Little Carter Creek. . . . It consisted of 1,800 acres belonging to Colonel Moore Fauntleroy in the seventeenth century.</q> RC  bequeathed it to Landon Carter. (<cit><bibl n="B29">Miller, <title>Place-Names . . .</title>, p. 93.</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="B30">Greene, <title>The Diary of Colonel Landon Carter. . . .</title>, 5.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>
                                  
<name id="JM" type="person">MATHEWS, JONATHAN,</name>  <name type="city">London</name> merchant, probably a member of the <name type="organization">Stationers Company</name>. He and his partner, <note n="JG"><name  type="person">John Goodwin</name></note>, with <note n="WC1"><name  type="person">William Churchill,</name></note> and RC owned the <hi rend="italics">Friendly Society</hi>, a 60-ton vessel trading from <name type="city">London</name> to <name type="island">Barbados</name> and Virginia. (<cit><bibl n="B13">Horwitz, <hi rend="italics">et al.</hi>  <title>London Politics 1713-1717. . . .</title> p. 103.</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="M7">"Collector's Return . . .,"  ff. 160.</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<name id="RM" type="person">MEEKS, RICHARD,</name> was described by RC in a letter of July 15, 1720, as the <q>general overseer</q> of the property that he consistently referred to by its tobacco mark of a double arrowhead or double <q>L</q>; it was the Lloyd properties belonging to <name type="person">John Lloyd,</name> widower of RC's niece, Elizabeth. Lloyd went to England about 1700. RC apparently leased the lands from him.<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="MH" type="house">MERCHANT'S HUNDRED</name></q>  is six miles southeast of <name type="town">Williamsburg;</name> in his will, RC directed that it be called <q><name type="house">Carter's Grove</name></q> in perpetuity, and this is the name it bears today. The house on the property today was built by RC's grandson, <name type="person">Carter Burwell,</name> beginning about 1750. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="AM">MOORE, AUGUSTINE,</name> (c. 1685-c.1734), of <q><name type="house">Chelsea,</name></q> <name type="county">King William County,</name> a justice and prominent leader. (<cit><bibl>J.H.P., "The Gorsuch and Lovelace Families," <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography.</title> 25(1917): pp. 431-44.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="MF1" type="farm">MORATTICO</name></q> was a large farm of some 1,800 acres in <name type="county">Richmond County</name> where there were several of that name. RC had bought it from <name type="person">Moore Fauntleroy;</name> <q>it was located on the hill just south of the present Totuskey Bridge.</q> The farm had eight slaves, thirty-six hogs, and a horse in the 1732 inventory of RC's estate. (<cit><bibl n="B29">Miller, <title>Place-Names of the Northern Neck. . . .</title>,  19, 102-103.</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="MF2" type="farm">MOUNTAIN</name></q> was a farm in <name type="county">Spotsylvania County;</name> in the inventory of RC's estate, it had 22 slaves, 7 horses, 73 hogs, and 59 cattle. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="NF" type="farm">NANSATICO</name></q> may be the Nanzatico Indian Path in <q><name type="county">Westmoreland County</name> near the King George County line. . . .</q> (<cit><bibl n="B29">Miller,  <title>Place-Names of the Northern Neck. . . .</title>,  19.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="FN" type="person">NICHOLSON, FRANCIS,</name> (1655-1728), professional soldier and administrator of five colonies,  served rather successfully in Virginia as lieutenant governor, June 1690-March 1692, and was then sent to Maryland. He returned to Virginia to serve a contentious term as  governor of the colony from 1698 to 1705. After his recall from Virginia, he served as governor of New York. (<cit><bibl><title>Dictionary of American Biography</title></bibl></cit>; <bibl id="A22">"Papers Relating to the Administration of Governor Nicholson and to the Founding of William and Mary College." <title>Virginia Magazine of History and
 Biography.</title> 2(1894-1895): 46-64</bibl>; and <cit><bibl n="B27">Billings. <hi rend="italics">et al.,</hi> <title>Colonial Virginia: A History, </title> esp. Chapter 7, "The Era of the Council."</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="NH2" type="farm">NOMINI</name></q>  or <q><name type="house">Nomini Hall</name></q> as it would later be called, was a tract originally containing about 3,500 acres in <name type="county">Westmoreland County</name> <q>south of Machodoc and Beales Corner near Howard's Fork</q>on Nomini Creek, which flows into the Potomac River.  RC built the original house there for his grandson, "Councillor" Robert Carter. (<cit><bibl id="B29">Miller.<title>Place-Names of the Northern Neck. . . .</title>,  p. 112.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="NF1" type="farm">NORMAN'S FORD</name></q> was a farm located on an important <name type="river">Rappahannock River</name> (earlier Hedgeman's River) crossing on the old Iroquois trail, later called the Carolina Road. Fairfax Harrison states that it received its name because <name type="person">Isaac Norman</name> patented the land in June 1726, but RC  referred to it by this name four years earlier. It is located where U.S. 29 and U.S. 15 cross the Rappahannock between Culpeper and Fauquier counties. <name type="person">Roger Oxford</name> was the overseer. ("The Old Roads and the Ordinaries," in <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison,  <title>Landmarks of Old Prince William</title>, 441-517, esp. fn. 37 on p. 500.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JO" type="person">ODAR, JOSH</name> was one of RC's overseers and is mentioned often in the diary.<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="OF" type="farm">OFFICE</name></q> was a farm apparently not too far from <q>Corotoman</q> in <name type="county">Lancaster County</name> because Carter mentions in his diary visiting it fairly often. It had seven slaves, twenty-four hogs, and thirty-five cattle in 1732 inventory of RC's estate. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>.)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="OO" type="farm">OLD ORDINARY,</name></q> a tract in <name type="county">Westmoreland County</name>, had 15 slaves, 87 hogs, 57 cattle, 27 sheep, and 6 horses in the 1732 inventory of RC's estate; James Whaley was then its overseer. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>.)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JCP" type="person">PAGE, JUDITH (CARTER),</name> (1695-<hi rend="italics">ca. </hi>1750), Robert Carter's fifth child "and the last by  his wife, <name type="person">Judith Armistead</name>, [and] was also named Judith following the first Judith who died in infancy. . . . She was the grandmother of <name type="person">John Page</name>, Governor of Virginia" through her marriage to <note n="MP1">Mann Page.</note> (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 211.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="MP1" type="person">PAGE, MANN,</name> (1691-1730), of <q>Rosewell,</q> <name type="county">Gloucester County,</name> married in late July or early August 1718 <note n="JCP"><name type="person">Judith Carter</name></note>, Robert Carter's fifth child by his wife <name n="JAC">Judith Armistead</name>. Page attended Eton and Oxford, and was appointed to the Council shortly after returning to Virginia. In 1726 he began the house at <q>Rosewell</q> but he did not live to complete it. <name type="person">Mann Page II</name> finished the construction; the house burned in 1916, and it is now a <q>romantic and  noble ruin.</q> (<cit><bibl n="A11">"Council Proceedings." <title>Virginia Magazine. . . .</title></bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="B25">O'Neal. <title>Architecture in Virginia. . . . </title> p. 101.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="PQ" type="farm">PARK QUARTER</name></q> lay in <name type="county">Stafford County.</name> In the 1732 inventory of RC's estate, <name type="person">James Seben</name> was overseer; it had twenty-four slaves, four horses, thirty-eight hogs, and fifty-four cattle. Carter bequeathed it to his son <note n="GC">George</note> and it came to Landon Carter in 1741 after George's death. (<cit><bibl n="B30">Greene. <title>The Diary of Colonel Landon Carter. . . .</title>, p. 5.</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>.)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JP" type="person">PEMBERTON, JOHN,</name> (d. 1744), merchant of 
<name type="city">Liverpool,</name> one of Robert Carter's most frequent correspondents. His was an old mercantile family; a John Pemberton, tailor, was removed from the Common Council of Liverpool in 1662 for failure to take the oath required by a Parliamentary act of that year. The later Pemberton  was a devout churchman as his name appears frequently in the vestry books. He is credited with being a leader in the economic revival of Liverpool in the early eighteenth century. (<cit><bibl n="B15">Picton. <title>City of Liverpool. . . . </title></bibl></cit>; <cit><bibl n="B14">Peet. <title>Liverpool Vestry Books. . . . </title></bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="A13">Clemens. "The Rise of Liverpool, 1665-1750."</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="MP" type="person">PERRY, MICAJAH,</name> (d. 1721), eminent <name type="city">London</name> merchant deeply involved in the colonial tobacco and other trade. With his brother Richard, and <name type="person">Thomas Lane</name>, he operated the firm of <name type="commercial">Perry, Lane and Company</name>. Another brother, <name type="person">Peter Perry</name>,  was a merchant in <name type="county">York County</name>, Virginia. Perry frequently represented the interests of Virginia in England, both officially and unofficially, and was often consulted when questions concerning Virginia were 
discussed by government bodies ranging from the <name type="governmental">Board of Trade</name> to <name type="governmental">Parliament</name>. There is some evidence that he had visited Virginia himself; he was widely knowledgeable about its citizens. (<cit><bibl n="A14">Donnan. "18th-Century English Merchants:  Micajah Perry,"</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B22">Price. <title>Perry of London. . . . </title></bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="PQ1" type="farm">POPLAR QUARTER</name></q> was a  <name type="county">Stafford County</name> farm, and <name type="person">William Threalkill</name> was the overseer there in the 1732 inventory of RC's estate, directing fourteen slaves with twenty-five hogs and thirty-one cattle on the farm. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>.)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="JP1" type="person">PURVIS, JOHN</name>, probably a <name type="city">London</name> merchant; one of the owners of the <hi rend="italics">Industry</hi>. <lb/><lb/>

<name  id="JR" type="person">RANDOLPH, JOHN</name> (1693-1737),  called to the bar in England in 1717.  He was appointed clerk 
of the <name type="governmental">House of Burgesses</name> after he returned to the colony where he carried on an extensive private practice, acted as 
Attorney General in 1726-1727, and filled other offices. He returned to 
England in 1728 as the agent of the colony, and was agent again in 
1732. At this time, he became very friendly with Sir <name type="person">Robert Walpole</name>, and won a knighhood for his work for the colony, the only colonial figure to be so rewarded. (<cit><bibl n="B1">Kukla. <title>Speakers and Clerks. . . . </title> pp. 118-123.</bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="RO" type="farm">RED OAK QUARTER</name></q> was in <name type="county">Prince William County</name>; in the  1732 inventory of RC's estate, <name type="person">John Wilcox</name> was overseer, and there were fourteen slaves, fifty-one hogs, forty-one cattle, and one horse. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>.)<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="RF1" type="farm">RICHLAND</name></q> was a farm located in <name type="county">King George County.</name> In the 1732 inventory of RC's estate, it had thirteen slaves, one horse named <q>Mountain,</q> seventy hogs, and fifty-five cattle. <name type="person">Tim Stamps</name> was the overseer here in 1726. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>.)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="WR" type="person">ROBERTSON, WILLIAM,</name> (d. 1739), an attorney, became clerk of the <name type="governmental">General Assembly</name> on May 13, 1702, and served until shortly 
before his death. He also served as clerk of the Council. (<cit><bibl n="B1">Kukla, <title>Speakers. . . . </title> pp. 120 and 148.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="WR1" type="person">ROBINSON, WILLIAM,</name> (d. <hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1721), of <name type="county">Richmond County,</name> a justice and burgess. (<cit><bibl n="B16">Inventory in Torrance, <title>Virginia Wills. . . . </title></bibl></cit>) <lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="RP" type="house">ROSEGILL</name></q> is the Wormeley home in <name type="county">Middlesex County</name>; it lies between <name type="house">Rosegill Lake</name> and Urbanna Creek, close to today's town of Urbana, and is slightly up and across the Rappahannock from <q><name type="house">Corotoman.</name></q><lb/><lb/>

<name id="NS" type="person">SMITH, NICHOLAS,</name> (1666-1734), of <name type="county">Richmond County</name>; he was justice and coroner, and later was on the first slate of justices for <name type="county">King George County</name> when it was formed in 1720; he served as burgess from King George as well. (<cit><bibl>C. W. Coleman. "Genealogy of the Smith Family of Essex County, Virginia," <title>William and Mary Quarterly</title>, 2d sers., 25(1916-17): 170-83.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="CS1" type="person">STAGG, CHARLES</name>  was a major overseer. There are many references to him in RC's diary where he is usually referred to as <q>Mr.</q><lb/><lb/>

<name id="WS" type="person">STROTHER, WILLIAM</name> (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1665-1726),  a prominent citizen of <name type="county">King George County</name> where he was a justice, sheriff, and burgess. His home lay two miles below the falls of the Rappahannock River. After his death, his widow sold the place to <name type="person">Augustine Washington.</name> Later called <q>Ferry Farm,</q> it was the boyhood home of <name type="person">George Washington</name>. Strother directed the work on <q>Carter's Mount</q> whose location is not presently known. (<cit><bibl>"Historical and Genealogical Notes," <title>William and Mary Quarterly.</title> 1st sers., 1(1892-93): 23, 143</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl>George Harrison Sanford King, "Washington's Boyhood Home," <title>William and Mary Quarterly.</title> 1st sers., 17(1908-09): 265-281</bibl></cit>.)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="AS" type="person">SWAN, ALEXANDER,</name> (d. 1710), of <name type="county">Lancaster County</name> was Robert Carter's brother-in-law through his marriage to <name type="person">Mary (Landon) Jones</name> (d. c. 1722). <lb/><lb/>

<name id="MJS" type="person">SWAN, MARY (LANDON) JONES,</name> (d. 1722) married first <name type="person">John Jones</name>, and later Captain <name type="person">Alexander Swan</name> of <name type="county">Lancaster County</name> who died in 1710. She died in 1722 leaving her property to the Carters. (<cit><bibl n="A17">"Pinkard Family." <title>William and Mary Quarterly</title></bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="A18">"The Landon Family." <title>Virginia Magazine. . . .</title></bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/> 

<name id="ET" type="person">TUCKER, EDWARD,</name> (d. 1739), merchant of <name type="city">Weymouth</name>, <name type="county">Dorset</name>, a prominent figure in that town, serving as mayor in 1705, 1716, 1721, 1725, and 1735, and as a member 
of Parliament. (<cit><bibl n="B6">Sedgwick. <title>The History of Pariament . . . Commons.</title> II, 485-6.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="GT" type="person">TURBERVILLE, GEORGE,</name> (d. 1742), of <q><name type="house">Hickory Hill</name></q> in Cople Parish, <name type="county">Westmoreland County,</name> a justice and burgess. He married <name type="person">Lettice Fitzhugh.</name>  (<cit><bibl>"The Fitzhugh Family," <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography</title>, 7(1899-1900): 196-199, 317-319, and 425-427</bibl></cit>; and  <cit><bibl n="B38">Norris. <title>Westmoreland County Virginia.</title></bibl></cit>.)<lb/><lb/>

<name id="WW" type="person">WAUGH, WILLIAM,</name>  an important overseer for RC until his death in January 1726; he seems to have been in charge of Jackson's mill as well.<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="WF" type="farm">WICCOCOMOCO</name></q>  was a farm owned by RC, probably located in <name type="county">Northumberland County</name> where there is a creek of this name.<lb/><lb/>

<q><name id="WH" type="farm">WOLF HOUSE</name></q> was a farm owned by RC located in <name type="county">Lancaster County</name> relatively close to Corotoman.<lb/><lb/>

<name id="EW" type="person">WORMELEY, ELIZABETH</name> (1682-1740), daughter of <name n="RW" type="person">Ralph Wormeley</name> (1650-1701) and <name type="person">Katherine Lunsford</name>; she married, on June 1, 1703, Dr. <note n="JL"><name type="person">John Lomax</name></note>. (<cit><bibl n="M6">Lomax Family Bible.</bibl></cit> )<lb/><lb/>

<name id="EAW" type="person">WORMELEY, ELIZABETH (ARMISTEAD)</name> was RC's sister-in-law through his first wife, <note n="JAC">Judith Armistead</note>, her sister. She married <note n="RW">Ralph Wormeley,</note> and was mother of Ralph (ca. 1681-1714) and John (1689-1727) for whom RC was one of a number of trustees.<lb/><lb/>

<name id="RW" type="person">WORMELEY, RALPH</name> (1650-1701), member of the Council and Secretary of State of Virginia, who lived at <q>Rosegill,</q> <name type="county">Middlesex County</name>. He was RC's brother-in-law, having married <note n="EAW"><name type="person">Elizabeth Armistead,</name></note> sister of <name n="JAC" type="person">Judith Armistead,</name> RC's first wife. <lb/><lb/>

 </p>

</div1>

</body>
</text>


</TEI.2>