<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>

<TEI.2 id="C02d08a">



 
<text id="C02d08aT"> 

<pb n="8"/> 
<body> 
 
<div1 type="document" n="1702-04-08"> 
<head><q>BY WAY OF REPLY TO COLLO. JENINGS'S PROPOSITIONS ABOUT THE 
WILL OF 
ESQR. WORMELEY DECEAS'D.</q><lb/> 
</head> 
 
<opener> 
<dateline> 
<name type="place">Rappa<add>hannock, Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia</add><lb/> 
Aprill the 6th. 1702</name> 
 
<date n="1702-04-06"></date> 
</dateline> 
 
<salute></salute> 
 
</opener> 
 
<p>That the <bibl target="n10">Widdow</bibl> hath her Choice out of the Household goods to 
the 
<lb/>Totall: of One hundred pounds, is plain from the Will.</p> 
<P>That she hath a Right to a fifth of the Personall Estate and ought [to] <lb/>be Serv'd in point 
of 
Choice is what I have Deliver'd as my Opinion <lb/>before this Day; tho' Seem'd to be Doubted 
by some 
Others.</P> 
<P>That she hath a Right of Dower in the Lands is beyond Controversy, <lb/>if it Can be done 
by 
apportioning plantations &amp;ca. as near an equ[al] <lb/>as may be `twill be the Easiest Way, 
but if this 
wont Satisfie the Widdow <lb/>Dower Comes to be assign'd her, he will be a Friend to the Estate 
<lb/>Can find a way to Lay it out without Charge for my part I Can['t]</P> 
<P>That Mrs. Eliza. Wormeley after the Widdows Choice of the Personall Estate [...] <lb/>out, 
hath the 
Choice of a Negro, is also the Plain English of the Will, and [she] <lb/>hath bin without him soe 
Long; 
hath bin and is a prejudice [to ?] <lb/>be granted and the only thing that I know Off, wherein 
any[thing] 
<lb/>in the Will hath bin a Sufferer for want of an Earlier Div[ision] <lb/>ont is 'tis only the 
Labour of a 
Negro for a few Months.</P> 
<P>That she hath already had the Other Legacys given to her [...] <lb/>it hath bin I suppose for 
want of 
fetching, That Collo [...] <lb/>about her Provision, That the Twenty pounds per ann. for he[r 
provision?] 
<lb/>Due to her as the Year Runs Out, and no Doubt ought to b[e paid?] <lb/>Collo. Jenings who 
Shipt 
the Yourk Tobaccoes Scruple [...] <lb/>to Apply too me, I will give her the Bills, Running the 
Haza[rd] 
<lb/>and so I shall Yearly while I am Concern'd wth. the Estate</P> 
<P>That <note id="11">Madm. Corbin</note> [11] hath a Legacy of Fifty pounds given her b[y 
the will 
is] <lb/>also very plain, but whether the Tobacco made use of by Collo. Cor[bin be<lb/>]long'd to 
the 
Estate in Gloster &amp; Westmoreland Countys goes in Q[uitt rents] <lb/>that Legacy or no is to 
me a 
Secrett, If Collo. Corbin hath any further [...] <lb/>none soe fitt as Collo. Jenings to settle it with 
him, and 
no Doubt [he] <lb/>Effects enough from the Concern under his Management to answer [that] 
<lb/>and a 
great Deale more.</P> 
<P>That the Will of Our Testator as I take it to be the Basis of our powe[r] <lb/>being held to the 
Glass 
of the Law, Ought to be the Directory to Our pro[ceeding] <lb/>and shall be soe to mine as far as 
I know 
it tho' in the Will Wee are [called] <lb/>Trustees, in Law Sence I apprehend Wee are Executors 
(the other 
Term [is] <lb/>no Law Phrase) and have the full power of Such Durante Minorita[te We]<lb/> 
want not 
any Deputation from One Another to Enable Us for the [manage]<lb/>ment of the Estate, Nor for 
my part 
shall I ever seek any, I have alre[ady] <lb/>paid Severall Debts and will pay all that Comes that 
appeares 
to be <lb/>I have paid the Quitt Rents Levys &amp;c. of the Estate, I sent for Clothes [and] 
<lb/>Other 
Necessarys for the familys Last year (wch. by the Providence of [God was] <lb/>Lost in Burford, 
I have 
bin providing as well as I Can for them in the Coun[try] <lb/>and Notwithstanding Collo. Jenings 
Opinion 
(who I am told has [open?]<lb/>ly said the Lost Goods I am Lyable for and he might as well 
[...]</P> 
<P>Collo. Corbin ought to bear the Loss of those he sent for, and the Tobaccoe <lb/>Shipt Last 
Year by 
Collo. Jenings went upon his Risqe. I shall send again <lb/>to England as soon as I Can for 
more,</P> 
<P>That in Shipping the Tobaccoes what I am Concern'd in, I shall Chiefly <lb/>Consider the 
Interest of 
the Children, wch. will be to send most to them who <lb/>makes the best Returns and when there 
is 
Money before hand, to Lodge <lb/>it in the Ablest hands where there is least appearance of 
failure, wch. 
is <lb/>the Method I observe to my self in my Own affairs, I have no Friends or <lb/>Relations 
there 
further then they Rendr. themselves by their good Managmt. <lb/>in my favour.</P> 
<P>That the Books of Accots. Papers &amp;c. Remain where they were to be <lb/>Viewed by 
the 
Trustees when they Please, but the Debts are soe Incon<lb/>siderable, Except the Sheriffs &amp; 
Clerks 
Accots. they are hardly Worth the <lb/>Solemn Way of Settling propos'd</P> 
<P>I shall be at all Times most Ready to give an Accot. to my Companions as <lb/>far as I am 
Concern'd 
in Management when they Desire it, but for a Dictatorshipp amongst Us I am unwilling to yeild 
to; will 
Rather <lb/>Cease to Meddle wth. any Dead Mans Estate while I Live </P> 
<P>The following is an Accot. of my Proceedings hitherto.</P> 
<P>A Short Time after the Death of Esqr. Wormeley, Wee took probate upon his <lb/>will, 
Collo. 
Jenings not there, and that Wee might be Enabled for the Divi<lb/>sion Mov'd the Court that an 
appraisement might be made by Judicious <lb/>Gentlemen and Obtained Order Accordingly. 
Severall 
Meetings Wee <lb/>had Month after Month, where I Constantly attended for the Division, but 
<lb/>for 
want of a Suitable Nombrs. of Appraisers, The Matter was not Effected <lb/>till December, 
Collo. 
Jennings at none of those Times, meeting, In the <lb/>mean time, I have not bin wanting in taking 
Care of 
the business of the Plan<lb/>tations, a very Good Cropp was made, is Preizd, and Freight I have 
<lb/>taken for the most part if not all, Good Overseers Settled for the Ensuing <lb/>year, and the 
plantations in very good Order.</P> 
<P>The Cropp made by Esqr. Wormeley I shipt as followth. </P> 
<P>Tenn hhds went to Mr. Corbin, wich I Left my Own Tobaccoe out for <lb/>and Lay by me all 
the 
year, He Writes me Generall he had sold for <lb/>Nine pence 1/2 But no Accot. as yett. Sixteen 
hogsheads went to Mr. Lee <lb/>of the same Tobo. sold at Nine pence 3/4, Tenn pence, and Tenn 
pence 
1/4 <lb/>he hath sent an Accot. of Sales but no accot. Currtt. Twenty seven hogsheads <lb/>went 
to 
Mathews &amp; Goodwin He writes but Two hogsheads were sold stript Leaf at <lb/>Tenn pence 
1/2, 
and that Price for the stemn'd, and Tenn pence for the Leaf he<lb/> hoped to Reach for them 
all.</P> 
<P>The Goods for the familys use Lost as above were sent for to Mathews &amp;c. 
<lb/>Amounting as 
per Invoice to &pound;86:2:2.</P> 
<P>Many Journeys I have made, and many more shall if I Continue in <lb/>the Managery of any 
part of 
the Estate tho' heartly Wish I were fairly Dis<lb/>Charg'd I have other Buizness enough for my 
Time 
&amp; thoughts,</P> 
<P>Could I Answer it to the Dead, and to the Living, should hard[ly] <lb/>Turmoile my Self wth. 
Other 
Mens Estate without the Least appear[ance] <lb/>of Profitt. Collo. Jenings hath but once pass'd 
yourk 
River <lb/>all this Time, I will not say to pay a Visit to a Bro[the]r but upon [cal]<lb/>le Submitt 
it to 
Judgement, to whom Esqr. Wormeleys Children [are] <lb/>most Oblig'd</P> 
<P>     As to the Division soe much urg'd for, it had bin Effected no d[oubt] <lb/>Long before 
now if all 
the Trustees had attended the appraisme[nt] <lb/>and it shall not be my fault, if it be not Effected 
soe soon 
a[s a] <lb/>full meeting of the Trustees Can be had for the Doing of it, [as] <lb/>for the Ninth of 
this 
Month to begin as propos'd, I Cannot possib[ly] <lb/>be soe long from home having a Publick 
Call to be 
att Willi[ams]<lb/>Burgh on the 15th. and perhapps must stay there for a Month or [six?] 
<lb/>Weeks 
together, Not having that great Conveniancy som[e per]<lb/>sons has of Lying every Night at 
home if 
they please</P> 
<P>Perhapps the Widdow may be upon Designs of Tasting the Swts. of [matri]<lb/>mony a 
Second 
Time, If soe a Hasty Division seems mos[t evi]<lb/>dent; Otherwise I must Reassume my former 
Opinion 
<lb/>it is most for the Childrens advantage the Estate Rema[in] as it is.</P> 
<p>As soon as may be after the Genll. Court <lb/>I shall be Ready to attend a Division  
 
 
</p> 
 
<closer> 
<salute></salute> 
</closer> 
 
</div1> 
 
<back> 
<div1 type="notes"> 
<head>Notes</head> 
 
<sourcedesc> source note here</sourcedesc><lb/> 
<note id="10">****</note> 
<note id="n11">Catherine (Wormeley) Corbin (d. <hi>ante</hi> 1707), daughter of Ralph 
Wormeley, was 
Gawin Corbin's first (of three) wives. <bibl id="A7"><q>Corbin Family</q></bibl>, VMHB 29 
(1921), 
520-528.</note> 
</div1> 
</back> 
 
</text> 


</TEI.2>
