<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2  SYSTEM  'teixlite.dtd' [ 
<!NOTATION jpg  SYSTEM  "jpeg"> 
<!ENTITY filename  SYSTEM  "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg> 
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM  "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1; 
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM  "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM  "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM  "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM  "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; 
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="C02d06a"> 
<teiHeader type="aacr2"> 
              
<fileDesc> 
<titleStmt> 
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to the trustees of Ralph Wormeley's estate, 1702 April 6</title> 
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title> 
     <author>Carter, Robert</author> 
   <respStmt> 
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp> 
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name> 
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp> 
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr., and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name> 
   </respStmt> 
</titleStmt> 
 
<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes </extent> 
 
<publicationStmt> 
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher> 
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace> 
     <idno type="ETC"></idno> 
     <availability> 
     <p>Publicly accessible</p> 
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/modeng.browse.html</p> 
         </availability> 
     <date>2001</date> 
</publicationStmt> 
 
<sourceDesc> 
     <biblFull> 
     <titleStmt> 
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to the trustees of Ralph Wormeley's estate, 1702 April 6</title> 

     <author>Carter, Robert</author> 
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent> 
<publicationStmt> 
     <date>1702-04-06</date> 
   <idno type="callNo"> Source copy consulted: Christ Church Parish, Lancaster County, 
Processioners' Returns, 1711-1783,and Wormeley Estate Papers, 1701-1710, 1716, Acc. 30126, 
Archives Research Services, Library of Virginia, Richmond, 147-149. The letter book contains a copy of 
Edmund Jenings's proposals, and an account "of the Profitts of the Secretary's Place Accrewing Due from 
the Public Clerks . . . 1700." 
</idno> 
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull> 
</sourceDesc> 
 
</fileDesc> 
     <encodingDesc> 
     <projectDesc> 
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p> 
     </projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl> 
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing 
analytical groupings.</p> 
</editorialDecl> 
 
<classDecl> 
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
     <bibl> 
     <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
     </bibl> 
     </taxonomy> 
</classDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
 
<profileDesc> 
     <creation> 
     <date>1702-04-06</date> 
     </creation> 
     <langUsage> 
     <language id="eng"></language> 
     </langUsage> 
     <textClass> 
     <keywords> 
     <term>non-fiction</term> 
   <term>prose</term> 
     </keywords> 
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term> 
     </keywords> 
     </textClass> 
</profileDesc> 
 
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="C02d06aT"> 


<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1702-04-06">April 6, 1702</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C02d06a</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to the trustees of Ralph Wormeley's estate, 1702 April 6</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter states his positions concerning the interpretation of the will of Ralph Wormeley and the actions he has taken with the portion of the estate under his control. He notes his differences in interpretation and action with Edmund Jenings as well as his willingness to meet the other trustees as soon as his responsibilites at the General Court in Williamsburg are completed.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body> 
 
<div1 type="letter" n="1702-04-06"> 
 
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to the Trustees<lb/>
 of <note n="RW">Ralph Wormeley's </note>Estate, April 6, 1702</head> 
 
<opener> 
 
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>  
<name type="place">Rappa<add n="ed">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/> 
 
<date value="1702-04-06">April 6, 1702</date> 
</dateline> 
 
                                             
<salute>By Way of Reply to <abbr expan="Colonel">Collo</abbr> Jenings's Propositions about the<lb/> 
Will of <note n="RW"><abbr expan="Esquire ">Esqr. </abbr> Wormeley</note> <sic corr="Deceased">Deceas'd</sic>.</salute> 
                   
</opener> 
 
<p>That the <sic corr="Widow ">Widdow</sic> hath her Choice out of the Household goods to the <lb/><sic corr="Total ">Totall</sic>: of One hundred 
pounds, is plain from the Will.</p>                                    
 
<p>That she hath a Right to a fifth of the <sic corr="Personal ">Personall</sic> Estate and ought <add resp="editor">[to]</add> <lb/>be 
Serv'd in point of Choice is what I have Deliver'd as my Opinion <lb/>before this Day; <abbr expan="though ">tho' </abbr> Seem'd to be 
Doubted by some Others.</p> 
 
<p>That she hath a Right of Dower in the Lands is beyond Controversy, <lb/>if it Can be done by 
apportioning plantations &amp;ca. as near an equ<add resp="editor">[al]</add> <lb/>as may be <abbr expan="it will ">`twill </abbr> be the 
Easiest Way, but if this wont Satisfie the Widdow <lb/>Dower Comes to be assign'd her, he will be a 
Friend to the Estate <lb/>Can find a way to Lay it out without Charge for my part I 
Can<add resp="editor">['t]</add></p> 
 
<p>That Mrs. <abbr expan="Elizabeth ">Eliza </abbr>. Wormeley after the <sic corr="Widows ">Widdows </sic> Choice of the <sic corr="Personal ">Personall </sic> Estate 
<add resp="editor">[. . .]</add> <lb/>out, hath the Choice of a Negro, is also the Plain English of the Will, and 
<add resp="editor">[she]</add> <lb/>hath <sic corr="been ">bin</sic> without him <sic corr="so ">soe</sic> Long; hath <sic corr="been ">bin</sic> and is a prejudice 
<add resp="editor">[to ?]</add> <lb/>be granted and the only thing that I know <sic corr="Of, ">Off,</sic> wherein 
any<add resp="editor">[thing]</add> <lb/>in the Will hath <sic corr="been ">bin</sic> a Sufferer for want of an Earlier 
Div<add resp="editor">[ision]</add> <lb/>ont is <abbr expan="it is ">'tis </abbr> only the Labour of a Negro for a few Months.</p> 

<p>That she hath already had the Other Legacys given to her <add resp="editor">[ . . . ]</add> <lb/>it hath <sic corr="been ">bin</sic> I 
suppose for want of fetching, That <abbr expan="Colonel">Collo </abbr><add resp="editor">[ . . . ]</add> <lb/>about her Provision, That the 
Twenty pounds per <abbr expan="annum ">ann. </abbr> for he<add resp="editor">[r provision?]</add> <lb/>Due to her as the Year Runs 
Out, and no Doubt ought to b<add resp="editor">[e paid?]</add> <lb/><note n="EJ"><abbr expan="Colonel">Collo </abbr> Jenings</note> who <sic corr="Shipped ">Shipt</sic> the <name 
type="place"><sic corr="York ">Yourk </sic></name> <sic corr="Tobaccos">Tobaccoes</sic> Scruple <add resp="editor">[ . . . ]</add> <lb/>to Apply <sic corr="to ">too</sic> me, I will 
give her the Bills, Running the Haza<add resp="editor">[rd]</add> <lb/>and so I shall Yearly while I am 
Concern'd wth. the Estate</p> 
 
<p>That <note target="n1"><abbr expan="Madam ">Madm. </abbr> Cor<sic corr="been ">bin</sic></note> hath a Legacy of Fifty pounds given her 
b<add resp="editor">[y the will is]</add> <lb/>also very plain, but whether the Tobacco made use of by 
<abbr expan="Colonel">Collo </abbr> Cor<add resp="editor">[bin be]</add><lb/>-long'd to the Estate in <name type="place"><sic corr="Gloucester">Gloster</sic></name> &amp; <name type="place">Westmoreland</name> Countys 
goes in Q<add resp="editor">[uitt rents]</add> <lb/>that Legacy or no is to me a <sic corr="Secret, ">Secrett,</sic> If <note 
n="GC1"><abbr expan="Colonel">Collo </abbr> Cor<sic corr="been ">bin</sic></note> hath any further <add resp="editor">[ . . . ] </add><lb/>none <sic corr="so ">soe</sic> <sic corr="fit ">fitt</sic> as 
<abbr expan="Colonel">Collo </abbr> Jenings to settle it with him, and no Doubt <add resp="editor">[he]</add> <lb/>Effects enough from 
the Concern under his Management to answer <add resp="editor">[that]</add> <lb/>and a great <sic corr="Deal ">Deale</sic> 
more.</p> 
 
<p>That the Will of Our Testator as I take it to be the Basis of our powe<add resp="editor">[r]</add> 
<lb/>being held to the Glass of the Law, Ought to be the Directory to Our 
pro<add resp="editor">[ceeding]</add> <lb/>and shall be <sic corr="so ">soe</sic> to mine as far as I know it <abbr expan="though ">tho' </abbr> in the Will Wee 
are <add resp="editor">[called]</add> <lb/>Trustees, in Law Sence I apprehend <sic corr="we ">Wee</sic> are Executors (the other 
Term <add resp="editor">[is]</add> <lb/>no Law Phrase) and have the full power of Such <note 
target="n2"><sic corr="durante minore aetate">Durante Minorita</sic></note> <add resp="editor">[te 
We]</add> <lb/>want not any Deputation from One Another to Enable Us for the 
<add resp="editor">[manage]</add><lb/>-ment of the Estate, Nor for my part shall I ever seek any, I have 
alre<add resp="editor">[ady]</add> <lb/>paid <sic corr="Several ">Severall </sic> Debts and will pay all that Comes that appeares to be 
<lb/>I have paid the <sic corr="Quit ">Quitt</sic> Rents Levys &amp;c. of the Estate, I sent for Clothes 
<add resp="editor">[and]</add> <lb/>Other Necessarys for the familys Last year (wch. by the Providence of 
<add resp="editor">[God was]</add> <lb/>Lost in <note n="JB2">Burford</note>, I have <sic corr="been ">bin</sic> providing 
as well as I Can for them in the Coun<add resp="editor">[try]</add> <lb/>and Notwithstanding <abbr expan="Colonel">Collo </abbr> Jenings Opinion (who I am told has <add resp="editor">[open?]</add><lb/>-ly said the Lost Goods I am <sic corr="Liable ">Lyable</sic> for 
and he might as well <add resp="editor">[ . . . ]</add></p> 
 
<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/> 
<p><abbr expan="Colonel">Collo </abbr> Cor<sic corr="been ">bin</sic> ought to bear the Loss of those he sent for, and the <sic corr="Tobacco ">Tobaccoe</sic> <lb/>Shipt Last Year by 
<abbr expan="Colonel">Collo </abbr> Jenings went upon his Risqe. I shall send again <lb/>to England as soon as I Can for more,</p> 
 
<p>That in Shipping the Tobaccoes  what I am Concern'd in, I shall Chiefly <lb/>Consider the Interest of 
the Children, wch. will be to send most to them who <lb/>makes the best Returns and when there is 
Money before hand, to Lodge <lb/>it in the Ablest hands where there is least appearance of failure, wch. 
is <lb/>the Method I observe to my self in my Own affairs, I have no Friends or <lb/>Relations there 
further then they <abbr expan="Render ">Rendr. </abbr> themselves by their good <abbr expan="Management ">Managmt. </abbr> in my favour.</p> 
 
<p>That the Books of Accots. Papers &amp;c. Remain where they were to be <lb/>Viewed by the 
Trustees when they Please, but the Debts are <sic corr="so ">soe</sic> Incon<lb/>-siderable, Except the Sheriffs &amp; Clerks 
Accots. they are hardly Worth the <lb/>Solemn Way of Settling propos'd</p> 
 
<p>I shall be at all Times most Ready to give an Accot. to my Companions as <lb/>far as I am Concern'd 
in Management when they Desire it, but for <lb/>a <sic corr="Dictatorship ">Dictatorshipp</sic> amongst Us I am unwilling to <sic 
corr="yield">yeild</sic> to; will Rather <lb/>Cease to Meddle wth. any Dead Mans Estate while I 
Live</p>  
 
<p>The following is an Accot. of my Proceedings hitherto.</p> 
 
<p>A Short Time after the Death of <abbr expan="Esquire ">Esqr. </abbr> Wormeley, <sic corr="we ">Wee </sic> took probate upon his <lb/>will, <abbr expan="Colonel">Collo </abbr> 
Jenings not there, and that <sic corr="we ">Wee </sic> might be Enabled for the Divi<lb/>-sion Mov'd the Court that an 
appraisement might be made by Judicious <lb/>Gentlemen and Obtained Order Accordingly. <sic corr="Several ">Severall</sic> 
Meetings <sic corr="we ">Wee </sic> <lb/>had Month after Month, where I Constantly attended for the Division, but <lb/>for 
want of a Suitable Nombrs. of Appraisers, The Matter was not Effected <lb/>till December, <abbr expan="Colonel">Collo </abbr> 
Jennings at none of those Times, meeting, In the <lb/>-mean time, I have not <sic corr="been ">bin</sic> wanting in taking Care 
of the business of the Plan<lb/>-tations, a very Good <sic corr="Crop ">Cropp</sic> was made, is <sic corr="prized">Preizd</sic>, 
and Freight I have <lb/>taken for the most part if not all, Good Overseers Settled for the Ensuing 
<lb/>year, and the plantations in very good Order.</p> 
 
<p>The <sic corr="Crop ">Cropp</sic> made by <abbr expan="Esquire ">Esqr. </abbr> Wormeley I <sic corr="shipped ">shipt</sic> as followth.</p>  
 
<p>Tenn hhds went to Mr. Cor<sic corr="been ">bin</sic>, wich I Left my Own <sic corr="Tobacco ">Tobaccoe </sic> out for <lb/>and Lay by me all the 
year, He Writes me <sic corr="General ">Generall</sic> he had sold for <lb/>Nine pence 1/2 But no Accot. as <sic corr="yet. ">yett.</sic> Sixteen 
hogsheads went to <note n="FL">Mr. Lee</note> <lb/>of the same Tobo. sold at Nine pence 3/4, Tenn pence, and Tenn pence 
1/4 <lb/>he hath sent an Accot. of Sales but no accot. Currtt. Twenty seven hogsheads <lb/>went to 
<note n="JM">Mathews</note> &amp; Goodwin He writes but Two hogsheads were sold <sic corr="stripted">stript</sic> Leaf at <lb/>Tenn pence 1/2, 
and that Price for the stemn'd, and Tenn pence for the Leaf he <lb/>hoped to Reach for them all.</p> 
 
<p>The Goods for the familys use Lost as above were sent for to Mathews &amp;c. <lb/>Amounting as 
per Invoice to &pound;86:2:2.</p> 
 
<p>Many Journeys I have made, and many more shall if I Continue in <lb/>the Managery of any part of 
the Estate <abbr expan="though ">tho' </abbr> heartly Wish I were fairly Dis<lb/>Charg'd I have other <sic 
corr="business">Buizness</sic> enough for my Time &amp; thoughts,</p> 
 
<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/> 
<p>Could I Answer it to the Dead, and to the Living, should hard<add resp="editor">[ly]</add> 
<lb/><sic corr="Turmoil ">Turmoile</sic> my Self wth. Other Mens Estate without the Least appear<add resp="editor">[ance]</add> 
<lb/>of <sic corr="Profit. ">Profitt.</sic> <abbr expan="Colonel">Collo </abbr> Jenings hath but once pass'd <sic corr="York">Yourk</sic> River <lb/>all this Time, 
I will not say to pay a Visit to a Bro<add resp="editor">[the]</add>r but upon 
<add resp="editor">[cal]</add><lb/>-le <sic corr="Submit ">Submitt</sic> it to Judgement, to whom <abbr expan="Esquire ">Esqr. </abbr> Wormeleys Children 
<add resp="editor">[are]</add> <lb/>most Oblig'd</p> 
 
<p>As to the Division <sic corr="so ">soe</sic> much urg'd for, it had <sic corr="been ">bin</sic> Effected no d<add resp="editor">[oubt]</add> 
<lb/>Long before now if all the Trustees had attended the appraisme<add resp="editor">[nt]</add> <lb/>and it 
shall not be my fault, if it be not Effected <sic corr="so ">soe</sic> soon a<add resp="editor">[s a]</add> <lb/>full meeting of the 
Trustees Can be had for the Doing of it, <add resp="editor">[as]</add> <lb/>for the Ninth of this Month to 
begin as propos'd, I Cannot possib<add resp="editor">[ly]</add> <lb/>be <sic corr="so ">soe</sic> long from home having a 
<sic corr="Public ">Publick</sic> Call to be <sic corr="at ">att</sic> Willi<add resp="editor">[ams]</add><lb/><sic corr="Burg ">Burgh</sic> on the 15th. and <sic corr="perhaps ">perhapps</sic> must stay 
there for a Month or <add resp="editor">[six?]</add> <lb/>Weeks together, Not having that great 
Conveniancy som<add resp="editor">[e per]</add><lb/>-sons has of Lying every Night at home if they 
please</p> 
 
<p><sic corr="Perhaps ">Perhapps</sic> the <sic corr="Widow ">Widdow</sic> may be upon Designs of Tasting the Sw<add resp="editor">[ee]</add>ts of 
<add resp="editor">[matri]</add><lb/>-mony a Second Time, If <sic corr="so ">soe</sic> a Hasty Division seems mos<add resp="editor">[t 
evi]</add><lb/>-dent; Otherwise I must Reassume my former Opinion <lb/>it is most for the 
Childrens advantage the Estate Rema<add resp="editor">[in]</add> <lb/>as it is.</p> 
 
<p>As soon as may be after the <abbr expan="General ">Genll. </abbr> Court <lb/>I shall be Ready to attend a Division</p>  

<p><abbr expan="Rappahannock">Rappa. </abbr> <sic corr="April">Aprill</sic> the 6th. 1702&mdash;</p>
 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
 
<back> 
<div1 type="notes"> 
<head>NOTES</head> 
 <note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi> Christ Church Parish, Lancaster County, 
Processioners' Returns, 1711-1783,and Wormeley Estate Papers, 1701-1710, 1716, Acc. 30126, Archives Research Services, Library of Virginia, Richmond, 147-149. The letter book contains a copy of Edmund Jenings's proposals, and an account "of the Profitts of the Secretary's Place Accrewing Due from the Public Clerks . . . 1700."  </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Catherine (Wormeley) Corbin (d. ante 1707), daughter of Ralph Wormeley, was Gawin Cor<sic corr="been ">bin</sic>'s first (of three) wives. (<cit><bibl n="A7">"The Cor<sic corr="been ">bin</sic> Family of Virginia."</bibl></cit>)</note>
 
<note id="n2">[2] During the minority</note> 

<note><hi rend="italics">This text revised June 5, 2008.</hi></note>
 
</div1> 
</back> 
</text> 
 

</TEI.2>