<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2  SYSTEM  'teixlite.dtd' [
<!NOTATION jpg  SYSTEM  "jpeg">
<!ENTITY filename  SYSTEM  "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM  "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM  "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM  "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM  "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM  "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="C02g15b">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Francis Lee, 1702 July 15</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr., and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">Modeng enter file ID</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/modeng.browse.html</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Francis Lee, 1702 July 15</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1702-07-15</date>
   <idno type="callNo"> Source copy consulted: Christ Church Parish, Lancaster County,
Processioners' Returns, 1711-1783,and Wormeley Estate Papers, 1701-1710, 1716, Acc. 30126,
Archives Research Services, Library of Virginia, Richmond, 152-154. Extract printed in William and
Mary Quarterly, 2nd ser., 17(1909), 256.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH">
     <bibl>
     <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
     </bibl>
     </taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation>
     <date>1702-07-15</date>
     </creation>
     <langUsage>
     <language id="eng"></language>
     </langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords>
     <term>non-fiction</term>
   <term>prose</term>
     </keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH">
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
     </keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C02g15bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1702-07-15">July 15, 1702</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C02g15b</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Francis Lee, 1702 July 15</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Francis Lee that he has sent 20 hogsheads of tobacco and that some of the other trustees of the Ralph Wormeley estate are pushing other merchants for the estate business, but as he has control of the estate's business on the Rappahannock (while Edmund Jenings supervises that on the York), he will continue to send crops to Lee. Carter states that it is strange that Wormeley, who had inherited large estates, should regularly have been in financial trouble. He notes that some of the trustees had previously wanted to bring Wormeley's sons home from England, but they are now content; their mother had asked that their expenses be kept at a moderate level, and this is important if Ralph and John are to inherit good estates. And he adds that he has observed that those boys  educated in England who had the most pocket money and finest clothes did not obtain the best education. He closes by noting that his sister-in-law, Elizabeth Wormeley, has a right to one-fifth of the proceeds of the previous year's crop, and will market her share herself in the future.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>


<body>

<div1 type="letter" n="1702-07-15">

<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="FL">Francis Lee</note>, July 15, 1702</head>

<opener>

<dateline>
<pb n="1"/><lb/>

Rappa[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]<lb/>

<date value="1702-07-15">July the 15th. 1702.</date>
</dateline>                      
                                           
</opener>

<p>My Last <del>[illegible]</del> went by the <name type="ship">Lawrell</name> of <name type="city"><sic
corr="Liverpool">Leverpooll</sic></name> <lb/>Bound for <name type="place">London</name>
Containing a Bill of Lading for <lb/>Twenty hogsheads of Tobacco, all Consisting of the home
<lb/>Cropps being well near the <note target="n1"><sic corr="Moiety ">Moyety</sic></note> of the Quantity made <lb/>there. Some of the Trustees, you may
Guess them <lb/>wth.out Naming have Endeavoured Strongly to Turn <lb/>most of the Consignments
Another way, but I have hither=<lb/>to had the Ordering of the Concerns in this River, the <lb/><sic
corr="York">Yourk</sic> Business under <note n="EJ">Collo. Jenings's</note> manage=<lb/>-ment;
I <sic corr="promised ">promist</sic> a More Particular Regard  to your <abbr expan="Letters. ">Lettrs. </abbr> <lb/>which take in these Words.</p>

<p>You <add place="supralinear">very much</add> Resent Mr. Secretarys Discourses before his Death <lb/>Do Assure you I Added
Nothing but Rather <sic corr="Diminished ">Diminisht</sic> <lb/>in the Relation. I know yor. Acquaintance was of a Long
<lb/>Standing, As for the Obligations on yor. Side, they were <lb/><sic corr="secrets ">secretts</sic> to the World; <abbr expan="it is ">tis </abbr> Strange to hear A Gentleman 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
to whom <sic corr="so ">soe</sic> Large a fortune Descended, Whose great <lb/>places of <sic corr="profit ">profitt</sic> <sic corr="sat ">satt</sic> fast to him for near
Thirty Ye<add resp ="editor">[ars]</add> <lb/>together, Ending not but wth. his Life should be <abbr expan="Under ">undr. </abbr> A<lb/>-
<sic corr="nnual ">nnuall</sic> Arrears for Money, but that it was <sic corr="so ">soe</sic> I Dou<add resp ="editor">[bt]</add> <lb/>not having yor. Word for it.</p>

<p>A <sic corr="Stir ">Stirr</sic> was made <sic corr="at ">att</sic> the Beginning to have the Children <lb/>Remov'd, One of the Trustees
Affirming, the Fathers Ord<add resp ="editor">[ers]</add> <lb/>was <sic corr="so ">soe</sic>, but that hott humor is now Off, and
no <lb/>Noise is made about them Nor I Believe will, unl<add resp ="editor">[ess]</add> <lb/>the occasion
Rises on yor. part. <abbr expan="It is ">Tis </abbr> an Old Rule in <lb/>the mean vertue Consists, If I forgett not <sic corr="it was">twas</sic> the
<add resp ="editor">[wish]</add> <lb/>of the Mother that the Childrens Expences should
<add resp ="editor">[Not]</add> <lb/>be too Excessive, nor too Scanty, If I may be Allow'd <add resp ="editor">[to
jud]</add><lb/>-ge theirs hitherto have too great a Taste of the former, and
<add resp="editor">[ . . . ]</add> <lb/>to me, to be above a proportion to the Comin<add resp ="editor">[g
in]</add> <lb/>If they be <sic corr="so ">soe</sic> Already, what will they be, a Y<add resp ="editor">[ear]</add> <lb/>hence,
they themselves, when th<add resp ="editor">[ey become]</add> <lb/>Men, will be the first that will Censure
<add resp ="editor">[the Trustees]</add> <lb/>if they Meet wth. Empty purses.</p>

<p>Their Father bore a very great Post in <add resp ="editor">[Virginia and]</add> <lb/>Liv'd as great,
perhapps more Expensive than a<add resp ="editor">[ny]</add> <lb/>Gentleman in't, but Every Year to Clear
Score <add resp="editor">[ . . . ]</add><lb/>behind the lighter as you Say, was a Temper <add resp ="editor">[I can't
?]</add> <lb/>tell how to <sic corr="Commend. ">Comend.</sic> If his Place and Cropps w<add resp ="editor">[ere]</add> <lb/>Little
enough to Support his Grandure, pray whe<add resp ="editor">[re would]</add> <lb/>he <sic corr="been, ">bin,</sic> If the former
had fail'd him, he must <add resp ="editor">[then]</add> <lb/>have Lower'd his Topsailes or gone off like a
Mus<add resp ="editor">[ket]</add> <lb/>as some of his Neighbours did before him.</p>

<p><note target="n2">Ralphy</note> In Prospect will have a fine Estate, <note target="n3">Joh<add resp ="editor">[n]</add></note> <lb/>a Tolerable good One;
<sic corr="yet ">yett</sic> <sic corr="it ">itt</sic> will hardly be Come<add resp ="editor">[nda]</add><lb/>-ble in either of them, to follow their Fathers
<sic corr="Step">Stepp</sic><add resp ="editor">[s in]</add> <lb/>all things, I will not Undertake to prophecy,
tha<add resp ="editor">[t]</add> <lb/>they will be Secretarys or <sic corr="Naval ">Navall</sic> Officers.</p>

<p>Uppon the whole <abbr expan="it is ">'tis </abbr> my Opinion if you Retr<add resp ="editor">[ench]</add> <lb/>their Expences what
Reasonably you Can, <abbr expan="it will ">`twill </abbr> be <add resp ="editor">[a]</add> <lb/>kindness to the Boyes, too much finery, and
too <add resp ="editor">[much]</add> <lb/>pockett Money most an End Raises in
youn<add resp ="editor">[g]</add> 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
<sic corr="Folks ">Foulks</sic> such Opinions of their Estates that they <lb/>hardly know how to take up when they Come <lb/>to
be their own Masters.</p>

<p>Tobacco hath held up its head for <abbr expan="several ">sevll. </abbr> <lb/>years together, but he that Measures his Expences
<lb/>by his seven Last Years gettings in Virginia, <lb/>may Seven years hence probably have Little to
<lb/>Spend, but perhapps I have harp'd too much already <lb/>upon this String, <sic corr="at ">att</sic> least I know <abbr expan="it will ">twill </abbr> not
be <lb/>very pleasing to the Boys. I have only One <lb/>Word more, from my Own Observations when I
<lb/>was in England, Those boyes that Wore the finest <lb/>Close and had the most Money in their
<sic corr="pockets ">pocketts</sic> still <lb/>went away, wth. the least Learning in their heads <lb/><sic corr="yet ">yett</sic> am I not for too Narrow a keeping neither.</p>

<p>I must not <sic corr="forget ">forgett </sic> to tell you that my <note n="EAW">sister <name type="person">Worme=<lb/>-ley</name></note> hath a
5th. part Due to her of the Produce of the last <lb/>years Cropp, She hath now her Tobo. to her self <lb/>I
am <abbr expan="Sir">Sr. </abbr></p>

<p><add place="marginbot"><add resp ="editor">[Presen]</add>t my kind Respects<lb/>to <add resp ="editor">[the
boys. I]</add> intend them all the Good <lb/><add resp ="editor">[Let]</add> them think, what they
will.</add></p>

<closer>Yor. Affectionate Country-<lb/>-man and humble Servt.</closer>


</div1>
</body>


<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

 <note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi> Christ Church Parish, Lancaster County, Processioners' Returns, 1711-1783, and Wormeley Estate Papers, 1701-1710, 1716, Acc. 30126, Archives Research Services, Library of Virginia, Richmond, 152-154. Extract printed in <title>William and Mary Quarterly,</title> 2nd ser., 17(1909): 256.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and state have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] A moiety is one of two approximately equal portions.</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Ralph Wormeley (ca. 1681-1714), Ralph Wormeley's (d. 1701) oldest son; Carter was among the trustees for the boys.</note>

<note id="n3">[3] John Wormeley (1689-1727), a younger son of Ralph Wormeley (d. 1701) for whom Carter was one of the trustees. When his older brother, Ralph died in 1714, John inherited all of their father's considerable estate in Middlesex and York counties.  He married Elizabeth ? and had six children. (See <bibl n="#Wormeley Estate">"Letters Concerning The Estate Of Ralph Wormeley" in the opening page of this web site.</bibl>)</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised June 9, 2008.</hi></note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>


</TEI.2>