<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2  SYSTEM  'teixlite.dtd' [
<!NOTATION jpg  SYSTEM  "jpeg">
<!ENTITY filename  SYSTEM  "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM  "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM  "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM  "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM  "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM  "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;
]>

<TEI.2 id="C03c01a">
<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Philip Ludwell, 1703 March 1</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr., and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">Modeng enter file ID</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/modeng.browse.html</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Philip Ludwell, 1703 March 1</title>
        <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>

    <extent>4 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date> 1703-03-01</date>
   <idno type="callNo"> Source copy consulted: CO 5/1313, ffs. 48 recto, 49 verso, Public Record Office, London. This appears to be the recipient's copy although it is difficult to tell from the microfilm copy in the collections of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing
analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH">
     <bibl>
     <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title>
     </bibl>
     </taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation>
     <date>1702-03-01</date>
     </creation>
     <langUsage>
     <language id="eng"></language>
     </langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords>
     <term>non-fiction</term>
   <term>prose</term>
     </keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH">
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
     </keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C03c01aT">


<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent>4 pp.</extent>
<date value="1703-03-01">March 1, 1703</date>
<idno rend="suppress">work id</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Philip Ludwell, March 1, 1703</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>[abstract here]</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>

<div1 type="letter" n="1703-03-01">

<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="PL1">Philip Ludwell</note>, March 1, 1703</head>

<opener>

<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>

Rappa[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]<lb/>

<date value="1703-03-01">March 3, 1703</date>
</dateline>
                                             
<salute><abbr expan="Honored Sir">Honrd. Sr. </abbr></salute>

</opener>

<p>Yours of the 7:th of <sic corr="April ">Aprill</sic> and 28:th of May <lb/>came Safe, giving me proofs beyond a pretence
<lb/>of your kindness to Virginia in General, and of <lb/>your friendship to me in particular, though they
<lb/>are not the first of both sorts that <sic corr="have ">hath</sic> resulted <lb/>from you, you have lived too long not to be
<lb/>acquainted with the unruliness of the Voice of <lb/>the People. I have formerly told you I would
<lb/>have had it otherwise, though am almost glad <lb/>your hand was not in it, Seeing We met with
<lb/>no better Success; and believing there was such <lb/>a Current the other way that 'twas very nigh
<lb/>impossible to stem the Tide with the Strong=<lb/>est arm; But as bad as it is can hardly think <lb/>it
worse than We deserve, And believe you <lb/>will be of my Opinion when you come to 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
understand that the very men that set the Thing <lb/>on foot, by some late proceedings, have almost
<lb/>given themselves the <sic corr="lie">Lye</sic>; magnifying ap=<lb/>plauding &amp;c the Treatments they
had before so <lb/>liberally complained of. Such and worse <sic corr="has ">hath</sic> <lb/>been our unsteadiness that it <sic corr="has "><sic corr="has ">hath</sic></sic>
not only put <lb/>a Slur upon our late [word omitted] but will be a Warn<lb/>ing for any other to wear
that Character hereafter <lb/>So that let what will come upon us Our Lesson <lb/>must be <note
target="n1">Sustine et abstine</note>. As another Disco<lb/>very against Our Complaint of Poverty,
Our great <lb/><sic corr="Politics ">Politicks</sic> runs so high lately to distribute among <lb/>the Officers of the House Six hundred
pounds and <lb/>therein answering the great End of laying the Im<lb/>position of Liquors for the
Less'ning the Levy <lb/>by the Poll. But the Circumstances We are left <lb/>in hereby, Our Cash is gone,
the Demand for <lb/>[word omitted] Suddenly to be made, Our Revisers <lb/>to be paid, Our Capitol
wants, according to <lb/>my Guess, the best part of a thousand pounds <lb/>to finish, Our Engagements
to our <gap>[word omitted]</gap> <lb/>if they will allow that to come in as an&mdash; <lb/>Article. All put together
makes a pretty round <lb/><sic corr="Sum. ">Sume.</sic> If I have the Security of keeping the <note target="n2">Trea<lb/>surers
Place</note>, it may be worth something in time</p>

<p>Our Assembly which had the Strength to <lb/>out live Death was forced to give up the ghost <lb/>at
the Six months End. We have a New one <lb/>to meet on the 17th Instant. Few Elections <lb/>over yet.
<sic corr="Gloucester">Gloster</sic> has been Steady in their <lb/>former Choice in their <note
target="n3">Chief Member</note>. His <lb/>unexampled management in the House before <lb/>will, no
doubt, prefer him to the same Station 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
there also, And then no doubt all things will go <lb/>on well under the Conduct of so experienced a
<lb/>Leader.</p> 

<p>The Country is highly indebted to <lb/><note n="MP">Mr Perry</note> for his Warmness in our affairs, And <lb/>I believe he
will hardly miss of thanks from most <lb/>of those who have any business with him; <lb/>And if the Brains
of our Patriots are not quite <lb/>brutified, We Shall look for no other person to <lb/>Countenance our
Affaires, unless we were So wise <lb/>to joyn you with him. It is a Strange fate <lb/>that We are under,
that everything that is said <lb/>against us Should be of such mighty weight, <lb/>and what We Say Our
Selves, though ever So true &amp; <lb/>convincing, Should all be but Dross &amp; uncurrent <lb/>Mettle</p>

<p>To be kept from Our homes and Our Business, <lb/>to be hired out week after week, without almost
<lb/>the pretense of anything to do, And the Burgesses <lb/>to go to play almost every day before our
great <lb/>Edifice, on purpose to be taken notice of; I say <lb/>that these things Should be hardships We
are <lb/>forced to endure here And yet that these things <lb/>elsewhere Shold be chargeable upon us as
<lb/>Crimes; That four of the upper House Should <lb/>be forced to undergo all the business, No
<lb/>more enduring to abide the Healot, the fatigues, <lb/>the Indignities, I say that these should be our
<lb/>Crimes too, What may we expect will pass <lb/>for reason on our Side, or what have We <lb/>to do,
but to lay our hands a cross and never <lb/>let our Tongues express our complaints any <lb/>more</p>

<pb n="4"/><lb/><lb/>
<p>I am very much obliged to you for <lb/>your Zeal in the <note target="n4"><sic corr="Affair ">Affaire</sic> of the Northern
<lb/>Neck</note>; not out of the mighty Love I have for <lb/>the Place, which carrys a great deal of
trouble <lb/>and uneasiness along with it, more I doubt <lb/>than the Profit will recompense, but for
<lb/>your earnest and unwearied Solicitations <lb/>in my favour.</p>

<p>If I take the thing right, Mr Perry is to <lb/>manage for the Proprietors, And accordingly <lb/>I have
entertained him with the Steps I have <lb/>taken.</p>

<p>The Power I had was not only as short in <lb/>form but in Proof too, as I have noted both <lb/>to
<note target="n5">my Lord</note> and Mr Perry, and have Sent <lb/>to the <sic corr="latter">later</sic>
Copies of the Power <note target="n6">F[it]zHugh</note> had to <lb/>be executed beyond
exception.</p>

<p>I have <lb/>tired you enough for once, yet Shall tres=<lb/>pass upon you again very Suddenly, Will
<lb/>therefore conclude at this time only with <lb/>taking leave to subscribe my Self what <lb/>in truth I
am</p>

<closer><abbr expan="Honored Sir,"> Hond Sr,  </abbr><lb/>
Your most humble Servt.<lb/><lb/>
<signed>ROBERT CARTER</signed>
</closer>

</div1>
</body>

<back>
<div1 type="notes">
<head>NOTES</head>
<note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi> CO 5/1313, ffs. 48 recto, 49 verso, Public Record Office, London. This appears to be the recipient's copy although it is difficult to tell from the microfilm copy in the collections of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert H. Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.
</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] RC apparently refers to the controversy between Commissary James Blair and other embers of the Council with Governor Francis Nicholson. Shortly after this letter was written, Carter was to join fellow Council members Blair, Philip Ludwell (1672-1727, son of the addressee of this letter), John Lightfoot, Mathew Page, and Benjamin Harrison in a petition and memorial to Queen Anne asking for Nicholson's recall. (<cit><bibl n="B17">Morton, <title>Colonial Virginia</title> I, 381-382.</bibl></cit> The petition is in <cit><bibl n="B18">Headlam. <title>Calendar of State Papers Colonial Series.</title> pp. 91-95</bibl></cit>;  and <cit><bibl n="B19"> McIlwaine. <title>Journal of the House of Burgesses, 1702/3-1705, 1705-1706, 1710-1712.</title> 101 ff. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] RC, then speaker of the House of Burgesses, had been elected treasurer of the colony by the House in 1699, and was continued in office until 1705 even though he had taken his seat on the Council on July 10, 1700. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 2(1699-1705):93.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Gloucester County had elected Peter Beverley as one of its burgesses to the previous session. He succeeded Carter as speaker in 1700, and was re-elected at each session through 1705, and again in 1710-1714. (<cit><bibl n="B1">Kukla. <title>Speakers and Clerks. . . .</title> pp. 103-105.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] See the discussion of Robert Carter's admininstering of the Northern Neck Proprietary linked from the home page screen.</note>

<note id="n5">[5] Thomas, fifth Lord Fairfax (1657-1710)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] William Fitzhugh (1651-1701) preceded Carter as agent for the Proprietors. See <bibl n="B5">Davis,  <title>William Fitzhugh. . . . </title>pp. 39-42, and other references in the index.</bibl></note>


<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised June 10, 2008.</hi></note>

</div1>
</back>
</text>


</TEI.2>