<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2  SYSTEM  'teixlite.dtd' [ 
<!NOTATION jpg  SYSTEM  "jpeg"> 
<!ENTITY filename  SYSTEM  "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg> 
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM  "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1; 
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM  "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM  "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM  "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM  "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; 
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="C04e26a"> 
<teiHeader type="aacr2"> 
              
<fileDesc> 
<titleStmt> 
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas Corbin, 1704 May 26 </title> 
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title> 
     <author>Robert Carter</author> 
   <respStmt> 
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp> 
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name> 
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp> 
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr., and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name> 
   </respStmt> 
</titleStmt> 
 
<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent> 
 
<publicationStmt> 
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher> 
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace> 
     <idno type="ETC"></idno> 
     <availability> 
     <p>Publicly accessible</p> 
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/modeng.browse.html</p> 
         </availability> 
     <date>2001</date> 
</publicationStmt> 
 
<sourceDesc> 
     <biblFull> 
     <titleStmt> 
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas Corbin, 1704 May 26</title> 
    
  
     <author>Robert Carter</author> </titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent> 
<publicationStmt> 
     <date> 1704-05-26</date> 
   <idno type="callNo"> Source copy consulted: Christ Church Parish, Lancaster County, 
Processioners' Returns, 1711-1783, and Wormeley Estate Papers, 1701-1710, 1716, Acc. 30126, 
Archives Research Services, Library of Virginia, Richmond, 160.</idno> 
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull> 
</sourceDesc> 
 
</fileDesc> 
     <encodingDesc> 
     <projectDesc> 
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p> 
     </projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl> 
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing 
analytical groupings.</p> 
</editorialDecl> 
 
<classDecl> 
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
     <bibl> 
     <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
     </bibl> 
     </taxonomy> 
</classDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
 
<profileDesc> 
     <creation> 
     <date>1704-05-26</date> 
     </creation> 
     <langUsage> 
     <language id="eng"></language> 
     </langUsage> 
     <textClass> 
     <keywords> 
     <term>non-fiction</term> 
   <term>prose</term> 
     </keywords> 
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term> 
     </keywords> 
     </textClass> 
</profileDesc> 
 
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="C04e26aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1704-05-26"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C04e26a</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas Corbin, May 26, 1704</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter write to London merchant Thomas Corbin that he is sending 10 hogsheads of tobacco with two different marks; some are to be credited to the account of John Wormeley and the remainder to RC's sister-in-law, Elizabeth (Wormeley) Churchill, widow of Ralph Wormeley. He encloses an order for goods, some of which are for the use of Judith Wormeley, unmentioned in her father's will, but whom Wormeley's trustees feel must be supported. He leaves it to Corbin and Edmund Jenings, another trustee, to decide how much should be spent.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>

 
<body> 
 
<div1 type="letter" n="1704-05-26"> 
 
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="TC">Thomas Corbin,</note> May 26, 1704</head> 
 
<opener> 
 
<dateline>
 <pb n="1"/>
<name type="person">Mr. Tho: Corbin</name><lb/> 

<name type="place"><add n="ed">[Rappahannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/> 
 
<date value="1704-05-26">May the 26. 1704</date> 
 
</dateline> 
                                              
<salute>Sr.</salute> 
 
</opener> 
<p>This Serves to Cover a Bill of Lading for Tenn hogsheads of <lb/>Tobo. Consign'd you in the <name 
type="ship">Richard and Wm.</name> <name type="person">Thomas Mattocks</name> <lb/>Master, 
They are of Two Marks and you must keep your <lb/>Accots. Distinct, The two Markt +JW. my <note target="n1">Sister Churchill</note><lb/>would have go upon her <note target="n2">Son 
Johnys</note> Accot. as the Cropp <lb/>of a Negro Woman he hath wch. was given him by his Grandfathr.</p> 
 
<p>herein is <sic corr="also">allso</sic> an Invoice for Some Goods Sent to me by <lb/>my Sister 
Churchill, The first part of it for the familys <lb/>use must <sic corr="be">me</sic> had, I think ther's 
nothing Extraordnary in <lb/>That, the Later part is for the Furniture of Judith Worme<lb/>=ley, The 
Overseer's all of them when they mett Together <lb/>did agree there Should be some Allowance given for <name type="person"></name>
her <lb/>Yearly Maintenance altho no Mention is made thereof in her <lb/>Fathers Will, but Whether what 
is here sent for be not <lb/>more than is Necessary I Leave to you and <note n="EJ"><sic corr="Colonel">Collonell</sic> 
Jenings</note> <lb/>to Determine I am for being as Sparing as possi<lb/>=ble by Reason Wee have no 
foundation for what wee do from <lb/>the Will, What Goods you send pray lett them Come in <lb/>a 
Good Shipp bound Directly here and Consign'd to me <lb/>for the familys use.</p> 
 <p><add place="marginleft">Per Mattocks&mdash;</add></p> 
<p><add place="marginleft">Per Ellis</add></p> 
<closer>I am Sr. Yor. humble servt. </closer> 
 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
 
<back> 
<div1 type="notes"> 
<head>NOTES</head> 
 
<note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi> Christ Church Parish, Lancaster County, Processioners' Returns, 1711-1783, and Wormeley Estate Papers, 1701-1710, 1716, Acc. 30126, Archives Research Services, Library of Virginia, Richmond, 160.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and state have been added for clarity.</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] RC refers to Elizabeth (Wormeley) Churchill, widow of Ralph Wormeley as his sister-in-law as he had married her sister. Elizabeth  married William Churchill of Middlesex County after Wormeley's death.</note>

<note id="n2">[2] John Wormeley (1689-1727), one of Ralph Wormeley's sons for whom RC was a trustee.</note> 
 
</div1> 
</back> 
</text> 
 
</TEI.2> 
