<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2  SYSTEM  'teixlite.dtd' [ 
<!NOTATION jpg  SYSTEM  "jpeg"> 
<!ENTITY filename  SYSTEM  "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg> 
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM  "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1; 
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM  "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2; 
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM  "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum; 
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM  "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub; 
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM  "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; 
]> 
 
<TEI.2 id="C05b26a"> 
<teiHeader type="aacr2"> 
              
<fileDesc> 
<titleStmt> 
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas Corbin, 1705 February 26</title> 
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title> 
     <author>Carter, Robert</author> 
   <respStmt> 
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp> 
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name> 
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp> 
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr., and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name> 
   </respStmt> 
</titleStmt> 
 
<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent> 
 
<publicationStmt> 
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher> 
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace> 
     <idno type="ETC"></idno> 
     <availability> 
     <p>Publicly accessible</p> 
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/modeng.browse.html</p> 
         </availability> 
     <date>2001</date> 
</publicationStmt> 
 
<sourceDesc> 
     <biblFull> 
     <titleStmt> 
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas Corbin, 1705 February 26</title> 
   
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
 </titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent> 
<publicationStmt> 
     <date> 1705-02-26</date> 
   <idno type="callNo"> Source copy consulted: Christ Church Parish, Lancaster County, Processioners' Returns, 1711-1783,and Wormeley Estate Papers, 1701-1710, 1716, Acc. 30126, Archives Research Services, Library of Virginia, Richmond, 162. Extract printed William and Mary Quarterly, 1st., 17(1909), 257.</idno> 
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull> 
</sourceDesc> 
 
</fileDesc> 
     <encodingDesc> 
     <projectDesc> 
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p> 
     </projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl> 
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p> 
</editorialDecl> 
 
<classDecl> 
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
     <bibl> 
     <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
     </bibl> 
     </taxonomy> 
</classDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
 
<profileDesc> 
     <creation> 
     <date>1705-02-26</date> 
     </creation> 
     <langUsage> 
     <language id="eng"></language> 
     </langUsage> 
     <textClass> 
     <keywords> 
     <term>non-fiction</term> 
   <term>prose</term> 
     </keywords> 
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term> 
     </keywords> 
     </textClass> 
</profileDesc> 
 
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="C05b26aT"> 


<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>x pp.</extent>
<date value="1705-02-26">February 26, 1705</date>
<idno rend="suppress">C05b26a</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas Corbin, February 26, 1705</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Thomas Corbin, February 26, 1705, to thank him for two letters and that he does not know how to respond to Corbin's comments about the "Mattrs. of State," an affair in which Carter is deeply involved. He  notes the deaths of William Byrd, David Gwinn, and Robert Tayloe, master of the Corbin,  which is being repaired on the bank of Corotoman Creek. In a lengthy postscript dated March 8th, he writes that he has received two more letters from Corbin, one via Barbados and the other through Pennsylvania which he suspects was opened. He is pleased with the sale of the Rappahannock tobacco but cannot comment on the needed work on the Corbin about which Corbin's brother will be better able to write him; he adds that the present master of the ship, Richard Cudlip, is not well qualified for the work. </p>
</div1>                 
</front>


<body> 
 
<div1 type="letter" n="1705-02-26"> 
 
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="TC">Thomas Corbin</note>, February 26, 1705</head> 
 
<opener> 
 <pb n="1"/>
<dateline> 
<name type="place">[Rappahannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</name><lb/> 
 Mr. Thos. Corbin<lb/> 
<date value="1705-02-26">Febry. the. 26th. 1704/5<lb/></date> 
 </dateline> 
                                              
<salute>Sr.</salute> 
 
</opener> 
 
 
<p>I am Indebted to you for two Lettrs. Since my Last <lb/>writing, Those parts that Relate to Mattrs. of 
State <lb/>I Don't know how to give a fitt Answer to it falls to my Share <lb/>to be Deeply Concern'd in a 
Cause that I Call the Countrys <del>that</del> I <lb/>drew my first breath in <del>wch must End either in Victory or the Ruin of thm.<lb/> who have made the attempt.</del><lb/>which I 
Suppose you and a great many Others have Other thoughts <lb/>of but the Event will prove who hath bin in the Right.</p>  
 
<p>I have Little to Say at this Time Relating to the young <lb/>Wormeleys Affairs.  I know 'twill be no 
News to you to give you <lb/>an Accot. of <note target="n1">Robt. Tayloes</note> Death of <note 
target="n2">Major. Gwins</note> Death <lb/>or of <note n="WB1">Collo. Birds</note> Death or of 
the Corbins being upon the <note target="n3">Careen</note> <lb/>in my Creek.</p>  
 
<p><seg type="postscript"><date><add resp="editor">[P. S.]</add> March the. 8th. 1704/5</date></seg></p> 
 <lb/>
<p>Since the Above I have Recd. Two more Lettrs. <lb/>from you One the 14th. of 8ber, the Other the 
6th of Janry. <lb/>of all the Rest you Mention none Come to hand Saving <lb/>those two by the way of 
<name type="place">Barbadoes</name> am very Suspicious <lb/>What you writt by the way of <name 
type="place">Pensilvania</name> hath Come under the <lb/>Managmt of Some of the Northern 
Engineers. Am <lb/>Glad to hear you have made So good a Sale of the 
Rappa<add n="ed">[hannock]</add>.<lb/> Tobo. Its much that you had from <sic corr="York">yourk</sic> 
Should fall soe <lb/>much Short I know not what to Say abt. the <name type="ship">Corbin</name><lb/>
<note n="GC1">Yor. brother</note> is the fittest Man to give Satisfaction to the Persons 
<lb/>Concern'd they all Live out of my way, I shall offer my <lb/>best arguments the first Time I see any 
of them &amp; acquaint thm. <lb/>what you Write  'Tis your Misfortune to have a <note 
target="n1">Master</note> that is but In=<lb/>differently Quallified for the post he is in how it will be 
help'd <lb/>I know not. The Shipps Bottome is in good order; and She might <lb/>be Quickly upon 
Loading were there <sic corr="anybody">any Boddy</sic> to Drive on her <lb/>business,</p> 
 
<p><add place="marginleft">Your most humble obedient Servt.</add></p>

<p><seg type="postscript"><add place="marginleft">I thank you for the Offer of Some Madera wine may be a <note 
target="n4">Chapman</note> for <lb/>Some when it Comes. Shall not add more but that I am Sr.</add></seg></p><lb/><lb/> 
 
<closer></closer> 

</div1> 
</body> 
 
<back> 
<div1 type="notes"> 
<head>NOTES</head> 

<note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi> Christ Church Parish, Lancaster County, Processioners' Returns, 1711-1783,and Wormeley Estate Papers, 1701-1710, 1716, Acc. 30126, Archives Research Services, Library of Virginia, Richmond, 162. Extract printed <title>William and Mary Quarterly</title> 1st. ser., 17(1909): 257.</note> 


<note id="n1">[1] Robert Tayloe of London, commander of the <hi rend="italics">Corbin</hi>, seems to have been a brother of William Tayloe of Richmond County, and also of Joseph Tayloe of Lancaster County. He died 
on this voyage to Virginia. He was succeeded in command by Richard Cudlip, the mate, of whom RC had a very low opinion.</note> 
 
<note id="n2">[2] David Gwynn of Richmond County</note> 
 
<note id="n3">[3] Careening was a process by which an unloaded ship was run aground on a sandy 
beach or a soft creek bank and, with ropes tied to her masts, pulled onto her side. The ship's bottom was 
thus exposed, especially at low tide, for repairs, cleaning, or caulking. </note>

<note id="n4">[4] A chapman is a peddlar or merchant.</note> 
 
</div1> 
</back> 
</text> 
 

</TEI.2>