<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C05e05e">
 
<text id="C05e05eT"> 
<pb n="30"/> 
<body>               
 
<div1 type="letter" n="1705-05-05"> 
 
<head><sender>Robert Carter</sender>, <sender>John Lightfoot</sender>, and <sender>Philip 
Ludwell</sender>to <addressee>Speaker and Gentlemen of the House of Burgesses</addressee> 
</head> 



<opener> 
<dateline> 
<name type="place"><add n="ed"> type='ed:'>[Wlliamsburg, Virginia] 
<note target="34">[May 5, 1705]</note> [1]]</add></name> 
 
<date n="1705-05-05"></date> 
 
<address> 
<addrLine></addrLine> 
</address> 
 
</dateline> 
 
<salute></salute> 
 
</opener> 
 
<p>You have not thought fitt, to Admitt us Personally to give You our reasons agt. your 
intermeddling 
wth: the Complaints &amp;c, against his Excellcy: which he hath laid before you. We have put some 
few of 
them in Writing, wch: we here send You, and we desire your Serious Consideration of before 
you 
proceed to any determination in that Affair. 
</p> 
 
 
<closer> 
<salute> We are Gent. Yor. most humble Servants </salute> 
J LIGHTFOOT 
 ROBERT CARTER 
PHILL. LUDWELL 
</closer> 
 
</div1> 
 
<div1 type="enclosure"> 
<p>
Reasons offered by John Lightfoot, Robert Carter &amp; Philip Ludwell Esqrs. agt. the makeing any 
Determination by the House of Burgesses upon the Complaint &amp; Affidavits against his Excellcy. 
</p> 
<p>
1st  That the Complaint was made by the Greater part of the Councill then in being who had 
given 
their attendance upon the publick affairs &amp; were both Eye &amp; Ear witnesses of the mismanagemts. 
there, 
&amp; therefore they were the most proper persons &amp; the most likely to make a true representation 
thereof. &amp; 
Since her Majesty hath been pleased to appoint them of the Councill, &amp; thereby hath made it 
their proper 
Province to give the best advice they can for preserving her Majestys Interest &amp; the peace &amp; 
welfare of 
her Subjects here; they take it to be a duty incumbent upon them in Case of the 
Mal-Administration of a 
Governr. to apply themselves to their Sovereign for Redress, &amp; this they think they have a right 
to doe 
without being lyable to any Censure but that of her Majesty. And they think that both her 
Majestys 
Service &amp; this Countries interest will be greatly promoted thereby. 
</p>
<p> 
2d.  That the matters contained in the Complaint for the most part are Mal-Administrations in the 
Councill in the Generall: Court &amp; in the Upper house of the Generll: Assembly; So that the 
Councill are 
not only the best acquainted with. the transactions there, but also they are most nearly concerned 
in thm. 
as relateing chiefly to their Libertys &amp; priviledges in wch. the House of Burgesses have no right 
to 
intermeddle. 
</p><p> 
3d.  That the Complaint consists of matters of fact wch. are provable by Evidences, &amp; the 
Complainants are able to make Sufficient proof of them whenever they shall be lawfully 
impowered so to 
doe, but at present they cannot do it, because her Majesty hath not thought fitt to give any 
directions 
therein, and they cannot believe that the House of Burgeses will ever be guilty of so great an 
absurdity as 
to proceed to Judgement of the truth or falsehood of any matter of fact, wch. doth not ly wth.in 
their own 
knowledge, wth.out Examining such Evidence as can be given to make proof thereof. 
</p><p> 
4.   That (whatever hath been suggested) the Complainants have always been far from 
endeavouring 
to raise partys or factions or to disturb the peace of the Country; on the Contrary their great 
moderation 
hath appeared in the patience &amp; Submission they they have shewed notwithstanding the many 
injuryes &amp; 
indignityes (not to be mentioned) tht. have been put upon themselves &amp; others by the Governrs. 
unjustifiable behaviour, &amp; in this particular Case they addressed themselves in the most 
peaceable &amp; 
humble manner to her Majesty the proper fountain of justice for their relief, &amp; she hath been 
gratiously 
pleased to take the same into her own Cognizance So that the House of Burgesses cannot 
concerne 
themselves in this matter without arrogateing to themselves a power to make a previous 
determination to 
tht. of her Majesty in an affair wch. she hath been pleased in an Especial manner to reserve for 
her own 
Consideration. 
</p><p> 
5th. That it appears plainly by her Majestys Order in Councill &amp; by the Letters from the Rt. 
Honble: 
the Lords Commissioners for Trade tht. the Complaint &amp; other papers were sent to the Govr. for 
him to 
make his answer; not that they should be brought to any tryall or determination here; it is so far 
from that, 
that he is commanded not to shew so much as any manner of resentment agt. the Complainants, 
till her 
Majestys pleasure be further known. And it is impossible the House of Burgesses should take 
upon them 
to make any Judgemt. in this matter wth.out going directly Contrary to her Majestys pleasure in 
this 
particular, &amp; to the very express Letter as well as intent of the command from the Lords 
Commissioners 
for Trade. 
</p><p> 
6th. That the House of Burgesses cannot take upon them to intermeddle in this affair without 
making 
themselves Judges of the Rights &amp; Priviledges of the Councill, wch. in Consequence may create 
lasting 
divisions &amp; misunderstandings between thm. &amp; the Burgesses; For whatever determination shall 
be made 
here it cannot be supposed tht. the Complainants will be so far wanting either in their duty to her 
Majesty 
or in their regard to their owne Characters or the Countrys interest as to Sitt Still patiently &amp; not 
endeavour to Sett all persons &amp; their proceedings in a true light. And it is not improbable but the 
misfortunes tht. may ensue to the Country upon such differences, may be what is chiefly aimed 
at. 
</p><p> 
7th. That the Complainants have been very Cautious of Concerning themselves wth. the House 
of 
Burgesses tht. they might not give thm. the least umbrage of disatisfaction. And surely the House 
of 
Burgesses have great reason to be as Cautious tht. they do not themselves Sowe those seeds of 
discord &amp; 
Contention wch. may in a short time grow up to interrupt the peace &amp; happiness of the whole 
Country. 
</p>
<p> 
J LIGHTFOOT  
ROBERT CARTER   
PHILL: LUDWELL 
<attestation>Copy Teste. William Randolph Junr. Clerk House Burgesses</attestation> 
</p>

</div1> 
 </body> 
<back> 
<div1 type="notes"> 
<head>Notes</head> 
 
<sourcedesc>State Archives, New York State Education Department, Albany. Series #1894, 
Colonial 
Manuscripts, Vol. 51, p. 32a-b. This document was copied for Governor Francis  Nicholson's 
private 
papers, and was carried by him to New York when he later became governor of that colony. The 
papers 
remained in New York, passing into the custody of the State Library which burned around the 
turn of the 
twentieth century, causing some damage to this series of records. These records have been 
transferred to 
the State Archives, and there are several copies of this document in the series. The text was 
transcribed 
from one that seems to be most contemporary in its handwriting to the early eighteenth century, 
and two 
other copies in the series have been used to supply words in the copy text that were damaged in 
the 
fire.</sourcedesc><lb/><lb/> 
 
<note id="34">. The date of the document was supplied from other records in the series 
pertaining to 
the actions of the House of Burgesses on this matter.</note> 
 
</div1> 
</back> 
 
</text>


</TEI.2>