<?xml version="1.0"?> 
 
<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?> 
 
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[ 
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">    
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>   
 
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;   
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;   
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;   
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;   
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]> 
<TEI.2 id="C15a01a"> 
 
<teiHeader type="aacr2"> 
              
<fileDesc> 
<titleStmt> 
     <title type="245">Letter from Thomas Hooper to Robert Carter,
1715 January 1  </title> 
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title> 
     <author>Robert Carter</author> 
   <respStmt> 
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp> 
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name> 
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp> 
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr., and the >University of Virginia
Library Electronic Text Center</name> 
   </respStmt> 
</titleStmt> 
 
<extent>ca. 16 kilobytes </extent> 
 
<publicationStmt> 
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher> 
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace> 
     <idno type="ETC">Modeng enter file ID</idno> 
     <availability> 
     <p>Publicly accessible</p> 
     <p n="public">URL:
http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/modeng.browse.html</p> 
         </availability> 
     <date>2001</date> 
</publicationStmt> 
 
<sourceDesc> 
     <biblFull> 
     <titleStmt> 
     <title>Letter from Thomas Hooper to Robert Carter, 1715 January
1</title> 
    
          <author>Thomas Hooper</author> 
</titleStmt> 
    <extent> 3 p.</extent> 
<publicationStmt> 
     <date>1715-01-01</date> 
   <idno type="callNo"> Source copy consulted: Brock Collection,
Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San
Marino, California.</idno> 
</publicationStmt> 
</biblFull> 
</sourceDesc> 
 
</fileDesc> 
     <encodingDesc> 
     <projectDesc> 
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic
Text Center.</p> 
     </projectDesc> 
<editorialDecl> 
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in establishing 
analytical groupings.</p> 
</editorialDecl> 
 
<classDecl> 
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"> 
     <bibl> 
     <title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title> 
     </bibl> 
     </taxonomy> 
</classDecl> 
</encodingDesc> 
 
<profileDesc> 
     <creation> 
     <date>1715-01-01</date> 
     </creation> 
     <langUsage> 
     <language id="eng"></language> 
     </langUsage> 
     <textClass> 
     <keywords> 
     <term>non-fiction</term> 
   <term>prose</term> 
     </keywords> 
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"> 
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term> 
     </keywords> 
     </textClass> 
</profileDesc> 
 
</teiHeader> 
 
<text id="C15a01aT"> 
 
 
<front> 
<div1 type="summary" n="1"> 
<head> 
<bibl> 
<abbr>ALS</abbr> 
<extent>3 pp.</extent> 
<date value="1715-01-01">January 1, 1715</date> 
<idno rend="suppress">C15a01a</idno> 
<title>Letter from Thomas Hooper to Robert Carter, 1715 January
1</title> 
</bibl> 
</head> 
<p>Thomas Hooper of Stafford County furnishes to Robert Carter
January 1, 1715, his report "of What Quantity of Land I think may be
unpatented in the Bodys of Stafford and Richmond Countys; And what
may be Surplus; And how far above the Seatments in those Countys the
Land is Patented." </p> 
</div1>                  
</front> 
 
 
<body> 
 
<div1 type="letter" n="1715-01-01"> 
 
<head>Letter from <note target="n1">Thomas Hooper</note> to Robert
Carter, January 1, 1715</head> 
 
<opener> 
<dateline> 
<pb n="1"/>  
[Stafford County, Virginia]<lb/> 
<date value="1715-01-01"><abbr expan="January ">Jan:ry </abbr> 1: 1714/5</date> 
</dateline> 
                                              
<salute>Worthy <abbr expan="Sir ">Sr. </abbr>&mdash;&mdash;</salute>              
 
</opener> 
                       
<p>In obedience to Yor. Commands, Requiring me to give an
<lb/>Accot. of What Quantity of Land I 
think may be unpatented <lb/>in the Bodys of <name
type="county">Stafford</name> and <name type="county">Richmond</name>
Countys;  And what <lb/>may be 
Surplus; And how far above the <sic corr="Settlements ">Seatments</sic> in<lb/> those Countys the 
Land is Patented.</p> 
 
<p>To all which after the Acknowledging my incapacity for the
performance <lb/>of so Difficult a Task I 
shall with due Submition Humbly offer my Rude <lb/>Conceptions as
followeth&mdash;</p> 
 
<p>First as to what Lands may be unpatented in the Bodys of those
Countys. <lb/>I must Confess myself 
to be too much <unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear> to Seek in the knowledge
of what Lands&mdash; <lb/>are already 
patented in those parts to give any Accot: wth. Certainty of what
Lands <lb/>may yet be unpatented by 
reason there is <abbr expan="Several ">Sevll: </abbr> large Tracts of Land  particularly in
<lb/>Stafford County which by Comon Report 
are under patents that as to Bounds Scitu=<lb/>=ation or place are
altogether unknown to any persons in 
these parts the Patentees <lb/>and imediate owners living out of
this Colony and no certain  Accot. to be 
given of &mdash;<lb/>them: I have <abbr expan="Endeavored ">Endeavrd. </abbr> as far as possible to
get what  information I could in <lb/>this 
particular both by Enquiry and other means but  cannot find any
Certainty&mdash; <lb/>in all my proceedings 
worthy to be laid before yor: View, I have <abbr expan="Endeavored ">Endeavrd: </abbr>
accord=<lb/>=ing to my notions of the <sic corr="Situation">Scituation</sic> of 
the Back or <sic corr="unihabited">unihabitted</sic> parts of both <lb/>Countys to draw a <sic
corr="scheme">Scheem</sic> for <abbr expan="your ">yor: </abbr> View, but upon my best 
performance I must <lb/>acknowledge it to be so imperfect and
uncertain, that I can in no way think 
<lb/>it worth relying on: It is a Vast Tract of Land Contained wthin
the <sic corr="limits">limmits</sic> <lb/>of those Bounds and 
so Desart &amp; Wild in a great many parts, that I must think
<lb/>no one person so well acquainted therewith 
as to give any Certain Accot: worthy to <lb/>be depended on, in
relation to the matter  now before me; 
besides there is nothing, <lb/>renders this design more uncertain
and Dark then the Charter or Grant 
Patent <lb/>Called the <note n="BT">Brent Town</note> Land<hi
rend="sup">2</hi> which is Variously Spoaken of by all 
persons And if <lb/>Mr. Brents notions (and those in that Interest)
are allowable, that Patent will 
<lb/>include all the Lands within Six Miles both of Rappa<add
resp="editor">[hannock]</add> and 
<name type="river" reg="Potomac">Patowmack</name> Rivers <lb/>from
the very Mountains down to the Old patents on <name type="river"
reg="Rappahannock">Rappa</name> and <sic corr="Potomac ">Patowmack</sic> 
<lb/>as low as the Falls of <abbr expan="Rappahannock ">Rappa: </abbr> and <name
type="stream">Acquia</name> on <sic corr="Potomac ">Patowmack</sic> and consequently leave
<lb/>but a small 
string of Land on <abbr expan="Rappahannock ">Rappa: </abbr> which as much of it, as is of any Vallue
<lb/>is already taken up to within  15 or 
16, Miles of the Montains and all on &mdash;<lb/><sic corr="Potomac ">Patowmack</sic> may be
reckoned under old Patents almost to the 
Falls thereof. &mdash;<lb/>this with Submition is as much as  my
weak Capacity can offer on this Head.</p> 
 
<p>I shall therefore proceed to the Second,</p> 
 
<p>Which is what Surplus Land may be Contain'd in those Lands
already Granted <lb/>with in those <sic corr="Limits.">Limmitts.</sic>&mdash;</p> 
 
<p>And here I must likewise Confess my Self as much to Seek to offer
anything&mdash; <lb/>Satisfactory as in 
the foregoing particular Only this I may presume to Say  
 
<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/> 
from what knowledge I have amongst the old Patents in Stafford
County that 
the <add resp="editor">[re]</add> <lb/>is no Part of the <name
type="place">Northern Neck</name> where there may be presum'd to be 
more <add resp="editor">[s]</add>u<add resp="editor">[r]</add>pl<add
resp="editor">[u]</add>s <lb/>Land then in 
that County most persons that hold old Patents dread the Execution
<lb/>of the Law concerning 
prosessioning of Land and I believe I may safely say there <lb/>is
no County in <abbr expan="Virginia ">Virga </abbr> but what has put 
forward for the Execution of that Law <lb/>Except Stafford County
where it has laid Dormant to this 
time. As for the &mdash;<lb/>Lands in the upper parts of Richmond
and Stafford Countys whole patents are&mdash; 
<lb/>of late Date  I have less reason to think there may be Surplus
Lands in them <lb/>because more Care 
has been taken in Surveys of Late then in former times. <lb/>Which
is what I shall presume at this 
time to Offer on this Head.</p> 
 
<p>And as to the last part Which is how far the Lands patented
abov<add resp="editor">[e]</add> <lb/>the 
<sic corr="Settlements ">Seatments</sic> in both Countys I shall presume to Offer as followeth</p> 
 
<p>In Richmond County the Land may be said to be all patented and
Seated in <lb/><abbr expan="Several ">Sevll </abbr> places as <sic corr="far ">farr</sic> 
above the Falls of <abbr expan="Rappahannock ">Rappa: </abbr> as the Deep Run which <lb/>goes out of
<abbr expan="Rappahannock ">Rappa: </abbr> about 12 Miles above the Falls 
thereof and heads with <lb/>the South Run of Acquia Creek going out
of <sic corr="Potomac ">Patowmack</sic> River about four 
<lb/>Miles above <sic corr="Potomac ">Patowmack</sic> Creek an inconsiderable <sic corr="parcel ">parcell</sic> of
&mdash;<lb/>Barren Land which lyes in small 
parcells, And here I presume it may <lb/>be about 18 or 20 Miles a
cross the Neck from the Mouth of the 
Deep &mdash;<lb/>Run  to some part of <sic corr="Potomac ">Patowmack</sic> River between <name
type="stream">Chappawamsick</name> and <lb/>Acquia Creeks, 
from the Deep Run where there is now two or three
&mdash;<lb/>Settlements going forward, up <abbr expan="Rappahannock ">Rappa </abbr> River 
there is not above 3500 Acres <lb/>of Land now patented <sic corr="until ">till</sic> one
Comes to the Great Marsh Run which is 
<lb/>computed to fall into <abbr expan="Rappahannock ">Rappa </abbr> River about thirty  miles above the
Falls&mdash; <lb/>thereof and here on <abbr expan="Rappahannock ">Rappa: </abbr> 
River <abbr expan="Colonel ">Colo</abbr> <note n="PL">Phillip Ludwell</note> holds about <lb/>6000
Acres, 2000 Whereof <sic corr="lies ">lyes</sic> 
on the lower side of the Mouth of the &mdash;<lb/><name
type="stream">Marsh Run</name>, and the rest on the upper side, which
is the highest&mdash; 
<lb/>Land under patent on <abbr expan="Rappahannock ">Rappa </abbr> River or in Richmond County.
The&mdash; <lb/>Marsh Run is Computed to 
Run into the Woods about three Miles and then&mdash; <lb/>begins the
<name type="place">Great Marsh</name> which holds  near a Mile in 
length and in some&mdash; <lb/>places a quarter and More in breadth,
about  a Mile above the great&mdash; <lb/>Marsh 
lyes two others of no great Extent on this Run and the Branches
<lb/>going out of it, I compute about 
7000 Acres of Land to be already taken <lb/>up and four or five
Settlements going forward, Here it is to 
be noted that <lb/>the Marsh Run heads against the head Branches of
the Main South  West <lb/>Run of 
Occaquan River, And that from the Mouth of the Marsh Run&mdash;
<lb/>to the  Mouth of Occaquan River the 
Neck may be computed to be very <lb/>near <sic corr="forty">fourty</sic> Miles a Cross</p> 
 
<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/> 
<p>O<add resp="editor">[n Peto]</add>wmack River in Stafford County
the Land is all in <abbr expan="Generally">Genll: </abbr> Patented 
<lb/><unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear>de,  to within two Miles or
thereabouts of the Falls thereof, Excluding the&mdash; 
<lb/>Land  for which <note target="n2"><abbr expan="Major ">Majr: </abbr> West<hi
rend="sup">3</hi></note> and others have a Warrant for, above and at 
the Falls.&mdash;<lb/>And the upper plantation is computed to be
about five miles below the Falls, there <lb/>was 
formerly a plantation Where <note target="n4"><abbr expan="Major ">Majr: </abbr> Ousley<hi
rend="sup">4</hi></note> lived about three miles below&mdash; 
<lb/>the Falls which is now deserted and grown up to a <sic corr="Thicket, ">Thickett,</sic>
here I must not <lb/><sic corr="omit">omitt</sic> mentioning 
that <note n="DM"><abbr expan="Captain ">Capt.</abbr> McCarty</note> of <name
type="county">Westmoreland County</name> has a patent for <lb/>7000 
Acres of Land about 25 Miles above the Falls of <sic corr="Potomac ">Patowmack</sic>
River&mdash; <lb/>comonly called the <abbr expan="Sugar ">Sugr: </abbr> Lands; 
As for the back Settlements in Stafford county, there <lb/>is none
that I know of, above three Miles from 
<sic corr="Potomac ">Patowmack</sic> River above <name type="stream">Occaquan</name> <lb/>R<add
resp="editor">[un but thr]</add>ee or four lately begun about 
<add resp="editor">[8 or]</add> 10 miles up t<add resp="editor">[he
south?]</add> Branch of <lb/><name type="stream">Pohick Run</name>, 
and it holds Generally so as <sic corr="low ">loe</sic> as Acquia Creek that there is
<lb/>none above four or five Miles from 
Navagable Water, but what are upon the <lb/>Main Runs of Occaquan,
where there are at least ten or 
twelve lately begun <lb/>but as I hinted before by Some persons
Reputed to be within the Bounds of 
<lb/>the  Brent Town Charter&mdash;&mdash; thus</p> 
 
<p>Worthy <abbr expan="Sir">Sr </abbr>&mdash;</p> 
 
<p>I have presum'd to <sic corr="Commit">Committ</sic> my rude Notions to&mdash; <lb/>Paper,
Always esteeming it my Duty to Exert 
my <lb/>best Abilitys for y<add resp="editor">[our serv]</add>ice
when <unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear> please 
<lb/>to lay  <abbr expan="Your ">Yor: </abbr> comands upon me; Hoping that if I have <lb/>been
wide of giving the Satisfaction you 
Expected&mdash;<lb/>it will be imputed to the Intricacy of the
Subject <lb/>and not to my want of Zeal for <abbr expan="Your ">Yor: </abbr> 
Service, being <lb/>as in Duty Bound,</p> 
 
<closer><abbr expan="Your ">Yor: </abbr> most Obliged <lb/>and Most Humble Servt:<lb/><lb/> 
<signed><abbr expan="Thomas ">Tho: </abbr> Hooper.</signed> 
</closer> 
 
</div1> 
</body> 
 
<back> 
<div1 type="notes"> 
<head>NOTES</head> 
 
<note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted: </hi>Brock
Collection, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical
Gardens, San Marino, California. This is the recipient's copy.</note> 
 
<note id="n1">[1] Thomas Hooper was appointed sheriff of Stafford
County in 1719.  He  was involved with RC's affairs as later letters
will show.</note> 
 
<note id="n3">[3] This probably is John West (d. <hi
rend="italics">ante</hi> 1748), third of that name in Virginia.
Fairfax Harrison speculates that he may have lived on the north
branch of Little Hunting Creek, "where the 'West's Grove' of later
generations stood." (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. .
. .</title></bibl></cit>)</note> 
 
<note id="n4">[4] Probably Thomas Owsley, clerk of Stafford
County.</note> 
 
 
</div1> 
</back> 
</text> 
 
 
</TEI.2> 
