<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C20g13d">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins,
1720 July 13</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia
Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 14 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL:
http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, 1720 July
13</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>unpublished</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Source copy
consulted:   Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227,
Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San
Marino, California.
</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic
Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject
Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1720-07-13</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term
type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C20g13dT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1720-07-13"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C20g13d</idno>
<title></title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant July 13, 1720, in a
letter by the <hi rend="italics">Carter</hi> that he is shipping 60 hogsheads of tobacco on
her, and 10 more in the <hi rend="italics">Mercury</hi>; he expects 11 pence per pound or he
will lose money. He reports that all goods came in good order but
coats for his two daughters were not included and should be sent next
season. He sends an order for more goods, writing "You tell me You
lay out my money wth. as much Caution as If It were Yor. own, This I
must Confess is all I can desire, yett give me leave to Say some of
them seems to be extraordinary Dear,"   and chides Dawkins about his
suggestion that Carter should follow Mrs. Heath's example in his
spending. "I must cutt my Coat according to my own Cloth and bless
God I am able to Do so well as I Do," he concludes. He presses
Dawkins to find employment for Ben Graves, the son of Carter's old
friend, ship captain Thomas Graves, and then discusses debts due
Dawkins from Thomas Cunningham, Patrick Connolly, and Mr. Heath. He
adds that he wants Dawkins to give him more information about his
sons, then in England at school, and especially about their expenses
which Carter thinks high and suggests that he may move them to the
Manchester School. He reports a bill of exchange, drawn on Dawkins,
that he has given Edmund Jenings, and that he has had numerous deaths
in his slave "familys" which are costing him a great deal to replace.
He also chides Dawkins for suggesting that they sell the <hi rend="italics">Carter</hi>
pointing out "unless another Ship Supplys her place Yor. business
will soon droope here." He asks for accounts from the <hi rend="italics">Catherine</hi>, and
expresses the hope that he will make some money from the <hi rend="italics">Carter's</hi>
voyage that will offset his losses from "Hastewell's estate."


</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="WD">William
Dawkins,</note> July 13, 1720</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<corr resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster
County, Virginia]</corr> </name><lb/>
<date value="1720-07-13">July 13. 1720</date><lb/>
Mr. <abbr expan="William ">Wm. </abbr> Dawkins<lb/>
Sir.&mdash;</dateline>
</opener>

<p>This Accompanys the <note n="CS"><name type="ship">Carter</name></note> She is loaded at &pound;10 <lb/>per
<sic corr="ton">Tun</sic> wch I hope will in some measure <sic
corr="retrieve">retreive </sic>the great <lb/>Great losses upon
he<corr resp="editor">[r] </corr> late Voyages, <abbr expan="Captain ">Capt.</abbr> > <corr resp="editor">[Baily]</corr>  Kent is threatned <lb/>Mightily to be
remembred when a Scarce Year comes but <lb/>that humour will go neer
soon to blow over There is no <lb/>reason that we who venture our
money Should be losers <lb/>by It&mdash;</p>

<p>There is in her 60 hogsheads of my Crop Tobo. coming to <lb/>You,
and 10 more Stemmed are designd to you per the <name
type="ship">Mercury</name> <lb/>wch. makes Yor. Quota 100 hhds
according to Yor. Desire. If <lb/>You Do not give us Eleven pence per
pound. now <sic corr="Freights">Freits</sic> are so high <lb/>we shall gett nothing, 
</p>

<p>The Goods You sent me came in good order, but the <lb/>two Coats
for <add place="supralinear">my</add> two Youngest Girls were never
sent, pray <lb/>lett me have Them the next Year all that were at the
<sic corr="opening">opning</sic> <lb/>the Goods that came for my
Children can vouch for the truth <lb/>of this, </p>

<p>Herein is an <sic corr="Invoice ">Invoyce</sic> for Goods to Supply my <lb/><sic corr="Families ">Family's</sic> the
next Year wherein I have bin as good a husband <lb/>as possibly I
can, You tell me You lay out my money <lb/>wth. as much Caution as If
It were Yor. own, This I must Con=<lb/>=fess is all I can desire,
<sic corr="yet ">yett</sic> give me leave to Say some <lb/>of them seems to be extraordinary
Dear, The earrings and <lb/>the <note target="n1">Tomb Stone</note>
cost abundance more than I expected or <lb/>Intended. I shall be
<sic corr="obliged ">obligd</sic> to You to lett me be the Master of <lb/>my own money, You <sic
corr="talk">taulk</sic> vainly to me in making <lb/><note
target="n2">Mrs. Heath</note> my Pattern, had I but one Daughter and
<lb/>She the Descendant of Two Successive Muck worms, perhaps <lb/>a
parallel might not be improper, my Circumstances <lb/>are other ways.
I must <sic corr="cut ">cutt</sic> my Coat according to my own <lb/>Cloth and bless God I am
able to Do so well as I Do
</p>

<p>I'm heartily sorry for poor <note target="n3">Ben Graves's</note>
misfortune <lb/>he's an honest brick man and I believe will hardly
long want <lb/>an Employ I shall be very well pleasd to hear he <sic corr="gets ">getts</sic>
<lb/>a Good one. His bro[<corr resp="editor">the]</corr> r Adam made a
wrong Step when <lb/><lb/>he left the <name type="ship">Carter</name>
however <sic corr="I think ">mythinks</sic> You Should be <lb/>So Generous to the memory of That
Good man 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
his father to find him a suitable birth in Some of Yor. <lb/>Ships
&amp; If my word will go any length wth. You <sic corr="it is ">tis</sic> my <lb/>Desire You
take care of him. </p>

<p>Yor. Debts I take the Same care of as I do of my own <lb/>gett
them when I can wth. out Law. <name type="person"><abbr expan="Thomas ">Thos. </abbr>
Cunningham</name> <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> <lb/><abbr expan="paid ">pd.</abbr> me upon Yor. Accot. his Debt of 26/3.
<note target="n4"><name type="person">Patrick Conolly</name></note>
is <lb/>in my Debt as well as Yors. he <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> two hogsheads on board
the <lb/>Carter to whom he Intends them <sic corr="yET ">Yett</sic> I dont know I shall
<lb/>Give You a line more <abbr expan="about ">abt. </abbr> <add place="supralinear">some</add>
other of Yor. Debts in another <lb/>Letter. 
</p>

<p>Mr. Heaths Debts are so scatter'd I dont know wt. <lb/>will
become of many of them but we shall write to him <lb/>A Joint Lettr.
I find he dos not come into my proposal <lb/><abbr expan="About ">Abt. </abbr> Mr. Jacksons Debt
To give him <sic corr="Satisfaction ">Sattisfaction</sic> In that <lb/>matter I have sent him the
Stated Accot. from our <lb/>records of that Estate whereby It appears
I have paid <lb/>off more Debts, Than the Estate amounted to
Including the <lb/>value of the land I sold &amp; sure Mr. Heath is
not such a <lb/>violent lover of money to Desire I Should pay other
<lb/>mens Debts out of my own Estate.</p>

<p>I Should be oblig'd to You If You took more frequent
<lb/><sic corr="Opportunities ">Opportunitys</sic> to give me an accot. of the welfare of my Sons
<lb/>I have not had one line concerning them since The Carter <lb/>I
want very much to know w<add resp="editor">[ha]</add>t. I am to trust
to In relation <lb/>of their maintenance, You gave me Yor. opinion
The two <lb/>Eldest would stand me in &pound;40 <sic corr="apiece">a
Ps.</sic> If you run me out any <lb/>more money upon them I'm upon
<sic corr="thoughts"><abbr expan="Thoughts ">Thots. </abbr></sic> of removing them <lb/>to <note
target="n5">Manchester School</note> where I am well <sic corr="advised ">advisd</sic> I can
main-<lb/>=tain them for a great deal less &amp; their education
<lb/>Every <sic corr="bit ">whitt</sic> as Good.,</p>

<p>I drew on You the other Day for &pound;200 payable to <lb/><note
n="EJ">Edmund Jennings</note> <abbr expan="Esquire ">Esqr </abbr> wch. request You to Ans<corr resp="editor">[we]</corr> r at time <lb/>Some more Drafts I Shall be
<sic corr="forced ">forc't</sic> to make <sic corr="before ">er'e</sic> long <lb/>have had great losses of my Negroes in
my <sic corr="families ">familys</sic> <lb/>this last winter The recruiting of wch. Swallows a
great <lb/>Deal of money, If You had sent me an Accot. Currt. <lb/>I
could have bin more Exact in my Care not to outrun <lb/>The
Constable,</p>

<p>You press me to Send You a Certificate <lb/>for the Cannister of
Tea You sent me two Year ago 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
It is here inclosed according to Yor. form, Sign'd by Mr. Pra<corr resp="editor">[tt]</corr>  <lb/>&amp; <note target="n6"><name
type="person">Mrs. <abbr expan="John ">Jno. </abbr> Robinson</name></note> whose hands and
persons are both well <lb/>enough known in England,</p>

<p>You make a proposal <abbr expan="about ">abt. </abbr> selling the <lb/>Carter I have reason to
fall into It I'm sure, I can hardly <lb/>believe You are in earnest
when that time comes You'l be the <lb/>Greatest Sufferer, unless
another Ship <sic corr="Supplies ">Supplys</sic> her place <lb/>Yor. business will soon <sic corr="drop ">droope</sic>
here,</p> 

<p>The Ship <name type="ship">Catherine's</name> Accots. You say are
not <sic corr="Yet ">Yett</sic> <lb/>made up when They are I shall be glad to gett some of
my <lb/>money back again, I hope If The Carter makes any thing by
<lb/>this voyage I shall be in the way of Getting my Debt <lb/>from
<note target="n7">Hastewells Estate,</note> You must Expect never to
Escape <lb/>Dunning till You have <sic corr="licked ">lickd</sic> me whole in that matter
<lb/>wch. Shall Conclude me at present </p>

<closer>Sir Yor. very humble Servt</closer>
</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi>  Robert Carter
Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art
Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed:
<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . .
.</title> pp. 10-13.</bibl></cit></note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of
"Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than
"Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially
to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for
clarity.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] RC's second wife, <note n="EWC">Elizabeth (Landon)
Willis,</note> had died in 1719, and the tombstone probably was to
mark her grave at Christ Church.</note>

<note id="n2">[2] When Louis Wright edited this letter for his 1940
edition, he speculated that Mrs. Heath might be a Mrs. Samuel Heath
of Northumberland County. According to more recent research by Alan
Simpson, Mrs. Heath probably was Katherine (Bailey) Heath, daughter
of <note n="AB2">Arthur Bailey, Jr.</note> and granddaughter of <note
n="RB2">Robert Bristow.</note> Bailey and Bristow had been partners
in a London mercantile firm and had owned ships in the Virginia
trade. Carter had lived in the Bailey household in the six years that
he spent at school and would have known Arthur Bailey's wife well. As
an heir to both wealthy men, Mrs. Heath could readily afford the
expensive jewelry of which Dawkins wrote Carter. (<cit><bibl
n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p.
11</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="A3">Simpson. "Robert Carter's
Schooldays." p. 173.)</bibl></cit></note>

<note id="n3">[3] Benjamin and Adam Graves were the sons of Captain
Thomas Graves, long a captain of vessels trading to Virginia, and a
special friend of RC.</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Patrick Connelly appears on a 1716 list of
titheables in Christ Church Parish, Lancaster County
(<cit><bibl>"Titheables in Lancaster Co., 1716." <title>William and
Mary Quarterly.</title> 1st. ser., 21(1912): 106-112, on p.
107</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] RC undoubtedly knew of the Manchester Grammar
School, in 1720 already over 200 years old. </note>

<note id="n6">[6] Katherine (Armistead) Hone Beverley married John
Robinson (1683-1749) about 1701; they lived in Middlesex County. 
(See the discussion of John Robinson in <bibl n="B39">Rutman and
Rutman, <title>A Place in Time: Middlesex. . . .
</title></bibl>)</note>

<note id="n7">[7] This was probably Edward Hastewell, a London
merchant who signed on November 23, 1699&mdash;as did <note
n="MP">Micajah Perry</note> and <note n="JG">John
Goodwin</note>&mdash; a memorial, on behalf of themselves and others
trading to Virginia, to the Commissioners for Trade and Plantations.
In a letter of July 13, 1720, to the Perrys, RC referred to Hastewell
as one of the owners of the <hi rend="italics">Carter.</hi> </note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised November 20, 2008.</hi></note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>