<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C20g14c">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah and Richard Perry, July 14, 1720</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 8 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah and Richard Perry, July 14, 1720</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>unpublished</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1720-07-14</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C20g14cT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 pp.</extent>
<date value="1720-07-14"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C20g14c</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah and Richard Perry, July 14, 1720</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchants Micajah and Richard Perry, July 14, 1720, concerning the affairs of the Lloyd estate (the lands belonging to John Lloyd, widower of Carter's niece, who had gone to England after his wife's death) that Carter aparently managed for the Perrys who held a lease from Lloyd. He reports bills of exchange drawn against the estate's accounts for Dr. Belfield's and Richard Meeks' (the overseer) salaries as well as one of his own for his use of four slaves on his lands, and some miscellaneous expenses. He comments that the estate's poor lands make it difficult to produce sufficient income, and that the estate's slave cooper is a "Bungler at the Trade" and the tobacco shipping casks are poor. He closes by asking the Perrys to remember the trouble he has had managing the estate's affairs if they should "find It necessary to give up Yor. Interest in That Affair." </p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="MP">Micajah</note> and Richard Perry, July 14, 1720</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1720-07-14">July 14th. 1720-</date><lb/>
Messrs. Micajh. &amp; Richd.<lb/>Perry<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Gent&mdash;&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>You have herein a bill of Lading for 54 hogsheads of <lb/>The <add resp="editor">[<note n="LL">Lloyd estate</note> tobacco]</add> mark being the Produce of The Labour of That Estate, The <lb/>Overseers Shares Excluded for the Year 1719 how long That concern will <lb/>be under my care I <sic corr="can't">cant</sic> tell, The Familys however will want goods <lb/>yearly an <sic corr="invoice">Invoyce</sic> for them for the next year is herein Enclosd wch. You <lb/>may either send or <sic corr="omit">omitt</sic> as You please I have drawn on you upon the <lb/>Accot. of That Concern as followeth, To Witt for the Impost of these <lb/>Tobos., To Doctr. <sic corr="Belfield">Belfeild</sic>, for &pound;15 for his <sic corr="salary">Sallary</sic> &amp; Medicines for <lb/>Looking after the Slaves in the Year 1719, To Dr. <sic corr="Belfield">Belfeild</sic> for &pound;50 <lb/>for his Damages <sic corr="sustained">Sustaind</sic> by the nonrepairs of his housing &amp;c <lb/>According to the tenour of <sic corr="Lloyd's lease">Loyd's Leese</sic> wch. You give me Directions <lb/>to pay, To <abbr expan="Richard">Richd.</abbr>
 <note n="RM"><sic corr="Meeks">Meekes</sic></note> The <abbr expan="general">genl.</abbr>
 Overseer &pound;35"-"- his Salary <lb/>for the Year 1719 wch. Desire You to pay on accot. of That Estate <lb/>my own Accot. will be but Small for working of four of the <lb/>Slaves upon my Lands, for 20 Bus<add resp="editor">[he]</add>ls of Salt &amp; for <sic corr="tailor's">Taylors</sic> <lb/>work amounting to as per The Enclosd Accot. 25"5"6 <lb/>wch. I desire Credit for. The rest of the Contingent Charges <lb/>we have made a Shift to Defray, by Sale of Corn &amp; provision</p>

<p>I have already sufficiently acquainted You wth. the <lb/>meaness of these Lands for the maintena<add place="supralinear">n</add>ce of so many slaves <lb/>and how Impossible It is to make <sic corr="tolerable">tollerable</sic> Crops wth. Such <lb/>A number To save the Charge of <sic corr="cooper's">Cooprs.</sic> work we have Em=<lb/>=ployd a Negro belonging to the Estate who is but a Bungler <lb/>at the Trade, The Tobo. is all <abbr expan="stemmed">Stem'd</abbr>
 &amp; straight Lade <lb/>but <sic corr="the casks they are">The Cask It is</sic> in are not so good as I could wish them</p>

<p>Whenever you find It necessary to give up Yor. <lb/>Interest in That Affair I hope <sic corr="you'll">You'l</sic> not forgett me for the <lb/>Trouble <add place="supralinear">&amp; care</add> I have bin at in the <abbr expan="management">managemt.</abbr>
 for the several Years I have <lb/>had It in my possession wch. is all I shall add at present </p>

<closer>but Gent<add resp="editor">[lemen]</add><lb/> Yor. most <lb/>hum<add resp="editor">[ble]</add> ser<add resp="editor">[vant]</add></closer>

</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>
<note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi>  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 21-22.</bibl></cit>
</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and state have been added for clarity.</note><lb/>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>