<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C20g13k">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Richard Perry,
July 13, 1720</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia
Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 13 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL:
http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Richard Perry, July 13,
1720</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>unpublished</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter
Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art
Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic
Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject
Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1720-07-13</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term
type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C20g13kT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1720-07-13"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C20g13k</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Richard Perry, July 13,
1720</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes at length to London merchant Richard Perry
(son of Micajah), July 13, 1720, thanking him for his advice about
handling attacks of gout; Carter will no longer drink claret. He
finds the prices realized for his tobacco quite acceptable but warns
again of his concern about selling his tobacco near the end of the
market, and then comments on Perry's complaint of Carter's tobacco
having "a Smoaky smell," noting that it is necessary to use fires in
the curing houses when there is "funky foggy weather."   He agrees
with Perry that the opening of the "The Spanish Trade as well as the
French" should make good markets for tobacco, and notes that ship
captains will be reporting at home the Virginian's expectations of
the best crop in some years. He is resolving to be more careful in
his tobacco production since he is irritated that Mr. Pratt gets
better prices for tobacco "that comes from all parts of their County
low lands as well as high" when his own lands are better. He
continues with comments on his bank stock and annuities, and "printed
proposals of the South Sea Company &amp; the Bank to the Parliament"
which Col. Harrison had when Carter was in Williamsburg. He asks that
Perry "act wth. the same prudent 
regard to my Interest as you Do for Yor. own."  And he adds some
remarks about his upcoming heavy expenses. He concludes by thanking
Perry for "the commendable Character You give me of my Son" which
pleases Carter as the expenses of John's education have been heavy
and any more would have left him "at a loss to know 
how to keep the rest of my family from want." </p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="MP">Richard
Perry,</note> July 13, 1720</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster
County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1720-07-13">July 13 1720</date><lb/>
Mr. <abbr expan="Richard ">Richd. </abbr> Perry<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>Yors. of the 13th. of <abbr expan="February ">Feb. </abbr> By a
Marylander <lb/>came to me 5 Days
<sic corr="ago">agon</sic>, The kind advice You give me for <lb/>the
<abbr expan="management">managemt</abbr>
 of my self in the Gout is very Acceptable, I <lb/>have had no touch
of It since my first <sic corr="fit. ">fitt.</sic> It made me quite
<lb/>leave off Drinking
<sic corr="claret">Clarrett</sic> as I resolve to do every thing else
<lb/><add place="supralinear">I shall be advis'd</add><lb/> That may
any ways contribute to that Distemper&mdash;</p>

<p>The <sic corr="prices">prizes</sic> You have sold my Tobacco at
hitherto I am well Enough <lb/><sic corr="pleased ">pleasd</sic>
wth. If you do but put off the
rest as well I shall be easy. <lb/>These <sic corr="lag">lagg</sic>
Sales are always <add place="supralinear">a terrour to me</add> You
complain of some <lb/>of my Tobo. having a <sic
corr="smoky">Smoaky</sic> smell I do not know the meaning <lb/>of It,
our Tobo. houses are Separated <sic corr="far">farr</sic> enough from
our <lb/>Q<corr resp="editor">[uarte]</corr> rs indeed Sometimes in
funky foggy weather <add place="supralinear">when Tobo. is just upon
turning</add> we are <sic corr="forced">forst</sic> <lb/>to make
smothers <del> under our <sic corr="houses ">howses</sic></del> <add
place="supralinear"> in
our <sic corr="houses">howses</sic></add> to Dry It, &amp; this is
what's <lb/>practiced by the best planters in virginia &amp; Ever was
since I <lb/>have bin acquainted wth. The
making of Tobo., We have <lb/>hopes The Spanish Trade as well as the
French being open <lb/>You will not find Yor. selves <sic
corr="mistaken">mistaking</sic> in Yor. Expectati<corr
resp="editor">[on] </corr>  <lb/>of a Standing <sic
corr="market">Markett</sic> for some Years, we reckon we have had
<lb/>a great many fewer Ships This Year than the last, indeed
<lb/><sic corr="they'll">they'l</sic> all go <sic
corr="near">neer</sic> to return full &amp; Some Tobacco will be left
<lb/>&amp; They will bring You the <sic corr="Story">Storey</sic> of
a fair Crop being in <lb/>the Ground. but how that will Issue no body
knows It <lb/>looks hitherto to promise to be better Tobo. than we
have <lb/>had for some Years I take up <abbr expan="resolutions
">resoluts: </abbr> to be nicer in the <lb/>handling of mine
than Ever I was <sic corr="Yet, ">Yett,</sic> It troubles <lb/>me
not a little that <note
target="n1">Mr. Pratt</note> should gett more for <lb/>his
Miscelaneous stuff that comes from all parts of <lb/>their County
<add place="supralinear">low</add> lands as well as high than I do
<lb/>for mine that is made wth. my own people &amp; upon as good
&amp; <lb/>proper <add resp="editor">[lands]</add> as any body can
boast of</p>

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<p>You have <sic corr="set ">sett</sic> me right about my bank Stock
I was afraid 100 <add
place="supralinear">taken away</add> would have <lb/><abbr
expan="proved">prov'd</abbr>
 100 Diminution but It seems the remaining 90 Stands in the place of
<lb/>The 100, Yor. observation of the Annuities I can say little to
more Than I <lb/>already have. In the begining of May at <abbr
expan="Williamsburg">Wmsburg</abbr>
 <note n="NH"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Colo. </abbr> Harrison</note>
by some <lb/>means had <sic corr="gotten ">gott</sic> the
<add place="supralinear">printed</add> proposals of the South Sea
Company &amp; the Bank <lb/>to the Parliament, wch. presently <abbr
expan="alarmed">alarm'd</abbr>
 me and from York <abbr expan="River">Rivr.</abbr>
<lb/>I <sic corr="wrote">writ</sic> to You <abbr
expan="about">abt</abbr>
. It. Desiring You <add place="supralinear">would</add> act wth. the
same prudent <lb/>regard to my Interest as you Do for Yor. own there
I left <lb/>It then And So I think must do now. That annuity what
time <lb/>I had come in It whether 96 or 99 Years I never <sic
corr="Yet ">Yett</sic> knew.
You may <lb/>please to remember that fund was never <sic corr="yet
">yett</sic> very
grateful <lb/>to me I took It in compliment to You because You told
me you had <lb/><sic corr="purchased ">purchasd</sic> It for me
otherwise I had rather bin wth.out <sic corr="Its">It</sic> 4 perCt.
is
<lb/>so poor a <sic corr="premium">premio</sic> I will never <add
place="supralinear">take so little again </add>This Year <lb/>I Shall
find so many ways for the Drawing out my money I have <lb/>no
occasion to <del>try</del> <add place="supralinear"> contrive</add>
new ones for <add place="supralinear">letting go any more upon</add>
Interest. <del>[ . . . ] the bank stock &amp; the<lb/>Annuity I have
already [ . . . ] If you do not find It necessary to<lb/>take in my
money I would have [ . . . ] </del> Yor. Father in his Lettr. 
 of the 20th of <abbr expan="February">Feb.</abbr>
 tells <lb/>me the bank <add place="supralinear"><sic corr="Does
">Doth</sic></add> buy up
all the Annuities they can <lb/>whether this will be any Salve to me
I know not <abbr expan="It is">Tis</abbr>
 <lb/>all in a great Measure a <sic corr="mystery ">mysterie</sic>
to us &amp; So I Shall <add
place="supralinear">pass</add> It, <lb/>The part I am to hold in
Bagwells Ship, a Draft of &pound;500 <lb/>I made on You <abbr
expan="the other">t'other</abbr>
 Day to <note n="EJ"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo. </abbr>
Jenings</note> &amp; some other large
<lb/>uses I must make of you in a Short time will sink me low
<lb/>enough If not too low I'm afraid for any present <abbr
expan="thoughts">thots.</abbr>
 of further <lb/>purchases </p>

<p>You please me very well in the commendable Character You
<lb/>give me of <note n="JC1">my Son.</note> <abbr expan="It
is">'tis</abbr>
 no small <sic corr="Satisfaction ">Sattisfaction</sic> to me to
have <lb/>a pennyworth for my Penny
to have spent so much money upon <lb/>a dunce or a Blockhead had
bin 
 most <sic corr="Intolerable ">Intollerable</sic> &amp; <sic
corr="Yet ">Yett</sic> <lb/>After all to have a <sic
corr="finicky">finicall</sic> inside &amp; not a Suitable Cover-
<lb/>=ing for the out Side <add place="supralinear">will</add> make
but a Schymity gentleman <del>I'm<lb/>Suspicious Mr. Randolph
<sic corr="has ">hath </sic></del> bad &amp; mean company to be sure
<lb/><sic corr="has ">hath </sic> bin  the bane of many a Young man
but certainly
&pound;200 <lb/>per Annum is no such Scanty Allowance to lay him
under any <lb/>Such Disadvantage If It be, I shall be at a loss to
know <lb/>how to keep the rest of my family from want That Yors. may
<lb/>Swim in a much Greater Affluence is the Cordial Desire of
</p><lb/><lb/>

<closer>Sir Yor. sincere humble Servt.<lb/><lb/>

<seg type="postscript">In my <abbr expan="account">Acct.</abbr>
 Currt. you omitted <lb/>giving me credit for my 30 <lb/>hogsheads
of Tobo. per Hancock indeed You <lb/>likewise omit making me debtor
<lb/>with a large bill you have <abbr expan="paid">pd.</abbr>
 for me <lb/>both which I expect will have their birth <lb/>in my
next Accot.</seg></closer><lb/><lb/>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>
<note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi>  Robert Carter
Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art
Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed:
<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . .
.</title> pp. 1-4.</bibl></cit>
</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of
"Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than
"Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially
to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for
clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Louis Wright has speculated that Mr. Pratt might
be William Pratt of Gloucester County as there were several Pratts
active in Virginia at this time. In his letter to Micajah and Richard
Perry written this same day, RC noted that "Mr. Pratt took care of
those [letters] for James rivr &amp; York" which makes Wright's
speculation as good as any. In the close-knit society of his time and
class, RC would certainly have learned what others were receiving for
their crops, but a definite identification of the irritating Mr.
Pratt is not possible. (<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of
Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 2.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised November 26,
2008.</hi></note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>