<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C20i27d">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, September 27and October 10, 1720</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, September 27and October 10, 1720</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1940</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1720-09-27</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C20i27dT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1720-09-27"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C20i27d.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, September 27 and October 10, 1720</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Micajah Perry, September 27and October 10, 1720, to inform him of bills of exchange he has endorsed and sent to Perry for &pound;281/16/11 being payment he has received for slaves from the ship Mercury, owned by Chamberlayne &amp; Sitwell. He believes the bills are good, but gives instructions for Perry's payment to the other merchants should any be protested. He reports the death of John Baylor, "The great Negro Seller &amp; in all respects 
the greatest Mercht. we had among us."  In a post script dated October 10th, Carter reported the depradations of a "Spanish privateer," but the paper of the addition is so badly damaged that it is nearly illegible.</p>

</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, September 27and October 10, 1720</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1720-09-27">Sepr. 27. 1720</date><lb/>
Messrs. Perry<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute><abbr expan="Gentlemen">Gent.</abbr>
&mdash;&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>The business of this is only to advi<lb/>=se You that this Day I have remitted Ten bills of <abbr expan="exchange">Exch</abbr>
 <lb/>all wth. my Endorsment to Messrs. Frans. Chamberlayn<add resp="editor">[e]</add> <lb/>&amp; Frans. Sitwell owners of the Ship Mercury amt.<lb/>=ing to the Sum of Two Hundred Eighty one pound <lb/>&amp; Sixteen Shill. &amp; Eleven pence paid to me <lb/>for accots. of Some Endorsment to Messrs. <abbr expan="Francis">Frans.</abbr> Chamberlayne <lb/>&amp; Francis Sitwell owners of the Ship <name type="ship">Mercury</name> amt<lb/>=.ing to the Sum of Two hundred Eighty one pound <lb/>Sixteen <abbr expan="shillings">Shill.</abbr>
 &amp; Eleven pence paid to me <lb/>for accots. of Some of their Slaves sold, these bills <lb/>I have good reason to believe will all meet wth. <lb/>due honour but If contrary to my Expectation any <lb/>of them Should be protested the <abbr expan="gentleman">Gent</abbr> Concernd have <lb/>the Same Direc<add resp="editor">[tion]</add>s as they had wth. the former bills <lb/>I remitted them, That is they are to deliver up <lb/>the protests to You That After sixty Days You <lb/><add resp="editor">[are]</add> to make <abbr expan="payment">paymt.</abbr> upon my Accot. taking proper <lb/><unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear> from them, this is my undertaking wth. <lb/>them, &amp; this I desire You to Comply wth. sending m<add resp="editor">[e]</add> <lb/>in wt. protest You receive by the first safe Conve=<lb/>=niency that offers&mdash;</p>

<p>Not many days ago I gave You the trouble of a <lb/>Lettr. to some length to wch. please to be <abbr expan="referred">referd.</abbr>
</p> 

<p>Poor <note target="n1">John Baylor</note> hath lately taken his leave <lb/>of this world The great Negro Seller &amp; in all respects <lb/>the greatest <abbr expan="merchant">Mercht.</abbr> we had among us, he made a mighty <lb/>noise while living.  I wish for the sake of his remain <lb/>at the winding up of his Cotton, the Cry did not <lb/>Exceed the wool </p>

<p>I am Gent <lb/>
Yor. most humble Servt. </p>


<p>A Postscript added To Mr. Perrys last <abbr expan="letter">Letr</abbr>
</p>

<p>Sir&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<abbr expan="October">Octr</abbr>
 10, 1720 </p>

<p><sic corr="It will">Twill</sic> not be amiss to add a Line of the <lb/>late damages done upon our Coast by a Spanish <lb/>privateer, The 28th of last may he took a Sloop <lb/>belonging to Martin, Nelson, &amp; Jones with <unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear> <lb/>th<unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear> Among a great many other prizes he <lb/>took a <name type="city">Liverpool</name> sloop last from <sic corr="Potomac">Petomack</sic> <lb/>wch. had the Good fortune to be retaken by a Sloop <lb/><unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear> On board were <lb/>two Spaniards and one Irishman <lb/><unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear> of war <unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear> and is to be ready this fortnight <lb/>but <unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear> ready nor could <unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear> no assurance <lb/>from her for the <abbr expan="captain">Captn.</abbr>
 declares <unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear> he has <lb/>received orders from the Admiral <unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear>ington <unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear>since then<lb/>
<unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear>[ . . . ]</unclear> I had <lb/>Just now from <note n="MP1">Collo. Page</note></p>


<closer><seg type="postscript"></seg></closer>

</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>
<note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi>  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 53-54, and 57.</bibl></cit>
 The page on which the post script is written is one of the worst in the letter book with a great deal of bleed through from the reverse and places where the ink has eaten entirely through the paper.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and state have been added for clarity. Either Carter dictated that the letter was to be sent to the "Messrs. Perry," or his clerk wrote this from habit; Carter knew that Richard Perry had died in April.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] John Baylor (d. 1720) lived first in Gloucester, and was burgess in 1692.  He subsequently moved to King and Queen County (which he represented in the Assembly in 1718), and became a prominent merchant with stores in Gloucester, King and Queen, and New Kent counties.  "His principal warehouses were at Baylor's on the Mattaponai between Walkerton and King &amp; Queen Court House." (<cit><bibl>"The Baylor Family." <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography.</title> 6[1898-1899]: 197-199.</bibl></cit>)</note>
</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>