<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C20i19b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas Evans, September19, 1720</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 5 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas Evans, September19, 1720</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1940</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1720-09-19</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C20i19T">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1720-09-19"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C20i19b.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas Evans, September19, 1720</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Thomas Evans, September19, 1720, that he has received Evans' April letter and is pleased with the tobacco sales reported in it. He adds that this years crop is plentiful and the best of it "superlatively good." He asks Evans to buy him a winter suit of broadcloth "of a suitable Colr." with two pairs of stockings of the same color; "Mr. How hath my Measure fitts me very well." He closes by reporting that he has not received the goods Evans sent to York River for him but expects them shortly.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="TE">Thomas Evans,</note> September19, 1720</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1720-09-19">Sepr. 19. 1720.</date><lb/>
Mr. Thos. Evans<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p>I have now Yors. of the 15th &amp; 28th of April am <abbr expan="pleased">pleas'd</abbr>
 to <lb/>find my Tobo. was all <sic corr="gone">Gon</sic> at 11d may the last Years Crop come <lb/>to as good a Markett, It is a living price &amp; truly to have less <lb/>will make but poor doings wth. us. This Year the <sic corr="vogue">Voge</sic> is <lb/>we have <abbr expan="generally">Genly.</abbr>
 a plentifull harvest the best of It <lb/>will be, It will be superlatively good, God willing 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
I resolve to be wonderfully nice in the handling <lb/>of mine.</p>

<p>I hope the Carter is with You before this <lb/><unclear>[. . .] </unclear>I omitted Sending to You for any wearing <lb/>Cloths, but now find I shall want a winter Suit <lb/>before the return of the next Shipping Therefore If <lb/>this <sic corr="gets">getts</sic> <unclear>[. . .]</unclear> brought to you please to send <lb/>me wool Suit of broad cloth <unclear>[. . .]</unclear>, <lb/>of a suitable <abbr expan="color">Colr.</abbr>
 to cost between 8 &amp; 10 pounds <lb/>a <abbr expan="pair">pr. </abbr>
of fine worsted &amp; a <abbr expan="pair">pr. </abbr> <abbr expan="milled">Milld.</abbr>
 Stockings <lb/>of the same Colour, Mr. How hath my Measure <lb/>fitts me very well </p>

<p>I have not <sic corr="yet">yett</sic> got the Goods <lb/>You sent me into <name type="river">York river</name> but hope I shall <lb/>in a little time wch. Shall be all at present from </p>

<closer>Sir <lb/>Yor. humble Servt.
</closer>

</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>
<note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi>  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 48.</bibl></cit>
</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and state have been added for clarity.</note><lb/>

<note>At the beginning of the second page of the draft of this letter (folio 19r), the letter book paper is of a different type, much more absorbent, causing thicker lines and much bleed through.  In addition, the outer edge of each page has damp stains that affect the background color. However, some of the letters entered on this absorbant paper were written with an ink that was not as easily absorbed; while it has faded a good deal, it is often easier to read. </note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>