<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C21a17a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Carter, January 17, 1721</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Carter, January 17, 1721</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1940</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1721-01-17</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C21a17aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1721-01-17"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C21a17a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Carter, January 17, 1721</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his son, John Carter, January 17, 1721, briefly reporting family news, and then turning to the newly-acquired lease of the Northern Neck proprietary which he has just received from Micajah Perry in London. He informs John that he needs to have the kind of power to make grants of land in the proprietary that he had previously had from Lady Fairfax; he has sent a copy of that power to Perry, and directs John to have it signed before witnesses who are coming to the colony.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to John Carter, January 17, 1721</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1721-01-17">Jan 17th. 1720/21</date><lb/>

</dateline>
<salute>Dear Son John</salute>

</opener>

<p>I writ to You plentifully in Novr. &amp; sent You <lb/>Duplicates. Yor. Relations are all well at this time for what<lb/> I know pray God this may find You &amp; Yor. <abbr expan="brothers">brors.</abbr> in the Same <lb/>s[ta]te Yor. Sister Page hath a Son born.</p>

<p>	I find in the lease <note n="MP">Mr. Perry</note> Sent me for the <note target="n1">Northern Neck</note> <add resp="editor">[Proprietary]</add><lb/> You are one of the Witnesses indeed I desired him to make You <lb/>privy to that affair. I am affraid upon this fall of Tobo. It <lb/>will prove a very disadvantagious bargain to me, I was always <lb/>Inform'd <note n="EJ"><abbr expan="Colonel">Collo.</abbr> Jennings</note> gave but two hundred &amp; fifty pounds <lb/>per Annum for It there is no repenting I am now bound and <lb/>must do the best I can with It, one great perquisite to the <lb/>Estate arises from the Granting away the lands that are <lb/>Yett to take up I doubt not the Lord Fairfax &amp; <note n="WC"><abbr expan="Colonel">Collo.</abbr> Cage</note> <lb/>for their own Interst as well as mine design'd me this Power <lb/>by their Lease &amp; I shall proceed accordingly however I <lb/>would have a fuller power from them have writ to <lb/>Mr. Perry abt. It &amp; have sent him a Coppy of the power I <lb/>received from my Lady Fairfax to Draw another by, <note target="n2">(rebus <lb/>sic Stantibus)</note> I would have You be very carefull of this <lb/>affair &amp; to have It executed before a Suff<add resp="editor">[icien]</add>t Number of <lb/>Witnesses bound to this place, when I am to Expect Yor. Company <lb/>Dont Yett know if not this Shipping to be sure the next It must <lb/>be, wth. my prayrs. for God's blessing upon You and Yor. <abbr expan="brothers">brors.</abbr></p>

<closer> I Conclude at present</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi>  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 63-64.</bibl></cit>
</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to persons abroad. The county and state have been added for clarity.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] For the Northern Neck proprietary, Lord Fairfax, etc., see "Robert Carter and the Northern Neck Proprietary" linked from the opening screen of this site.</note>

<note id="n2">[2] A Latin phrase meaning so long as condtions have not substantially changed.</note>



</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>