<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C21b10a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Carter,
February 10, 1721</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia
Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL:
http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Carter, February 10,
1721</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1940</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter
Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art
Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic
Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject
Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1721-02-10</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term
type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C21b10aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1721-02-10"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C21b10a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Carter, February 10,
1721</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes  to his son John Carter, February 10, 1721,
then
in London, concerning his lease of the Northern Neck proprietary,
asking John to clarify with Colonel William Cage, one of Lady
Fairfax's trustees, whether land grants in the proprietary that
Carter makes must carry only the name of the underage Lord Fairfax,
or those of his trustees as well. He turns to the question of the
Brent Town grant within the proprietary, the need for a survey of its
30,000 acres, and the difficulties that shroud taking up lands there
when the bounds remain unknown. He asks John to pursue the question
of a survey with Robert Bristow, the current owner of the Brenton
grant, and also asks him to contact the heirs of London Alderman John
Jeffreys concerning the 14,000 acres granted to Cadwallader Jones in
Stafford County that has not been settled, and which has not paid
quit rents.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="JC1">John Carter,</note>
February 10,
1721</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <corr resp="editor">[Lancaster
County, Virginia]</corr> </name><lb/>
<date value="1721-02-10"><abbr expan="February ">Feby.  </abbr>10th.
1720/21</date><lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Son John</salute>

</opener>
<p>The Foregoing was to come by a <name type="city">Bristol</name>
man She <sic corr="passed">past</sic> <lb/>by with<corr
resp="editor">[out
stop]</corr> ping Its necessary, to say something more to You
<lb/>about the <xref to="/users/berkeley/#Northern Neck">Northern Neck</xref> affair, The Power of <sic
corr="attorney ">Atturney</sic> already
<lb/>Mentiond to You must be had and I must have the Proprietors
<lb/><abbr expan="Directions ">Direcs. </abbr> in whose name the
Grants
I make for Lands must <lb/>run whether in the <note n="TF">Lord
Fairfax's</note> name
alone or with the <lb/>Addition of <note n="WC"><abbr expan="Colonel
">Collo.</abbr> Cage</note>
&amp; the other Trustee of My Ladys will</p>

<p>I have sent to <note n="MP">Mr. Perry</note> also <sic
corr="copies ">Copys</sic> of the <note
n="BT"><sic corr="Brent Town ">Bronton</sic></note> <sic
corr="patents ">Pattents</sic> <lb/>upon perusial of wch. <abbr
expan="You will ">You'l </abbr> find
My Lord Culpeper in 1686 Grants <lb/>to <note n="RB">Alderman
Bristow </note> and others Thirty Thousand Acres of <lb/>uncertain
Lands in the Back Woods at the rent of two <abbr
expan="shillings ">Shills:</abbr>
 <lb/>per a hundred Acres in 1688 he Releases this Rent and only
<lb/>reserves the acknowledgemt. of a Beaver Skin Yearly in the
<lb/>First Grant there is a Provisoe for my Lord to Survey in the
<lb/><abbr expan="latter ">Lattr.</abbr>
 no notice of any such Provisoe, Brent a long time <lb/>ago makes a
Settlement upon the Lower part of these lands <lb/>soon after his
Death It was deserted and ever since hath <lb/>layn without any
Cultivation from any of the Grantees <lb/>and the bounds of this
Grant wholly unknown to this day <lb/>where they will Extend which
makes people mightily affra<add resp="editor">[id]</add> <lb/>to take
up back Lands very much to the Damage of the 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
Proprietors and I Should think not at all to the advantage of
<lb/>those that Claim this Grant for certainly the more the Lands are
<lb/>Peopled thereabouts the more value will their Estate be of and
<lb/>besides if Any persons shall take new Grants of the Lands by
<lb/>Mistake &amp; Should <sic corr="set ">Sett</sic> down with
their <sic corr="families ">familys</sic> and
<del>Improve</del> <add place="supralinear">make chargable</add>
<lb/>Improvements thereon <abbr expan="it would ">`twould </abbr> be
a harsh Case and I believe
a<lb/>Difficult one to turn them of, upon the whole seeing
accord=<lb/>=ing to my Thoughts <add resp="editor">[everybody's
in]</add>terest Should prompt them <lb/>to Contribute what in them
<sic corr="lies ">lyes</sic> to give bounds to these Lands <lb/>with
all possible Expedition
<note target="n1"><add place="supralinear"><hi rend="italics">I cant
see wt. should
obstruct it</hi></add></note> I shall do all I can when I receive
<lb/><abbr expan="directions ">direcs. </abbr> about It, but <abbr
expan="it would ">`twould </abbr> be
best and Easiest done if both <lb/><sic corr="parties ">partys</sic>
were Consenting and will
pay their proportion of the <lb/>Charge, You are accquainted with
<note n="RB2">Mr. Bristow</note> I believe and <lb/>You know where to
apply to the Proprietors, I would have You <lb/>leave no Stone
<abbr expan="unturned ">unturn'd </abbr> to <sic corr="get
">gett</sic> this business <del>Effected</del> put upon some
<lb/>Foot or other It would be a mighty <sic corr="satisfaction
">Sattisfaction</sic> to the people
<lb/>as well as a benefit to all concernd.</p>

<p><note target="n3"><abbr expan="Esquire ">Esqr</abbr>
Jeoffrys</note> holds 14,000 and <add
resp="editor">[odd]</add> Acres of Land in the <lb/>backwoods of
<name type="place">Stafford County</name> It was never <sic
corr="yet ">yett</sic> Seated or paid <lb/>
any <note target="n2"><sic corr="quit ">Quitt</sic> Rents</note>
nor are the bounds Certainly known. I would <lb/>have You know his
mind <abbr expan="about">abt.</abbr> this Land and where I'm to apply
<lb/>for my <sic corr="quit ">Quitt</sic> Rents, As I suppose the
<sic corr="patents ">Pattent</sic> for them is in
<lb/>the name of <note target="n3">Cadwalliter Jones</note> who
<abbr expan="conveyed ">convey'd </abbr> them over to the
<lb/>Alderman or <abbr
expan="Sir">Sr.</abbr> Jeoffrys this is a matter worth looking
<lb/>After the Rents in my time will come to above four score
<lb/>pound, I tell <note n="MP">Mr. Perry</note> I have instructed
You in all these matters <lb/>and You will Ease him of the greatest
part of the trouble</p>

<closer><seg type="postscript"></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi>  Robert Carter
Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art
Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed:
<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . .
.</title> pp. 64-66.</bibl></cit></note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of
"Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than
"Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially
to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for
clarity.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] This sentence was written into the draft by Robert
Carter as is indicated by the use of italics.</note><lb/>

<note id="n2">[2] Quit rent was the term used for the
payment due from the holder of land to the "lord of the manor," in
this case, to the proprietors of the Northern Neck. Carter as the
proprietor's agent, collected these payments. No services were
required of the landholder as had been true in mediaeval
times.</note><lb/>

<note id="n3">[3] Cadwallader Jones (1652?-1700?), an Indian trader
and fighter, was lieutenant colonel of the Stafford militia. Fairfax
Harrison writes that "in 1677 he patented, with David Jones, 17,114
acres in the Stafford backwoods . . . on the drains of Accotink and
Pohick." (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title>
p. 608.</bibl></cit>) He got into financial trouble, and left for
England in 1687. The holders of many of his debts were the Jeffreys,
prominent London merchants. The alderman to whom RC refers is John
Jeffreys (1614-1688), master of the Grocers Company and alderman in
1661. He was in business with his nephew, Sir Jeffrey Jeffreys, MP,
who was his heir. (<cit><bibl>J. R. Woodhead, <title>The Rulers of
London.</title> London: London and Middlesex Archaelogical Society,
1965. pp. 97-98.</bibl></cit>; <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison.
<title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 607-612.</bibl></cit>; and various
references in <cit><bibl n="B5">Davis,  <title>William Fitzhugh. . .
.</title>)</bibl></cit></note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised March 17,
2009.</hi></note>

 
</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>