<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C21b13d">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry Sr. and Jr., February 13, 1721</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry Sr. and Jr., February 13, 1721</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1940</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1721-02-13</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C21b13dT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1721-02-13"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C21b13d.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry Sr. and Jr., February 13, 1721</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchants Micajah Perry Sr. and Jr., February 13, 1721, that he has received their letters which were full of bad news concerning the poor quality of the tobacco he has sent to them for sale. He argues that he has sent them good tobacco, especially that shipped by Captain Wharton, and that there will always be good and bad tobacco in every crop and shipment. He writes about the Northern Neck proprietary affairs and his need for an account before he can take Edmund Jenings to court for his unpaid debts to the proprietors. Charles Grymes has talked of his taking over the management of the Lloyd properties, but the overseers have come to Carter to renew their yearly contracts. In conclusion he complains about the poor prices her received for tobacco shipped "per Lisband" and hopes he will not lose much from his annuity.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry Sr. and Jr., February 13, 1721</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1721-02-13">Febr. 13. 1720/21</date><lb/>
Messrs. Micajh. Perry<lb/>Senr. &amp; Junr.<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Gent:&mdash;&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>Yor Lettrs by York and also Yor box by <note target="n1">John <lb/>Fitzhugh</note> came to me two days ago they are full of such bad news <lb/>I dont know how to give them a proper answer find I must keep at <lb/>the Labouring Oar as long as I live, The Complaints You make of <lb/>the badness of my Tobo is one heavy Article I am sure abundance <lb/>of the parcells You had Especially That by Wharton was choice <lb/>Good Tobo and Such as Nice <note target="n2">Mr. Pratt</note> can't pretend to have <lb/>in his mixt Medly and no one in <abbr expan="Virginia">Virga</abbr> can Exert more care <lb/>with their overseers than I do nor be stricter in their orders but <lb/>Tis impossible we Crop men Should make all our Tobo. alike <lb/>Some mean hogsheads in Every Crop there will be that must keep <lb/>company with the better Sort, I have tyed up my Tobo. this <lb/>Year for the most part in the Middle in pretty large bundles <lb/>and now It Seems that is become displeasing if the humour of <lb/>Trade after Every Year Tis Impossible we Should keep pace with <lb/>It. Tis Some comfort that Every person I meet with speak of <lb/>Complaints they have of their Tobo am glad to find my Credit <lb/>is not Yett lost, I Shall avoid as much as possibly I can making <lb/>large drafts upon You this Year,</p>

<p>	The Northern Neck business is like to prove a bitter Pill <lb/>to me, I have the Proprietors Lettr. and one to <abbr expan="Colonel">Collo.</abbr> Jennings <lb/>if he will not do them Justice without Law they must send me <lb/>An attested account what is due to them, before I Shall be in a <lb/>Capacity to manage him, I have alredy <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> told You he hath <lb/>Assured me he gave positive orders to his son to Settle wth them <lb/>&amp; to pay what was their Due, as farr as I can understand <lb/>the Yearly rent Due to the Crown which is &pound;6"13"4 hath <lb/>not bin paid Since I went out of the business 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
this money must be paid by some body It is the foundation <lb/>of the Proprietors Grant I desire You to discource them about <lb/>It I have writ to them already That I may have orders <abbr expan="what">wt.</abbr> <lb/>to do, and desire they will give themselves the Trouble of a Frequent <lb/>Correspondency with me for I Shall have many things to say <lb/>to them for the better Settleing of their affairs.</p>

<p><note target="n3">Charles Grymes</note> hath bin very forward to publish he <lb/>Should have the management of Loyd's Concern, some of the overseers <lb/>I have bin told went to offer their Service to him but since have <lb/>had the manners to Contract wth. me for the Ensuing Year</p>

	<p>Yor Accot of sales of the Nine hogsheads per Lisband is a poor <lb/>Storey at Such prices my debt from Offley will come to nothing <lb/>You say a great deal about my annuity hope I shall be no looser <lb/>by it in the End Shall not add further at present but Gent </p>

<closer>Yor. Most humble Servt</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi>  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 71-72.</bibl></cit></note><lb/>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and state have been added for clarity.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] John Fitzhugh (d. 1733) of Stafford County, a younger son of William Fitzhugh of "Bedford." He was a burgess from Stafford in 1727. (<cit><bibl>"The Fitzhugh Family." <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography.</title> 7[1899-1900]: 317-19.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Louis Wright has speculated that Mr. Pratt might be William Pratt of Gloucester County as there were several Pratts active in Virginia at this time. In his letter to Micajah and Richard Perry written 13 July 1720, Carter noted that "Mr. Pratt took care of those [letters] for James rivr &amp; York" which makes Wright's speculation as good as any. In the close-knit society of his time and class, RC would certainly have learned what others were receiving for their crops, but a definite identification of the irritating Mr. Pratt is not possible. (<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 2.)</bibl></cit> </note>

<note id="n3">[3] Charles Grymes (ca. 1692-1743) of "Morratico," Richmond County where he was sherriff in 1724-1725, and burgess, 1727-1734; he was a son-in-law of Edmund Jenings. (<cit><bibl>"The Grymes Family." <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography.</title> 28[1920]: 90-96, 187-94, 283-85, 374-75.</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="B31">Ryland. <title>Richmond County Virginia. . . . </title> 500, 504, 514.</bibl></cit>)</note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>