<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C21b10b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to  Micajah Perry, Sr., and Jr., February 10, 1721</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia
Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL:
http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to  Micajah Perry, Sr., and
Jr., February 10, 1721</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1940</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic
Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject
Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1721-02-10</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term
type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C21b10bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1721-02-10"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C21b10b.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to  Micajah Perry, Sr., and Jr.,
February 10, 1721</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Micajah Perry, Sr., and his grandson, February 10, 1721, to ask their assistance in pressing Colonel William Cage, trustee under the will of Lady Fairfax, and the underage heir, the current Lord Fairfax, concerning his procedure in granting lands in the Northern Neck proprietary, for which Carter has taken a lease as agent. He also is concerned about the Brent Town grant and its unsurveyed borders and wants the properitors' instructions concerning a survey because the lack of one scares Virginians from settling in the area. He is also concerned about a 14,000-acre grant that he presumes if owned by Sir Jeffrey Jeffreys, MP. Carter informs the Perrys that he has written details of these matters to his son John in London and directed John to pursure these
matters.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to  <note n="MP">Micajah Perry,
Sr.,</note> and <note n="MP2">Jr.,</note>
February 10, 1721</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster
County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1721-02-10"><abbr expan="February ">Febr. </abbr> 10th.
1720/21</date><lb/>
Messrs. Perry<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>&mdash;&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>The foregoing was designd by a Ship which passd by my house <lb/>
without calling Its necessary to press You a little further upon the <xref to="/users/berkeley/#Northern Neck"> Northern<lb/> Neck affair</xref> besides the full power of <sic corr="attorney ">Atturney</sic> I have already mentioned to you <lb/>
I want <abbr expan="directions ">direcs. </abbr> from my Lord <del>Culpeper</del> <add 
place="supralinear"><note n="TF">Fairfax</note></add> and <note n="WC"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> Cage</note> in whose name I am to <lb/>
pass the Lands that I shall give deeds for whether in my Lords alone as <lb/>
the heir or whether <abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> Cage who is the <abbr expan="executor ">Exer.</abbr> and the other Trustee of my <lb/> 
Ladys will must be <sic corr="joined ">joind</sic> with him these things are very necessary to be <lb/>
known that I may not commit an Error.<note target="n1"></note></p>

<p>	There is another thing that the Proprietors Should Exert <lb/>
themselves about which will conduce much to their Interest as
well as <lb/>
mine, The Lord Culpeper in the Year 1686 makes a <note
target="n2">Grant</note> of Thirty <abbr
expan="thousand ">Thousd.</abbr> <lb/>Acres of Land in the upper parts
of his Territory wth very uncertain <lb/>bounds unto George Brent
Alderman Bristow <abbr expan="Richard ">Richd</abbr> Foote &amp;
Nicholas <lb/>Hayward Reserving a rent of twenty <abbr
expan="shillings">Shills.</abbr> for a <abbr expan="thousand ">Thd
</abbr> Acres &amp; <lb/>a Provisoe is in the
Deed That the said Lord Culpeper might Survey the <lb/>Said Lands and
give bounds Thereto in 1688 My Lord makes a deed<lb/>
of Release to the <abbr expan="aforesaid ">aforesd.</abbr> <abbr expan="gentlemen ">Gents. </abbr> of the <abbr expan="reserved ">Reserv'd </abbr> Rent only a Beaver <lb/>
Skin to be paid Yearly as an acknowledgement
Brent in his life <lb/>time makes a Settlement upon some of these
Lands wch has bin long <lb/>Since deserted and not a Foot of these
Lands any otherways Im=<lb/>=prov'd to this Day by any of the
afforenamed Gent., To <sic corr="set ">sett</sic> this matter
<lb/>in a clear light I send You <sic corr="copies ">Copys</sic> of
the Deeds, This Grant
scares <lb/>people very much from taking up back Lands, <del>now
so</del>of which there <lb/>is a great Quantity lying between the
above mentioned Settlement and <lb/>the Mountains, Now who must bear
the Charge of this Survey is the <lb/>Question and if the Proprietors
<abbr expan="does ">dos</abbr> It without the Consent of the
<lb/>Persons <abbr expan="concerned ">concern'd, </abbr> whether
they will be bound by It is another
<lb/>Question and <sic corr="yet ">yett</sic> highly reasonable It
is the bounds of this
Grant <lb/>Should be known and I Should think the Doing of It with
all <lb/>possible Expedition <abbr expan="does ">dos</abbr> as much
Concern the Grantees as the <lb/>Proprietors, for if other men by
mistake Should <sic corr="set ">Sett</sic> Down upon <lb/>these
Lands that <sic corr="lie ">lye</sic> thus
<sic corr="uncultivated ">unculltivated</sic> and make <abbr
expan="improvements ">Improvemts.</abbr>
<lb/>Thereon It will be very hard hereafter for them to be amoved
<lb/>by this Sleeping Grant, <note n="RB2">Mr. Bristow</note> of
London I take to be <lb/>heir to the Alderman who has the Right of
Hayward and <lb/><sic corr="Foote ">Foot</sic> I cant Say Brents
Heirs are here these things
are well <lb/>worth the Consideration of the Proprietors and I would
willingly <lb/>have their Opinion what <del>they will instruct me to
do</del>methods I shall take in this 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
Affair.
</p>

<p><abbr expan="Esquire ">Esq. </abbr> Jeoffrys of London with whom
I suppose You are well
<lb/>Accquainted owns 14000 &amp; odd Acres of Land in the upper
parts of <lb/><name type="place">Stafford</name> which nobody <sic
corr="has ">hath </sic> Ever paid any <note target="n3"><sic
corr="quit ">Quitt</sic> Rents</note>
for and <lb/><sic corr="lies ">lyes</sic> under as uncertain bounds
as the <note
n="BT">Brenton Grant</note> as I take <lb/>It his Father had these
Lands made over to him <add place="supralinear">by <note
target="n4"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> Jones
</note></add>for a debt, my <lb/>Son <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> a
full Account of all these
things and has my orders to ease <lb/>You of the greatest part of the
trouble he will apply to You for <lb/>the <sic corr="copies
">Copy's</sic> I now Send and taken
Yor. advice in Everything I Shall <lb/>not give You further trouble
at present <note target="n5">but am</note>&mdash;</p>

<closer>Sirs <lb/>Yor. most humble Servt.</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics">Source copy consulted:</hi>  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227,  Hntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 64-66.</bibl></cit></note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than
"Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] Written on the page at this point are several words&mdash;"then" and "Mr. Perry C and so," and at the beginning of the next line, "the"&mdash; in the clerk's hand.</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n2">[2] The complicated affairs of the <xref to="/users/berkeley/#Brent">Brent Town grant</xref> may be reviewed in the section "Brent Town Within the Proprietary" linked from the opening screen of this web site.</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n3">[3] Quit rent was the term used for the payment due from the holder of land to the "lord of the manor," in this case, to the proprietors of the Northern Neck. Carter as the proprietor's agent, collected these payments. No services were required of the landholder as had been true in mediaeval times.</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n4">[4] The 14,000-acre grant was originally made to Cadwallader Jones and later taken over by John Jeffreys (1614-1688), master of the Grocers Company and London alderman in 1661, to whom Jones was in debt. Jeffreys was in business with his nephew, Sir Jeffrey Jeffreys, MP, who was his heir, and it is to him that Carter
refers. (<cit><bibl>J. R. Woodhead, <title>The Rulers of London.</title> London: London and Middlesex Archaelogical Society, 1965. pp. 97-98.</bibl></cit>; <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 607-612.</bibl></cit>; and various references in <cit><bibl n="B5">Davis,  <title>William Fitzhugh. . . .</title>)</bibl></cit></note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n5">[5] Written on the page prior to the word "Sirs" in the complimentary close is the word "thee."</note><lb/><lb/> 


<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised March 19, 2009.</hi></note>
</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>