<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C21b13b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Recipients' Copies and Draft of a Letter from Robert Carter to Lord Fairfax and William Cage,  February 13, 1721</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia
Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL:
http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Recipients' Copies and Draft of a Letter from Robert Carter to Lord Fairfax and William Cage, February 13, 1721</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1940</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Recipient's copies, and Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1721-02-13</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term
type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C21b13bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 pp.</extent>
<date value="1721-02-13"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C21b13b.xml</idno>
<title>Recipients' Copies and Draft of a Letter from Robert Carter to Lord Fairfax and William Cage, February 13, 1721</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Lord Fairfax, the under-age owner of, and William Cage, trustee for, the proprietary of the Northern Neck, in England, February 13, 1721, concerning his assumption of the lease and his attempts to get
Edmund Jenings, the former agent, to settle his accounts. He requests a stronger power of attorney concerning the granting of lands as agent, and informs them that he has sent for their review a copy of the power he had held when he formerly was agent and hopes they will send him an equally strong one. He also needs the power to deal with escheats which he does not presently have. He intends to communicate often, as he hopes they will, but notes he will send the more tedious details through Micajah Perry and his son John.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Recipient's Copy of a Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="TF">Lord Fairfax</note> and <note n="WC">William Cage,</note>
February 13, 1721</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <corr resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</corr> </name><lb/>
<date value="1721-02-13">Febr.  13th. 1720/21</date><lb/>
Right Honble.  Lord Fairffax<lb/>
and Wm.  Cage Esqr. <lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>My Lord and Sir</salute>

</opener>

<p>The <abbr expan="honor ">Honr.</abbr>  of Yor. Lettr. of the 18th of <abbr expan="September ">Sepr</abbr> <lb/>
<sic corr="reached ">reacht</sic> my hands but two days ago with one to <abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr>  <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic><lb/>
which I shall take care to <sic corr="let ">lett</sic> him have in a Short time. <lb/>
The <xref to="/users/Berkeley/#Northern Neck">Lease</xref> You Executed with <note n="MP">Mr. Perry</note>with Yor. power <lb/>
of Atturney <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> bin with me some months, I <sic corr="immediately ">immediatly</sic> <lb/>
made a demand upon <abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr>  <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic> of what Arrears <lb/>
were due to You he Assured me more than once that he <lb/>
gave Effectual <abbr expan="orders ">ordrs.</abbr> to his Son at his Departure to settle <lb/>
that matter to <note target="n1">Yor.</note> <sic corr="Satisfaction ">Sattisfaction</sic> and I hope he will <lb/>
have so much Regard to his own <abbr expan="honor ">honr.</abbr> not to want <lb/>
any Compulsory means to oblige him to do You Justice, <lb/>
if there should be a necessity for it, You must Arm me <lb/>
with an Attested Accot. of Yor. Claim <sic corr="sworn "> Sworne</sic> to before <lb/>
a proper officer in the presence of Witnesses coming <lb/>
here, and Yor. clear <abbr expan="directions ">direcs </abbr> I would have what Steps I <lb/>
am to take, I have hinted all this to Mr. Perry Our <lb/>
Courts of Law are dilatory and if he will be obstinate <lb/>
you may be kept out of Yor. money a Considerable time <lb/>
but sure his own Reputation will be more dear to him <lb/>
than to carry me into any of that sort of Trouble&mdash;&mdash;</p>

<p>Both the Lease and Yor. power <sic corr="lie ">lye</sic> <abbr expan="unproved ">unprov'd </abbr> <lb/>
<sic corr="until ">till</sic> the Witnesses Arrive. however I have appointed 

<pb n="2"/><lb/>

Receivers of the Rents for the <abbr expan="several ">sevl.</abbr> <sic corr="counties "> Countys</sic> but am <lb/>
unwilling to open an office For Granting of Lands &amp; <lb/>
<sic corr="disposing ">Disposeing</sic> of  <note n="ES">Escheats</note> &amp;c. till the Latter part 
of the <lb/>
Summer being desirous of a Fuller power from You <lb/>
and to have Yor. <abbr expan="directions ">Direcs. </abbr> whose name I must pass <lb/>
the Grants in, I have sent a Copy of the last <abbr expan="power ">Powr.</abbr>  I <lb/>
<abbr expan="received ">Rec'd</abbr> from my <note target="n1">Lady Fairfax</note> to Mr. Perry such a=<lb/>
=nother I ought to have with only the Alteration of <lb/>
the Circumstances of the Case as it is at present, there <lb/>
are several other things I write to Mr. Perry about that <lb/>
are so absolutely conducive to the Interest of the Estate <lb/>
as well as mine that I cannot doubt but you will <lb/>
readily come into my proposals, The particulars of what <lb/>
I have to Say I shall from time to time communicate <lb/>
to him, I begg Yor. Lordship &amp;c will <abbr expan="honor">honr.</abbr> me with a <lb/>
Frequent Correspondence.</p>

<p>I Do Assure Yor. Lordship I  am like to have <lb/>
a very hard bargain of It, It was always Bruited <lb/>
here <abbr expan="Colonel">Collo.</abbr>  <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic> paid but &pound;250 per Annum he <lb/>
<sic corr="has ">hath </sic> had the greatest luck of any man alive Tobo. <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> <lb/>
held up all his time and now Its become very mean <lb/>
The Commodity that most of Yor. Rents are paid in <lb/>
I remember two or three of the last Years I was in the <lb/>
business before I was not able to make of the Estate <lb/>
&pound;300 per Annum <sic corr="salary">Sallary</sic> and all and I fear we are very <lb/>
near Such bad times again I shall not take upon me <lb/>
to discant upon <abbr expan="Colonel">Collo.</abbr>  <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic>'s proceedings Any further <lb/>
than to Claim what is my Due from the Expiration of <lb/>
his Lease but I may be fairly Justifyed in this General 

<pb n="3"/><lb/>
<lb/>
Observation that things appear to me under more Confusion <lb/>
than when I went out of the business</p>

<p>I am inform'd That the Yearly Rent due to the Crown <lb/>
of &pound;6"13"4 is in Arrear since my last payment if it be so <lb/>
I shall desire direc<add resp="editor">[tion]</add>s. who shall be answerable for this <lb/>
money &amp; certainly Its highly necessary It should be paid <lb/>
by somebody being the Reserv'd Consideration of my Lord <lb/>
Culpeper's Grant.</p>

<p>Another thing 'tis proper to Inform Yor. Lordship <lb/>
of the Legal way of passing Escheats is first by finding an <lb/>
office by an Escheat Master and twelve men now <lb/>
this power I have not as Yor. Atturney, I cannot order a <lb/>
<sic corr="sheriff">Sherrif</sic> to Summon a Jury for this purpose unless I had <lb/>
a Commission from the <abbr expan="governor">Govr:</abbr> here or a proper qualification <lb/>
from home with Liberty to appoint Deputy Escheaters <lb/>
Yor. Direc<add resp="editor">[tion]</add>s Assistance &amp; Advice upon a proper Method <lb/>
for this Affair I strongly desire as I shall always Yor. <lb/>
Deliberate answers to the Entertainments I shall have <lb/>
Repeated occasions to trouble You with however the more <lb/>
tedious Storeys Shall come through the hands of Mr. <lb/>
Perry and my Son with whom I request You will <lb/>
hold a Communication, I shall Study to approve <lb/>
my self, </p>

<closer>Sirs <lb/>
Yor. Lordships &amp; <abbr expan="Colonel">Collo.</abbr>  Cage's <lb/>
most faithfull &amp; most humble Servt. <lb/>

<signed><hi rend="italics">ROBERT CARTER</hi></signed><lb/><lb/>

<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>
<hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Because of the rare existance of both the draft  and the recipients' copies of a Carter letter, the editor has  entered below<lb/>
the text of the draft  below to show the careful revisions made before the copies to be sent were written.</hi></hi><lb/>
<lb/><lb/><lb/>


<hi rend="bold">Draft of a Letter from Robert Carter to Lord Fairfax and William Cage, February 13, 1721</hi><lb/><lb/>


Right Honble.  Lord Fairfax Rappa Febr. 13. 1720/21<lb/>
 &amp; Wm.  Cage Esqr.<lb/>
 My Lord and Sir&mdash;&mdash;<lb/><lb/>



The Honr.  of Yor. Lettr. of the 18th of Sepr reacht <lb/>
 my hands but two days ago with one to Collo. Jenningswhich I shall<lb/>
 take care to lett him have in a Short time.  The Lease You<lb/>
Executed with Mr. Perry with Yor. power  of Atturney hath  <lb/>
bin with me some months, I immediatly  made a demand upon<lb/>
Collo.  Jennings of what Arrears  were due to You he Assured me <lb/>
more than once that he  gave Effectual ordrs. to his Son <lb/>
at his Departure to settle  that matter to Yor. Sattisfac-n<lb/>
and I hope he will  have so much Regard to his own honr. <lb/>
not to want  any Compulsory means to <del>bring</del> <add
place="supralinear">oblige</add> him to do<lb/>
You Justice, if there should be a necessity for it, You must <lb/>
Arm me  with an Attested Accot. of Yor.  Demands. <add
place="supralinear">Claim</add> to be<lb/>
Sworne to before  a proper officer in the presence of Wit=<lb/>
=nesses coming  here, and Yor. clear direcs  I would have wt.<lb/>
Steps I  am to take, I have hinted all this to Mr. <lb/>
 Perry Our  Courts of Law are dilatory and if he will be<lb/>
Obstinate  you may be kept out of Yor. money a Consider=<lb/>
=able time  but sure his own Reputation will be more <lb/>
     Dear to him  than to carry me into any of that sort of trouble<lb/><lb/>

Both the Lease and Yor. power lye unprov'd <lb/>
till the Witnesses Arrive. however I have appointed  Receivrs.<lb/>
of the Rents for the Sevl. Countys but am  unwilling to open<lb/>
an office For Granting of Lands <add place="supralinear">for
disposeing of  Escheats &amp;c.</add> till the Latter part of the<lb/>
Summer being desirous of a Fuller power from You  and to <lb/>
have Yor. Direcs.  whose name I must pass  the Grants in,<lb/>
I have sent a Copy of the last Powrer I  Rec'd from<lb/>
my Lady Fairfax to Mr. Perry such another I ought<lb/> 
to have <del>[illegible]</del> with only the Alteration of  the
Circumstans.<lb/>
of the Case as it is at present, there  are sevl. other 

<pb n="2"/>  
things I write to Mr. Perry abt that  are so <del>absolutely </del>
<del>necess </del><add place="supralinear">conducive</add><lb/>
<del>ary </del> <add place="supralinear">to</add> the Interest of
the Estate  as well as mine that I canno<lb/>
t Doubt but you will  readily come into my Proposals, The partic.s <lb/>
of what  I have to Say I shall from time to time communicat<lb/>
to him, I begg Yor. Lordship <add place="supralinear">&amp;c</add>
will honr. me with a  frequent<lb/>
Correspondence.I Do Assure Yor. Lordship I am like to have<lb/>
a very hard bargain of It, <add place="supralinear">. . . ix Yor Lordship I am like to have</add>It was always Bruited  here Collo.<lb/>
Jennings paid but two hundred and fifty pounds per annum<lb/>
he  hath  had the greatest luck of any man alive Tobo. hath<lb/>
held up all along his time and now It's become very<lb/>
mean  The Commodity that most of Yor. Rents are paid in<lb/>
I remember two or three of the last Years I was in the<lb/>
business before I was not able to make of the Estate  <add
place="supralinear">&pound;</add>300<lb/>
per Annum Sallary and all and I fear we are very near<lb/>
Such bad times again. I shall not take upon me  to dis=<lb/>
=cant upon Collo. Jennings's proceedings Any further than<lb/>
to Claim what is my Due from the Expiration of  his Lease<lb/>
but I may be fairly Justifyed in this Genl. Observation that<lb/>
things appear to me under more Confusion than when I<lb/>
     went out of the business <del>I a</del><lb/><lb/>

I am inform'd That the Yearly Rent due<lb/>
to the Crown  of Six pounds Thirteen &amp; Four pence is in<lb/>
Arrear since my <del>time </del>last paymt.  if it be so  I shall desire<lb/>
Direcs. who shall be answerable for this  money &amp; certainly<lb/>
Its highly necessary It should be paid  by somebody being<lb/>
the <add place="supralinear">reservd</add> Consideration of my Lord 
     Culpeper's Grant.<lb/><lb/>

Another thing tis proper to Inform Yor. Lordship of<lb/>
the Legal way of passing Escheats is first by finding an<lb/>
office by an Escheat Master and twelve men now  this<lb/>
power I have not as <del>being </del> Yor. Atturney, I cannot order a<lb/>
Sherrif to Summon a Jury for this purpose unless I had<lb/>
a Commission from the Goverr: here or a proper qualification<lb/>
from home with Liberty to appoint Deputy Escheaters<lb/>
Yor. Dires. Assistance &amp; advice upon a proper Method<lb/>
for this affair I strongly desire as I shall always<lb/>
Yor.  deliberate answers to the Entertainments I shall have  

<pb n="3"/>  
repeated occasions to trouble You with, however the<lb/>
more tedious Storeys Shall come thro the hands of Mr.  Perry &amp;<lb/>
my Son with whom I request You will  hold a Communica<lb/>
=tion, I shall Study to approve  myself, <lb/><lb/>

>Sirs<lb/>
Yor. Lordships &amp; Collo.  Cages<lb/>
     most faithfull &amp; most hum Servt.  <lb/><lb/>

</seg>
</closer>
</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi>  Recipient's copies and Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. The first text was transcribed from the recipient's copies of which there are two at the Huntington; one is marked "Copy" at its foot, and is endorsed "Febr. the 13 1720 Coll Carter." [BR 227, folder 11]  The text of the draft was transcribed from the letteer book. The recipoient's copies are signed by Robert Carter as indicated by the use of italics. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 68-70.</bibl></cit></note> 

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than 
"Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to persons abroad. The county and colony have  een added for clarity.</note> <lb/><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] Catherine Culpeper, widow of the fifth Lord Fairfax (d. 1710); from her father, the 2nd Lord Culpeper, she had inherited about 1689 his five-sixths interest in the <xref to="/users/Berkeley/#Northern Neck">Northern Neck Proprietary</xref> in Virginia. Lord Fairfax consulted Micajah Perry about the affairs of the Propietary, and Perry had recommended Robert Carter to be the Virginia agent in 1702. He held the post until 1710 
when Lady Fairfax transferred the agency to Edmund Jenings with Thomas Lee as the deputy agent. When she died in 1719, she bequeathed her Virginia property to her son Tom, but she made Wiliam Cage and Edward Filmer, tustees of the proprietary. Filmer soon died, and Cage, a kinsman of the 6th Lord Fairfax, became the sole trustee. 
From his grandmother, Margaret Lady Culpeper, the 6th Lord Fairfax inherited the other one-sixth of the roprietary. Cage consulted Perry, and Robert Carter was again made agent in 1721, holding the post until his death ten years later.</note><lb/> 

  <lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised March 232009.</hi></note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>