<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C21c03a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter  to [Mann Page], March 3, 1721</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to ]</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1940</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1721-03-03</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C21c03aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1721-03-03"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">]</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter  to [Mann Page], March 3, 1721</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his son-in-law, [Mann Page], March 3, 1721, reporting that his sons in England were in good health as of October 24th which he has learned from Bailey Kent, the captain of the <hi rend="italics">Carter.</hi> He commisserates with Page over his gout, and writes at length about his own recent attack of it. There have been fifteen deaths among his slaves, he writes, and adds that he hopes to return the coffee soon. He closes with blessings to all, sending the greetings of Mrs. Swan and Ann Vitty.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter  to [<note n="MP1">Mann Page</note>], March 3, 1721</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Corotoman, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1721-03-03">Mar. 3d. 1720/21</date><lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Honble. Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>Yor. man <del>Will</del><sic corr="got ">gott</sic> hither about 10 <sic corr="o'clock ">a Clock</sic> last night <lb/>The health of my Children is always most pleasing news to me, <lb/>Will at <note target="n1"><sic corr="Machens ">Mitchams</sic></note> <sic corr="picked ">pickt</sic> up a Lettr. from <note target="n2"><sic corr="Bailey ">Baily</sic> Kent</note> who gives <lb/>me the most perticular accot. of my Childrens health there. the 24th <lb/>of <abbr expan="October ">Octr.</abbr> the Date he desires his service may be remembered to all <lb/>his friends among whom I know Yor. Familys are <abbr expan="placed ">plac'd </abbr><lb/>in the first rank,</p>

	<p>I condole with You for Yor. present affliction <lb/>under that Strong mortifying <sic corr="physic ">Physick</sic> the Gout, and I do It <lb/>with the greater sympathy because at this time I am under <lb/>the <sic corr="strokes ">Stroaks</sic> of the same distemper, having bin <abbr expan="confined ">confind</abbr> to my <lb/>Chamber these Eight Days, Wednesday last was <note target="n3">sennight</note> in <lb/>the morning I was taken lame however <sic corr="ventured ">venturd</sic> out in my <lb/>Coach to my home <abbr expan="quarters ">Qrs.</abbr> to visit my Sick. Next morning I was <lb/><sic corr="easier ">Easyer</sic> in hopes <sic corr="it would ">twould</sic> go off, &amp; <sic corr="hobbled ">hobled</sic> about the Yard pretty <lb/>often that Day at Night, my pains <sic corr="increased ">Encreas'd</sic> my ancle &amp; <lb/>Instep <abbr expan="swelled ">swelld</abbr> I then Expected nothing less than a Conflic<add resp="editor">[t]</add> <lb/>with the Gout, which <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> bin very Complaisant with me for <lb/>almost two Years, It brought me to my Crutch the three first days <lb/>since the pain <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> bin much abated, on Tuesday I <sic corr="caught ">catcht</sic> <lb/>some cold by what means I know not, by lying bare foot In <lb/>bed I'm sure <abbr expan="it was ">twas</abbr> not, this brought on a <sic corr="fever ">F eaver</sic> a pain in my <lb/>head &amp; swellings &amp; soreness behind my Ears &amp; Neck at Night <lb/>I thought It proper, to put a blister above my most <abbr expan="pained ">pain'd </abbr> Ear <lb/>&amp; going to bed I took some of <note n="AP">andersons pills</note> <sic corr="during ">dureing</sic> my <lb/><sic corr="fever ">feaver</sic> I had a heavy oppression upon my Spirits as that <lb/>abated the other also went off with It. I <abbr expan="cupped ">cupp'd </abbr> twice my <lb/><sic corr="physic ">Physick</sic> wrought very well, I <abbr expan="clapped ">clap'd </abbr> another blister above <lb/>the other Ear and yett after all my head remains all <lb/>over prodigiously sore, I have not Eaten one mouth full of <lb/>flesh all this time nor drank any thing Stronger 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
than Small beer, Except three Glasses of <abbr expan="English">Eng.</abbr> <sic corr="cider ">Cyder</sic> wth <note n="CS1">Stagg</note> on <sic corr="Satur ">Satter</sic>=<lb/>=day night.&mdash;</p>

<p>The <sic corr="mortalities ">Mortalitys</sic> in my <sic corr="families ">Familys</sic> are <abbr expan="increased ">Increasd</abbr>
 I think <lb/>Since You were here three or four, Sloop Toney is recovered <lb/>poor Harry Weaver a Negro Yor. wife knows very well went <lb/>off two Days ago., The Number of my Dead is now fifteen work<lb/>=ing Slaves, I thank God I bear these things with a Great <lb/>deal of <del>Easyness </del><add place="supralinear">Resignation</add>. afflictions are very proper for us in our way <lb/>to Heaven. Its a <sic corr="rugged ">ruggid</sic> path <sic corr="yet ">yett</sic> It is the road that all the <lb/>blessed above have trod before us, I have heard lately <lb/>from all my <sic corr="families ">Familys</sic> in Westmoreland at the <note n="FQ">Falls</note> <lb/>who have no manner of Sickness among them Its pretty remark<lb/>=able these Distempers Should go about in Clouds as it were, we <lb/>have lost abundance in our Parish&mdash;</p>

	<p>You have bin very kind in <sic corr="sparing ">Spareing</sic> me so much Coffee <lb/>I hope to be able to return It in a short time now, <note n="EJ"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic></note> <lb/>gives It me under his hand, that he had received my Lords Lettr.<lb/>and that I sent by Robin Innis, The rest <add place="supralinear">to Pray for the continuance of all Yor. healths</add> to give my <lb/>proper respects to my Dear Children, to Yor. Children &amp; to Yor. <lb/>Self, Mrs. <note target="n4">Ann <add resp="editor">[Vitty]</add></note> &amp; <note n="MJS">Mrs. Swan</note> are Yor. humble Servants. I am </p>

<closer>Yor</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi>  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 86-87.</bibl></cit></note><lb/>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Corotoman,"  the name of his home, on his Virginia correspondence. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note><lb/>

<note>Although the letter does not bear an addressee's name, it is clear from the text that it is addressed to a family member, and as Mann Page, Carter's son-in-law, suffered from gout, it seems likely that he was the addressee.</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] A ferry across the Rappahannock from Lancaster County was located at this Middlesex County property, probably owned by Thomas Machen who appears in the records of Christ Church Parish, Middlesex, in 1725. It was a short distance from Machens across the county to another ferry located at Seatons in Gloucester County on the south bank of the Piankatank River. Carter regularly took this route to Williamsburg. As Mann Page lived in Gloucester County, his servant certainly would have taken this route to go to "Corotoman." (<cit><bibl>Churchill Gibson Chamberlayne, <hi rend="italics">editor.</hi> <title>The Vestry Book of Christ Church Parish Middlesex County, Virginia 1663- 1767.</title> [Richmond:  Old Dominion Press, 1927] p. 202.</bibl></cit>)</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n2">[2] Kent was the captain of the <hi rend="italics">Carter.</hi></note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n3">[3] Sennight means a week.</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n4">[4] Ann Vitty was Carter's housekeeper.</note><lb/><lb/>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised March 26, 2009.</hi></note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>