<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C21e27g">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Edward Tucker, May 27, 1721</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 5 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Edward Tucker, May 27, 1721</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1940</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1721-05-27</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C21g27gT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1721-05-27"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C21g27g.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Edward Tucker, May 27, 1721</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Weymouth merchant, Edward Tucker, May 27, 1721, to report that he has received letters Tucker sent with captains Russel and Wilson. The latter had a stormy passage and had to throw overboard 300-400 "foot of my stones." He complains about the poor prices Tucker has sold his tobacco for and notes that William Dawkins in London found a better market. He is sending 30 hogsheads on board Russel, reports the large numbers of ships in the colony, many of which will not be able to find cargoes, and complains about the pirates and the lack of protection provided against them.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="ET">Edward Tucker,</note> May 27, 1721</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1721-05-27">May the 27th. 1721</date><lb/>
Mr. Edward Tucker<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>I have received Yors. by <note target="n1">Capt. Russel</note> &amp; Wilson, the latter <lb/>had 15 weekes passage by Stress of weather he was <abbr expan="forced">forc'd</abbr> to heave over <lb/>board three or four hundred foot of my Stones, I wish I could Say the <lb/>Sales of my Tobo. pleas'd me. <add place="supralinear">You tell me</add> You had Sold half mine by Russel last <lb/>Year none above 9d. a poor price for my <abbr expan="stemmed">Stemd</abbr>, <note n="WD">Mr. Dawkins</note> Sold all <lb/>my Tobo. at 11d. if I understand him right, all my <abbr expan="stemmed">Stemd</abbr> at <sic corr="Liverpool">Leverpool</sic> <lb/>went at 10 and 10½ Thus You see <abbr expan="what">wt.</abbr> little Encouragement. I have at <lb/>Yor. Markett, however I shall have 30 hogsheads in Russel who loads <lb/>apace, I have drawn on You lately for &pound;17" to one Henry Thomp=<lb/>=son, We have a prodigious Swarm of Ships in this Year, I cant think <lb/>there will be Tobo. found to Load them all, You will hear the Storey of the <lb/>Pyrates Threatning our Harbours, It's a pitty full case no more care <lb/>Should be taken of so vast a fleet of Ships as comes to our Bay. I <lb/>Conclude at present Sir&mdash; </p>

<closer>Yor. humble Servt.</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi>  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 97.</bibl></cit></note><lb/>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and state have been added for clarity.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] Captain Samuel Russell of the <hi rend="italics">Princess Amelia</hi> entered at Weymouth in October 1720. (Survey Report 9711, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert H. Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.)</note>
 

</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>