<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C21f22a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to  Peter Hedgeman, June 22, 1721</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 7  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to  Peter Hedgeman, June 22, 1721</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1940</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1721-06-22</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C21f22aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1721-06-22"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C21f22a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to  Peter Hedgeman, June 22, 1721</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Peter Hedgeman, June 22, 1721, to inform the son of his general manager, who has recently died in an accident, that he has insufficient experience to succeed his father in that position, and that John Johnson has already been appointed to it.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to  <note target="n1">Peter Hedgeman,</note> June 22, 1721</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1721-06-22">June the 22d. 17<hi rend="underline">21</hi></date><lb/>
Peter Hedgeman&mdash;<lb/>
</dateline>

</opener>

<p>The unexpected Death of <abbr expan="Your">Yor.</abbr> father was very Shocking<lb/>
to me. I heartily wish he had <sic corr="met">mett</sic> with a more natural fate, he <sic corr="has">hath</sic> bin <lb/>
a very great delinquent of late from my business much contrary to the <lb/>
Articles he was under to me, had he bin in the Discharge of his Duty &amp; at the <lb/>
place he ought to have made his home he might have bin a living <lb/>
man at this day, I Shall be willing to do him Justice for the time he <lb/>
was in my Service, You have done very well to go to the <abbr expan="Several quarters">Sevl. Qrs.</abbr> &amp; to take <lb/>
a written Accot. of my Stocks and Goods there, I have <abbr expan="Employed">Imploy'd</abbr> one 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
John Johnson <sic corr="has">hath</sic> bin my Overseer for some years to succeed Your <lb/>
Father as my <abbr expan="General">Genl</abbr> Overseer to him I would have You give up the <abbr expan="Accounts">Accs</abbr> <lb/>
You have taken &amp; I would also have You not remove <abbr expan="Your">Yor.</abbr> Fathers <lb/>
bed but <sic corr="let">lett</sic> him have the use of It, <sic corr="until">till</sic> he can gett up one of his <lb/>
own which will be by the next Sloop that comes, I hope You have <lb/>
<abbr expan="followed">follow'd</abbr> my orders, in Marking &amp; weighing my <abbr expan="Tobacc">Tobo.</abbr> &amp;c, and that the Sloop <lb/>
is <sic corr="dispatched">dispatcht</sic> away before now, besides the Goods <sic corr="that">tht.</sic> went in the last Sloop <lb/>
<abbr expan="Your">Yor.</abbr> Father had a great many other Goods of mine under his Care <lb/>
which I Expect You will take care to See <abbr expan="delivered">deliver'd</abbr> to the <abbr expan="afforesaid">affores'd</abbr> John<lb/>
=son, The greater <abbr expan="Your">Yor.</abbr> diligence is in what relates to me, to more Induce <add place="supralinear">me</add> <lb/>
I shall have to be <sic corr="easy">easie</sic> in repect to <abbr expan="Your">Yor.</abbr> Fathers negligences that he <lb/>
<sic corr="has">hath</sic> bin guilty of in my business altogether contrary to the Conditions <lb/>
that were between us,</p>

<p>As to <abbr expan="Your">Yor.</abbr> proposal of Succeeding <abbr expan="Your">Yor.</abbr> Father in my busi<lb/>=ness It appears to be a very odd Thought in You, You must have some more <lb/>
Years over <abbr expan="Your">Yor.</abbr> head &amp; a greater Share of Experience in the world as well <lb/>
as to <sic corr="let">lett</sic> It be Seen what <sic corr="courses">cources</sic> You will fall upon in the <abbr expan="management">managemt.</abbr> <lb/>
of <sic corr="Yourself">Yorself</sic> &amp; <abbr expan="Your">Yor.</abbr> own business, before any Judicious person will think <lb/>
You capable of Such a Charge as mine is, what kindness will <sic corr="lie">lye</sic> in my <lb/>
way in respect to the long <sic corr="Employment">Imploy</sic> <abbr expan="Your">Yor.</abbr> father had under me <lb/>
I shall be ready to do you who am </p>

<closer>Yor. Friend</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi>  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 104-105.</bibl></cit> Carter's home and the county and state have been added to this unheaded draft letter for clarity.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] As is clear from the context, Peter Hedgeman was the son of Nathanel Hedgeman who is identified in footnote 2. He became a lawyer, and "long represented Stafford in the Assembly, and was one of the Crown Commissioners for the location of the Northern Neck boundary in 1746." (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title>p. 203.)</bibl></cit></note>

<note id="n2">[2] Nathaniel Hedgeman had settled his family at "Accokeek" on Potomac Creek in 1707, having purchased it from "the first George Mason."  He had been Carter's chief overseer in the falls area, but had died recently apparently in an accident. (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title>p. 203.)</bibl></cit></note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>