<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C21g05a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to [Thomas Lee], July 5, 1721</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C21g05a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2001</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to [Thomas Lee], July 5, 1721</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1940</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1721-07-05</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C21g05aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1721-07-05"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C21g05a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to [Thomas Lee], July 5, 1721</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to [Thomas Lee], July 5, 1721, concerning the affairs of the Northern Neck proprietary for which Lee had been acting agent in Virginia until 1715 while the agent, his uncle Edmund Jenings, was in England. He notes that Lee had granted land to his uncle in 1719, and informs Lee that he and Jenings had reached an agreement about the payment of quit rents that Jenings owed, and that they have also agreed to refer the question of "Downings Composition" to lawyers for settlement. He asks Lee to send him payment for certain lands that Lee has granted to himself after the expiration of his power of attorney from Lady Fairfax. Carter then turns to the matter of the Ashton lands owned by "Esq. Jeoffrys, the heir of Ashton in England." The remainder of the letter is missing.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to [<note target="n1">Thomas Lee,</note>] July 5, 1721</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Corotoman, <corr resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</corr> </name><lb/>
<date value="1721-07-05">July 5th. 1721</date><lb/>

</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>You have <abbr expan="thought ">Thot.</abbr> <sic corr="fit ">fitt</sic> to <abbr expan="favor ">favr.</abbr> me with a Sight of Yor. <abbr expan="power ">powr.</abbr> from <lb/><note target="n2">My Lady Fairfax,</note> by It I find what I knew before, That You were <lb/>her <sic corr="attorney ">Atturney</sic> <sic corr="until ">till</sic> You were <sic corr="superseded ">Superseeded</sic> by <abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> <note n="EJ"><sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic></note> in the Year <lb/>1715, what I objected to was Yor. Granting <add place="supralinear">him</add> lands in 1719 when <lb/>Yor. power was long before <sic corr="revoked ">revoakd</sic>, with a Salvo for his not paying <lb/>his <note target="n3"><sic corr="quit ">Quitt</sic> Rents</note> till the Year 1725 but <abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic> undertakes <lb/>to pay all the rents of those Lands Yearly, So that matter will be no <lb/>longer a bone of Contention, The business of Downings Composition <lb/>We have agreed to refer to Lawyers, <note n="JH">Mr. Holloway's</note> opinion I <lb/>value as much as any mans in the Country when he <sic corr="sits ">Setts</sic> Judicialy <lb/>&amp; <sic corr="has ">hath </sic>heard both partys, but what he or any other Lawyer Says <lb/>upon the State of a Case from one Side <del>only</del> can be <sic corr="called ">calld</sic> but <lb/>An opinion Ex parte at the Most, <abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr>  <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic> <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> <abbr expan="delivered ">deliver'd</abbr> <lb/>me up the rent rolls &amp; <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> made me fair promises in other <lb/>respects which if he <sic corr="performs ">performes</sic> believe he and I Shall hardly Quarrel&mdash;</p>

<p>In the List You gave me You own there are several <lb/><sic corr="pieces ">peices</sic> of Land that You owe me for the Composition of being <lb/>Granted after the Expiration of <abbr expan="Colone l">Collo.</abbr> <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic> Lease I <lb/>hope <sic corr="you'll ">You'l</sic> find a time to do me Justice in these at least</p>

<p>You hold Lands in <abbr expan="Westmoreland, ">Westm.ld,</abbr> Stafford, Richmond <lb/>&amp; Northumberland, You are likewise <add place="supralinear"><sic corr="attorney ">atturney</sic></add> to <note target="n4"><abbr expan="Esquire ">Esq. </abbr> Jeoffrys,</note> the heir <lb/>of Ashton in England &amp; are <sic corr="concerned ">concernd</sic> with the management of <note target="n5"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Col.</abbr> <lb/>Fitzhughs Land</note><add resp="editor">[s]</add> It will be but reputable in You <note target="n6">to</note></p>

<closer><seg type="postscript"></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi>  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1720 July-1721 July, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 106-107.</bibl></cit></note><lb/>

<note>The county and colony have been added for clarity to the name of Carter's home. It is clear from the context that this letter was sent to Thomas Lee.</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] Thomas Lee (1690-1750) of Westmoreland County was the son of Richard Lee II, and nephew of Edmund Jenings; he would build "Stratford," and succeed Carter on the Council. For a good article on Thomas Lee, see  "<xref to="http://www.stratfordhall.org/collections-research/staff-research/thomas-lee-of-stratford-1690-1750/">Thomas Lee of Stratford</xref> 1690-1750" by Jeanne A. Calhoun on Stratford plantation's website. (<cit><bibl>Burton J. Hendrick. <title>The Lees of Virginia: Biography of a Family.</title> [Boston: Little Brown, 1935]. pp. 48, 51, etc.</bibl></cit>)<lb/><lb/>

<note id="n2">[2] For Lady Fairfax, see the discussion of the <xref to="/users/berkeley/#Northern Neck OR #Brent">North Neck proprietary</xref> accessed from the opening screen of this site.</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n3">[3] Quit rent was the term used for the payment due from the holder of land to the "lord of the manor," in this case, to the proprietors of the Northern Neck. Carter as the proprietor's agent, collected these payments. No services were required of the landholder as had been true in mediaeval times.</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n4">[4] Carter probably refers to Sir Jeffrey Jeffreys, MP, heir to the business affairs of his uncle, John Jeffreys (1614-1688), master of the Grocers Company and alderman in 1661.Carter had been interested in the Ashton lands for some time, and had written about them in a <xref to="C21c25a.xml">letter to William Dawkins</xref> on  25 March 1721. The lands probably were those on the Potomac River "known as Chatterton or Chatterton Landing and . . .  now located in King George Co." bequeathed by Colonel Peter Ashton to "James Ashton, his brother of Kirby Underwood County, Lincolnshire and to John Ashton his brother of Lowell, Lincolnshire. . . . " (<cit><bibl>J. R. Woodhead. <title>The Rulers of London 1660-1689.</title> [London: London and Middlesex Archaeological Society, 1965]. pp. 97-98;</bibl></cit>  <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> pp. 607-612);</bibl></cit>  <cit><bibl>ENG-CAMBRIDGESHIRE-L Archives" in RootsWeb, http://archiver.rootsweb.ancestry.com/th/read/ENG-CAMBRIDGESHIRE/2007-08/1188575208,  5/14/2009; </bibl></cit>  and <cit><bibl>"Elkins Genealogical Data" http://homepages.rootsweb.ancestry.com/~darburns/elkins/reports/chrono1.html   5/14/2009</bibl></cit></note><lb/>

<note id="n5">[5] William Fitzhugh (1755-1701), lawyer,  emigrated from England, married, and settled at "Eagle's
Nest" in Stafford County by 1674 where he became burgess and later, justice and militia officer. He became, with George Brent, agent for the proprietors in 1693 and held the office until his death. (<cit><bibl n="B5">Davis,  <title>William Fitzhugh. . . .</title> pp. 3-55.</bibl></cit>)</note><lb/>

<note id="n6">[6] This letter ends here as further pages of the letter book are missing.</note><lb/><lb/>



<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised May 12, 2009, and again January 26, 2015.</hi></note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>