<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C23f29b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter [and Mann Page] to Micajah Perry, June 29, 1723</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C23f29b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter [and Mann Page] to Micajah Perry, June 29, 1723</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 pp.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert H. Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1723-06-29</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C23f29bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 pp.</extent>
<date value="1723-06-29"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C23f29b</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter [and Mann Page] to Micajah Perry, June 29, 1723</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter and his son-in-law, Mann Page, write to London merchant Micajah Perry, June 29, 1723, to send an invoice for goods to be purchased on the account of the estate of Nathaniel Burwell for the benefit of Burwell's children. They add some comments on laws concerning tobacco shipping and planting recently considered by the colony's assembly, and advise Perry of two bills of exchange drawn on the estate's account.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter [and <note n="MP1">Mann Page</note>] to <note n="MP2">Micajah Perry,</note> June 29, 1723</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1723-06-29">June the 29th. 1723</date><lb/>
Mr. Micajh. Perry<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p>This serves to cover an Invoice <del>of</del> <add place="supralinear">for</add> Goods for <lb/>the Supply of <note n="NB">Mr Burwells</note> families to be sent into <name type="place">York <lb/>river</name> either in the <name type="ship">Burwell</name> or in some other of the forward<lb/>est of your Ships bound thither, we used our Endeavors <lb/>to get a law to restrain Shipping Tobos before the 1st of <abbr expan="February">Febry.</abbr> <lb/>&amp; after the Last of July which we <sic corr="believed">beleived</sic> would have <lb/>been very agreeable to the <abbr expan="merchants">Merchts.</abbr> of <name type="place">London</name> at least <lb/>but it miscarried  in the lower house the Burgesses would <lb/>not hear of it</p>
 
	<p>We have a Law passed laying a Stint upon our <lb/>Planting how it will [be] <sic corr="relished">releshist</sic> at home is the great doubt <lb/>it is to take place the 1st of <sic corr="April">Aprill</sic> next to give time that <lb/>the Kings pleasure may be known about it we have Strong <lb/>hopes the Merchants will <sic corr="join">Joyn</sic> their Strength with <add resp="editor">[ours]</add>

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
 <add resp="editor">[to]</add> get it allowed for a year or two at least that our <lb/><add resp="editor">[t]</add>rade may be in some measure revived from the present <lb/>unhappy <sic corr="circumstances">Curcustances</sic> it is under </p>

	<p>We are Yet to advise You of the following bills <lb/>of <abbr expan="exchange">Exche.</abbr> we  have drawn on You on Accot of Mr Burwells Estate <lb/>To Witt for &pound;94"15 to Docter <note target="n1"><abbr expan="Archibald">Archd</abbr> Blair,</note> and for &pound;108"6"8 <lb/>to Mr <note target="n2">Lewis Burwell,</note> these Sums You are to make <abbr expan="payment">paymt</abbr> <lb/>of &amp; to charge to that Estate, which Shall be all at Psent <lb/>from&mdash;&mdash; </p>

<closer>Sir   Yor. most humble Servts.</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1723 June 16-1724 April 23, Robert Carter Papers, (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.  There is a nineteenth-century transcript of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note><lb/>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and state have been added for clarity.</note><lb/>

<note>While the name of Mann Page does not appear on the draft, it was written as if by two persons, and because Carter and Page looked after the affairs of Carter's widowed daughter, Elizabeth Burwell, it is likely that Page joined in this letter.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] Archibald Blair (c. 1665-1733), younger brother of James Blair, came to Virginia before 1700 and settled in Williamsburg where he practiced medicine and operated a retail store. (<cit><bibl n="B42">Kneebone <hi rend="italics">et al.</hi>,  <title>Dictionary of Virginia Biography.</title> 1:535-6.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Lewis Burwell (d. 1743) lived "at one of the large properties he acquired on the north bank of the James River south of Williamsburg." He became a prominent citizen of James City County, serving as justice and burgess. He built a fine mansion at his Kingsmill plantation near "Carter's Grove." (<cit><bibl n="B42">Kneebone <hi rend="italics">et al.</hi>,  <title>Dictionary of Virginia Biography.</title></bibl></cit>) 2:433-4.</note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>