<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C23g04a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to William Cage, July 4 and 22 and 22, 1723</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 14 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C23g04a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Cage, July 4 and 22, 1723</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>4 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1938</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Fairfax Papers, Box 1, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1723-07-04</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C23g04aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>4 p.</extent>
<date value="1723-07-04"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C23g04a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Cage, July 4 and 22, 1723</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to William Cage, trustee of  Lady Fairfax's estate, July 4, 1723, concerning the debts owed by the former agent of the Northern Neck proprietary in the colony, Edmund Jenings, to the proprietors. Carter believes he has collected all that is possible and that the next alternative is to file a suit. He notes that Jenings is in very poor physical and financial health. He then turns to the problem of establishing the boundaries of the Brent Town grant within the proprietary and reports that George Brent and his mother have sworn they will not permit Carter to survey it. He adds that he always reminds Micajah Perry when writing him to have the rent money ready for Cage but hopes Cage will not call for it sooner than it is needed. In a lengthy poost script dated July 22, 1723, Carter reports the steps he has taken in the colony to force the authorities to recognize the rights of the proprietors to certain types of property. His case is to be heard by the General Court, and he asks Cage to obtain legal opinions in England that would support Carter's Virginia lawyers.</p>               
</div1>                 
</front>




<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="WC">William Cage,</note> July 4 and 22, 1723</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1723-07-04">July the 4th: 1<hi rend="underline">723</hi></date><lb/>
Wm Cage Esqr.&mdash;&mdash;<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p><sic corr="Although ">Altho</sic> you have not been pleased to let me have <lb/>a line from you in some Years, I must not <sic corr="omit ">omitt</sic> to let you <lb/>hear from me Especially how your Affair with <note n="EJ"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Colln.</abbr>  <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic></note> <lb/>Stands, <abbr expan="it was ">twas </abbr> a lucky chance I had to <add place="supralinear">get</add> so much of your debt from <lb/>him last Year, but I <sic corr="can't ">cant</sic> get a penny more from him, I have <lb/><sic corr="lately ">latly</sic> got an Accot: Settled under his hand a <sic corr="copy ">coppy</sic> of which <lb/>I now send you also a <sic corr="copy ">coppy</sic> of part of a Lettr  of yours to &mdash;<lb/>Edmund <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic> whereby he reckons to discharge himself of <lb/>a <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> Above a hundred pound of his debt, he <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> no other Voucher <lb/>to do it by, and I must observe to you that both the Letter and <lb/>the name seems to be all of your own hand <sic corr="writing ">writting</sic>, wherein <lb/>your Demand was but for two Years rent, so that he reckons&mdash; <lb/>that you <sic corr="received ">reced</sic> of Mr. Adamson on his Accot: more Money <sic corr="than ">then</sic> <lb/>he can make appear from any of the Accots: he has to show <lb/>from Adamson, It will <add place="supralinear">be</add> proper for you to consider of this&mdash; <lb/>Matter and let me know your thoughts of it&mdash;&mdash;</p>

<p>I have his repeated promises that he will dispose <lb/>of some of his Virginia Estate to raise money for you, these <lb/>are but words, I take his Circumstances to be very Desperate <lb/>and he is a very decayed man, so that I am of Opinion the <lb/>Safest way is to bring <del>a</del> Suit against him which I am not very <lb/>willing to do <sic corr="until ">till</sic> you send me your positive Orders to <sic corr="justify ">Justifie</sic> <lb/>me in going into these harsh measures with him</p>

<p>I shall find a great deal of Difficulty in the <lb/>laying Off the <note n="BT">Brenton Grant,</note> I have given some <sic corr="public ">publick</sic> <lb/>Notice about, <note target="n1">Young Brent</note>  and his Mother declare <lb/>if I Offer to Stretch a chain there they will Stop me, I <lb/>must try whether they will be as good as their words, If <lb/>they do I shall go near to call them before their betters, <lb/>I hope your money upon my Lease is punctually paid <lb/>you, I hardly write a Letter to Mr. Perry but I <lb/>press him to pay your rents at the Succeeding Year it <lb/>is due, last winter he tells me your money was ready <lb/>for you at your call&mdash;&mdash;

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
	I thank God I never am in want of Money in his hands to answer your Claim <lb/><sic corr="although ">Altho</sic> I take it as a kindness that in regard <lb/>to the hard Bargain I am under <lb/>In respect to the dead times of <sic corr="tobacco ">Tobbo.</sic> that you are <lb/>not too pressing and hasty with me faster <sic corr="than ">then</sic> your <lb/>Occasions calls for it, believing you take your <lb/>money to be as Safe in my hands as in your own</p>

<p>I reckon in writing to you it is as Acceptable <lb/>as If I <sic corr="joined ">joyned</sic> his Lordship with you. with great <lb/>respect I am <abbr expan="Sir ">Sr</abbr>
 </p>

<closer>Your most <abbr expan="Obedient ">Obedt.</abbr> humble <abbr expan="Servant ">Servt. </abbr> <lb/><lb/>

<signed><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">ROBERT CARTER</hi></hi></signed>

<seg type="postscript">
<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;A Clause to be added to <abbr expan="Colonel ">Coln.</abbr> Cages Le<add resp="editor">[tter]</add><lb/>

<hi rend="underline"><abbr expan="Sir ">Sr</abbr></hi>&mdash;	&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;July the 22d <hi rend="underline">1723</hi><lb/><lb/>

When I <sic corr="wrote ">writ</sic> the above <sic corr="it was ">twas</sic> out of my head to let <lb/>you know that I had a <sic corr="controversy ">Controversie</sic> with the Crown about <lb/>the meaning of some words in the Proprietors Grant to wit <lb/>this Clause (All and all manner of Deodands goods of <lb/>"felons and fugitives Treasure Trove waifs Strays fines <lb/>"forfietures Escheats advowsons Royalltys and Heridita <lb/>
"whatsoever) Notwithstanding these strong words all <abbr expan="Colonel ">Colln:</abbr> <lb/><sic corr="Jenings ">Jenning's</sic> time the Deodands have been taken by the <lb/>Governour the felons=goods, and the fines and forfietures <lb/>have been <abbr expan="received ">reced</abbr> by the Officers of the Crown and Accounted <lb/>for to the Revenue, Soon after I <abbr expan="received ">reced</abbr> your power of <lb/>Attorney I asserted <del>our</del> <add place="supralinear">the  <abbr expan="proprietors ">proprs</abbr> Right</add> and made a Demand of the <lb/>receiver <abbr expan="General ">Genll:</abbr> and had a hearing before <note target="n2"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Coln.</abbr>  Spotswood</note> <lb/>the then Governour and the Council, whereupon an order <lb/>of Council was made that the Kings Attorney should prep<add resp="editor">[are] </add> <lb/>a case to be argued before the Judges of the <abbr expan="General ">Genll:</abbr> Cour<add resp="editor">[t]</add> <lb/>This case now <sic corr="lies ">lyes</sic> for <sic corr="trial ">Tryall</sic> <sic corr="until">till</sic> the next Court

<pb n="4"/><lb/><lb/>
I have feed the best Lawyers we have in maintenace <lb/>of this <sic corr="controversy ">Controversie</sic> and I hope both his Lordship and you <lb/>will <sic corr="justify ">Justifie</sic> me in it to the <sic corr="utmost, ">uttmost,</sic> my Lease wears out <lb/>apace it will be no great loss to me to let it go as it will <lb/>but it may come to be of considerable advantage to those <lb/>that may hereafter Enjoy this Estate and will be richly <lb/>worth contending for<lb/><lb/>

If the cause should go against me my present <lb/>thoughts are to Appeal to the King <del>and</del> in Council, but I pray you <lb/>will take the first Opportunity to let me have your full <lb/>Instructions about it, and if you send me the <sic corr="opinion ">Oppinion</sic> <lb/>of some of <add place="supralinear">the</add> ablest of your Lawyers none better to be sure <lb/><sic corr="than ">then</sic> the Attorney <abbr expan="General ">Genll:</abbr> and the Solicitor <abbr expan="General ">Genll:</abbr> <add place="supralinear">wch will be of great use to me</add>, I believe <lb/>it may be advisable for me if I can to get the case set <lb/>over <sic corr="until ">till</sic> our Spring <abbr expan="General ">Genll.</abbr> Court whereby you will <lb/>have time to let me hear from you, pray present my <lb/>humble Duty to <note n="TF">his Lordship</note> and allow me to Subscribe <lb/>myself <hi rend="underline"><abbr expan="Sir ">Sr</abbr></hi>&mdash; <lb/><lb/>Your most <abbr expan="Obedient ">Obedt:</abbr> &amp; most humble. <abbr expan="Servant ">Servt. </abbr></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi>  The recipient's copy of the July 4, 1723, letter is in the Fairfax Papers, Box 1, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 111-12.</bibl></cit> The draft of the letter and of the post script are in Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 - 1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, and there is a nineteenth-century transcript of the letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note><lb/>

<note>The address leaf of the recipient's copy bears the following: "To Wm. Cage Esqr | Of Milgate | Near Maidestone | To the Care of Capt. Benja. Graves | &amp; delivd to his own hand | Per the Carter." There is a note on the address leaf: "BG to Inclose this as directed. &amp; desire | an answer as to the receipt of it by the | Generall Post." The letter is endorsed by Cage,  "July 4, 1723."</note><lb/>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to persons abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] George Brent inherited from his grandfather, George Brent (d. 1699) of "Woodstock," Stafford County (who was the "resident partner in Virginia" for the development of the Brent Town grant by Nicholas Hayward), the family's claim to a portion of the Brent Town grant. </note><lb/>

<note id="n2">[2] Alexander Spotswood (1646-1740) had been the governor from 1710 to 1722.</note><lb/>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised August 21, 2009.</hi></note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>