<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;

<!NOTATION html SYSTEM "HTML">
<!ENTITY Ext17 SYSTEM "http://www.pbs.org\/wgbh\/aia\/part1\/1p269.html" NDATA html>


 ]>
<TEI.2 id="C23g13a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, July 13, 1723</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 13 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C23g12a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, July 13, 1723</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date>1842</date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1723-07-13</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C23g13aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 p.</extent>
<date value="1723-07-13"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C23g13a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, July 13, 1723</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Micajah Perry, July 13, 1723, concerning the value of the Virginia estate of his niece's husband, John Lloyd, which Perry is negotiating to buy for Carter. He estimates the value of slave, and notes that cattle and  horses have only modest value whensold individually, and that hogs have no market value. Carter has managed the estate for many years. He tells Perry to let the sellers know that he will match any other offer, and will pay as promptly as the  sellers wish.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="MP2">Micajah Perry,</note> July 13, 1723</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Rappahannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1723-07-13">July the 13th. <hi rend="underline">1723</hi></date><lb/>
Mr. Micaja Perry<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sr&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>I have already sent you an Inventory of the <lb/><note n="LL">LL</note>'s Estate that <sic corr="It">It't</sic> <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> may appear the clearer before you I now <lb/>send it you Distinguished under its <sic corr="several">Severall</sic> Species by wch. <lb/>you and the <abbr expan="Gentlemen">Gentm.</abbr> concerned will be the better Enabled to pass <lb/>your Judgements upon the value of it if they are in <add place="supralinear">Earnest</add> to Sell and <lb/>can make a good title, however, I shall give you here the best <lb/>Accot. I can, how the prices of Virginia Estates run from man <lb/>to man, as for Negroes Suppose you know the prices they are <lb/>Sold at well Enough, two Year ago <note n="MP1"><abbr expan="Colonel">Coln.</abbr> Page</note> bought <add resp="editor">[...]</add> <lb/>Bombera<add place="supralinear">man</add> Slaves the finest that ever I saw between a<add resp="editor">[...]</add> <lb/>18 and 28 years of age not one Exceeding Thirty I dare say 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
of <abbr expan="Captain">Capt y</abbr> <abbr expan="Francis">Francs.</abbr> Willis Agent of the <note target="n1">African company</note> at Seven<lb/>teen pound per head, last Year I bought men for Twenty Women <lb/>Eighteen and Girls of 10 and 12 Years of age for 10 pound per <lb/>head, this Year I know of no large Quantity have been sold <lb/>together, the small folks and Middling people have been <lb/>the only buyers. I have known <sic corr="several">Severall</sic> Single choice men <lb/>bought for 20&pound; <sic corr="apiece">peice</sic> the choicest have gone at 40&pound; <lb/>this <sic corr="has">hath</sic> been the rule with the Sellers as far as I have heard <lb/>I doubt not would I have taken a Quantity I might have <lb/>had them considerably cheaper, You must know the Slaves <lb/><del>such as</del> that come from Gambia such as <abbr expan="Colonel">Coln.</abbr>
 Page had are of a <lb/>much larger size and have more Sense and more used to <lb/>work <sic corr="than">then</sic> any other, I would freely give at any time 40<abbr expan="shillings">S</abbr> <lb/>a head more for them Slaves <sic corr="than">then</sic> for the Cites <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add></p>

<p>As for Cattle there is no Such thing as Selling a stock <lb/>together for <del>ready</del> Money, the common price for a young fat <lb/>Cow in killing time is Thirty five Shillings Cash and for a <lb/>Steer 7 Year old Fifty Shillings this you may be Informed of <lb/>by your Masters when they buy fresh meat, <del>The horses and mares </del></p>

<p>The horses and mares you must understand are <lb/>of very small Value among us they swarm upon us and are <lb/>degenerated into such runts that you may buy them as they <lb/>run almost for any thing, not many Years ago I sold Six out <lb/>of my pasture to <note n="JL"><abbr expan="Doctor">Doctr.</abbr> Lomax</note> of three Years old for shipping <lb/>of as 20<abbr expan="shillings">S</abbr> per head some of these you will observe are very old <lb/>and some very Young,</p>

<p>For the <sic corr="hogs">hoggs</sic> I dont know what to say to them <lb/>as they run in the woods <sic corr="we">wee</sic> Esteem <add resp="editor">them</add> little better <sic corr="than">then</sic> <sic corr="Vermin,">Vermine,</sic> <lb/>and tis not common to put them into the Inventory of our Estates, <lb/>Indeed after <sic corr="we">wee</sic> have spent a <sic corr="Barrel">Barrell</sic> of Corn upon them per <sic corr="hog">hogg</sic> <lb/>to make them <sic corr="fit">fitt</sic> for killing, they will fetch you from 20<abbr expan="shillings">S:</abbr> to 25<abbr expan="shillings">S:</abbr>
<lb/>per head the Barrows and <sic corr="Spayed">Spaid</sic> Sows <add place="supralinear">of 3 years old</add> <sic corr="Current">Currant</sic> Money, for the <lb/><sic corr="household">houshold</sic> goods tis very old and mean as you may very well <lb/>conceive having been under the use of such various hands, <lb/>There is 9 of the Negroes as I have already observed are so much 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
past their labour that they are rather a charge <sic corr="than">then</sic> anything <lb/>Else, their Levy and <sic corr="clothes">cloathes</sic> come to more then they make <lb/>there is three of them at one place put in for a Share and at <lb/>no place under two for a Share and a lusty Girl or Boy to <lb/>help out with their work to Boot, and yet the Overseers Grumble <lb/>very much to allow any thing for them,</p>

<p>The Lands and Plantations you have often had a <lb/><sic corr="particular">perticular</sic> Accot. of, when Carey has got that plantation away <lb/>as no <add place="supralinear">doubt </add>but he will <add place="supralinear">(if he can make his title good) the only objection against him</add> <sic corr="though">tho</sic> I will defend it to the <sic corr="Utmost">Uttmost</sic> if you will <lb/>Send me such orders, There will be but Nineteen hundred Acres <lb/>or thereabout, every Plantation cleared quite out and no <lb/>Timber left for building, <del>This</del></p>

<p>This is a true representation of this Estate; old <lb/><note target="n2"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Willis</note> knows as well the value of a Virginia Estate as any <lb/>man let him but consider the great difference there is between <lb/>Lands in those parts of the <sic corr="Country">Countrey</sic> and <sic corr="Gloucester">Gloster</sic> where he <lb/>lived, the low Ebb that <abbr expan="tobacco">Tobbo</abbr> is at and the little Income we <lb/>make at this day of our Virginia Estates and I could almost <lb/>agree he should set the Value upon it himself,</p>

<p>I must confess in regard I have had this Estate so <lb/>long under my Government that the best of the Slaves went from <lb/>hence with <note n="ECL"><add place="supralinear">my</add> Brothers Daughter</note>  <sic corr="Lloyd's"> Loyd's </sic>first Wife and are very <lb/>much related to <sic corr="several">Severall</sic> of my families of Slaves, having <lb/>lands in plenty to Settle them upon I am very <sic corr="desirous">desireous</sic> to be <lb/>the purchaser, and will pay the money in as little time as they <lb/>can reasonably desire it and will give as much as any other <lb/>person that will Offer at the Estate <sic corr="Entirely">Intirely</sic> together and I <lb/>hope if not for my Sake at least for my son whom they Seem <lb/>to have very much in their Esteem <add place="supralinear"><hi rend="italics">to whom this Estate may probably come</hi></add> <note target="n3">they</note> will let me have the <lb/>first refusal of it, Thus you have this Affair fully before y<add resp="editor">[ou]</add> <lb/>as I can set it <sic corr="until">untill</sic> I hear futher from you about it I a<add resp="editor">[m]</add> <lb/><hi rend="underline"><abbr expan="Sir">Sr</abbr> </hi></p>

<closer>Your most humble Serv<corr resp="editor">[ant]</corr></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. There is a 19th-century copy of the letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia. Published in Volume 2 (February 1842) of <hi rend="italics">The Southern Planter,</hi> pp. 40-41.</note><lb/>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. His usual return address, the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] The Royal African Company, founded in 1672, grew out of earlier slave-trading companies that had been founded in the middle of the  seventeenth century, and that held monopolies on the English trade in slaves. The trade proved so  profitable that Parliament was lobbied successfully to rescind the monopoly and open the trade to anyone which happened in 1698. Carter anticipates that the company will fight the proposed tax on imported slaves even through it is to be paid by the colonial purchasers, not the importers. He was correct for the law was not allowed to stand due to lobbying against it in England. (<cit><bibl><xref to="http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/aia/part1/1p269.html">"Royal African Company Established,"</xref> </bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="B27">Billings. <hi rend="italics">et al. </hi> <title>Colonial Virginia: A History.</title> p. 232.</bibl></cit>)</note><lb/>


<note id="n2">[2] Francis Willis (1690-<hi rend="italics">post</hi> 1749) of Ware Parish, Gloucester County, who served as burgess. (<cit><bibl>"Willis Family." <title>William and Mary Quarterly.</title> 1st ser. 5(1896): 24-27, 171-176; 6(1897): 27-29, 206-214.)</bibl></cit></note><lb/>


<note id="n3">[3] The preceding words in italics were entered by Carter between the lines of the clerk's draft.</note><lb/>


<note><hi rend="italics">Text revised November 30, 2007, and October 1, 2009.</hi></note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>