<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; 

<!NOTATION html SYSTEM "HTML">
<!ENTITY Ext6 SYSTEM "http://www.fraudaid.com\/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms\/bill_of_exchange.htm" NDATA html>

]>
<TEI.2 id="C23g29c">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Captain Benjamin Graves, July 29, 1723</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.9  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C23g29c.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Captain Benjamin Graves, July 29, 1723</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1723-07-29</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C23g29cT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1723-07-29"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C23g29c.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Captain Benjamin Graves, July 29, 1723</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his old friend, Captain Benjamin Graves, July 29, 1723, whose ship was anchored in one of the colony's rivers, with general news. He states that the news from England confirms the amendment to the tobacco bill in Parliament will  prohibit the importation of stemmed tobacco into England, and suggests that if English merchants could only be adept as Scots in avoiding dutys, they would maintain the trade. He adds that there is wet weather that may, should it continue, help the planters by limiting the crop. He wishes his friend health and success, and hopes he will write when he can. In a post script, he requests Graves bring him in a cauldron of coal on his next voyage.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Captain <note target="n1">Benjamin Graves,</note> July 29, 1723</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1723-07-29">July 29. <hi rend="underline">1723</hi></date><lb/>
Capt. Benja. Graves<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p>I hope this will find You in health as I thank <lb/>God It leaves me, This Encloses to You a Second <note target="n2">bill of <abbr expan="exchange ">Exche.</abbr></note> <lb/>of Gwain Thacker on Mr. Evans payable to <note target="n3">Yor. Brother</note> <lb/>for Five pound Nine <abbr expan="shillings ">Shills.</abbr> &amp; three pence which I believe <lb/>was the Desire of Your Sending It to Me,</p>

<p>I have begun Saving the Plank, for the <note n="CS"><name type="ship">Carter</name></note> <lb/>According to the <abbr expan="directions ">Direcs. </abbr> You left <del>wth me</del></p>

<p>I do not Yet hear whether You had the luck to Join the James <lb/>River Ships,</p>

<p><note target="n3">Hopkins</note> is <sic corr="arrived ">arrivd</sic> My Lettrs. are not come up, <lb/><abbr expan="Several ">Sevl.</abbr> <del>illegible</del> <add place="supralinear">Letters</add> at <sic corr="Gloucester ">Gloster</sic> Court on Thursday last, <sic corr="confirm ">confirme</sic> the Re=<lb/>=port, we had, that the <note target="n4">Scotch</note> had got a clause into the Tobo. Act <lb/>for a Prohibition of the Importation of all <sic corr="stemmed ">Stemd</sic> Tobo. how <lb/>pleasing this is to us here You may Easily Imagine, We <lb/>Are now only to look for our Mercys from heaven, our fellow <lb/>Subjects It seems have none for us, If the English <abbr expan="merchants ">Merchts.</abbr> <lb/>can be but as Arch in finding out ways of fraud as the North=<lb/>=Brittains are, they will be able to keep way with them, but <lb/>We that are the Planters, are <sic corr="tied ">tyed</sic> down to the full payment of <lb/>the <sic corr="duties ">Dutys,</sic> I will not pretend to forsee the consequences of <lb/>this fatal Streak, It looks like a very black cloud at present</p>

<p>The heavens have bin Somewhat propicious to us of <lb/>late, The General Report of the Country is that Tobo. is but Mean <lb/>We have now a very wet spell over us, If it <sic corr="does ">dos</sic> but Continue <lb/>three or four days longer It may be a help to Us, Since the <lb/>Parliament has bin so severe We have little reason to Expect <lb/><add resp="editor">[the] </add> Ministry will show any Countenace to <note target="n5">Our Stint Act
</note>
<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
nothing but the Destruction of our Labour from the kind hand <lb/>of Providence will then be our relief, I wish <add resp="editor">[you] </add> Success <lb/>In Your Undertakings and health in Your Constitution &amp; <lb/>If You would allow Yourself the <sic corr="leisure ">leizure</sic> to give me a free <lb/>line of News by Every opportunity You meet with, It <lb/>will be very acceptable to, </p>

<closer>Your <del>very </del><abbr expan="affectionate ">affect.</abbr> Friend &amp; Servt.
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>
I would Desire You to bring me in a <lb/><note target="n6"><sic corr="cauldron ">Chaldron</sic> of coals</note> I know you can <lb/>do it without putting me to the Charge <lb/>of any thing to bring them in,</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>It is surprising to find the return address of "Rappahannock" (for the river on which he lived) rather than "Corotoman," (the name of his home) on this letter as he generally used it on letters sent out of the colony. His county and the colony have been added for clarity to the brief heading on the draft.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] Benjamin Graves was the son of Captain Thomas Graves (d. <hi rend="italics">ante</hi> 1720), long a captain of vessels trading to Virginia, and a special friend of Carter. Benjamin also commanded vessels in the trade, especially the <hi rend="italics">Carter</hi>.  (<cit><bibl>Adm. 68/194-196, ff. 33r, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note><lb/>

<note id="n2"> [2] A bill of exchange is a kind of check or promissory note without interest.  It is used primarily in international trade, and is a written order by one person to pay another a specific sum on a specific date sometime in the future.  If the bill of exchange is drawn on a bank, it is called a bank draft.  If it is drawn on another party, it is called a trade draft.  Sometimes a bill of exchange will simply be called a draft, but whereas a draft is always  negotiable (transferable by endorsement), this is not necessarily true of a bill of exchange. (<cit><bibl><xref to="Ext6">"Dictionary of  Financial Scam Terms."</xref> http://www.fraudaid.com/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms/bill_of_exchange.htm. 8/22/2005</bibl></cit>)</note><lb/>


<note id="n3">[3] Adam Graves was also a son of Captain Thomas Graves [d. <hi rend="italics">ante</hi> 1720], long a captain of vessels trading to Virginia, and a special friend of Robert Carter's. Adam Graves commanded the <hi rend="italics">Bailey</hi> in 1725-1727, a ship that belonged to London merchant William Dawkins. (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800, and Adm. 68/194-196 found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert  and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</bibl></cit>)</note><lb/>


<note id="n3">[3] Captain James Hopkins would be in command of the <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi> in 1727-1728. He was then working for London merchant Robert Cary. He is mentioned several times in Carter's diary. (<cit><bibl>Adm. 68/194, ff 77v, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note><lb/>

<note id="n4">[4] The trading policies of Scots merchants were of considerable concern to Virginia planters and English  merchants at this time, and the matter came before Parliament in 1723. Vessels sent by Scots were crewed by captains and factors authorized to pay good prices in Virginia which enabled them to  obtain full cargoes. English merchants argued that the only way the Scots could afford to pay such good prices was their ability to avoid paying duties on the tobacco at home. Micajah Perry appeared before Parliament and gave statistics of the duties paid by his firm in earlier years and the far smaller amounts paid in the past several years because his ships could not obtain full cargoes in Virginia.  (<cit><bibl n="B22">Price. <title>Perry of London. . . . </title> pp. 64-65.</bibl></cit>)</note><lb/>

<note id="n5">[5] For the Virginia Council's reasons for assenting to this proposed tobacco law to reduce the quantity of tobacco planted, see  <cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:45-51.  </bibl></cit></note><lb/>

<note id="n6">[6] Chaldron is "an obsolete form of cauldron" and means "a dry measure of 4 quarters or 32 bushels. . . ." ( <title>Oxford English Dictionary</title> )</note>


<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised October 14, 2009.</hi></note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>