<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C23g04g">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, July 4, 1723 </title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 11 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C23g04g.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, July 4, 1723</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1723-07-04</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C23g04gT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 p.</extent>
<date value="1723-07-04"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C23g04g.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, July 4, 1723</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Micajah Perry, July 4, 1723, concerning his shipments of tobacco on several vessels, and the care that has been taken in the production of the tobacco. He then writes at length about &pound;1,500 that will be returned to him from an annuity with the Bank of England which he urges Perry to hold at 5% interest. Carter notes that he can obtain 6% in Virginia but would prefer Perry to have it. He asks Perry to find out why his Bank of England stock has paid only 6% interest when he had been promised 8% at the time that he bought it. He closes by informing Perry that 7 hogshead of the tobacco that is being shipped he has collected from Essex and Middlesex and prized it at his home; it belongs to his son John and the profit should be transferred to John's account but accounted for to Carter.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, July 4, 1723</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Rappahannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1723-07-04"><hi rend="underline">July the 4th 1723</hi></date><lb/>
Mr Perry&mdash;&mdash;<lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;to be writ<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p>By <note target="n1">Keeling</note> I sent you 41 hhds of my own Crops <lb/>by Jos Bradbey Ten and  now herein you have a bill of Lading <lb/>for 30 hhds more on Board thee <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> <note n="CS">Carter</note> <add place="supralinear">all the same Tobbo: of my Crops</add>, I hope they are with<add resp="editor">[out]</add> <lb/>all manner of faults I am sure it hath been my uttmost Endea<lb/>vour they should be so they have been <sic corr="viewed">veiwd</sic> and <sic corr="reviewed">reveiwd</sic> a<add resp="editor">[nd]</add> <lb/>every Overseer that made them <sic corr="passed">pass,d</sic> them upon <lb/>Oaths, You gave me a hint in one of your late L<add resp="editor">[etters]</add> 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
that the Parliament were about paying of the Redeemable <lb/>Annuities, that mine was one, you beleived they would <lb/>do it in September, and advised me to consider how <lb/>I would order the laying out of that money, in answer <lb/>I told you I was <sic corr="desirous">desireous</sic> you should take it of me <del>[illegible]</del><lb/>if you will Afford to give me 5 percent, which is the <lb/>common Interest passing between man &amp; man &amp; which <lb/>I am very apt to 
<sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> you often pay yourself, and <lb/>which I am very well Informed <note target="n2"><abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> Heath</note> pays for <lb/>near three Thousand pound <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> of <note n="WC1">Mrs. Churchills</note> Money, <lb/>The constant Interest here is 6 per Cent, and where we <lb/>are in any doubt we can have land and Negroes for <lb/>Security, In this manner <note n="NB">Mr. Burwells</note> money is put <lb/>out, so is Mrs. Churchills  youngest Daughters, and so <lb/>I have a pretty deal of money out my self, and so I can <lb/>let out this if I please, however I had rather have <lb/>it <sic corr="lie">lye</sic> in your hands at 5 per Cent and look upon it as <lb/>an Obligation from you, but if no reasons will prevail <lb/>with you, and that the money be paid into your hands, <lb/>at the time you Expect it, I desire you will <add place="supralinear">take</add> the first <lb/><sic corr="opportunity">Oportunity</sic> to let me know it that I may loose no <lb/>time in disposing of it either here or in England, <lb/>but <sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> I shall choose rather to let it out here, <lb/>If I take the matter right for my Fifteen hundred pound <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> <lb/>you will receive <del>for me</del> of the Bank Fifteen <abbr expan="hundred">hundd</abbr> pounds <lb/>for me, without any Diminution.</p>

<p>	Now I am upon this Toppick I shall desire <lb/>you to let me into the Reason why the bank for some <lb/>years past pays but 6 perCent Interest for their Stock <lb/>you may know if you please to look back to the time  <lb/>I purchased that my Stock cost me very dear I <sic corr="bought">bout</sic> <lb/>it under the Expectation that I should always have <lb/>had 8 perCent for my Money,</p>

<p>In the bill of lading above mentio<add resp="editor">[ne]</add>d there is 37 <lb/>hhds 7 of them are sweet <sic corr="scented">sented</sic> Tobbo. came out  of Essex &amp; <lb/><add resp="editor">[M]</add>iddlesex. I gathered it together and prized it at home 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
That is the Essex Tobbo. the Middlesex I did not see these 7 hhds <lb/>are properly my sons Tobbo. but are of my Shipping and I Expect <lb/>to have the discounts and a distinct Accot. of Sales <sic corr="returned">returnd</sic> to me <lb/>the neat proceeds if you <sic corr="please">pleas</sic> you may Transfer to my <note n="JC">Sons</note>&mdash; <lb/>Accot: I am <sic corr="Sir">Sr. </sic></p>

<closer>Your most humble Servt.</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note><lb/>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. His usual return address, the county, and state have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] Captain William Keiling commanded the <hi rend="italics">Betty.
</hi> (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley  Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] This may be Edmund Heath, husband of Katherine (Bailey) Heath, grandaughter and daughter of the Carter family's old English friends, <note n="AB1">Arthur Bailey</note> and his son, <note n="AB2">Arthur Bailey,</note> as Alan Simpson has speculated. (<cit><bibl n="A3">Simpson. "Robert Carter's Schooldays." p. 173, fn. 29.)</bibl></cit>)</note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>