<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; 

<!NOTATION Ext15 SYSTEM "htm">
<!ENTITY Ext15 SYSTEM "http://www.poslfit.homeip.net/cgi-bin/genea2.pl?id=10301.htm" NDATA htm>
<!NOTATION Ext16 SYSTEM "htm">
<!ENTITY Ext16 SYSTEM "http://www.mathewscommunications.com/mathews/mw1/mw1g93.htm#6068" NDATA htm>

]>
<TEI.2 id="C23g03d">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Captain John Hyde &amp; Company, July 3, 1723</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 11 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">filename</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Captain John Hyde &amp; Company, July 3, 1723</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley  Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1723-07-03</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C23g03dT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 p.</extent>
<date value="1723-07-03"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C23g03d.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Captain John Hyde &amp; Company, July 3, 1723</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Captain John Hyde &amp; Company, July 3, 1723, to report that a shipment of goods arrived while he was at the Assembly, but he has been so busy since his return that he has not had time to review the goods. Hyde's ship must remain in the colony until the next crop is ready; the last harvest has all been shipped. The Scots ships that came in together have not been able to obtain full cargoes while "our Ships are all got full." He describes the terms of the recent Assemblly's law restraining the quantity of tobacco planted, and states some arguments for the approval of the  law by the government. He encloses a bill of lading for 40 hogsheads of tobacco, an invoice for goods for his children,  and a bill of exchange (none present). </p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Captain <note n="JH2">John Hyde</note> &amp; Company, July 3, 1723</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1723-07-03">July the 3d: <hi rend="underline">1723</hi></date><lb/>
not yet coppy'd<lb/>
[Captain] Jno. Hyde &amp; Compa:<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Gent:&mdash;&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>Yours of the 28th of March by <abbr expan="Captain ">Capt.</abbr> Burton came to hand <lb/>According to your orders he sent down his long Boat with my goods <lb/>they came when I was from home at our Assembly had not the <lb/><sic corr="opportunity ">Oportunity</sic> of <sic corr="writing ">writting</sic> him an answer <note target="n1">Mrs: Chew</note> Acquaints <lb/>me their <abbr expan="tobacco ">Tobbo.</abbr> was all gone Your Ship must <sic corr="lie ">lye</sic> over <sic corr="until ">till</sic> the <lb/>next Crop and urges me to provide some early <abbr expan="tobacco">Tobbo </abbr> for <lb/>her to which I dont know what to say, I have heard it <sic corr="tallked ">talkd</sic> <lb/>that after <abbr expan="tobacco ">Tobbo</abbr> has paid the Duty here they have Exacted the <lb/>Duty there over again which if true is a very great <lb/>Discouragement to the Trade and to a Communication <lb/>between the two Governments. I shall enquire  into it and <lb/>shall be very willing to serve your Interest</p>

<p>We have had a long assembly which <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> kept <lb/>me from home <sic corr="until ">till</sic> very lately and puts me into such a hurry <lb/>cannot spare time <del>at present</del> to <sic corr="ooverhaul ">overhall</sic> the goods Shall <lb/>say nothing of them <sic corr="at ">att</sic> present</p>

<p>You tell me and indeed all agree the same that <lb/>while the <note target="n2">Scotch Affair</note> was on foot there was no Selling <lb/><abbr expan="tobacco ">Tobbo:</abbr> but that you were then Intreaty for a good <sic corr="parcel ">Parcell</sic> <lb/>of my <abbr expan="tobacco ">Tobbo:</abbr> I have hopes by this time you have sold <lb/>it of all what these Ships find on hand <sic corr="it is ">tis</sic> to be <sic corr="feared ">feard</sic> will <lb/>not do very well, our Ships after abundance of Struggling <lb/>and <note target="n3">dobbling</note> are all got full, The Scotch Fleet that came all <lb/><del>came</del> in <sic corr="at ">att</sic> once upon us many of them cannot find <abbr expan="tobacco ">Tobbo:</abbr>. <lb/>and <abbr expan="several ">Sevll.</abbr> of the MaryLand Ships <sic corr="lie ">lye</sic> over,</p>

<p><del>Herein</del></p>

<p>You have been so kind from time to time to advise <lb/>me of the Steps of the Scotch affair in return I shall tell you what <lb/>we have been doing here towards our releif, our <note n="HD">Good Governour</note> 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
in Compassion to our Sufferings <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> adventured to p<add resp="editor">[ass a ?] </add> <lb/>Law, laying a Stint upon our planting to 6<abbr expan="thousand ">m</abbr> plants per <add resp="editor">[head]</add> <lb/>which is not to be in force <sic corr="until ">till</sic> <sic corr="April ">Aprill</sic> next that the King m<add resp="editor">[ay]</add> <lb/>have time to <sic corr="let ">lett</sic> his pleasure be known whether he will be <lb/>Graciously  pleased to allow it a being, The Damage to the <lb/>revenue will be the great cry again <sic corr="it ">itt</sic> <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> the reasons for <sic corr="it ">itt</sic> <lb/>being but too many <sic corr="we ">wee</sic> hope will preponderate the <abbr expan="merchants ">Merchts </abbr><lb/>we Expect will be <sic corr="pleased ">pleas'd</sic> with it and their own Interest <lb/>as well as ours Engage them to Exert their Uttmost Vigour <lb/>in the Support of it</p>

<p>The very low ebb that the Trade is come to. a low <lb/><sic corr="market ">Markett</sic> at home the Shipping now coming full, and the greatest <lb/>Crop upon the Ground that ever was known, nothing but fatal <lb/>ruin threatens us unless we can have the <sic corr="relief ">releif</sic> of <note target="n\4">this Law</note></p>

<p>After all there will not be such a mighty Dimi<lb/>nution to the revenue as some Imagine 6<abbr expan="thousand ">m</abbr> plants upon <lb/>the best of our Grounds Nicely tended will probably make <lb/>more and better <abbr expan="tobacco ">Tobbo.</abbr> <sic corr="than ">then</sic> 10 or 12 (<abbr expan="thousand ">m</abbr>) of the bad as well <lb/>as the good are thrown in to Augment the Quantity, many <lb/>more reasons you will be able to Suggest to  your Selves <lb/>and we hope you will have none to put you upon Endea-<lb/>vours for Destroying <sic corr="it, ">itt,</sic> I might give you a much larger <lb/>Entertainment of the proceedings of our Assembly, but there is <lb/>no fear of news Mongers enough without any help of mine</p>

<p>Herein I send you a bill of Lading for 40 hhds  <lb/>of my Crop <abbr expan="tobacco ">Tobbo</abbr> on Board the  <note n="CS">Carter</note> <sic corr="stemmed ">Stem'd</sic> and <sic corr="straight ">Strait</sic> laid <lb/><sic corr="separated ">Seperated</sic> from all manner of Trash <sic corr="passed ">passd</sic> upon Oath, and <lb/>I have avoided the fault of hard prizing, all these Circum<lb/>stances <add place="supralinear">will</add> make It Acceptable or I shall Conclude it <lb/>out of my Power</p>

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
<p>Herein I also  send you a small Invoice for my <lb/>Childrens things, <del>you pl</del> and some odd things for myself <lb/>you <abbr expan="pleased ">pleas'd </abbr> both them and me so well last Year that I am <lb/>not Desirous to change hands, by <abbr expan="Captain ">Capt.</abbr> Hopkins I flatter <lb/>myself with hopes to have some good news of  my business <lb/>already under your care I am Sr.&mdash;&mdash;</p>

<closer>Your most humble Servt<lb/><lb/><seg type="postscript">Herein is a bill of <abbr expan="exchange ">Exche.</abbr> on Yor. <lb/>Self for 2"0"6. lately come to <lb/>my hands of Daniel Watt's Draft  </seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1723 June 16-1724 April 23, Robert Carter Papers, (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.  There is a nineteenth-century transcript of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note><lb/>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony y have been added for clarity.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] This may have been Hannah (Roy) Chew, wife of  Larkin Chew (1676-1728) a burgess 1723-26, sheriff of Spottsylvania County, 1727-1728, where he owned 17,000 acres of land. (<cit><bibl><xref to="http://poslfit.homeip.net/cgi-bin/genea2.pl?id=10301">"Genealogical Record: Larkin Chew,"</xref>  at http://poslfit.homeip.net/cgi-bin/genea2.pl?id=10301</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl><xref to="http://www.mathewscommunications.com/mathews/mw1/mw1g93.htm#6068">"Mathews-Williams Family Genealogy,"</xref> at  http://www.mathewscommunications.com/mathews/mw1/mw1g93.htm#6068</bibl></cit>. both 8/20/2009)</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n2">[2] The trading policies of Scots merchants were of considerable concern to Virginia planters and English  merchants at this time, and the matter came before Parliament in 1723. Vessels sent by Scots were crewed by captains and factors authorized to pay good prices in Virginia which enabled them to  obtain full cargoes. English merchants argued that the only way the Scots could afford to pay such good prices was their ability to avoid paying duties on the tobacco at home. Micajah Perry appeared before Parliament and gave statistics of the duties paid by his firm in earlier years and the far smaller amounts paid in the past several years because his ships could not obtain full cargoes in Virginia.  (<cit><bibl n="B22">Price. <title>Perry of London. . . . </title> pp. 64-65.</bibl></cit>)</note><lb/>

<note id="n3">[3] Carter may have dctated "doubling" in the sense of "a sudden turn in running" meaning that the ship captains had to do a lot of work in obtaining full cargoes.  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary</title></bibl></cit>)</note><lb/>

<note id="n4">[4] For the Council's reasons for assenting to this proposed tobacco law, see
 <cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:45-51. 
</bibl></cit></note><lb/>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised August 25, 2009.</hi></note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>
