<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C23g04d">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, July 4 and 26, 1723</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C23g04d.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, July 4 and 26, 1723</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1723-07-04</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C23g04dT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1723-07-04"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C23g04d.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, July 4 and 26, 1723</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Micajah Perry, July 4 and 26, 1723, concerning the estate of John Lloyd, his niece's husband, who had gone to England after her death. Carter, who has been looking after the estate for Lloyd, informs Perry that he will buy the property if a good title can be made. He adds that whoever is to take charge of the property the next year must order goods for the maintenance of the families (slaves). He sends a bill of lading for 33 hogsheads of tobacco from the Lloyd's properties, and closes with a note that he will soon draw on Perry for the salaries of the head overseer and the doctor. In a post script dated July 26th, he reports that he has drawn for Richard Meerks' salary and soon will do so for Dr. Belfield's.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="MP2">Micajah Perry,</note> July 4 and 26, 1723</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Rappahannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1723-07-04">July the 4th 1723</date><lb/>
Mr Micaja Perry<lb/><lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;To be writ<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>By Keeling I writ a pretty large letter to you upon <lb/>the <note n="LL">LL</note> Affair and sent you a particular Inventory of that whol<add resp="editor">[e]</add>  <lb/>Estate and told you if they were in Earnest about the Selling <lb/>of and can make a good title I should be wlling to be the <lb/>purchaser I am in such a hurry at present I can do no more <lb/><sic corr="than">then</sic> to Refer you to that Letter, after the <note n="CS">Carter</note> is gone <lb/>and I have a little <sic corr="leisure">leasure</sic> time I  shall consider that <lb/>Affair more closely</p>

<p>Whosoever is concerned to take care for the <lb/>provision of that Estate the next Year it will be necessary <lb/>there be sent in for the Maintenance of the families such <lb/>another parcell of goods as came in the last the same <lb/>Sorts in every Respect will do well Enough, I herein send <lb/>you a bill of Lading for 33 hhds: of those Crops Strip'd leaf <lb/>and Strait laid, Seperated from all Trash and passed <lb/>on the Oaths of them that made it, <del>in a short time</del></p>

<p>In a short time I shall draw upon you for <lb/>the Salarys due to the <abbr expan="doctor">Doctr.</abbr>  and the <note n="RM">Overseer</note> and send <lb/>you an Accot. of the Contingent charges that have not <lb/>been paid here, I am <hi rend="underline"><abbr expan="Sir">Sr</abbr></hi> 
</p>

<closer>Your most humble Servt<lb/><lb/>
<seg type="postscript">I now draw upon you for the <lb/>Impost of this Tobbo: to Ben <lb/>Graves &pound;3:7s:-d.<lb/><lb/> 
<add place="marginleft">July 26.  Since the Above I have drawn on You for 35&pound; to Richard Meeks the head <lb/>overseer his Salary and shall shortly draw for Doctor Belfields&mdash;&mdash;</add></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note><lb/>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. His usual return address, the county, and state have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note><lb/>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>