<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C23h01c">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, August 1, 1723</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 10 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C23h01c.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, August 1, 1723</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia. </idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1723-08-01</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C23h01cT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1723-08-01"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C23h01c.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, August 1, 1723</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes despondantly to London merchant Micajah Perry, August 1, 1723, that the sales accounts he has received recently for his stemmed tobacco sales are the poorest in 10 years, and portend the new act forbidding the important of such tobacco. He expects the effect of the act will be much fraud accompanied by a strong drive by Scots merchants to take over the trade in sweet scented tobacco. In the long term, he expects the English merchants to resist the Scots. On the brighter side, he expects better prices for stemmed tobacco until the act goes into effect.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="MP2">Micajah Perry,</note> August 1, 1723</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1723-08-01">Augst. 1st. 1723&mdash;</date><lb/>
[Mr.] Micajh. Perry<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p>Since Sealing up my Lettrs. for the <name type="ship">Sarah</name> <lb/>Yor. Packetts by <note target="n1">Hopkins</note> are come to hand, Most <del>Mortifying</del> <add place="supralinear">Shocking</add> <lb/>News they bring, The Poorest Accots. for <sic corr="stemmed">Stemd</sic> Tobo. that we <lb/>have seen this 10 <abbr expan="years">Yrs.</abbr> Day, and an Act of Parliament, <lb/>forbidding Us to make any more, Mortifying Considerations <lb/>Indeed, Were it not for the Remembrance  that We have but <lb/>A Short time to be in this Inconstant World, &amp; that a few <lb/>Years will make it Equal to me, how things are Transac=<lb/>=ted here,</p>
  
<p>The reasons prevailing it Seems have bin the <lb/><add place="supralinear">Lawton</add> Advantage to the Kings Revenue, which I am Very much of the <lb/>Opinion will be found In Experience to be a great Mistake <lb/>It seems probable a New Door of fraud is <sic corr="opened">opned, </sic>The Scotch <lb/>Will now drive Furiously after the <sic corr="sweet scented">Sweat Sented</sic> Trade wch. <lb/>they could not so well do while <sic corr="stemming">steming</sic> was in Fashion <lb/>The Consequence whereof will be, dammage to the Shipping <lb/>In their Freights, and to Us the. <abbr expan="consignors">Consignrs.</abbr> who must pay the <lb/>full Duty, Insomuch that in a few <abbr expan="years">Yrs.</abbr> neither the English <lb/><abbr expan="merchants">Merchts.</abbr> nor the <abbr expan="gentlemen">Gentn.</abbr> in the Country will be able to live <lb/>but I have Strong hopes, that the Eyes of Our Superiors will <lb/>be soon <sic corr="opened">Opned</sic> &amp; that the <sic corr="interest">Interst,</sic> of the <abbr expan="English merchants">Eng. Merchts.</abbr> will Ere <lb/>long revive again, &amp; will never Suffer the Trade to be wholly <lb/><sic corr="ravished">ravishd</sic> out of their hands, and as for the <sic corr="enlarging">Enlargeing</sic> the Quan=<lb/>=tity, We that Consigne home our Own Tobo. must handle it <lb/>More nicely than Ever we did, &amp; heave away all the Ground <lb/>leaves and All the <abbr expan="shattered">shatter'd</abbr> &amp; broken <sic corr="pieces">peices,</sic> Although the <lb/>Small Tobo, &amp; the Luggs  well <sic corr="managed">Manag'd</sic> is really as good, &amp; <lb/>As Acceptable to the Pipe, as the best Top <sic corr="leaves">Leafes</sic> from whence <lb/>I reckon the Quantity will be <add place="supralinear">as</add> much <sic corr="lessened">lessend</sic> as it is now <lb/>by heaving away the Stems, It should seem as if this Act <lb/>would raise the price of the <sic corr="stemmed">Stemd</sic> Tobo. now <sic corr="gone">gon</sic> home, which I <lb/>believe is the Neatest &amp; the Cleanest from Trash that Ever <lb/>You Saw a Crop, The Smoakers will be for laying in Great <lb/>Stocks, which If reason takes place will Enliven Your <lb/><sic corr="market">Markett</sic> Some Folks think You will hasten away <lb/>Your Ships, that they may return before the Act Commen<lb/>=ces,  We Shall be in a great <del>illegible</del> <add place="supralinear">dilemma</add> what to do <lb/><sic corr="until">till</sic> we hear from You, Our Crop is Early &amp; may reasonably <lb/>be made <sic corr="fit">fitt</sic> for Shipping at least the greatest part  by Christmas  

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<note target="n2"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Richardson</note> will Inform You of the Dammage <add resp="editor">[...]</add> <lb/>done to our Crop, by a pretty Smart <sic corr="storm,">Storme,</sic> Four <add resp="editor">[days ago]</add> </p>

<closer>I am Sir &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Yor. very humble. Ser<add resp="editor">[vant]</add>.
<lb/><lb/><seg type="postscript">I Observe in the Act of Parliament <lb/>there is now only Eight pound of Tobo. <lb/>upon a hhd. <sic corr="allowed">Allowd</sic> at the Scale this Allowance <lb/>I take to belong to the Importer.</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1723 June 16-1724 April 23, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a nineteenth-century transcript of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Captain James Hopkins would be in command of the <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi> in 1727-1728. He was then working for London merchant Robert Cary. He is mentioned in Carter's diary. (<cit><bibl>Adm. 68/194, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Captain [James?] Richardson commanded the <hi rend="italics">Sarah</hi> and was based in Weymouth.</note>





</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>