<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C23i17c">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Stark, September 17, 1723</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.7  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C23i17c.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Stark, September 17, 1723</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1723-09-17</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C23i17cT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1723-09-17"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C23i17c.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Stark, September 17, 1723</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Glasgow merchant John Stark, September 17, 1723, complaining mildly of the poor tobacco sales the merchant has reported. He requests Stark find him a good barber surgeon either in Glasgow or Edinburgh, and adds later in the letter that he also needs a coachman, a carpenter, a blacksmith, a tailor, a brickmaker, and a bricklayer. He lets Stark know that a ship captain from another firm has solicited his business but that he will stay with Stark until he believes he is "Ill used."</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">John Stark,</note> September 17, 1723</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1723-09-17">Sepr. 17th 1723&mdash;</date><lb/>
Mr. Jno. Stark<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>I have lately received Yours of the 18th of June I am <lb/>Sorry to find Your Market was under no better prospect of an <lb/>Alteration, I hope when You came to See some of your ships <lb/>not loaded &amp; have the News of the Poor Crop we are like to <lb/>make It will mend&mdash; </p>

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<p>I am in Great want of a Barber Surgeon in my fa<add resp="editor">[mily who] </add> <lb/>Can Shave well, dress <sic corr="wigs ">wiggs,</sic> let Blood, Dress Sores <add resp="editor"> [ . . . ] </add>  <lb/>&amp; the like, I'm told there are Abundance of such Journey<add resp="editor">[men] </add>  <lb/>&amp; Young fellows that find It hard Enough to live among <add resp="editor">[you] </add>  <lb/>I desire You if possibly You can to send me in such a one of <lb/>honest character &amp; sober principles If You cannot mee<add resp="editor">[t] </add> <lb/>with one In Your City for my purpose I dare say You may <lb/>have one <sic corr="procured ">procurd</sic> at <sic corr="Edinburgh ">Edenborough,</sic> If you can oblige me  <lb/>with Such a person it will be a considerable kindness but no= <lb/>=thing will please me so much as Your Selling my Tobo. <lb/>Well,</p>

<p>I have now been tempted by <note target="n2"><abbr expan="Captain ">Capt.</abbr> Grayson</note> to ship  <lb/>four and Twenty hhds. of Tobo. more to Your Port in him and <lb/>You may believe <sic corr="have ">hath</sic> been very much Solicited to Consign <lb/>It to his Owner but Seeing I have begun with You I will not be  <lb/>Persuaded to make use of any other person, until I think myself  <lb/>Ill used, in the cource of my Life, I have several times found the  <lb/>Larger my business <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> been, the less Encouragement I have <lb/>met with, and the Meaner <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> been my returns, I wish I come <lb/>off better <del>with</del> Now, I Shall the next Year be in want of a <lb/>Coachman, I know Such Cattle are very plenty both in Your  <lb/>City &amp; in <sic corr="Edinburgh ">Edenburgh</sic> If You can Supply <add place="supralinear">me</add> with a Towardly Young <lb/>fellow of a good Character, that Shall have five Years to  <lb/>Serve You will oblige me, a 
good Smith, a Carpenter <lb/>a Joiner, a Taylor, a Brickmaker, a Bricklayer are <lb/>Tradesmen would very well <sic corr="suit ">Sute</sic> my occasions I am 
</p>

<closer>Sir  Yor. very humble Servt.
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>A Bill of Lading for this <lb/>Tobo. is here Inclosed. </seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1723 June 16-1724 April 23, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a nineteenth-century transcript of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia. </note><lb/>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] John Stark was a  prominent Glasgow merchant in the sugar trade. He served as as baillie and provost (mayor) from 1725-1727. (<cit><bibl>John M'ure. The History of Glasgow. [Glasgow: D. Macvean and J. Wyllie &amp; Co., 1830. pp. 227-228]</bibl></cit> as seen on Google books; and <cit><bibl>"Provosts of Glasgow" at "Welcome to Glasgow" at http://www.glasgow.gov.uk/en/AboutGlasgow/LordProvostsmessage/Provosts+of+Glasgow.htm. </bibl></cit></note><lb/>

<note id="n2">[2] Benjamin Grayson was, according to Fairfax Harrison, "one of the earliest of the Scots merchants to be established on Quantico, where Dumfries was to arise." He was appointed a justice of Prince William County in November 1731. (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> pp. 156</bibl></cit>and <cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:
256.</bibl></cit>)</note><lb/>


<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised April 1, 2010.</hi></note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>