<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C23i03a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to [John Wormeley] September 3, 1723</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C23i03a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to [John Wormeley] September 3, 1723</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1723-09-03</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C23i03aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1723-09-03"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C23i03a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to [John Wormeley] September 3, 1723</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to [John Wormeley] September 3, 1723, that his recent trip to visit the younger man has brought on an attack of gout which has confined him to his house for over a week. He turns to his attempts to obtain money due the proprietors from Edmund Jenings in which Wormeley is assisting him and states that he will not take Jenings to court immediately as he has written Colonel Cage in England. The sale of Negroes from the estate may raise the sums needed, as will taking over an estate.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">[John Wormeley,]</note> September 3, 1723</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Corotoman, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1723-09-03">Sept. 3d. 1723.</date><lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Dear Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>I Shall first Acquaint You that I reckon my Night Voyage <lb/>home when I left You <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> brot. upon me a <sic corr="fit ">Fitt</sic> of the Gout On Monday <lb/>Morning I found my self lame In my right Ancle &amp; the pain Increasd so <lb/>fast that by Night I was an Entire Cripple &amp; so have continued <sic corr="until ">till</sic> <lb/>Yesterday Morning not being able to stir a foot, but as I have bin carried <lb/>In a Chair between two, It <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> handled me severely Enough, but hope <lb/><sic corr="it will ">twill</sic> prove a Short fit, both my Feet are now <sic corr="swelled ">swelld</sic> the Extreamity <lb/>of the pain is over, &amp; I can hobble about the house without the help of a <lb/>Stick, In my Gouty Slippers</p>

<p><abbr expan="Yours ">Yors.</abbr> came last Night &amp; I must Acknowledge I am <sic corr="pleased ">pleasd </sic><lb/>You have <sic corr="pushed ">pushd</sic> <note n="EJ"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> <sic corr="Jenings's ">Jennings's</sic></note> Affair wth. So much Vigour &amp; am Contented <lb/>upon <note n="JH">Mr. Holloway's</note> complying wth. his promise of giving me from under <lb/>his hand of his Consent to the Sale of the <abbr expan="Negroes ">Negs.</abbr> &amp; that he will do his <lb/>Utmost the Money Shall be <sic corr="applied ">Applyd</sic> to the Payment of this Two hundred <lb/>&amp; Odd pound to the <abbr expan="proprietors ">Proprs</abbr>, &amp; also If <abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic> will make his promise <lb/>to me under his hand In <sic corr="terms ">Termes</sic> as You Shall think proper that then <lb/>I wll <sic corr="take ">tacke</sic> <del>up</del> <add place="supralinear">out</add> no Process to this General Court on the <abbr expan="proprietors ">Proprs.</abbr> Accot.. Although <lb/>If I remember my Lettrs. I fear I have <sic corr="promised ">promiss'd</sic> <note n="WC"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> Cage</note> I would delay <lb/>no longer, but pray be <sic corr="satisfied ">Sattisfied</sic> with nothing but Writing, You know that <lb/>Sound Maxim, <note target="n2">Littera Scripta Manet,</note></p>

<p>The time of the <note target="n3">Lady <sic corr="Fairfaxes' ">Fairfaxs's</sic></note> Death, I can't tell how to Collect <lb/>Nor Indeed can I see the necessity of It, <abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic> <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> Accounted to me <lb/>Under his hand wch. I look upon to be Foundation Enough for the prosecution <lb/>when You have Transacted this matter to this Issue, the next Work will <lb/>be to Fall upon a Method to get my own Interest</p>

<p>It Seems to be their Intention to pay no more of that, but I will <lb/>Endeavour not to be so <abbr expan="served, ">serv'd, </abbr> If <abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic>  will give me the present <lb/>possession of the Estate, there will then only the last Years Interest be <lb/>Due, which I will be patient in Staying For a little longer, Or If <lb/>they will bring my Interest Money Into the promise wth. the <abbr expan="proprietors ">Proprs</abbr>. <lb/>For the payment of It upon the Sale of these <abbr expan="Negroes ">Negs.</abbr> I Shall be <sic corr="erasy, ">Easie,</sic> or <lb/>If they will give me any Other Good Security For It, but If neither of <lb/>these <sic corr="satisfactions ">Sattisfactions</sic> will be given me, I must desire You to take out a <lb/>proper process, Upon the Covenant In the Mortgage, <note n="JR">Mr. Randolph</note> <lb/>is my Lawyer &amp; will Direct the <del>affair</del> Matter,</p>

<p>As for Mr Holloway's Reasonable consideration If his reason <lb/><abbr expan="squared ">Squar'd </abbr> with mine, he would think One Thousand pound a very large <lb/>Consideration for that Estate, were I to have the Fee simple of It I should <lb/>be very unwilling to give so much by a great deal, let <abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> <sic corr="Jenings ">Jennings</sic> but <lb/>find me my Money &amp; then he may Make his Consideration as Extensive <add resp="editor">[as] </add>he pleases.</p>

<p>The Interest for the Two hundred &amp; fifty pound his other Bond <lb/><add resp="editor">[I']</add>ll find a way to pay myself, Out of the Arrears of his <note target="n4">Quit Rents</note> <lb/><add resp="editor">[ . . . ]</add> but get the Money out of my <abbr expan="collectors ">Collrs.</abbr> hands</p>

<p>I heartily wish Your firm health &amp; am </p>

<closer><seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1723 June 16-1724 April 23, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a nineteenth-century transcript of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia. </note><lb/>

<note>The county and colony have been added for clarity to the return address on this draft.</note><lb/>

<note>Carter's diary entry for August 24, 1723, noted that he had visited "mr wormeleys wth my Son" and that he  "came home that Night slept in the boat good part of the way the Awning down." It seems likely that this draft was intended for a letter to Wormeley.</note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] John Wormeley (1689-1727), a younger son of Ralph Wormeley (d. 1701) for whom Carter had been a trustee in John's youth. When his older brother, Ralph died in 1714, John inherited all of their father's considerable estate in Middlesex and York counties.</note><lb/>

<note id="n2">[2] Carter remembered his Latin well; the phrase "littera scripta manet" means "the written word endures."</note><lb/>

<note id="n3">[3] Catherine Culpeper (d. 1719) was the widow of the fifth Lord Fairfax (d. 1710). From her father, the 2nd Lord Culpeper, she had inherited about 1689 his five-sixths interest in the Northern Neck Proprietary in Virginia. Lord Fairfax had consulted Micajah Perry about the affairs of the Proprietary, and Perry had recommended Robert Carter to be the Virginia agent in 1702. He held the post until 1710 when Lady Fairfax transferred the agency to Edmund Jenings with Thomas Lee as the deputy agent. When she died in 1719, she bequeathed her Virginia property to her son Tom, but she made Wiliam Cage and Edward Filmer, trustees of the proprietary. Filmer soon died, and Cage, a kinsman of the 6th Lord Fairfax, became the sole trustee. From his grandmother, Margaret Lady Culpeper, the 6th Lord Fairfax inherited the other one-sixth of the Proprietary. Cage consulted Perry, and Robert Carter was again made agent in 1721, holding the post until his death ten years later. (For sources, see those listed at the end of the <xref to="/users/berkeley/#Northern Neck"> discussion of the Proprietary</xref> on the home page.)</note><lb/>

<note id="n4">[4] Quit rent was the term used for the payment due from the holder of land to the "lord of the manor," in this case, to the proprietors of the Northern Neck. Carter as the proprietor's agent, collected these payments. No services were required of the landholder as had been true in mediaeval times.</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised February 4, 2010.</hi></note>
</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>