<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C23k29a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, November 29, 1723</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 11 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C23k29a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, November 29, 1723</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1723-11-29</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="CT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1723-11-29"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C23k29a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, November 29, 1723</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant William Dawkins November 29, 1723, that he has learned that Robert Jones has lost his case tried in England. He informs the merchant that he wishes to be involved without his name being connected with it in another case that will be appealed from the judgment of the General Court in Virginia to England. The case was brought by a wealthy "Esqr. Hallow's," who lives near Liverpool against the heirs of Manley in Virginia. Carter recused himself from sitting on the case because he had bought an estate from Manley, and reports that Edmund Jenings's vote carried it before the council even though he is so old and infirm that he really does not know what he is voting on. </p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="WD">William Dawkins,</note> November 29, 1723</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1723-11-29">Novr 29th. 1723</date><lb/>
Mr Willm. Daqwkins<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p>I understand Mr <note n="RJ">Robert Jones</note> <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> <lb/>met with a defeat in his appeal Mr Sewell by his letter <lb/>informed me he was pretty sure the Court were of opinion <lb/>the will of <note target="n1">old Brereton</note> gave an estate <note target="n2">Tail</note> in his lands <lb/>but it seem's the Judges have <abbr expan="determined ">dermin'd </abbr> otherwise and Jones <lb/>is quite blow'n</p>
 
<p>I am now concerned more nearly in another <lb/>appeal one <note target="n3"><abbr expan="Esquire ">Esqr.</abbr> Hallow's</note> a <abbr expan="gentleman ">Gent:</abbr> of Lancaster not far <lb/>from <sic corr="Liverpool ">Leverpool</sic> <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> sued the  <del>[illegible]</del> <add place="supralinear">heirs</add> of one <note target="n4">Manley </note>for <lb/>a Seat of Land <add place="supralinear">in Westmorland county</add> and <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> had the good luck upon a 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<gap reason="damage"/><add resp="editor">[gre]</add>at nicety in the Law to get the Judgment of our <lb/>General Court in his favour.  The Court was divided <lb/><sic corr="until ">till</sic> it came to <note n="EJ"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Colo:</abbr> Jenings</note> who is so debilitated in his <lb/>understanding by Age and infirmities that in reality <lb/>he <sic corr="does ">doth</sic> not know what he says or does his Vote <sic corr="carried ">carry'd</sic> <lb/>it against these poor Orphan's he may have <abbr expan="happened ">happen'd </abbr> to <lb/>have hit right but sure I am it was absolutly guess work <lb/>in him I did not <sic corr="sit as a ">set a</sic> Judge in the Cause having <abbr expan="purchased ">purchas'd </abbr> <lb/>another Estate of this Manly to <sic corr="avoid ">avoy'd</sic> all <del>[illegible] </del> reflections <lb/>I have <abbr expan="promised ">promis'd </abbr> to the Orphan's to support them in the <lb/>Charge of this appeal if the Judgment of the Court here <lb/>be affirmed against  <del>thn</del> them  The Orphan's will be <abbr expan="turned ">turn'd </abbr> <lb/>naked into the world to look for a being and the Will of <lb/>their Mother under which this Hallows also claims in=<lb/>tirely Defeated in her <abbr expan="designed ">design'd </abbr> provision for them, I <lb/>intend not now to enter into the particulars of the case <lb/>your Lawyer will receive the best information from <lb/>the Case it self which will be sent you in a short time <lb/>all that I design at this time is that you may <add place="supralinear">be</add> early <lb/>in feeing some of the ablest counsel you are to know it <lb/><sic corr="has ">hath </sic> been whisper'd that Mr Hallows sent in an opinion <lb/>of <note target="n5"><sic corr="Sir ">Sr</sic> Robert Ramonds</note> which <abbr expan="seemed ">seem'd </abbr> to favour his side <lb/>of the question, I know this Opinion <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> been industri=<lb/>ously <abbr expan="talked ">talk'd </abbr> of whether this report <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> had any influ=<lb/>ence upon our Court I shall not pretend to say Hallows <lb/>is reported to be both eminent and rich and having the <lb/><sic corr="judgment ">Judgement</sic> here on his side makes the Struggle the more <lb/><sic corr="doubtful ">doubtfull</sic> You were some years ago Desirous of <sic corr="getting ">geting</sic> <lb/>business from hence for your Friend Mr Sewell commending <lb/>very much both his diligence and Skill gives me the en=<lb/>couragement to expect this will be no <sic corr="ungrateful ">ungratefull</sic> trouble 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
to you, the Solicitor general appears to be a very g<add resp="editor">[ood] </add> <lb/>man in the Law if to be had so <sic corr="does ">doth</sic> Waerg <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> but Mr Sew<add resp="editor">[ell] </add> <lb/>can no doubt better judge whose Talents are the best of fite<add resp="editor">[d]</add> <lb/>for the Court where our Appeals have their <sic corr="trials, ">tryals,</sic> I wo<add resp="editor">[uld]</add> <lb/>be as Strenuous as I could in this affair and yet without th<add resp="editor">[e]</add> <lb/>mention of my name in it I am <abbr expan="Sir">Sr. </abbr> </p>

<closer>Your very Humb: Servt&mdash;&mdash;<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>per Fowler<lb/>Copy per <note target="n6">Keiling </note></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1723 June 16-1724 April 23, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a nineteenth-century transcript of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] The "old Brereton" mentioned here may be Thomas Brereton, clerk of the Council in the seventeenth century. (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> pp. 45, 53.</bibl></cit>
)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Carter refers to the legal process of entail which is "to restrict (property) by limiting the inheritance to the owner's lineal descendants or to a particular class thereof "; or  "to convert (an estate) into a 'fee tail' (feudum talliatum); to settle (land, an estate, etc.) on a number of persons in succession, so that it cannot be bequeathed at pleasure by any one possessor." (Merriam-Webster [Dictionary] online at http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/entailment?show=0&t=1290188110, 11/19/2010; and  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title></bibl></cit>)</note><lb/>

<note id="n3">[3] John Hallowes (Hallows) (1615-1657) had come to Maryland as an indentured servant, but later moved to Westmoreland County where he acquired extensive tracts of land. Some of that land was purchased in 1733 by Thomas Lee from Samuel Hallowes of County Lancaster, England, who "as a great newphew of Major John Hallowes," had acquired title in an important legal case decided in 1722, probably the one to which Carter refers. This land became part of Stratford. Carter may have hoped to acquire a tract from Samuel Hallowes to add to Nomini (see fn4)  as John Hallowes had lived near that plantation of Carter's. John Randolph sailed to England in 1727 to become the colony's agent, and represented Hallowes in negotiations with Carter. ("Major John Hallowes. 1615-1657." <cit><bibl n="B38">Norris. <title>Westmoreland County, Virginia.</title></bibl></cit> pp. 99-103.)</note><lb/>

<note id="n4">[4] A William Manly (Manly) (b. 1686) of Westmoreland County was a descendant of John Hallowes (<hi rend="italics">q.v.</hi>), and inherited  considerable land in the county, David Eaton wites, "Manly also gathered in one body the large tract called 'Nomini Hall' and sold the same to the Hon. Robert Carter, March 11, 1712. W[estmoreland] D[eed] B[ook] 2, page 71." (<cit><bibl>"Notes." <title>William and Mary College Quarterly Historical Magazine,</title>15[3, Jan. 1907]:48</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl>David W. Eaton. <title>Historical Atlas of Westmoreland County Virginia.</title> [Richmond: Dietz Press, 1942], in an undated reprint. p. 46.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] Sir Robert Raymond (1673-1733), was Attorney General,1720-1724, and a member of Parliament. He became a judge in 1724, and would later be later Lord Chief Justice (1725-1733). He was regarded as one of thethe foremost lawyer of his day. (Entry for Robert Raymond, <hi rend="italics">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</hi> online at http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/23207, 11/19/2010.)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] Captain William Keiling commanded the <hi rend="italics">Betty. </hi> (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800 summarizing Adm. 68/194, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley  Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text revised November 19, 2010.</hi></note>



</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>