<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C23k29c">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, November 29, 1723</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 6 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C23k29c.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, November 29, 1723</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1723-11-29</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C23k29cT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1723-11-29"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C23k29c.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, November 29, 1723</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant <note n="MP2">Micajah Perry,</note> November 29, 1723, to send him the papers (not present) concerning the case he has brought before the General Court in Virginia over the proprietors' rights to certain items such as "fines and Felons goods." He asks Perry to get him the opinions of the best lawyers in England, especially those of the Attorney and Solicitor general if possible. He calls on Perry because the proprietors are very slow in responding to him although, in this cae, he thinks they should be very interested since there is money involved.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, November 29, 1723</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1723-11-29">Novr. 29. 1723</date><lb/>
Mr Micajh: Perry<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p>If I do not mistake I have already <lb/>acquainted you of the Case I had before the General <lb/>Court upon the exposition of some parts of the Pro=<lb/>prietors Grant  <del>[illegible] all and all ma[illegible]</del> <lb/>the words that the dispute rises upon are in the <lb/>enclosed paper for fear I should not have mentioned <lb/>them to you before, I have sent them to the Propri=<lb/>etor's already urging them to send me in the opinions <lb/>of some of the best Lawyers in England both the <lb/>Attorney General's and Solicitor's if to be got, have <lb/>told them I have <sic corr="employed">imploy'd</sic> some of the best Lawyers <lb/>here and the great consequence it will be to their 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
Estate and that I would get the <sic corr="trial">Tryal</sic> <sic corr="delayed">delay'd</sic> <add resp="editor">[until]</add> <lb/>April Court <add place="supralinear">which is accordingly done</add> that I might have these opinions be<add resp="editor">[fore]</add> <lb/>it comes on, but knowing how slow they are in th<add resp="editor">[eir]</add> <lb/>answers to me I repeat my request to you to get these <lb/>great mens Opinions sent into me <add place="supralinear">or at least some other able <sic corr="counsel's">Counsell's</sic></add> which will be <lb/>of great service to the Cause, and one would think <lb/>their own interest especialy My Lords to whom the <lb/>inheritance wll come is inducement enough to <del>quick<add place="supralinear">en</add></del><lb/>quicken them. There is something or another that hap<add place="supralinear">pens</add> <lb/>frequently particularly fines and Felons goods and <lb/>within this month something that is considerable which <lb/>makes me the more Solicitous that you will be in=<lb/>dustrious in this Affair wherein you will much <lb/>oblidge Sr </p>

<closer>Your Most Humb: Servant</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1723 June 16-1724 April 23, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a nineteenth-century transcript of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>