<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C24a29a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas Colmore, January 29 and February 15, 1724</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.9  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C24a29a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas Colmore, January 29 and February 15, 1724</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1724-01-29</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C24a29aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1724-01-29"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C24a29a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas Colmore, January 29 and February 15, 1724</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Thomas Colmore, January 29 and February 15, 1724, reporting the arrival of Captain Wills' ship, and complaining about the merchant's sales of his and the Burwell estate's tobacco. He also complains of Colmore's method of preparing the account current that he sent to Carter. Mr. Pratt has kept his tobacco to be sent on Wills' ship, and he adds that he is sending some more Burwell estate tobacco to Colmore in the hope that he will receive better sales this time. In a post script dated 1724 February 15, Carter lets Colmore know that the slaves' shoes the merchant has shipped were far too small for the sizes maked on them; "Your Shoomaker hath bin a Arrant Cheat." He orders 6 dozen pairs to be shipped as soon as possible.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">Thomas Colmore,</note> January 29 and February 15, 1724</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;per Fowler<lb/> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Copy per Keiling<lb/>
Mr. Thos. Colmore
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1724-01-29">Janr. 29th. 1723/4&mdash;</date><lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p><note target="n2">Captain Wills</note> Arrivd into York the 10th. of this month, We <lb/>were most of us in <sic corr="dispair">dispare</sic> of his coming time Enough to get away in <lb/>March The <note target="n3"><name type="ship">Burwell</name></note> got in three Weeks before him, I took freight there <lb/>for the last of my Tobo. not above ten days before Your Ship came, Some small <lb/>help I can now afford her, but not much,  Wills's Sloop is <del>[illegible]</del>up our <lb/><note target="n4">River,</note> put my Goods on Shoar as they went by, is to call in her way <lb/>down for Some Tobo., You must allow me to tell You that neither <lb/>my own nor <note n="NB">Mr. Burwell's</note> sales are pleasing to me, They come out con=<lb/>=siderably less than the Same Tobo. other Men had the Sale of. twelve hhds. <lb/>of my Tobo. You give me no Accot. of, although Your former Letters pro=<lb/>=mise me <sic corr="complete">compleat</sic> Accots. I cant <sic corr="guess">ghess</sic> at Your meaning in it. I hope <lb/>the Tobo. is not lost, Your Accots. are made up in a different manner to <lb/>Other Mens, You charge Brokerage as a Standing Article in all <lb/>my Accots. which I never saw before unless where the Tobo. was Sold to <lb/>Export, certainly Mr. Levitt who was the buyer of most of my Tobo. and <lb/>Mr. Mayne are persons of higher <sic corr="note,">Noat,</sic> than to want Brokers to find <lb/>them out, You have also a Charge for postage of Lettrs. in Every Accot. <lb/>of Sales, an Article Intirely new to me, I always meet with the Charge <lb/>of Postage in my Accot. Currt. &amp; there I desire to find it &amp; not in my <lb/>Sales, I hope You will think it proper to give me Credit for these <lb/>Wrong charges, and that in some of the Ships that are to come, I shall <lb/>receive an Accot. of my twelve hhds.</p>

<p>Mr. Pratt hath bin so firme to Your Interest to keep his <lb/>Tobo. for Yor. Ship, and therein run a very great hazzard, I am told tht. <lb/>Wills is Secure of his Loading &amp; 'tis not doubted but will get away <lb/>in good time, Some of Mr. Burwells Tobo. You will have in him <lb/>being willing to make another Tryal in hopes You will be able <lb/>to sell our Tobo. for as much as other Men do, The <name type="ship">Bailey</name> got in <lb/>but two days before Your Ship, I am,</p>

<closer> Sir Yor. most humble Servt. 

<seg type="postscript">Febr. 15. 1723/4<lb/><lb/>I have <sic corr="overhauled">overhauld</sic> Yor. Shoes &amp; find none of them large Sizes that I writ <lb/>for Your <sic corr="shoemaker">Shoomaker</sic> hath bin a Arrant Cheat He hath markd sizes <lb/>Upon the Bottoms of them much beyond their bigness, I shall be in a mighty <lb/>Streight to <sic corr="fit">fitt</sic> my large People, I pray You will take the first opportunity <lb/>to send me in Six <abbr expan="dozen">doz</abbr> of the best Strong plain <note target="n5">Carmens </note><sic corr="shoes">Shoos</sic> that <lb/>You can buy for Money, well nailed, one half of <abbr expan="them">thm.</abbr> to be of the large 16s. <lb/>the other of the 14s.  I hope You may be able to get these <sic corr="shoes">Shoos</sic> to me sometime <lb/>in the Summer or at least by Fall,<lb/><lb/></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Thomas Colmore was a London merchant. (<cit><bibl>A 1740 London directory,<title> A Compleat Guide . . . ,</title> consulted by Francis L. Berkeley, Jr., in London, listed Colmore as a resident of Pudding Lane, Eastcheap.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Captain Peter Wills commanded the  <hi rend="italics">Booth</hi> in 1723 and the <hi rend="italics">Amity</hi> in 1727. (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small  Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] This vessel was commanded by Captain Constantine Cant and may have been owned by William Dawkins and Micajah Perry as Carter reported her December 1723 arrival to each of them. (<cit><bibl>Adm. 68/194-195, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] The Rappahannock.</note>

<note id="n5">[5] A carman was a worker with carts, and Carter seems to mean here a worker who wears good, stout shoes for his job.</note>



</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>