<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;

<!NOTATION html SYSTEM "HTML">
<!ENTITY Ext6 SYSTEM "http://www.fraudaid.com\/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms\/bill_of_exchange.htm" NDATA html>

 ]>

<TEI.2 id="C24c25a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, March 25, 1724</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 14 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C24c25a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002, 2011</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, March 25, 1724</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>4 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1724-03-25</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C24c25aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>4 p.</extent>
<date value="1724-03-25"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C24c25a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, March 25, 1724</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant William Dawkins, March 25, 1724, concerning a shipment of tobacco on board the <hi rend="italics">Bailey,</hi> some of which he has committed to Micajah Perry and some to Thomas Evans. He devotes considerable space to his displeasure with the <hi rend="italics">Bailey's</hi> captain, Adam Graves, and his slights to Carter who had done some particular favors to ensure the ship's large cargo. He reports that Captain Holliday has arrived bringing Carter's son Charles who is in good health, and adds, "I return you a great deal of thanks for your care and kindness both to him and his brother Since they have been with you." While neither had achieved scholatically quite what Carter has hoped, he believes they have good morals and will  succeed in life. In his own hand he adds to the draft several paragraphs concerning bills of exchange and a promise to comment on his sons' expenses while in England.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="WD">William Dawkins,</note> March 25, 1724</head>

<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
Mr Wm. Dawkins&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;per the Bailey&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1724-03-25">March the 25th: 1723/4</date><lb/>

</dateline>

</opener>

<p>I have 29 hhds: on Board the <name type="ship">Bayley</name> for wch: <lb/>I have no Bill of Lading 16 of them under two Marks are to <lb/>come to you 11 of them all <sic corr="stemmed ">Stem'd</sic> <del>and Luggs</del> of my own Crop <lb/><sic corr="straight ">Strait </sic>laid the three <sic corr="numbered ">Numbred</sic> wth Lettrs: Luggs which I will not com<lb/>mend the other two <sic corr="straight ">Straitt</sic> laid and very good Tobbo: It was prized <lb/>at my own house and I saw it often 3 of my Number goes to <lb/><note n="MP2">Mr. Perry</note> the other 10 to <note n="TE">Mr. Evans,</note> The way I took to get so <lb/>much for your Ship was thus <note n="AG"><abbr expan="Captain ">Capt.</abbr>Graves</note> being once in <lb/>a great deal of fear of getting his load I <sic corr="persuaded ">perswaded</sic> <note target="n1">Keel<lb/>ing</note> to Spare me 10 hhds of what I had promised 10 hhds more <lb/>was to be taken in by the <name type="ship">Booths</name> Sloop, but she got her load up <lb/>the River and left them.  <note target="n2"><abbr expan="Captain ">Capt</abbr>
 Wills</note> sent me word <sic corr="immediately ">imediately</sic> <lb/>he would send for them let the damage be what it would <lb/>to him If I <sic corr="pressed ">prest</sic> it <sic corr="supposing ">suposing</sic> it would be <del>no dis</del><add place="supralinear">a </add>kindness to <lb/><abbr expan="Captain ">Capt.</abbr> Graves I <sic corr="easily ">easiely</sic> Excused Wills, This Tobo: I sent on <lb/>Board in my own Craft two hhds. more being the last <sic corr="stemmed ">Stem'd</sic> <lb/>I had left I sent to his side but he was so crowded he turned <lb/>them ashore again, The report I had of his proceedings was <lb/>that he would clear out this Day <del>but he</del> which made m<gap reason="damage"/><add resp="editor">[e]</add> 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
think I should have time Enough to write my Lettrs: but <lb/>he <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> been more Expeditious and broke ground Yesterday <lb/>falling down almost as low as my house, Indeed the hurry <lb/>he has been in and the confusion by Tobo. pressing upon <lb/>him in such an unexpected manner the Slight he put on <lb/>me in turning my two hhds ashore I cannot much fault <lb/>him for but his taking his leave of me in Such an abrupt <lb/>manner without giving me Bills of Lading or paying <lb/>me for the <abbr expan="tobacco ">Tobbo:</abbr> I have carried on board of him <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> <lb/>been a little Extraordinary, I suppose he will be saying <lb/>a great deal in justification of himself and therefore <lb/>tis necessary to tell you the Story; last night after nine <sic corr="o'">a</sic> <lb/>Clock he comes <sic corr="on ">a</sic> Shore in much hurry desiring me to <lb/>spare him a <sic corr="barrel ">Barrell</sic> of pitch which  I refused but fully <lb/>designed to let him have one in the morning, he then <lb/><sic corr="pressed ">press'd</sic> me to do my business, I told him I would <sic corr="forgo ">foregoe</sic> <lb/><sic corr="having ">haveing</sic> my Bills of Lading rather then begin such a <lb/>work at that time of night, he was also in a mighty way <lb/>with my Skipper who brought him 75 hhds: on Board <lb/>threatning he would <note target="n3">drub</note> him if he fell in his way <lb/><sic corr="charging ">chargeing</sic> him with taking in <sic corr="several ">Severall</sic> mens <abbr expan="tobacco ">Tobbo</abbr> that <lb/>he had no orders for and leaving out others that he had <lb/>I must own he is an Illiterate fellow but he is as well <lb/>acquainted with the rivers as a man can well be <add resp="editor">[he] </add><sic corr="has ">hath </sic> <lb/>been in my Employ for this 25 Years together almost <lb/>without interruption And in Excuse of himself <del>[illegible]</del> <add place="supralinear"><hi rend="italics">tells</hi></add> me <lb/>that <abbr expan="Captain ">Capt</abbr> Graves Notes were so dark and confused he <lb/>did not know what to do, The rest of the Story I shall <lb/>leave to the other side Graves <sic corr="staid ">stayes</sic> with <add place="supralinear"><hi rend="italics">me</hi></add> <sic corr="until ">till</sic> after a <lb/>Eleven of the clock and then takes his departure I sup<lb/>pose for this <sic corr="voyage ">Voaige</sic></p>

<p>I agreed with <abbr expan="Captain ">Capt</abbr> Graves for bringing <lb/>his <abbr expan="tobacco ">Tobbo:</abbr> on board with my Sloop and hands to <add place="supralinear">be</add> paid at <lb/>the rate of 5 Shillings: Sterling per hhds for the 29 hhds <lb/>went from my house he owes me at least 3 Shillings <lb/>per hhds&mdash; I have spared him <sic corr="tar ">Tarr</sic> and pitch at <sic corr="several ">Severall</sic> 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
times <del>the</del> which he was to return me in kind the Quan<lb/>tity I cant well tell his Carpenter knows I cant charge <lb/>him less for the pitch <del>less</del> then 22:<abbr expan=" shillings ">s</abbr>: and for the <sic corr="tar ">Tarr</sic> <lb/>14:<abbr expan=" shillings ">s</abbr>: per <sic corr="barrel ">Barrell</sic></p>

<p>I Expect there will be another contention <lb/>about the <sic corr="terms ">termes</sic> of his freight not long after his first <lb/>coming in there was a strong report brought down the <lb/>river that a Ship which brought in hither Convicts had <lb/>set up for <sic corr="stemmed tobacco ">stemed Tobbo:</sic> and <sic corr="offered ">offerd</sic> to take Seven pound <lb/>I then told him there was necessity for it to declare for 8 <lb/>pound and he was then of the same Opinion. I told him <lb/>I would give no more the <sic corr="terms ">termes</sic> I gave to Keeling and to <lb/><note n="JH2"><abbr expan="Captain ">Capt</abbr> <sic corr="Hyde's ">Hides</sic></note> Ship and so I Expect, <sic corr="although ">Altho</sic> I hear lately he <lb/><sic corr="has ">hath </sic> Signed some of his bills of Lading how many I <lb/>cant say at 8&pound;:10<abbr expan=" shillings ">s</abbr>:</p>

<p>I am now to Acquaint you of the safe arriv<lb/>val of <note target="n4">Holloday</note> and my Son <note n="CC1">Charles</note> being at home in good <lb/>health, and I return you a great deal of thanks for your care <lb/>and kindness both to him and his brother Since they have <lb/>been with you <sic corr="although ">altho</sic> they are not under such <abbr expan="improvements ">Improve:<add place="supralinear">mnts</add></abbr> <lb/>as I Expect, however they promise to be well <sic corr="moraled ">morald</sic> <lb/>youths God sparing me Life am not in doubt they will <lb/>come to make a good figure in the world and be able to get <lb/>their bread</p>

<p>I have had the oportunity to discourse one <lb/>that lives in the house with <note target="n5">Skreen</note> about your <note target="n6">bill of <abbr expan="exchange ">Excha</abbr></note><lb/>he tells me Skreen absolutely denies the drawing of it <lb/><sic corr="although ">altho</sic> by comparing the hands the<add resp="editor">[y]</add> seem to be as like as two <abbr expan="peas ">Ps:</abbr> <lb/>If I can serve you in this matter I will</p>

<p>You are to pay <abbr expan="Esquire ">Esqr:</abbr> Heath ten pounds part <lb/>of Haynes debt I have lately got the money.</p>

<p><hi rend="italics"><sic corr="It is ">Tis</sic> a Vast charge You have put me to for my Sons <lb/>Expences this last Year and yet their furniture is not Extraordinary <lb/>I shall Enter into the particular Examination of it when I have time <lb/>&amp; give You my thoughts upon it</hi></p>

<p><hi rend="italics">I am to Advise You of a Bill I have drawn on You for four <lb/>pound ten <abbr expan="shillings ">Shills</abbr> to Henry Thompson.</hi></p>

<pb n="4"/><lb/><lb/>
<p><hi rend="italics">Herein I send You a bill of <abbr expan="exchange ">Exche.</abbr> of <abbr expan="John ">Jno.</abbr> Hudnals on Yor.self <lb/>for &pound;20.6"11 which desire Credit for&mdash;</hi></p>




</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">

<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note>Carter edited the clerk's draft of this letter and added the final three paragraphs in his own hand as is noted by the use of italics.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Captain William Keiling commanded the <hi rend="italics">Betty.
</hi> (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley  Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Captain Peter Wills commanded the  <hi rend="italics">Booth</hi> in 1723-1724, and the <hi rend="italics">Amity</hi> in 1727. He is mentioned in Carter's diary for June 1723.  (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small  Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Drub, according to the <title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title> means "to beat with a stick or the like, to cudgel, flog; in early use, spec. to bastinado; to thrash, thump, belabour; also, to beat in a fight. . . ."</note><lb/>

<note id="n4">[4] William Holladay commanded a ship named the <hi rend="italics">Princess Carolina.</hi> (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small  Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] William Skreen of Hanover Parish, Richmond County, and two others had taken a patent for 1020 acres in what was then Essex County August 17, 1720. A patent held by William Skrien (Skreen, Skrine) is referred to in a number of  patents taken out in St. George's Parish, Spotsylvania County, in the 1720s. (<cit><bibl>Nell M. Nugent. <title>Cavaliers and Pioneers: Abstract of Virginia Land Patents and Grants.</title> [Richmond: Virginia State Library, 1979] 3(1695-1732):198, 222, 308, 317, 411.</bibl></cit>
)</note><lb/>

<note id="n6"> [6] A bill of exchange is a kind of check or promissory note without interest.  It is used primarily in international trade, and is a written order by one person to pay another a specific sum on a specific date sometime in the future.  If the bill of exchange is drawn on a bank, it is called a bank draft.  If it is drawn on another party, it is called a trade draft.  Sometimes a bill of exchange will simply be called a draft, but whereas a draft is always  negotiable (transferable by endorsement), this is not necessarily true of a bill of exchange. (<cit><bibl><xref to="Ext6">"Dictionary of  Financial Scam Terms" at </xref> http://www.fraudaid.com/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms/bill_of_exchange.htm. 8/22/2005</bibl></cit>)</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2002, was revised March 4,  2011, to add footnotes, and to strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>



</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>