<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C24d06a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Chelton, [April 6, 1724]</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.9  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C24d06a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002, 2011</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Chelton, [April 6, 1724]</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1724-04-06</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C24d06aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 p.</extent>
<date value="1724-04-06"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C24d06a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Chelton, [April 6, 1724]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to John Chelton (Chilton), [April 6, 1724], to explain that he cannot issue warrants for surveys  to be made for land on Cub Run. Carter understands that, although Chelton and others had had surveys for land in the  area made in 1714, and had presented them to Thomas Lee, then the proprietors' agent, they and Lee had differed  about the details and "deeds" were not issued. He tells Chelton that he cannot become involved with the dispute with Lee. He would do a disservice to others who have had patents in the area since, and to the proprietors who have had no  rents, were he to issue patents for these lands. He tells Chelton that since he became the agent, he has issued orders to  the surveyors to look for the best lands there for his children, and that John Savage is preparing the survey since John  Coppege's death. He has refused George Mason's application for lands in the area, and will refuse all others until "I am  served." He promises to assist Chelton once his own surveys are completed, and sends Chelton three warrants (not  present), reminding Chelton of the fees due for them.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">John Chelton,</note> [April 6, 1724]</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1724-04-06"></date><lb/>
Mr. Jno. Chelton&mdash;&mdash;<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p>Yours of the 31st of March came to me Yesterday <lb/>at Church which I shall now answer, It seems you were at <lb/><lb/>some charge in the Year 1714 for the laying out some land <lb/>on the <note target="n2"><sic corr="Cub ">Cubb</sic> run</note> a branch of the <note target="n3">Bull <sic corr="Run ">runn</sic></note> in Stafford <lb/>County and that upon presenting these Surveys to the <lb/><xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/#Northern Neck"> proprietors Office</xref> <note target="n"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Collon:</abbr> Lee</note> the then Officer and You <lb/>differed about the Composition and that he would not <lb/>pass your Deeds, In the first place you are to know <lb/>that I do not take my self at all concerned to Vindicate <lb/><abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo:</abbr> Lee in that Office or to make good what he did <lb/>not carry on to perfection, but I must suppose in this&mdash; <lb/>matter that he demanded of you no more <sic corr="than ">then</sic> the Settled <lb/>Composition and upon your <sic corr="refusal ">refusall</sic> of payment he <lb/>denied passing your Deeds as I should have done had <lb/>I been in his place, whether he did you injustice or <lb/>no You <del>[illegible]</del> <add place="supralinear"><hi rend="italics">are</hi></add> to dis pute  it with him, but I am sure if I <lb/>should comply with your desire and make you a<lb/>title by Deeds upon them Surveys to take place from 1714 <lb/>I should do a great <sic corr="piece ">peice</sic> of injustice both to the proprietors <lb/>and to all persons that <sic corr="have ">hath</sic> taken out warrants Since <lb/>for any of those Lands, to the first that they have had <lb/>no <note target="n5"><add place="supralinear"><sic corr="Quit"><hi rend="italics">Quitt</hi></sic></add> rent</note> nor Composition all this time, and other ad<lb/>venturers to be at the charge of warrants &amp;Ca: and yet <lb/>to pass Deeds of a Prior Date to destroy all they have bee<gap reason="damage"/><add resp="editor">[n]</add> <lb/>doing, Certainly upon a full Consideration you wil<gap reason="damage"/><add resp="editor">[l be]</add> <lb/>of Opinion I have neither reason nor power to <gap reason="damage"/><add resp="editor">[oblige]</add> <lb/>you</p>

<p>But I shall now tell yo<gap reason="damage"/>/<add resp="editor">[u a] </add>

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
Story in this matter upon my first having this Office <lb/>I was <sic corr="desirous ">desireous</sic> to Inform myself the best I could <del>to learn</del> <lb/>where I could find some large Quantities of good Land <lb/>to take up for my Children and Grand Children and soon <lb/>became Acquainted that you <abbr expan="Captain ">Capt.</abbr> Morriss Jones <abbr expan="Captain ">Capt</abbr> <lb/><note target="n6">Charles Lee</note> and others had Surveyed some quantities of <lb/>Land upon the Branches of this Bull <sic corr="Run ">runn</sic> <del>upon w</del> among <lb/>which this Cubb <sic corr="Run ">runn</sic> was Mentioned and that by your <lb/>Neglects none of You got Deeds every body conclu<lb/>ding that you totally declined any further meddling <lb/>hereupon I directed both <note n="TH">Hooper</note> and <note target="n7">Coppedge</note> to take&mdash; a <lb/>view of these Lands Accordingly Coppedge did <sic corr="giving ">giveing</sic> <lb/>me a very good Accot. of them Encourageing me to hope <lb/>he could take up for me at least Ten Thousand Acres of <lb/>very good land Accordingly I made an Entry in one of <lb/>my Sons names and sent up a warrant for the Surveying <lb/>it which was in the possesion of Coppedge at his Death <lb/>and in the last Letter he <sic corr="wrote ">writ</sic> to me he promises me <lb/>that this should be the first work he should do and I <lb/>have Since given <note target="n8">Mr Savage</note> the present Surveyor <lb/>Directions to lay <sic corr="off">of</sic> the best of these lands for me&mdash; <lb/><note target="n9"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colln:</abbr> Mason</note> <sic corr="wrote">writ</sic> to me for a warrant to take up&mdash; <lb/>Some lands on this <sic corr="Cub Run">Cubb runn</sic> which I denied to <lb/>send him for the <sic corr="aforesaid ">Afforesaid</sic> reason and must be <lb/>so plain to tell Every body that I will Issue no&mdash; <lb/>warrants for any Lands in those places <add place="supralinear"><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="italics"><sic corr="until ">till</sic> I am served</hi></hi></add>, and I hope <lb/>no body will blame me for regarding my own&mdash; <lb/>Children in the first place, <del>Y</del> if after my Surveys are <lb/>are <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> made You can find any <sic corr="berth ">birth</sic> I shall be ready to <sic corr="oblige ">Oblidge</sic> <lb/>you Here with I send you the three warrants you desire&mdash; <lb/><gap reason="damage"/><add resp="editor">[I now]</add> look upon you to be my pay master for the fees now Due 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
which <add place="supralinear"><hi rend="italics">is</hi></add> 175 pound of <abbr expan="tobacco ">Tobbo:</abbr> from Each, I never Issue these <lb/>warrants but I take caution for these fees and I desire you would <lb/>do so before you let them have their warrants for it is&mdash; <lb/>upon your Accot: I send them I am&mdash;</p>

<closer>Your humble Servt: </closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1723 June 16-1724 April 23, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a 19th-century copy of the letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.
</note>

<note>The name of Carter's home, "Corotoman," the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note>

<note>This undated draft appears in the letter book following two other undated drafts whose internal evidence has led to the date of April 5, 1724, being assigned. In addition, this letter is followed by one dated April 7,  1724.</note>

<note>Carter has reviewed the clerk's draft of this letter and made a few corrections which are indicated by the use of italics.</note><lb/><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] John Chelton [Chilton] (d. 1726),  lived in Westmoreland County where his name is on the lists of justices of that county from 1712 to 1721. (<cit><bibl>David W. Eaton. <title>Historical Atlas of Westmoreland County Virginia.</title> [Richmond: Dietz Press, 1942], in an undated reprint. pp. 52, 67;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B38">Norris. <title>Westmoreland County, Virginia.</title> pp. 675-76.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Cub Run lies in today's Loudoun and Fairfax counties, rising in the southern portion of the Dulles Airport reservation, and running more or less south, emptying into Bull Run. It was the original boundary between the two counties. (<cit><bibl>Alexandria Drafting Company. <title>Regional Northern Virginia.</title> [Alexandria, VA: Alexandria Drafting Company, 2002], pp. 16, 23, 30,151;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> Map of Old Prince William" before p. 351.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Bull Run is a major tributary of the Occoquan River, forming the foundary between today's Prince William and Fairfax counties, and then between Prince  William and Loudoun counties. (See the sources for footnote 2.)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Thomas Lee (1690-1750) was the son of Richard Lee II, and nephew of Edmund Jenings; he would build "Stratford," and succeed Carter on the Council. (<cit><bibl>Burton J. Hendrick. <title>The Lees of Virginia: Biography of a Family.</title> [Boston: Little Brown, 1935]. pp. 48, 51, etc.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] Quit rent was the term used for "a (usually small) rent paid by a freeholder . . .  in lieu of services which might otherwise be required; a nominal rent paid (esp. in former British colonial territories to the Crown) as an acknowledgement of tenure," in this case, to the proprietors of the Northern Neck. Carter as the proprietor's agent, collected these payments. (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online </title></bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] <xref to="http://www.thesocietyoftheleesofva.org/index.php?c=4&kat=Lee+Family+Homes">Charles Lee</xref> (1684-1741) of Cobbs Hall, Northumberland County. He was sheriff of that county in 1725 and 1726. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]: 86, 100. </bibl></cit> )  
</note>

<note id="n7"> [7] John Coppedge  (d. <hi rend="italics">ante</hi> 1724) appears as surveyor of Northumberland County in 1714, but was not listed in 1726 there when the name appears as the surveyor of Lancaster County.  (<cit><bibl>Louis des Cognets, Jr., <title>English Duplicates of Lost Virginia Records.</title> [Baltimore: Genealogical Publishing Co., Inc. 1981], pp.  27, 36;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>,  3[1705- 1721]; 223. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n8">[8] John Savage was a surveyor, later (1734) to be employed by Lord Fairfax while attempting to establish the boundaries of the proprietary. (<bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 619.</bibl>)</note>

<note id="n9">[9] George Mason III (c. 1690-1735), justice, sheriff, burgess, and
county lieutenant of Stafford County, father of the constitutional theorist. (<cit><bibl n="B24">Copeland and MacMaster, <title>The Five George Masons.</title> pp. 50-86</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl>George Harrison Sanford King, <title>The Register of Overwharton Parish Stafford County Virginia 1723-1758 And Sundry Historical and Genealogical Notes</title>. [Fredericksburg, VA: privately printed, 1961.]</bibl></cit>)</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2002, was revised August 16,  2011, to add footnotes, and to strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>





</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>