<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C24d13d">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Savage, April 13, 1724</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 13 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C24d13d.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002, 2011</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Savage, April 13, 1724</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1724-04-13</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C24d13dT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1724-04-13"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C24d13d.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Savage, April 13, 1724</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to John Savage, April 13, 1724, to repeat and emphasize the instructions for surveys Savage is to make for Carter on the colony's frontier. He reminds Savage that Thomas Barber is to assist with the work, and that Carter is sending to Savage by Barber some deeds for lands in the area of Bull Run. Some surveys were made in the area ten years earlier, but Savage is to ignore them.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">John Savage,</note> April 13, 1724</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1724-04-13">Aprill the 1<hi rend="underline">3th. 17234</hi></date><lb/>
Mr: Jno. Savage&mdash;&mdash;<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p>I have already <sic corr="written ">writ</sic> you word I Should Employ <lb/><note target="n2">Mr. Barber</note> to assist you in my Surveys, this comes with him <lb/>I have given him an Accot: of the places acording to <note target="n3"><abbr expan="Captain ">Capt</abbr> Russells</note> <lb/>Information, that is the two places upon the <note target="n4">broad <sic corr="run ">runn</sic></note> the Lands <lb/>upon the <note target="n5">Bull <sic corr="run ">runn</sic></note> and its branches up towards the <note target="n6">Sugar Land <lb/><sic corr="run ">runn</sic></note> and the Lands upon the <note target="n7">Goose Creek</note> from the fork there <lb/>of and outwards, Resolve if possible to have my Surveys <lb/>made this Spring and next fall, I Expect he will <sic corr="make ">mak</sic> two <lb/>three or may be <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic </hi>]</add> four Surveys before he comes Down, I think <lb/><sic corr="it will ">twill</sic> be the best way to Send him upon the <sic corr="broad ">broard</sic> <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic </hi>]</add><sic corr="run ">runn</sic> and <lb/>I Should be very Glad if you will <sic corr="go ">goe</sic> upon the branches of <lb/>the bull <sic corr="run ">runn</sic> and likewise upon the head of Goose Creek <lb/>this Creek it seems forks into two branches <note n="GT"><abbr expan="Captain ">Capt.</abbr> <sic corr="Turberville ">Turbervill</sic></note> <lb/>would have had a warrant to Survey the fork of that <lb/>Creek but I resolve to give no warrant there about <sic corr="until ">till</sic> I am <lb/>Served, My Last Letter to you was by <note n="GE"><abbr expan="Captain ">Capt</abbr> Eskridge</note><lb/> who undertook to Send it to <note n="NS">Major Smiths</note> from whom he <lb/>said you would be Sure of it, I now write to <sic corr="both ">bothe</sic> Russells <lb/>who you know have promised me to be your Guides I also <lb/>write to the <note target="n8"><sic corr="Germans ">Jermans</sic></note> to be your Chain carriers upon whom <lb/>I hope I may Depend, If you think proper to make use <lb/>of Mr. Barber in any of the Surveys upon the warrants&mdash; <lb/>Directed to you he will be Contented to take half the pay <lb/>and I am Sure there will be work Enough for you both <lb/>during my time, people wait <sic corr="until ">till</sic> my warrants <add place="supralinear">&amp;Ca. According to my Directions</add> are laid <lb/><sic corr="off ">of</sic> and then there are Abundance that Offer to take up <lb/>Lands so that I think in respect to your own Interest a<add resp="editor">[s]</add><lb/>well as mine You ought to be Glad of the Assistanc<add resp="editor">[e of]</add> <lb/>Mr. Barber and to give him all the Encourage<add resp="editor">[ment]</add> <lb/>that possibly you can&mdash;</p> 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<p>The Division of the Great Tract into two plats and Surveys <lb/>I hope you will finish and Send me in a Short time, There is <lb/>my warrant for <sic corr="enlarging ">Enlargeing</sic> my Tract called the <note target="n9">Red Oak Land</note> <lb/>you may do at your leisure Sometime in the Summer I <lb/>hope you may find a time for it</p>

<p>Mr. <note n="JC2">James Carter</note> tells me that <note target="n10">Mr. Scott</note> the <lb/>Minister wants his <sic corr="Patent ">Pattent</sic> for the waste Land about <lb/>200 Acres <sic corr="joining ">Jonning</sic> to a Thousand Acres he bought of <abbr expan="John ">Jno. </abbr><lb/>Waugh upon <note target="n11"><sic corr="Run ">Woolf Runn </sic> </note> that it was Surveyed by <note n="TH">Hooper</note> <lb/>and Appears in the <sic corr="plat, ">platt</sic>, now I know nothing of all this <lb/><note n="TC1">Mr. Carter</note> tells me of <sic corr="several ">Severall</sic> other persons want their <lb/><sic corr="patents, ">pattents,</sic> Crosbys Deed is gone and I have never a Survey now <lb/>before me that a Deed <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> not Issued upon So that I must Send <lb/>all these people to you for Satisfaction, As for your Direct<lb/>ions about my own Surveys I was so full and perticular <lb/>to you when you was here that I dont know how to say more <lb/>only to desire you to redouble your <sic corr="diligence ">Dilligence</sic> and to Treat <lb/>Mr. Barber with all kindness and Civility</p>

<p>Mr. Barber <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> <sic corr="copies ">copys</sic> of <sic corr="several ">Severall</sic> Deeds that <sic corr="lie ">lye</sic> <lb/>upon the bull <sic corr="run ">runn</sic> which will be proper to be had by him <lb/>that goes there, Mr. <note target="n12">Jns: Shelton</note> of Westmoreland made some <lb/>Surveys about Ten <sic corr="years ago, ">Year agoe,</sic> Mr. Heath Mr. Morriss Jones <lb/>also made Surveys and some others upon the bull <sic corr="run ">runn</sic> <lb/>and the branches of it but took out no Deeds, these Surveys <lb/>I would have you take no notice of and if Sam Russ Lands <lb/>or <abbr expan="Captain ">Capt</abbr> Eskridges <sic corr="lies ">lyes</sic> in your may you may surround them <lb/>if you find it proper <sic corr="it is ">tis</sic> but <sic corr="making ">makeing</sic> an Exception in the <lb/>Deed, Here I have aprehension there may be taken up a <lb/>large quantity of very good Land </p>




</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1723 June 16-1724 April 23, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] John Savage was a surveyor, later (1734) to be employed by Lord Fairfax while attempting to establish the boundaries of the proprietary. (<bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 619.</bibl>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Thomas Barber of Richmond County was a surveyor, and would be appointed a justice of that county in 1730, tobacco inspector in 1734, and sheriff in 1736. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]: 215, 342, and 369.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] William Russell (1680?-1741) was a well-known ranger and explorer who eventually settled in Prince William County (later Fauquier). Fairfax Harrison thinks he may have been one of the rangers who accompanied Spotswood's Knights of the Golden Horseshoe. (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison,  <title>Landmarks of Old Prince William.</title> p. 204.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Broad Run extends southwest from Lake Manassas in Prince William County and joins Kettle Run just west of present-day Lake Jackson of the Occoquan River, south of the town of Manassas. (<cit><bibl>ADC. <title>Regional Northern Virginia.</title> [Alexandria, VA: Alexandria Drafting Company, 2002.] pp. 77, 84, 85, 89.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] Bull Run is a major tributary of the Occoquan River, forming the boundary between today's Prince William and Fairfax counties, and then between Prince  William and Loudoun counties. <cit><bibl>ADC. <title>Regional Northern Virginia.</title> <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi></bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] Sugarland Run flows north into the Potomac River in modern Loudoun County north of the town of Herndon. (<cit><bibl>ADC. <title>Regional Northern Virginia.</title> <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi></bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n7">[7] Goose Creek flows into the Potomac River just east of Leesburg in modern Loudoun County. (<cit><bibl>ADC. <title>Regional Northern Virginia.</title> <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi></bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n8">[8] Governor Alexander Spotswood had encouraged immigration of Germans into Virginia in 1714, and they settled "in what was then Stafford Co. . . .. later Prince William and now Fauquier."  The men worked in Spotswood's iron mines, but around 1718 took grants in the proprietary in what was then Stafford County. (See "Germantown" in <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title></bibl></cit> pp. 207-221. and <cit><bibl>Elizabeth Chapman Denny Vann and Margaret Collins Denny Dixon. <title>Virginia's First German Colony. </title> Richmond: Privately printed, 1961.</bibl></cit> p. 33.) </note>

<note id="n9">[9] Red Oak Quarter was in Prince William County; in the <xref to="/users/berkeley/public/C33inven.xml">1733 inventory,</xref>  John Wilcox was overseer, and there were fourteen slaves, fifty-one hogs, forty-one cattle, and one horse. (<cit><bibl n="A26">Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>.)</note>

<note id="n10">[10] Alexander Scott (d. 1738), had received an M. A. degree from the University of Glasgow before coming to Virginia. He was the minister of Overwharton Parish, Stafford County, and a considerable land speculator. There are numerous references to him in Fairfax Harrison's  <title>Landmarks of Old Prince William.</title> (<cit><bibl n="B24">Copeland and MacMaster. <title>The Five George Masons. . . .</title>p. 78;</bibl></cit> <cit><bibl>John K. Nelson. <title>A Blessed Company: Parishes, Parsons, and Parishoners in Anglican Virginia, 1690-1776.</title> [Chapel Hill and London: University of North Carolina Press, 2001]. p. 172-3, 318, 375, 428;</bibl></cit>  and <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> pp. 146, 158, 200, 257, 284-85, 337, 665.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n11">[11] Wolf Run lies in present-day Fairfax County where it empties into the Occoquan Reservoir. in Fountainhead Regional Park. It does not appear: on the Fry -Jefferson map. (<cit><bibl>Alexandria Drafting Company. <title>Regional Northern Virginia.</title>[Alexandria, VA: Alexandria Drafting Company, 2002.] pp. 32, 37-38. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n12">[12] The reference to "Jns. Shelton" may be to John Chilton (Chelton) (d. 1744), who was a "son of Mark and Sarah (Keys) Chilton, who described himself as a planter of Prince William County when on 1733 July 17-18 he sold to Richard Blackburn 764 acres. . . ." He apparently lived in Westmoreland County earlier because his name is on the lists of justices of that county from 1712 to 1721. (<cit><bibl>Jeff Carter. "<xref to="http://reocities.com/heartland/acres/2234/chilton/biography/chb012.html">John Chilton.</xref>" </bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="B38">Norris. <title>Westmoreland County, Virginia.</title> pp. 675-76.</bibl></cit>)</note>


<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2002, was revised August 22,  2011, to add footnotes, and to strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>



</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>