<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C24g09a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to William Cage, Esqr., July 9, 1724</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 11 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C24.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Cage, Esqr., July 9, 1724</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Fairfax Papers, BR 227, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1724-07-09</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C24g09aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>LS</abbr>
<extent>3 p.</extent>
<date value="1724-07-09"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C24g09a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Cage, Esqr., July 9, 1724</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to the trustee of the Fairfax estate,William Cage, of County Kent, England, July 9, 1724, detailing his success in collecting &pound;200 due the proprietor from Edmund Jenings, the former Virginia agent. He notes that he has received the sum by threatening a law suit and taking a mortgage, and Lord Fairfax and Cage may collect the money from Micajah Perry in London. In order to collect a further &pound;100 on their behalf, he needs more evidence from them, but he notes Jenings' deteriorating mental and physical health. He reports a secret survey he has had made of the Brent Town grant that will not be binding on anyone but which will open some land to grants. He turns to the law suit he has brought in the colony to determine the proprietor's right to certain fines, fees, etc., and requests that Cage show the proprietors' grant to the Attorney and Solicitor General and send their opinions to the colony where they will bear much weight with the court. He asks for instructions about an appeal to the King in Council should the case be lost in the colony.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="WC">William Cage,</note> Esqr., July 9, 1724</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1724-07-09"><hi rend="underline">July 9th. 1724</hi></date><lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sr.</salute>

</opener>

<p>Your favour of the 2d. of <abbr expan="December">Decemr.</abbr> came safe to <lb/>me at last after some doubting of its miscarriage I was glad <lb/>to hear of <note n="TF">his Lordships</note> health beg you will do me the honour <lb/>in making my compliments to him letting him know how <lb/>much I am his Lordships most obedient humble servt:</p>

<p>It is a pleasure to me to find both his Lordship &amp; <lb/>your self under so much satisfaction with my management <lb/>of your affairs. I have now got <sic corr="paid">pay'd</sic> into my hands two hun=<lb/>dred pounds more of your debt from <note n="EJ"><abbr expan="Colonel">Col:</abbr> Jennings</note> I shall not <lb/>magnify my merit in getting this mony for you, yet must <lb/>take the liberty to tell you it was not easily come at and nothing <lb/>less <sic corr="than">then</sic> hanging a severe law suit over his head would bring <lb/>him into the humour of doing you justice, and at last it is <lb/><sic corr="hauled">hall'd</sic> out of a Mortgage that he hath made for the security <lb/>of some other persons. This two hundred pounds I have <sic corr="ordered">orderd</sic> <lb/><note n="MP2">Mr Perry</note> to pay when you are pleased to call for it but <lb/>I shall take it as a favour if you are not too quick upon <lb/>him <sic corr="until">untill</sic> he is in cash upon the sale of a large quantity <lb/>of Tobo. he hath of mine in his hands.</p>

<p>As for the remaining balance between you and <abbr expan="Colonel">Col</abbr> <lb/>Jennings it remains yet unadjusted; I in your behalf de=<lb/>manding one hundred twenty nine pounds for want of <lb/>vouchers and he insisting (taking advantage of your letter <lb/>to his son) that there is only twenty nine pounds behind; <lb/>for the balance of this <abbr expan="account">Acct.</abbr> when tis Setled as well as for <lb/>the security of a larger sum he <sic corr="owes">ows</sic> to myself I am let into <lb/>the tail of a Mortgage which must confess I do not like very <lb/>well, however tis the best I could get and I believe the best <lb/>he can give for as I stand informed he hath not a negroe <lb/>nor an Acre of land but is under Mortgage to some person 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
or another Now it is necessary for you to send me the clearest proof <lb/>you have of the nonpayment of this hundred pounds to take <lb/>the force of your expressions to his son and if you can send <lb/>your own testimony how far your knowledge goes about the <lb/>nonpayment of this hundred pounds to my <note target="n1">Lady Fairfax </note><lb/>it may not be amiss; <abbr expan="Colonel">Col:</abbr> Jennings is at this time under <lb/>so great a decay both of mind and body that tis expected by <lb/>all he cannot hold out much longer</p>

<p>I have got some lines run about the Lands tht. <lb/>I think must be deemed to be what the <note n="BT">Brenton Grant</note> <lb/>designed including something more than thirty thousand <lb/>Acres but this I was forced to do without noise both <note target="n2">Mrs. Brent</note> <lb/>and the inhabitants about this place and within these <lb/>bounds <sic corr="threatening">threatning</sic> to stop the surveyer whenever he came &amp; <lb/>indeed <sic corr="waylaid">way-lay'd</sic> him on purpose but he had the luck to pass <lb/>them before They were aware. Now I cannot conclude this <lb/>private survey will be binding either to you or to the Proprietors <lb/>of the Brenton Grant however it will have this good effect <lb/>to lay open a large quantity of back Land toward the Moun=<lb/>tains that people have been hitherto <sic corr="afraid">affraid</sic> to Meddle <lb/>with being kept in <sic corr="awe">aw</sic> by that Grant&mdash;</p>

<p>Your cause with the Crown upon the words of <lb/>your Grant is still depending <sic corr="until">untill</sic> the opinions of the Attorney <lb/>and Solicitor General can be had this method both our <lb/><note n="JC3">Attorney General</note> and my self with the advice of the Lawyers <lb/>I have <sic corr="employed">imployd</sic> came readily into and if <sic corr="you'll">you'l</sic> please to <lb/>produce your Grant to these great men &amp; send me their <lb/>opinions upon the Clause wherein is given to you All and <lb/>all manner of fines <del>&amp;</del> forfeitures Escheats goods of felons &amp; <lb/>fugitives &amp;c whether they shall extend to fines set in our <lb/>County Courts upon offenders for <sic corr="contempts">contemptes</sic> and other misde=<lb/>menaours that are of course inherent in the Crown whether <lb/>these fines and foreitures goods of felons &amp; fugitives escheats <lb/>&amp;c belong to you or to the Crown is the jet of the Controver=<lb/>sy. If the opinion of these great men be with you as 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
my Lawyers think there is no manner of doubt of, I'm <lb/>in <sic corr="hopes">hop's</sic> the Attorney General here will think it proper <lb/>to decline the tryal at least I expect it will have a <lb/>great weight with the Court.</p>

<p>I desire you will let me have your full <lb/>orders if the cause should go against you here whether <lb/>you will have me carry it before the King in Council by an appeal</p>

<p>Some other parts of your letter are yet <lb/>unanswered but that I shall give you the trouble of <lb/>in another Letter. I AM</p>

<closer> Sr. <lb/>Your Most Obedient <lb/>And Most Humble Servt:<lb/><lb/>
<signed><hi rend="bold">ROBERT CARTER</hi></signed> 

<lb/><lb/><seg type="postscript"><note n="JC1">My Son</note> lives at one=<lb/> end of the Country &amp; <lb/>I at <sic corr="the other">tother</sic> his <abbr expan="compliments">complimts:</abbr> <lb/>I must supply for him<lb/><lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Copy</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi>  Fairfax Papers, BR 227, folder 21, Huntington Library, Art Collections, and Botanical Gardens, San Marino, California. Printed: <cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 114-16.</bibl></cit></note><lb/>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to persons abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note><lb/>

<note>This text is a signed recipient's copy sealed with Carter's arms and with the following on the conjoined address leaf:  To Wm. Cage Esqr. | Of Milgate | In the Parish of Bearshead | In the County of Kent&mdash; | To be left at Mr. Micaj Perrys | Of | London |Per the Spotswood | Capt. Bagwell. It is endorsed in Cage's hand, "July 9th 1724 | Coll Carter." </note><lb/>

<note id="n1">[1] Catherine Culpeper, widow of the fifth Lord Fairfax (d. 1710); from her father, the 2nd Lord Culpeper, she had inherited about 1689 his five-sixths interest in the Northern Neck Proprietary in Virginia. Lord Fairfax consulted Micajah Perry about the affairs of the Propietary, and Perry had recommended Robert Carter to be the Virginia agent in 1702. He held the post until 1710 when Lady Fairfax transferred the agency to Edmund Jenings with Thomas Lee as the deputy agent. When she died in 1719, she bequeathed her Virginia property to her son Tom, but she made Wiliam Cage and Edward Filmer trustees of the proprietary. Filmer soon died, and Cage, a kinsman of the 6th Lord Fairfax, became the sole trustee. From his grandmother, Margaret Lady Culpeper, the 6th Lord Fairfax inherited the other one-sixth of the Proprietary. Cage consulted Perry, and Robert Carter was again made agent in 1721, holding the post until his death ten years later.</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Mrs. Brent was the mother of George Brent who inherited from his grandfather, George Brent ([d. 1699] of "Woodstock," Stafford County, the "resident partner in Virginia" for the development of the Brent Town grant by Nicholas Hayward), the family's claim to a portion of the Brent Town grant. She was a considerable thorn in Carter's side concerning the grant and its boundaries. (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 178 ff.</bibl></cit> See Carter's letter to Cage 1723 July 4.) </note>
	





</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>