<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27a14a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to the [Board of Trade and Plantations], January 14, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 11 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27a14a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003, 2011</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to the [Board of Trade and Plantations], January 14, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>4 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  CO5/1320, Public Record Office, London.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-01-14</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27a14aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1727-01-14"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27a14a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to the [Board of Trade and Plantations], January 14, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to the Board of Trade and Plantations, January 14, 1727,  that he has carried out instructions directed by the Board to the late governor by giving instructions to the various officers to prepare accounts of the taxes collected under various acts; he expects to send the accounts soon. He sends the Council journals, and will send  the journal of a recent meeting once it has been read and approved. Also sent are various reports of taxes, and the Naval Officers' records of imports and exports. The Assembly had been prorogued by the governor before his death, and that proroguation has been continued. Carter intends to propose at the next Council that the Assembly be further prorogued until a new govenor arrives. He closes by reporting the death of Council member Philip Ludwell.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to the [<note target="n1">Board of Trade and Plantations</note>], January 14, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Virginia</name><lb/>
<date value="1727-01-14">January the 14th 1726/7</date><lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>My Lords</salute>

</opener>



<p><hi rend="bold">A</hi>	</p>
<p>I had lately the <sic corr="honour ">Honr</sic> to receive Yor <abbr expan="Lordships ">Lordps</abbr> <lb/>Letter of the 30th of June directed to <note n="HD">Governor Drysdale,</note> and <lb/>have in obedience to Your commands, given directions to the <lb/>proper officers to prepare Accounts, as well of the money collected <lb/>for the duty on <sic corr="Negroes ">Negros</sic> during the containuance of the Act <lb/>for laying a duty on Liquors and Slaves, as of the number of <lb/><sic corr="Negroes ">Negros</sic> imported since 1718 by the <note target="n2">African company</note> &amp; Separate <lb/>Traders respectively; and hope by the next conveyance I <sic corr="shall ">shal</sic> be <lb/>able to <sic corr="transmit ">transmitt</sic> both in the manner Yor <abbr expan="Lordships ">Lordps</abbr> require.<lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;The</p>


<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<p>The last letter I had the <sic corr="honour ">honr</sic> to write to Yor <abbr expan="Lordships ">Lordps</abbr> <lb/><sic corr="enclosed ">inclosed</sic> the Duplicates of the <sic corr="public ">publick</sic> papers sent before by the late <lb/>Governor; and as I have advice that the Ships in which both the ones <lb/>and the other were forwarded, are safely arrived, I hope those papers <lb/>are got to Yor <abbr expan="Lordships ">Lordps</abbr> hands, and that I need not trouble you with fresh <lb/>transcripts; but <sic corr="shall ">shal</sic> pursue Yor <abbr expan="Lordships ">Lordps</abbr> directions in my future <lb/>Correspondence.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">B</hi>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;The <name type="ship">Mansell Galley,</name> <abbr expan="Captain ">Capt</abbr> James Trevisa bound for London, <lb/>affording me a Conveyance for the <sic corr="public ">publick</sic> dispatches to Yor. <abbr expan="Lordships ">Lordps</abbr> <lb/><del>and</del> Board, I would no longer dilay sending Yor. <abbr expan="Lordships ">Lordps</abbr> the Journals <lb/>of council, <sic corr="though ">tho</sic> they contain little of moment, or that require any <lb/>particular Remark. there remain to be transmitted the Minut<add resp="editor">[e]</add>s <lb/>of a Council held the 14th &amp; 15th of last month, wch are not yet read <lb/>and approved: but the next Council wch I intend to call the begining <lb/>of next month will give me an opportunity to perfect them, and <lb/>to forward the proceedings of both by a Ship I expect to sail Soon <lb/>after.<lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Among</p>


<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
<p>Among other <sic corr="public ">publick</sic> papers which go herewith, is the <lb/>last half years <sic corr="account ">Accompt</sic> of the two shillings per hogshead, on wch <lb/>there is a considerable ballance remaining in Bank; and from the <lb/>large demand of Rights for taking up new lands, as well as the Crop <lb/>of Tobacco no ready to be <sic corr="shipped, ">Shipd,</sic> and which tis believed will near <lb/>equal that of the preceding Year, there is reason to expect as <lb/>good addition to that Revenue.</p>

<p>Herewith Yor <abbr expan="Lordships ">Lordps</abbr> will also receive the Naval Officers <lb/>accots of the Imports and Exports from <note target="n3">Lady day</note> to Christmas last <lb/>past, whereby Yor. <abbr expan="Lordships ">Lordps</abbr> will have a View of the Trade of this <lb/>Colony for that time.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">C</hi>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;The General Assembly which was under prorogation at the <lb/>death of the late Governor, has been since further prorogued to the <lb/>fifteenth of February, and since the <sic corr="public ">publick</sic> affairs do not require <lb/>my convening it; I intend at next Council a further prorogation, that <lb/>whosoever His Majesty is <sic corr="pleased ">pleasd</sic> to appoint Governor here may find <lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;an

<pb n="4"/><lb/><lb/>
an Assembly subsisting at his arrival.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">D</hi>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;I'm sorry to <sic corr="inform ">informe</sic> Yor. <abbr expan="Lordships ">Lordps</abbr> that <note n="PL1"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Colo</abbr> Ludwell,</note> who for many <lb/>years worthily served as a Member of his Majestys Council of this <lb/>Colony <sic corr="died ">dyed</sic> on the 10th of this month. I am with the greatest Respect </p>

<closer>My Lords <lb/>Your <abbr expan="Lordships ">Lordps</abbr> <lb/>Most dutiful &amp; most obedient <lb/>humble Servant <lb/><lb/><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">ROBERT CARTER</hi></hi>
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>The Mansel Galley being <sic corr="gone">gones</sic> <lb/>I send this by the <name type="ship">Exchange</name> of <lb/><name type="place">Biddiford,</name> <abbr expan="Thmas">Thos.</abbr> Whitfield M<add resp="editor">[aste]</add>r. <lb/>being unwilling to delay till an opportunity <lb/>offers for London,
</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> CO5/1320,  ff.130-131, Public Record Office, London, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. This is the recipient's copy, signed by Carter with his usual large and prominent signature, indicated here by the use of bold italics. Endorsed: "<hi rend="underline">Virginia</hi> | Letter from | Colo Carter President of the | Council of Virginia | dated Octr 2d, 1726 | Janry: 14th. 1726/7 | Reced April 3: 1727 | Read April 28: 1727." </note>

<note>Someone, probably a clerk in the Boad of Trade office, has added letters in alphabetical order to the paragraphs that begin topics of Carter's letter; the letters of the alphabet  are indicated here in bold type.</note>

<note>At a later time the large oval seal of "Her Majesty's State Paper Office" was applied to the obverse or reverse of the pages. </note>

<note id="n1">[1] Established in 1696 as successor to a similar body, the Lords Commissioners of Trade and Plantations was "an advisory group, subordinate to king and Privy Council, and with no executive, financial, or penalizing powers, the Board of Trade was nevertheless able . . . to exert a far reaching and often determining influence in colonial matters. . . . It prepared the royal instructions for the governors overseas. . . ." (<cit><bibl>Henry Hartwell, James Blair, and Edward Chilton. Hunter Dickinson Farish, <hi rend="italics">ed.</hi> <title>The Present State of Virginia, and the College.</title> [First published, 1940, by Colonial Williamsburg, Inc., and reprinted Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1964.] pp. xvi-xvii.</bibl></cit>)</note>


<note id="n2">[2] The Royal African Company, founded in 1672, grew out of earlier slave-trading companies that had been founded in the middle of the  seventeenth century, and that held monopolies on the English trade in slaves. The trade proved so  profitable that Parliament was lobbied successfully to rescind the monopoly and open the trade to anyone which happened in 1698.  (<cit><bibl>http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/aia/home.html</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="B27">Billings. <hi rend="italics">et al. </hi> <title>Colonial Virginia: A History.</title> p. 232.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3]   "A day on which a religious festival in honour of the Virgin Mary is celebrated. Now only March 25th, the Feast of the Annunciation. . . . Lady Day . . . is the first of the traditional quarter days . . . and until the adoption of the Gregorian calendar (1752 in Britain) marked the first day of the new year." (<xref to="http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/105017?redirectedFrom=Lady%20Day#eid">OED Online.</xref> Oxford University Press. 10/3/2011)</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2003, was revised October 3,  2011, to add footnotes, and to strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>