<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27a05a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Peter Leheup, January 5, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 11 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27a05a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Peter Leheup, January 5, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  CO5/1320, Public Record Office, London.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-01-05</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27a05aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>ALS</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1727-01-05"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27a05a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Peter Leheup, January 5, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Peter Leheup, January 5, 1727, Virginia's agent in England, to thank him for his offer of assistance concerning his salary while administering the colony, and expressing his support for the liquor law recently passed by the Assembly. He closes by noting that he believes the merchants are attempting to harrass the colonists "out of our Estates by loading us with Interest upon Interest," which he believes can best be avoided by not getting in their debt.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">Peter Leheup,</note> January 5, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-01-05">Jany: the 5th: 1726/7</date><lb/>
Peter Leheup Esqr.<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sr&mdash;</salute>

</opener>



<p>I have already acquainted you of the honour of being <lb/>in possession of his Majestys Sign Manual of the 12th: of July. And Sent <lb/>you my bills on <note n="MP2">Mr. Perry</note> for the charge. I am now to own your Second <lb/>favour of the 28th: of <abbr expan="September">Sepr:</abbr> And with it the honour of a Letter from his <lb/>Grace the <note target="n2">Duke of New Castle,</note> Signifying his Majestys Satisfaction <lb/>of my present Acting in the Administration&mdash;</p>

	<p>I have bin under a Sickly wasting Indisposition <lb/>all this year, which hath disabled me from giving my Attendance <lb/>so long or so often at the <note target="n3">Seat of the <abbr expan="Government">Governmt:</abbr></note> as I Should otherwise have <lb/>done, however I hope nothing hath bin Omitted within the Duty of <lb/>my place I bless God since the winter months came in, am in some <lb/>measure recruited&mdash;</p>

<p><note n="JC1">The Secretary</note> hath acquainted me with yor: kind <lb/>readiness to do all good Offices in relation to the Salary but I see no <lb/>Occasion for application to obtain a <abbr expan="warrant">Warrt:</abbr> upon that Accot: his <lb/>Majestys Instruction being plain in <sic corr="entitling">Intitleing</sic> the President to a <lb/><note target="n4"><sic corr="moiety">Mojety</sic></note> of the Salary and the perquisites according to which I have <lb/>proceeded, A Copy of this Instruction herewith I Send you&mdash;</p>

<p><hi rend="underline"><note target="n5">It will be</note> very greatfull to the Country to have</hi> <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Turn Over

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<hi rend="underline">the Liquor Law obtain the royal Assent. It is the only Expedient <lb/>we have left to answer the Charges of the Governmt: by&mdash;</hi></p>

	<p>I was always doubtfull the representation about the <lb/>Case between Randolph and Perry would hardly meet with a <lb/>favourable reception; I shall not enter into the Circumstances of the <lb/>Case however in Confidence it may be <sic corr="observed">observ'd.</sic> If the Merchants <lb/>can <note target="n6"><sic corr="worry">wurry</sic></note> us out of our Estates by loading us with Interest upon <lb/>Interest we Shall be in a bad Condition The best remedy will be <lb/>not to get into their Debts,</p>

<p>Whatsoever <abbr expan="favours">favrs:</abbr> I shall receive from Yor: influence <lb/>Shall be greatfully Acknowledged by </p>

<closer>Sir&mdash; <lb/>Yor: most <abbr expan="Obedient">Obed:</abbr> humble Servt:
<lb/><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">ROBERT CARTER</hi></hi></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> CO5/1320, ff. 118, Public Record Office, London. At the foot of the first page: "Peter Leheup Esqr." It is the recipient's copy, signed by Carter. Leheup turned the letter over to the Board of Trade among whose records it was found. It is endorsed: "Recd March 4: | Read Do: 10: | }1726/7."</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence to persons abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Peter Leheup, an English Treasury clerk, was Virginia's  and other colonies' agent in England for some years. He was related by marriage to the Prime Minister's brother who was secretary of the Treasury. His influence would be greater near the end of Carter's life.(<cit><bibl n="B22">Price. <title>Perry of London. . . . </title> pp. 75-77, 80, 83.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Thomas Pelham-Holles, the 1st Duke of Newcastle, was Secretary of State in the Walpole government; Richard L. Morton notes that the duke carried on a policy of "`saluatory neglect' of the colonies which lasted until the Seven Years' War." (<cit><bibl n="B17">Morton. <title>Colonial Virginia.</title> p. 506.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Williamsburg</note>

<note id="n4">[4] A moiety is one of two approximately equal portions.</note>

<note id="n5">[5] This entire paragraph has been underlined, presumably by Leheup, to draw attention to Carter's comment on the liquor law. See Hening for the text of the act entitled "An Act for Laying a duty on Liquor" which would have sent &pound;200 per year of the proceeds of this duty to the College of William and Mary. (<cit><bibl>William Waller Hening. <title>The Statutes at Large; being A Collection of All the Laws of Virginia. . . .</title>  [Richmond: privately printed, 1820. Facsimile reprint, 1969.] 4:143-150.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] Carter probably uses an original meaning of the word "worry" which was to choke or strangle.</note>

 




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>