<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C2727e15b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to [William Robertson,] May 15, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27e15b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to [William Robertson,] May 15, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>4 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-05-15</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27e15bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>4 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-05-15"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27e15b.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to [William Robertson,] May 15, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to [William Robertson,] May 15, 1727, clerk of the Council, to alert him that he had not signed, as naval officer, one of his lists of shipping, and to give him instructions about the celebration of the King's birthday. He encloses a letter to be forwarded to his son John, secretary of state of the colony, whom he is asking to stand in for himself because his ill health will not allow him to attend. In an enclosure, he gives further and specific instructions about the illumination of Williamsburg and details of the celebration.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="WR">[William Robertson,]</note> May 15, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-05-15">May 15th: 1727</date><lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>Yor: Messenger with the Expresses my Boat <sic corr="fetched">fetcht</sic> <lb/>over last night after all <note n="RC">Mr. Carys</note> delays he hath not Sent me <lb/>duplicates which he promised me and I must have <add place="supralinear"><del>which</del> desire to let him know it</add> and you <lb/>must prepare me duplicates also.  You have not <sic corr="signed">Signd</sic> <note target="n1">yor: <lb/>list</note> of Entrys inward, reckoning I Suppose yor: <add place="supralinear">Signing the</add> Clearings&mdash; <lb/>outward Serves for both I note it because the other Officers <lb/>Sign all their lists, a copy of the Letters to the board of Trade I <lb/>Shall take care to keep, here are <note target="n2">Keeling,</note> <note target="n3">Hopkins,</note> <note target="n4">Woodward</note> <lb/>Londoners Suddenly bound out therefor<add resp="editor">[e]</add> keep the <sic corr="public">Publick</sic> <lb/>Papers to be sent in one of them</p>
 
<p>Pray, let Mr. <note target="n5">Jacob Walker</note> have an Order <lb/>to provide a <sic corr="flag">flagg</sic> for point Comfort and do you provide <lb/>another for the Battery at York it is my Duty to pay all <lb/>possible respects to the <note n="WG">Govr:</note> when he Arrives</p>

<p>You have forestalld me two or three days <lb/>in respect to the Kings birthday I intended <add place="supralinear">to</add> wait but till <lb/>Wednesday night <del>before</del> and then to have <sic corr="dispatched">dispatchd</sic> dire<add resp="editor">[ct]</add><lb/>ions to you about it You very well know my Innate Prin<lb/>ciples have all along bin Strong and Entirely for the <lb/>family and in the Post I am now in my Duty require<add resp="editor">[s me]</add> <lb/>to Celebrate his Majestys birthday. My Dayly Indispo<add resp="editor">[sitions]</add> <lb/>deny me the Satisfaction of being present at the <note target="n6">seat of G<add resp="editor">[overnment]</add></note> <lb/>my Self. Yesterday I was so Very ill could hardly Stay t<add resp="editor">[o the]</add> <lb/>End of Divine Service and afterwards was forced to <add resp="editor">[ride]</add> <lb/>out half a dozen mile to get my breath without Eatin<add resp="editor">[g a]</add> <lb/>mouthfull of Victuals <add place="supralinear">in the</add> whole day it was w<add resp="editor">[ith]</add> <lb/>Difficulty I held out the Court The Oyer and Term<add resp="editor">[iner]</add> <lb/>I must be at if it be possible.  The Load of my own bu<add resp="editor">[siness is]</add> <lb/>in its greatest throng however I resolve to have the <add resp="editor">[birthday]</add> <lb/><add place="supralinear">kept</add> with as much Show as it was by <note n="HD"><abbr expan="Colonel">Coll</abbr> Drysdale </note></p>

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<p>In order to this herewith I Send a Letter to the <note n="JC1">Secretary</note> wch: <lb/>you are to Send away <add place="supralinear">by</add> Express <sic corr="desiring">Desireing</sic> him to Personate <lb/>my room and if he Should decline it I must rely Upon <lb/>You and <note target="n7">Mr. Hickman</note> to do your utmost and I will by you <lb/>request the Town Gentlemen, <note n="JC3">Mr. <sic corr="Attorney">Atturney,</sic></note> <note n="JH">Major Holloway </note><lb/>and <note target="n8"><abbr expan="Major">Majr:</abbr> Blair</note> to be Assisting in the <abbr expan="government">Governmt.</abbr> &amp; direct<add resp="editor">[ing]</add> <lb/>the Affair.  The <abbr expan="Governor's">Govrs:</abbr> house to be Sure is the fittest place You <lb/>may <del>be sure</del> <add place="supralinear">very well Conclude</add> when I laid in that wine at Town I had this <lb/>day in my thoughts in Case a <abbr expan="governor">Govr:</abbr> should not Arrive Wt: <lb/>ever Sorts of drink Colonel Drysdale had I would have the Same <lb/>and in all respects keep pace with him My Salary is as <lb/>large and I thank God I have as little reason to be Sparing <lb/>of it I Speak more particularly in the Enclosed paper,</p>

<p>The warrants for the apprehending of <note target="n9">Prowse</note> <lb/>I have <sic corr="signed">Signd</sic> and have <sic corr="dispatched">dispatchd</sic> away Seven of them for <lb/>the Northern Countys and for Middlesex.  The rest are returnd.  <lb/>I am </p>

<closer>Sir&mdash; <lb/>Yor: most humble Servt:<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>
<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
The Necessarys requisite for the Birth Night in all respects <lb/>Equall the last birth night,<lb/><lb/>

The <abbr expan="Governor's">Govrs:</abbr> house to be Illuminated Mr. Clayton <lb/>also and likewise the Capitol if it was so before I <sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> the <lb/><note target="n10"><sic corr="College">Colledge</sic></note> and all the houses in <note target="n5">Town</note> will be <del>also</del> Illuminated <lb/>bonnfires to be made as before,<lb/><lb/>

All the Loyall healths to be drunk. The Guns <lb/>to be fired and the Batterys to fire. The <sic corr="flags">flaggs</sic> to be hoisted <lb/>as was orderd by Colonel Drysdale<lb/><lb/>

The Gentlemen and Ladys that will come to <lb/>Invited Cold Treats to be provided a Ball to be had for the <lb/><add resp="editor">[la]</add>dys, The Gentlemen of the Council and their familys 

<pb n="4"/><lb/><lb/>
particularly to be Invited Mr. Grimes's family I shall invite <lb/>whatever I have Omitted to be <sic corr="Supplied">Supplyd</sic> The charge an Ac<add resp="editor">[count]</add> <lb/>to be kept of and paid of <note n="JG2">Mr. Grimes</note> I Expect will let me <lb/>have the money<lb/><lb/>

My wine you may be free with I beleive one <lb/>of the Pipes will Sufficiently answer the Occasion Other <lb/>Liquors &amp;ca: you must provide as well as you can I am <lb/><lb/>Sir Yors: ut Supra&mdash;<lb/><lb/>
All Immaginable care must be <lb/>taken to prevent disorders and <lb/>disasters</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. There is a 19th-century transcript of the letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.
</note>

<note>Pages three and four are the enclosure mentioned in the letter.</note>

<note id="n1"><note target="n1"></note>[1] Robertson had been appointed a naval officer in 1719, and Carter refers to lists of ships entering and departing the colony prepared by these officials as one of their duties. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 3[1705-1721]:512. </bibl></cit> )</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Captain William Keiling commanded the <hi rend="italics">Betty.
</hi> (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley  Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Captain James Hopkins commanded the <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi> in 1727-1728. He was then working for London merchant Robert Cary. He is mentioned in Carter's diary. (<cit><bibl>Adm. 68/194, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Thomas Woodward commanded the <hi rend="italics">Providence</hi> during a number of voyages to the colony, 1723-1727. (<cit><bibl>Adm. 68/194 and 195, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] Carter had forgotten that George (not Jacob) Walker was the "Gunner and Storekeeper of the Battery at point Comfort" at the eastern end of the peninsula between the James and York rivers southeast of Williamsburg. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:33. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] Williamsburg</note>

<note id="n7">[7] After Lt. Gov. Drysdale's death in July 1726, Richard Hickman had been appointed by the Council to keep up the governor's home. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:114. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n8">[8] Archibald Blair was a prominent merchant of Williamsburg, and was chosen one of the Council's representatives to convey its message of sympathy to Mrs. Drysdale after the death of her husband, the lieutenant governor. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:17, 114. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n9">[9] John Prowse was being sought because he had been accused of the murder of an Indian. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:133, 453. </bibl></cit>) </note>

<note id="n10">[10] The buildings of the College of William and Mary</note>







</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>