<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27e15a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to [John Carter,] May 15, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27e15a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to [John Carter,] May 15, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-05-15</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27e15aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-05-15"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27e15a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to [John Carter,] May 15, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his son, [John Carter,] May 15, 1727,to attend the celebration of the King's birthday because he is too unwell. He gives instructions about invitations to certain persons, and then sends family news.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="JC1">[John Carter,]</note> May 15, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-05-15">May 15th: 1727</date><lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Dr: Son&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>It seems very likely the <note target="n1"><abbr expan="governor">Govr:</abbr></note> will not arrive <lb/>before the birthday I fully purposed to have <sic corr="discoursed">discourst</sic> you <lb/>about it but the hurry I was in when I came away put it <lb/>quite out of my thoughts I am under such daily &amp; hourly <lb/>Afflictions with my distemper that it is hardly possible for <lb/>me to give my Attendance at the <note target="n2">Seat of <abbr expan="government">Governmt.</abbr></note> in s<add resp="editor">[uch]</add><lb/>a <sic corr="fatigue">fateigue</sic> Yesterday I was ready to <sic corr="die">Dye</sic> for want of breath <lb/>Could eat no victuals and was forced to ride half a dozen <lb/>Mile in the Evening to over come the pressure I was under <lb/>It was with a great deal of difficulty I held out the Court <lb/>the Oyer and Terminer I must be at if it is possible <add resp="editor">[The]</add> <lb/>throng of my own business <del>th </del>at this season of the y<add resp="editor">[ear]</add> <lb/>you know however I resolve to have the Kings birt<add resp="editor">[hday]</add><lb/> kept with as much Solemnity as the late <note n="HD"><abbr expan="governor">Govr:</abbr></note> did <lb/>and have given directions to <note n="WR">Mr. Robertson</note> accordin<add resp="editor">[gly]</add> <lb/>And now who is so proper to think of to personating	 <add resp="editor">[me]</add> <lb/><add resp="editor">[but your]</add> Self. Therefore I Earnestly desire you to be there 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<add resp="editor">[if]</add> possible a Convenient Time before the Day <note n="WB1">Colonel Bird</note> &amp; <lb/>his family by all means must be invited, The rest <lb/>Mr. Robertson is instructed in. <note n="NH"><abbr expan="Major">Majr:</abbr> Harrison</note> and his family <lb/>Should be invited, If I can <sic corr="persuade">perwade</sic> yor: Brothers to meet you <lb/>there I will. I hear by a Random <sic corr="Story">Storey</sic> that <note n="MP1">Colonel Page</note> di<add resp="editor">[d]</add> <lb/>not get out of Town last week that his Boat went for him <lb/><del>on Sun</del><add place="supralinear">yester</add>day pray God grant him to recover so well to let his <lb/>family partake of the Diversions I hope yor: wife is well <lb/>and may have health and inclination to Accompany <lb/>you.</p>

<p>I have Curtis's promise for two hogsheads of heavy <lb/><abbr expan="tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> for you.  Turner's two hogsheads I shall not forget Your <lb/>sister <note n="MMCB">Mary</note> is at this Time very unwell <note n="RC2">Robin</note> &amp; his Wife <lb/>have not bin at home since my return The rest I thank <lb/>God are in health I may say with a great deal of truth <lb/>the days are come upon me that I have no pleasure in <lb/>I am </p>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.  There is a 19th-century transcript of the letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note>

<note>This letter was sent to William Robertson, clerk of the Council, for forwarding to John Carter who lived near Williamsburg. See Carter's letter to Robertson of this same date.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Sir William Gooch (1681-1751), lieutenant governor of the colony under the govenor, George Hamilton, Earl of Orkney, would reach Williamsburg in September 1727. He would serve during Carter's lifetime (and until August 1749). (<cit><bibl>Emily J. Salmon and Edward D. C. Campbell, Jr. <title>The Hornbook of Virginia History.</title>Richmond: The Library of Virginia, 1994. p. 106.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Williamsburg</note>







</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>