<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; 

<!NOTATION html SYSTEM "HTML">
<!ENTITY Ext6 SYSTEM "http://www.fraudaid.com\/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms\/bill_of_exchange.htm" NDATA html>


]>
<TEI.2 id="C27e18b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Peter Leheup, May 18, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27e18b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003, 2012</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Peter Leheup, May 18, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-05-18</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27e18bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-05-18"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27e18b.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Peter Leheup, May 18, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Peter Leheup, the colony's agent in London, May 18, 1727, to inform him of the actions Carter has taken as acting governor, especially of reports and payments made. He notes particularly the concern in the colony that war with Spain may have begun, and that the warship stationed in the colony is convoying ships well off the coast.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">Peter Leheup,</note> May 18, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County] Virginia</add></name>&nbsp;&nbsp;<date value="1727-05-18">May 18th: 1727</date><lb/>
Peter Leheup Esqr:<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>



<p>On the 16th: of March I took the Opportunity to <lb/>Answer yor. favour of the 7th: of <abbr expan="Nvember">Novr:</abbr> Acquainting <add place="supralinear">you</add> of my Tranmitt<lb/>ing all the Public Papers to the Lords of the <note target="n2">Board of Trade,</note> I now Se<add resp="editor">[nd]</add> <lb/>to their Lordships the <note target="n3">Naval Officers lists,</note> Accounts of the <sic corr="public">publick</sic> <lb/>revenue <add place="supralinear">the proclamations</add> and the <sic corr="minutes">minuits</sic> of the Council for the last Council And <lb/>do my Self the honour to write to their Lordships. I have also sent <lb/>to my <note n="GH">Lord Orkney</note> <note target="n4">bills of Exchange </note>for his <add place="supralinear">Salary and his</add> <sic corr="Moiety"><note target="n5">Mojety</note></sic> of the perquisities <lb/>to the 25th: of <sic corr="April">Aprill</sic> which I hope will give his Lordship Entire <lb/>Satisfaction. Your own bill for &pound;10"&mdash;"6 I <del>rec'd</del><add place="supralinear">Expect</add> you have long <lb/>Since <abbr expan="received.">rec'd.</abbr> I have Sent to <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> <note target="n6">Birchet</note> my Exchange for &pound;5:- for four Medite<lb/>rranean Passes Private Letters and Some prints tell us that <lb/><sic corr="War">Warr</sic> is begun by the <note target="n7">Siege of Gibralter </note><sic corr="We">Wee</sic> have no <sic corr="Public">Publick</sic> <lb/>press concerning it. <sic corr="We">Wee</sic>  have not thought it adviseable to lay <lb/>a Strict Embargo upon our Shipping but have taken the best <lb/>measures we can that they Shall go in fleets and <note target="n8"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Peirce </note><lb/>his Majestys Station Ship is ready to Accompany them <sic corr="off">of</sic> <del>of</del> <lb/>this Coast. he is now <sic corr="gone">gon</sic> out with a Small Fleet and Intends to <lb/>be ready for another in a Short time,</p>

<p><sic corr="We">Wee</sic> are in daily Expectation of the Arrival of <lb/>Our <note n="WG"><abbr expan="Governor">Govr:</abbr></note> I am </p>

<closer>Sir <lb/>Yor: most Obedt: humble Servt
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>per <note target="n9">Hopkins</note></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>The name of Carter's home and county have been supplied for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Peter Leheup, an English Treasury clerk, was Virginia's  and other colonies' agent in England for some years. He was related by marriage to the Prime Minister's brother who was secretary of the Treasury. His influence would be greater near the end of Carter's life.(<cit><bibl n="B22">Price. <title>Perry of London. . . . </title> pp. 75-77, 80, 83.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Established in 1696 as successor to a similar body, the Lords Commissioners of Trade and Plantations was "an advisory group, subordinate to king and Privy Council, and with no executive, financial, or penalizing powers, the Board of Trade was nevertheless able . . . to exert a far reaching and often determining influence in colonial matters. . . . It prepared the royal instructions for the governors overseas. . . ." (<cit><bibl>Henry Hartwell, James Blair, and Edward Chilton. Hunter Dickinson Farish, <hi rend="italics">ed.</hi> <title>The Present State of Virginia, and the College.</title> [First published, 1940, by Colonial Williamsburg, Inc., and reprinted Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1964.] pp. xvi-xvii.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] The naval officer was an official in the colony that reported to the Commissioners of Customs, a body that had first been established in 1663; the group was reorganized several times, especially after 1688. The board was "intrusted with collection of customs both in England and the colonies." The board helped write many of the instructions for colonial governors in collaboration with the Privy Council. "Their direct connection with the colonies was through the governors, who were instructed to correspond with the commissioners, and to send them, every three months, lists of clearances, and also reports of illegal trading. The governor's agent in matters of trade was the naval officer whom he was empowered to appoint, but who was required by the 7th and 8th William III to give security to the commissioners of customs." (<cit><bibl>Louise Phillips Kellogg. <title>The American Colonial Charter. A Study of English Administration in Relation Thereto, Especialy after 1688.</title>  [Annual Report, American Historical Association. Vol. 1, Govt. Print. Off., 1904], p. 226.</bibl></cit> For a recent study, see <cit><bibl>Alvin Rabushka. <title>Taxation in Colonial America</title> [Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2008.]</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4"> [4] A bill of exchange is a kind of check or promissory note without interest.  It is used primarily in international trade, and is a written order by one person to pay another a specific sum on a specific date sometime in the future.  If the bill of exchange is drawn on a bank, it is called a bank draft.  If it is drawn on another party, it is called a trade draft.  Sometimes a bill of exchange will simply be called a draft, but whereas a draft is always  negotiable (transferable by endorsement), this is not necessarily true of a bill of exchange. (<cit><bibl><xref to="Ext6">"Dictionary of  Financial Scam Terms,"</xref> 8/22/2005</bibl></cit>)</note>


<note id="n5">[5] A moiety is one of two approximately equal portions.</note>

<note id="n6">[6] Josiah Burchet is presumed to have been an Admiralty official responsible for collecting the fees for Mediterranean passes which merchant ships needed to protect themselves from Barbary pirates. See <xref to="/users/berkeley/public//C27e13b.html">Carter's letter </xref>to Burchet, May 13, 1727.</note>

<note id="n7">[7] H. R. McIlwaine wrote in 1910, "It is true that in 1727 . . .  England was at war with Spain, but the war was one in which not much blood was shed and which was soon over." As Carter was writing in 1727, the Spanish were indeed beseiging Gibralter, but they were not successful and gave up in July. A treaty of peace was to be signed in 1729. (<cit><bibl>H.R. McIlwaine, <hi rend="italics">ed.</hi> <title>Journals of the House of Burgesses of Virginia, 1727-1734, 1736-1740.</title> [Richmond: Virginia. General Assembly. House of Burgesses, Virginia State Library,
 1910], xiii.</bibl></cit>) </note><lb/>

<note id="n8">[8] Captain Vincent Pearse was the commander of the <hi rend="italics">Tartar,</hi> the British warship on station in the colony. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:136. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n9">[9] Captain James Hopkins commanded the <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi> in 1727-1728. He was then working for London merchant Robert Cary. He is mentioned in Carter's diary. (<cit><bibl>Adm. 68/194, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>


<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2003, was revised July 4, 2012,  to add footnotes and strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>



</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>