<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; 

<!NOTATION html SYSTEM "HTML">
<!ENTITY Ext6 SYSTEM "http://www.fraudaid.com\/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms\/bill_of_exchange.htm" NDATA html>

<!NOTATION php SYSTEM "php">
<!ENTITY Ext4 SYSTEM "http://www.stratfordhall.org\/learn\/lees\/thomaslee.php" NDATA php>

]>
<TEI.2 id="C27f28c">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, June 28, July 26, and August 22, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 20 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27f28c.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003, 2013</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, June 28, July 26, and August 22, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>5 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-06-28</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27f28cT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>5 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-06-28"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27f28c.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, June 28, July 26, and August 22, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant William Dawkins, June 28, 1727, that he is sending 28 hogsheads of tobacco from the estate of Nathaniel Burwell on board Dawkins' ship, the <hi rend="italics">Bailey, </hi> and Mann Page will send the bill of lading. Because a large share of the estate's tobacco is being sent to Dawkins this year, he hopes the merchant will exert himself to get the best prices for it to justify Carter's faith in him. He sends an invoice (not present) for goods for the Burwell children, and two bills of exchange. Adam Graves has come to see Carter to deny that he has made disparaging remarks about the <hi rend="italics">Carter,</hi> and Carter asks Dawkins to forget what he has written previously about Graves in this matter. He reports that Captain Dove (of the <hi rend="italics">Carter</hi>) hopes to have a load of 300 hogsheads, but will probably not make the next fleet. In closing, he notes that he has been preparing invoices for his goods in hopes of receiving them earlier than usual, but they are not ready. In a lengthy post script dated July 26th, Carter adds details of many bills of exchange, sends an order (not present) for goods, payment to him of a debt due Dawkins from George Devenport, the further problems of Captain Dove and the <hi rend="italics">Carter,</hi> and the news in the colony of the raising of the siege of Gibralter. In a second post script dated August 22nd, he reports that the <hi rend="italics">Carter</hi> will sail without being fully loaded which he attributes to her late arrival in the colony. He sends an invoice and a bill of lading (not present) and a number of bills of exchange.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="WD">William Dawkins,</note> June 28, July 26, and August 22, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
Mr: Wm: Dawkins&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name>&nbsp;&nbsp;
<date value="1727-06-28">June the 28th: 1727</date><lb/>

</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>Yor: Ship <note target="n1"><name type="ship">Baily</name></note> makes ones of this first Fleet <lb/>there are on board her 28 <abbr expan="hogsheads">hhds:</abbr> belonging to <note n="NB">Mr. Burwells</note> Estate and <lb/>of his best Crops <sic corr="Consigned">Consignd</sic> to you a bill of Lading I Expect <note n="MP1">Colonel Page</note> <lb/>Sends you a large Share of those <abbr expan="tobacco">Tobbos:</abbr> comes under your management <lb/>this year I hope you will Exert <sic corr="yourself">your Self</sic> in keeping up <add place="supralinear">their</add> reputation <lb/>and not let mine Suffer in ordering So much to you. I Compute <lb/>there is money Enough in your hands to entitle the Estate to all the <abbr expan="Discounts">Discots:</abbr> <lb/>however a payment of Some money belonging to it falling into Colonel <lb/>Pages hands I have desired him to lodge some more of it with you I <lb/>wish you were more frequent wi<add place="supralinear">th</add> your Accots: Currt: that we might <lb/>be at a nicer Certainty,</p>

<p>An Invoice for a Supply to Mr. Burwells Children <lb/>for the next year comes herewith In which I hope you will Study <lb/>to please their Mother both in the goodness and Cheapness,</p>

<p>Herein I Send you two <note target="n2">bills of <abbr expan="exchange">Exche:</abbr></note> of my own drawn <lb/>upon <sic corr="yourself">your Self</sic> Colonel Pages for &pound;100"&mdash;"&mdash; and <note target="n3">John <sic corr="Taliferro">Taliaferrio </sic></note><lb/>for &pound;9:16:3 which I desire Credit for</p>

<p>Adam Graves <sic corr="hath">has</sic> bin with me to give me Satis<lb/>faction about the reports he was made the author of in disparagement 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
of the <note n="CS"><name type="ship">Carter</name></note> which he utterly <sic corr="denies">denys</sic> therefore pray let what I w<add resp="editor">[rote]</add> <lb/>you about him Stand for nothing I Shall be very unwilling to recas<add resp="editor">[t]</add> <lb/>any prejudice against him in your Esteem without a Just Cause <lb/>Dove moves on as fast as he can he is now in hopes of geting to 800 <lb/><abbr expan="hogsheads">hhds:</abbr> <abbr expan="tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> comes out unpectedly Flatter <sic corr="myself">my Self</sic> he will Exceed <lb/>that number but am afraid he will not be ready for the next Fleet <lb/>which is appointed the 25th of next month</p>

<p>Being desirous to have my goods in Earlier <sic corr="than">then</sic> <lb/>I have had them for these two or three years past I have bin prepare<lb/>ing my own Invoices Time is so Short I cannot finish them now <lb/>must let them <sic corr="lie">lye</sic> for another Opportunity I am </p>

<closer>Sir&mdash;<lb/>Yor: very humble Servt:
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>per <note target="n4">Watkinson</note>
<lb/>Copy per <note target="n5">Trice</note></seg><lb/><lb/>

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>

<seg type="postscript">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Added to his Letter of 28 June<lb/>
Mr. William Dawkins&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Rappahannock July the  26:  1727<lb/>
Sir&mdash;<lb/>
<p>herein you have the Seconds of the former bills <lb/>of Exchange Also five Small first bills to <sic corr="wit">witt</sic> William Eustace on yorSelf <lb/>for &pound;1:12"&mdash; Robert Carter &amp; <note n="RL"><abbr expan="Richard">R:</abbr> Lee</note> on <abbr expan="Ditto">Do:</abbr> for &pound;14:12"1 <note n="GT">George <sic corr="Turberville">Turvbervile</sic></note> <lb/>on <abbr expan="Nathaniel">Nat</abbr> Gundry for &pound;2:16:6 Peter Pressly on <abbr expan="Ditto">Do:</abbr> for &pound;3"6 and <abbr expan="Thomas">Thos.</abbr></p>


<pb n="4"/><lb/><lb/>
<note target="n6">Lee</note> on <note n="JB3">John Burridge</note> for &pound;16:8"11 Amounting to Thirty Eight <abbr expan="pounds">pds:</abbr> <lb/>Fourteen and Eleven pence,<lb/><lb/>

<p>On the 25th of May I drew on you to <note n="RJ"><abbr expan="Robert">Robt:</abbr> Jones</note> for &pound;15/&mdash; <lb/>On the the 3d June I drew on you to Colonel <sic corr="Braxton">Braxston</sic> for &pound;182:5:11. <lb/>Colonel Page and I drew on you to <note n="CS1">Mr. Stagg</note> for &pound;8"-"- and to <note n="ECB"><abbr expan="Doctor">Doctr.</abbr> <lb/>Nicholas </note>for &pound;117"18"2, on Accot. of <note n="NB">Mr. Burwells</note> Estate&mdash;</p>

<p>Mr. <note n="RL">Richard Lee</note> and I have <add place="supralinear">drawn</add> on you on Accot of the <abbr expan="Orphan">Orph:</abbr> <lb/>of <note target="n7">Hancock Lee</note> to <note n="WS">William Strother</note> for &pound;11"-"- to <abbr expan="Elizabeth">Eliz:</abbr> Lee &pound;7"10 <lb/>to Robert Carter &pound;14:12:1 These I think are all the bills you are to be <lb/>advised of at present&mdash;</p>

<p>Herewith comes an Invoice for Some goods in the <lb/>buying and <sic corr="Shipping">Shiping</sic> of which I desire you will follow the directions <lb/>therein given its Considerably larger <sic corr="than">then</sic> I have had from you these <lb/>late years,</p>

<p>The other day I <abbr expan="received">rec'd</abbr> from <abbr expan="George">Geo:</abbr> Devenport <abbr expan="Your">Yr.</abbr> Debt from <lb/>William Devenport for Thirty Shillings and Six which you must charge <lb/>me with I See little hopes of getting any more Except from two or three <lb/>and when they will be able to pay I cant tell <note target="n8">Skrine</note> tells me he <sic corr="hath">has</sic> <lb/>Sent you <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> for his Debt and I <sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> it because I heard nothing <lb/>from you this year about him</p>

<p>I <sic corr="Called">Calld</sic> on board the Carter last night Dove is a little ailing <lb/>of the Gout instead of <sic corr="Increasing">Encreasing</sic> he grows Short in his hopes he<del>ll</del> will fall <lb/>Short of 800 hundred hogsheads reckons to be ready for Sailing about the 10th next <lb/>Month he is in some hopes of making a little freight by Some <sic corr="Walnut">Wallnut</sic> <lb/>plank,</p>

<p>Several ways <sic corr="we">wee</sic> have the news of <sic corr="raising">raiseing</sic> the Seige of <lb/><note target="n9">Gibralter </note>and it is brought from <name type="city"><sic corr="New">new</sic> York</name> that the differences between <lb/>the Contending Powers are to be Settled in a Congress how true <sic corr="we">wee</sic> must <lb/>leave to Time I am</p>

<closer>Sir&mdash;<lb/><lb/>Yor: very humble <add place="supralinear">Ob<corr resp="editor">[edient]</corr></add> Servt:&mdash;
</closer>
<sic corr="herein">here in</sic> I Send you two Small bills of <lb/>Exchange to wit Hugh Brent on yourself for 1:8:9 <lb/>James Ball on <abbr expan="Joseph">Jos:</abbr> Ball for &pound;3:7:3 <lb/>which I desire Credit for&mdash;<lb/><lb/>

Per <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Trice<lb/>Copy per Carter</seg><lb/><lb/>


<seg type="postscript">
<pb n="5"/><lb/><lb/>

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Added to Mr. Dawkins the 27 July<lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Rappahannock, <abbr expan="August">Augst:</abbr> the 22d: 1727<lb/>
Sir,	&mdash;<lb/>
<p><sic corr="We">Wee</sic> are now come to the Time of the <name type="ship">Carters </name> <sic corr="Sailing">Saleing</sic> <lb/>She falls Short Considerably of 800 hogsheads which I am <sic corr="Satisfied">Satisfyed</sic> is <lb/>partly owing to her being so late a Ship had she bin in one month <lb/>Sooner she would not have bin a hogshead short I cant Say but <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Dove <lb/>has done his utmost and whoever had bin her Master I <sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> he <lb/>would have met with the same fate; if you cannot make her an <sic corr="earli">early</sic><lb/>er ship it is my Present thoughts She will be in danger of faring a<lb/>nother year as badly as she has done this, I have done her all the Service <lb/>I possibly could have loaded upon her 150 hogsheads but all would not do <lb/>I Shall leave the rest of the <sic corr="Story">Storey</sic> to Doves telling</p>

<p>herewith Send you A Copy of my Invoice also Seconds <lb/>of Some <del>other</del> former bills likewise a bill of Lading for 76 hogsheads of my <lb/>own crops on board the Carter they are <sic corr="marked">markt</sic> of 2 marks 20 of them <lb/>with the mark I used to send to <note n="MP2">Mr. Perry</note> making my Consignments <lb/>this year near 100 hogsheads <sic corr="hoping">hopeing</sic> I Shall not come <sic corr="off">of</sic> as some times I <lb/>have done the larger my business hath bin the worse hath bin my <lb/>fare You have here <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Doves bills of Exchange upon you for &pound;41:18:4 <lb/>which I desire Credit for I have desired Dove to bring me in a few things <lb/><del>which</del> I have <sic corr="ordered">orderd</sic> him to apply to you for the money to pay for <del>them</del> <lb/>for.</p>

<p>herein I Send you also Six Small billsof Exchange to wit <lb/>Margret Rimor on Thomas Longman  <name type="place">Bristol</name> for &pound;2:6:10&mdash;<lb/><name type="person">Henry Stevenson</name> on <note target="n10"><name type="person">Peter How</name></note> &amp; Company in <name type="place">Whitehaven </name> &pound;3:-:- <lb/><note n="NS"><name type="person">Nick Smith</name></note> on <note n="JK">John King</note> Bristol for &pound;12:9:5 <name type="person"><abbr expan="Charles">Cha:</abbr> Broad<lb/>water</name> on <note n="JH2"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Hyde</note> &pound;3:17:4 <note target="n11">John Fitzhugh</note> on <name type="person"><abbr expan="Walter">Walt.</abbr> Lutwidge </name><lb/><name type="place">Whitehaven </name>&pound;5:2:10 <note n="LCF"><name type="person">Henry Fitzhugh</name></note> on <note target="n12"><name type="person">Foster Cunliffe</name></note> <abbr expan="Liverpool">Level.</abbr> <lb/>for &pound;14&mdash; Amounting to Forty pound, Sixteen Shillngs and five <lb/>Pence which I desire your <abbr expan="Management">managemt:</abbr> of</p>

<p>I have this day drawn upon you for &pound;8 to Mrs. <note target="n13"><abbr expan="Elizabeth">Eliz</abbr> <lb/>Young</note> and for &pound;92:10 to <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> <note target="n14"><abbr expan="William">Wm:</abbr> Denton </note>of <abbr expan="Liverpool">Lev:</abbr> these Sums I <lb/>desire you to pay on my Accot. Wishing the Carter a Safe passage to <lb/>you I take my leave at present. I am </p><lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sir, <lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Yor: very humble Servt.&mdash;<lb/>
per the Carter

</seg>

</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copies consulted:</hi></hi> The original letter and post scripts are in Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1]  The <hi rend="italics">Bailey</hi> was a London ship owned by William Dawkins and commanded at various times by Adam Graves (1725-1730) and by Thomas Dove (1731-1732). She was a vessel of some 250 tons and carried 15-17 crew members. (<cit><bibl>Survey report 6801 summarizing Adm. 68/195, 156v, and other data in Adm. 68/194 and /196, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small  Special Collections Library, University of Virginia;</bibl></cit> A letter of Carter's to Dawkins <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C32e12b.html">May 12, 1732,</xref> refers to "your ship Bailey." as does a letter of August 10, 1733, from Carter's executors to Dawkins. [<cit><bibl>Lloyd T. Smith, Jr., <hi rend="italics">ed.</hi> <title>The Executors' Letters of Robert Carter of Corotoman, 1732-1738. </title> (Irvington, VA: Foundation for Historic Christ  Church, 2010) p. 76].</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2"> [2] A bill of exchange is a kind of check or promissory note without interest.  It is used primarily in international trade, and is a written order by one person to pay another a specific sum on a specific date sometime in the future.  If the bill of exchange is drawn on a bank, it is called a bank draft.  If it is drawn on another party, it is called a trade draft.  Sometimes a bill of exchange will simply be called a draft, but whereas a draft is always  negotiable (transferable by endorsement), this is not necessarily true of a bill of exchange. (<cit><bibl><xref to="Ext6">"Dictionary of  Financial Scam Terms,"</xref> 8/22/2005</bibl></cit>)</note>


<note id="n3">[3] John Taliaferro (1687-1744),  would be one of the first justices of Caroline County in 1728, and sheriff of that county in 1730. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:87, 98, 105, 172, 188, 195, 215,</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Watkinson was captain of the <hi rend="italics">Vine,</hi> a ship that may have been owned by Micajah Perry. (<xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C24c25b.html">Carter to Pemberton</xref>, March 25, 1724.)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] The 140 ton <hi rend="italics">Welcome</hi> was owned by London merchant James Bradley to whom Carter would write about her on <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27e17a.html">May 17, 1727</xref>. John Trice (Frice) was her captain, 1723-1727. (<cit><bibl>Adm 68/195, 154r, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5]  Thomas Lee (1690-1750) of Westmoreland County was the son of Richard Lee II, and nephew of Edmund Jenings; he would build "Stratford," and succeed Carter on the Council. For a good article on Thomas Lee, see  that <A HREF="http://www.stratfordhall.org/thomas.html?RESEARCH">by Jeanne A. Calhoun </A>on Stratford plantation's website. (<cit><bibl>Burton J. Hendrick. <title>The Lees of Virginia: Biography of a Family.</title> [Boston: Little Brown, 1935]. pp. 48, 51, etc.</bibl></cit>)</note>

 <note id="n7">[7] Hancock Lee (1653-1709) was an intimate friend of Robert Carter who was named in Lee's will as "a good friend," and appointed one of the trustees of his children.  (<cit><bibl n="B11">Lee. <title>Lee Chronicle . . .</title> pp. 33-35.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n8">[8] William Skreen of Hanover Parish, Richmond County, and two others had taken a patent for 1020 acres in what was then Essex County August 17, 1720. A patent held by William Skrien (Skreen, Skrine) is referred to in a number of patents taken out in St. George's Parish, Spotsylvania County, in the 1720s. (<cit><bibl> Nell M. Nugent. <title>Cavaliers and Pioneers: Abstract of Virginia Land Patents and Grants.</title> [Richmond: Virginia State Library, 1979] 3(1695-1732):198, 222, 308, 317, 411.</bibl></cit> ) </note>

<note id="n9">[9] In early 1727, Britain was allied with France and Prussia against Spain and Austria, and the Spanish had laid siege to Gibralter; it was not successful. The conflict would end in 1729 with the treaty of Seville by which Britain obtained Gibralter. (<cit><bibl>J. H. Plumb. <title>England in the Eighteenth Century (1714-1815).</title> [Hammersmith, Middlesex: Penguin Books, 1953] pp. 64-65.</bibl></cit>) </note>

<note id="n10">[10] Peter How was a merchant of Whitehaven (on the Irish sea in northwest England), who, with Richard Kelsick, traded with the Fredericksburg, Virginia, area from the early 18th century. "In 1745, Peter How and Richard Kelsick built a store on the corner of Caroline and Hanover streets (Lot 16). While Kelsick continued to be based on the Northern Neck, How ran the Fredericksburg store, returning to Whitehaven sometime before 1756. The store operation evidently continued, for his ships made the annual voyage into the 1760s. The property was acquired in 1767 by James Ritchie &amp; Co. of Glasgow; but How was back in Spotsylvania in the 1770s pursuing debtors." (<cit><bibl>Paula S. Felder. "Fredericksburg and Whitehaven Connection to English Port a Forgotten Chapter in Area's Colonial History Living-history Program," Fredericksburg Free-Lance Star, 7/2/2005.</bibl></cit>)  "He had interests in coal and iron-ore mines and set up an iron-working forge at Low Mill in 1750. Debts incurred by the forge and the decline in the tobacco trade may have contributed to his bankruptcy in 1763."  Notes on a portrait of  "Mrs Peter How and her Two Children, Peter and Christian,"  http://www.artfund.org/acq/artworkDetail4_5.asp?appref=2247, 2/22/2006. )</note>

<note id="n11">[11] John Fitzhugh (d. 1733) of Stafford County, a younger son of William Fitzhugh of "Bedford." He was a burgess from Stafford in 1727. (<cit><bibl>"The Fitzhugh Family." <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography.</title> 7[1899-1900]: 317-19.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n12">[12]  Foster Cunliffe (d. 1767) was a merchant and prominent citizen of Liverpool who worked to expand manufacturing and the capacity of the harbor; he served a number of terms as mayor.  He and Richard Gildart undertook "a major reorginization of business with Maryland and Virginia . . . beginning in the early 1720's [they] sent numerous factors to the region." They established stores in which retail goods were sold, purchased the produce of the region, had it ready for loading when ships arrived, and also moved into the sale of slaves. (<cit><bibl>James A. Picton, <hi rend="italics">ed.</hi> <title>Liverpool Municipal Archives and Records. . . .</title> [Liverpool, 1907.] pp. 27, 31, 79, 90, 96, etc.</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl>Paul G. Clemens. "The Rise of Liverpool, 1665-1750." <title>Economic History Review.</title> 24[May 1976]:211-225.</bibl></cit>)</note>
 
<note id="n13">[13] Mrs. Elizabeth Young was Carter's housekeeper. He had agreed  with her for one year's service in 1724 but found her satisfactory for a longer term. She went to England in May 1728. (DiaryJune 2,  1727, and this letter for her first name. <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C28e08a.html">Carter to Pemberton</xref>  May 8, 1728, for her sailing to England.)</note>

<note id="n14">[14] The <hi rend="italics">John &amp; Betty</hi> was a Liverpool ship owned by merchant John Pemberton; she often carried slaves into the colony. In 1726 the captain was John Gale, and in the next year, she was commanded by a Captain William Denton. The ship would be lost in 1729. (<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 18, n. 23</bibl></cit>; <cit><bibl><xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C30d15c.html">Carter to Pemberton,</xref> April 15, 1730;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl><xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27f28c.html">Carter to William Dawkins,</xref> June 28, July 26, and August 22, 1727, for Denton's first name.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2003, was revised January 9, 2013, and December 18, 2014, to strengthen the footnotes and modern language version text.</hi></note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>