<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27f21a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Randolph, June 21, 1727
</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 11 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27f21a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003, 2012</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Randolph, June 21, 1727
</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-06-21</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27f21aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-06-21"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27f21a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Randolph, June 21, 1727
</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to John Randolph, June 21, 1727, attorney general of the colony, to obtain his legal advice concerning the demand of the governor of Maryland that a Virginia citizen, Richard Thacker, who had been robbed by Maryland men at a house in King William County, Virginia, appear before the Maryland governor. Carter notes that the governor has not written to Carter (then acting governor of Virginia) to have the accused persons arrested and brought before a Virginia court to determine the facts. He has decided to refer the matter to Randolph before taking any action.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="JR">John Randolph,</note> June 21, 1727
</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-06-21">June the. 21st: 1727</date><lb/>
Mr. John Randolph<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>Here is a Case of an Extraordinary nature <lb/>&amp; of the first Impression <add place="supralinear">within</add> my Experience come before me and attend<lb/>ed with so many difficulties that I do not care to take any measures <lb/>in it without your advice and Assistance. A Robbery Committed <add place="supralinear">by some inhabitants of <abbr expan="Maryland">Maryld:</abbr></add> <lb/>upon the Bearer Richard Thacker at the house of one George Yeates <lb/>in King William County. <hi rend="underline">The <note target="n1"><abbr expan="Governor">Govr:</abbr> of Maryland</note> by his Letter,</hi> <lb/>A Deposition of the Facts taken before Colonel Phillip Lee One of the <lb/>Judges of that province <add place="supralinear">a Letter from</add> The <abbr expan="Governor">Govr: </abbr>requiring Thacker the Injured <lb/>person to attend him with this deposition <del>and</del> <add place="supralinear">a Verbal</add> Order <add place="supralinear">to</add> him (as <lb/>he informs me) without <sic corr="writing ">writeing</sic> to apply to me for Justice <lb/><del>against these Robbers</del> I have had my thoughts upon Several <lb/>ways <del>of proceeding</del> first to write to the <abbr expan="Governor">Govr: </abbr>that if he thought <lb/>fit to have these Criminals apprehended and <sic corr="delivered">deliverd</sic> over to <lb/>one of our <sic corr="Sheriffs">Sherifs</sic> upon <sic corr="Potomac">Patowmack</sic> to take care of their Con<lb/>veyance to the <sic corr="Sheriff">Sherif</sic><del>s</del> of King William and a Court by him to be <lb/>Called for Examination in <add place="supralinear">to</add> this Case in order to their <abbr expan="Committment">Committmt.</abbr> <lb/>to our publick <sic corr="Jail">Goal</sic> If they find the facts proved <del>upon them</del> <lb/>but upon further Consideration I have Concluded it most Ad<lb/><sic corr="visable">viseable</sic> to Send this Complain<add place="supralinear">ant</add> unto you to give <abbr expan="directions">directs:</abbr> for <lb/>the proper <del>Prosess</del> Process whether you will think it necessary <lb/>that the <del>Examination</del> <add place="supralinear">Depositions</add> of the <sic corr="Witnesses">Wittnesses</sic> to these facts be first taken <lb/>by Some of the Justices of that County who may Issue process after <lb/>these accused persons or whether a precept from me <add place="supralinear">to</add> One of our North<lb/>ern <sic corr="Sheriffs">Sherrifs</sic> to receive these prisoners from the <abbr expan="Maryland">Maryl'd</abbr> <abbr expan="Government">Governmt</abbr> <lb/>In Order to their being Carried to our <sic corr="Jail">Goal </sic>or what other way <lb/>you Shall think more proper I Shall Leave to yor. Judgement</p>

<p>Upon Examing Thacker and his Companion <add place="supralinear">Brumfeild</add> <lb/>who was with him when he was robbed you will be let into a full <lb/>light of the Circumstances of the matter If you are of Opinion a pre<lb/>cept immedately from me will do the business you must Send it ready <lb/><sic corr="prepared">prepard</sic> for my Signing I Suppose Thacker must Enter into recog=<lb/>=nizance to prosecute and Brumfeild also to give Evidence <del>upon</del><add place="supralinear"> at</add> 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
the <sic corr="Trial">Tryal</sic> but I <del>will</del> <add place="supralinear">must</add> not <sic corr="Invade"><sic corr="Invade">Envade</sic></sic> your province who know much better I am </p>

<closer>Sir&mdash; <lb/>Yor: most humble Servt:</closer>


</div1>

</body>




<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. There is a nineteenth-century copy of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia. The unknown copyist recorded this text probably from the letter book which is used here as the copy text. </note>

<note>"Corotoman," the name of Carter's home, the county and colony have been added for clarity to the  unheaded draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Charles Calvert (1699-1751), fifth Lord Baltimore, was governor of Maryland,1720-1727.  (<cit><bibl><xref to="http://www.msa.md.gov/msa/speccol/sc3500/sc3520/000100/000195/html/msa00195.html">"Maryland State Archives Biographical Files."</xref>6/4/2003; 10/26/2012.)</bibl></cit></note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2003, was revisedNovember 6, 2012,  to strengthen the  modern language version text.</hi></note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>