<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27f02c">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to William Robertson, June 2, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27f02c.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Robertson, June 2, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-06-02</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27f02cT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-06-02"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27f02c.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Robertson, June 2, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to William Robertson, June 2, 1727, clerk of the Council, asking him to review a letter and give "Mr. Cary" advice "in the Duty of his Office" as a friend because Cary "Seems not yet well to understand." He sends Robertson all the news he has received from letters and gazettes just arrived concerning the siege of Gibraltar and concerns in Britain.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="WR">William Robertson,</note> June 2, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock<add resp="editor"> [Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-06-02">June 2d: 1727</date><lb/>
Mr. Wm: Robertson<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>



<p>The Enclosed will inform you of the business <lb/>the Bearer comes upon I have advised him to call upon <lb/>you in his way that you may give <note target="n1">Mr. Cary</note> your advice <lb/>as a friend in the Duty of his Office <add place="supralinear">which</add> as to me he Seems not <add place="supralinear">yet</add> well <lb/>to understand The Bearer will show you Mr. Carys Permit <lb/>however I have Sent you a Copy of it and in what you Say <lb/>to him I hope you will lay a Side all private Views. after you <lb/>have perused my Letter I desire <sic corr="you'll">you'l</sic> Seal it up and deliver <lb/>it to the Master.</p>

<p>A Ship from Bristol arrived here this day <lb/>brings to me Several Letters from London of the 15 &amp; 16 of Ma<add resp="editor">[r]</add>ch <lb/>Also Some prints I mean <sic corr="Gazettes">Gazetts</sic> to the 4th: of <abbr expan="March">Mar.</abbr> and a Vote <lb/>of the Commons of the 13th: of <abbr expan="March">Mar:</abbr> The nation is a fire, At the 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<note target="n2">Memorial of Monsieur De Palm</note> the <sic corr="Commons">Comons</sic> address  <del>[illegible]</del><lb/>so do Several of the great bodies of the nation and no doubt addresses <lb/>will fly from all parts The royal Burroughs of Scotland have <lb/><abbr expan="Addressed">Address'd</abbr> The Deputy <abbr expan="Lieutenants">Leiuts:</abbr> and the Justices of the Peace for the County <lb/>of Middlesex The <sic corr="President">Prisedent</sic> Vice President and the whole <lb/>body of <sic corr="Artillery">Artillary</sic> of the City of London The Mayor &amp;c: of Devon <lb/>of Leeds, of <sic corr="Worsham">Warcham</sic> in Dorset. of Thetford. of Kingstone up<lb/>on Thames, of Lewis in <sic corr="Sussex">Sussexs</sic> as to the <note target="n3">Seige of Gibralter</note> there <lb/>is nothing new about it The Master who left Bristol the 1st <lb/>of <sic corr="Appril">Aprill</sic> Says there <add place="supralinear">is</add> no manner of fear of the fate of that place <lb/><note target="n4">Mr. Bradley</note> Says they are in daily Expectation the <sic corr="war">warr</sic> <lb/>will be declared against the <sic corr="Emperor">Empourer </sic><add place="supralinear">In</add> which he reckons <del>will<lb/>Engage</del> most of the powers in Europe will be Engaged on one Side <lb/>or the other, <note n="MP2">Mr. Perry</note> is afraid if the blaze break out if will not <lb/>be Easily Extinguished, Mr. Cary of the 22d: of March Says there <lb/>is little <sic corr="likelihood">likelyhood</sic> of the Spaniards taking Gibraltar and so hopes <lb/>matters will Soon come to an Accommodation for general <lb/>peace thus you have the <sic corr="Chief">Cheif</sic> of my <sic corr="public">publick</sic> news I am </p>

<closer><hi rend="underline">Sir</hi> <lb/>Yor: most humble Servt:</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] The Mr. Cary to whom Carter refers may have been Wilson Cary who had been appointed naval officer of the lower district of James River on 1726 April 28, but there were several men of the name at this time. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:99-100. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Carter's reference has not been identified.</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Britain had seized Gibraltar from Spain during a war in 1704, and had been given it permanently by the 1713 Treaty of Utrecht. However, Spain was never happy with the loss, and had threatened, and then laid siege to Gibraltar in March 1727. The effort was unsuccessful and abandoned in June of that year. The treaty of Seville of 1729 ceded Gibraltar to Britain. (<cit><bibl>"Gibraltar" http://www.worldstatesmen.org/Gibraltar.html  5/28/2003</bibl></cit>)</note>



<note id="n4">[3] James Bradley was a London merchant with whom Carter dealt from at least 1723 until his death. As noted in his letter to Bradley of 1727 May 17, Bradley owned the <hi rend="italics">Welcome,</hi> but little information about Bradley has been located.</note>





</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>