<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; 

<!NOTATION html SYSTEM "HTML">
<!ENTITY Ext6 SYSTEM "http://www.fraudaid.com\/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms\/bill_of_exchange.htm" NDATA html>

]>
<TEI.2 id="C27f28e">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, June 28, July 26, and August 23,1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 23 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27f28e.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003, 2013</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, June 28, July 26, and August 23,1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>6 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, and Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-06-28</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27f28eT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>6 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-06-28"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27f28e.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, June 28, July 26, and August 23,1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Liverpool merchant John Pemberton, June 28, 1727, enclosing a bill of lading for tobacco other than 17 hogsheads that should have been shipped on the <hi rend="italics">John and Betty.</hi> He tells the merchant that 5 of those hogsheads had been damaged in the collapse of a storage house, but he does not know how to ship it except to Liverpool. He tells Pemberton to charge his account with &pound;62 due Pemberton, and also for "Gales bill protested." He also sends two bills of exchange , an invoice for goods  which he wishes to have shipped by an early ship, and a bill of lading  for 30 hogsheads shipped on the <hi rend="italics">Rappahannock.</hi> He concludes by reporting that his negotiation for some of "Esqr. Hallows" land is at a standstill over the price. In a lengthy post script dated July 26th, Carter adds information about other bills of exchange, the safe arrival of Pemberton's slave ship, the <hi rend="italics">John and Betty,</hi> and Carter's handling of the sale of the slaves. In a second lengthy post script dated August 23 Carter encloses a bill of lading for tobacco  and orders that it be "sold at the Mast." He also encloses an account of the sales of slaves and 30 first bills of exchange received during the sale, noting that he is sending second bills of exchange by the <hi rend="italics">Carter.</hi> He and Captain Denton have had a dispute over Carter's role in the sale and the commission charged for his services; he writes that he had undertaken the sale as a favor to Pemberton, an old friend, and that he will deal only with the principal in such matters, not with the ship's master. None of the enclosures mentioned are present.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="JP">John Pemberton,</note> June 28, July 26, and August 23,1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
Mr. John Pemberton&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<date value="1727-06-28">June the. 28th: 1727</date>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>This by <note target="n1">Watkinson</note> brings you a bill of <lb/>Lading but for 17 <abbr expan="hogsheads">hhds:</abbr> of the <note target="n2"><name type="ship">John and Bettys</name></note> <abbr expan="tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr>  he Sent his <lb/>Boat for 5 hhds: more but when the men went for them an Accid<lb/>ent had <sic corr="happened">happend</sic> by the house they were in falling down they had <lb/><sic corr="Suffered">Sufferd</sic> Some damage so they brought them to my house and left <lb/>them behind Immediately they were uncased and all the damaged <lb/><abbr expan="tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> taken out which amounts to no more then 90 pounds weight there <lb/>remains now of that Concern to Ship 17 hhds besides some debts <lb/>outstanding <sic corr="We">Wee</sic> hear nothing of <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Denton yet if he Should <lb/>come it will be impossible for him to get his Load what to do with <lb/>this <abbr expan="tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> I dont know how to Ship it to any other port <sic corr="than">then</sic> yor. own <lb/>I have no orders I hear <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Preston in the <note target="n3"><name type="ship">Mary</name></note> of your Port takes <lb/><sic corr="freight">freit</sic> if I can get him to take it in I think to do it but if I can <lb/>meet with no Opportunity to Ship it I Shall think it a Service <lb/>to you to get it home in Some of my own Craft for its preservation</p>

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<p><add resp="editor">[Th]</add>e outstanding Sterling debts amounting to Sixty two pounds I <lb/><del>have got <add place="supralinear">not yet <unclear>[[ . . . ]</unclear></add></del> in <add place="supralinear">to pay which</add><del>you must pay your Self and  Dentons Accot. with <lb/>that Sum</del> I have not yet got all in however I am desirous you Should <lb/>be paid therefore <add place="supralinear">please to</add> <sic corr="debit">devite</sic> my Accot: <del>for</del> that Sum also you must  &mdash;<lb/>charge my Accot: with Gales bill protested &pound;15:18- which is money <lb/>I Shall be out of a year if not two or three&mdash;</p>

<p>	Herein are two Small <note target="n4">bills of Exchange</note> drawn upon <lb/>your Self which I desire Credit for <abbr expan="Thomas">Thos:</abbr> Beale for &pound;5:10::17 Robert <lb/>Gordon for &pound;4"10"8 3/4&mdash;Also an Invoice for Some goods which I <lb/>desire my be Sent in In one of you<corr resp="editor">[r]</corr> forwardest Ships, the goods coming <lb/>so late this year was an inconveniency to me You have likewise <lb/>now a bill of Lading for 30 hhds: of my own Crop <abbr expan="tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> in the <note target="n5"><name type="ship">Rappahannock</name></note> <lb/>I take all the Care I can to make it good hope it will prove so and meet <lb/>with a Comfortable Sale I have not news yet of the Arrival of <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Morton in the <note target="n6"><name type="ship">Content,</name></note></p>

<p><note n="JR">Mr. Randolph</note> <note target="n7"><abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> Hallows Lawyer</note> has had <abbr expan="Several">Sevl:</abbr> <lb/><sic corr="discourses">discours's</sic> with me about the Purchase of his Land his lowest <abbr expan="demand">dem'd</abbr> <lb/><sic corr="hath">has</sic> bin Seven hundred pounds I have bid him five and will give <lb/>no more thus that matter Stands as to me I remain </p>

<closer>Sir&mdash;<lb/>Yor: very humble Servt:
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>per <note target="n8">Watkinson</note>
<lb/>Copy per <note target="n9">Trice</note></seg><lb/>


<lb/><pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>

<seg type="postscript">Mr. <abbr expan="John ">Jno.</abbr> Pemberton Added to his Letter June 28&nbsp;&nbsp; Rappahannock, July the 26th: 1727<lb/><lb/>
Sir&mdash;<lb/>
<p>In mine of the 3d: of June you were advised of a bill of <lb/>Exchange I had drawn upon you for &pound;300/-/- to <note n="MCB">George <sic corr="Braxton">Braxston</sic></note> two days <lb/>after I drew on you for &pound;45"3 to <note n="WS">William Strother</note> the 13th: Instant 

<pb n="4"/><lb/><lb/>
I draw on you for &pound;8"-"- to <note target="n10">Mrs: Young</note> herewith Comes the Seconds <lb/>of the former bills also a Copy of my Invoice</p>

<p>I am pleased that I can give you the welcome news of the <lb/>Safe Arrival of the <note target="n11"><name type="ship">John and Betty</name></note> <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Denton he came in the 15th Instant <lb/>his Cargo about One hundred and forty Slaves thirty six or thirty Seven <lb/>of them men 55 women the rest Boys and Girls many of them very <lb/>Small <sic corr="We">Wee</sic> began the Sale the 20th: and there is now but 15 remains <lb/>you must <sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> that so <sic corr="disproportioned">disproportiond</sic> a Cargo will turn out but low <lb/>I have done my utmost for your Service I am in hopes to bring them <lb/>out at 16&pound; round I have bin under the necessity to take a great deal <lb/>of Cash at 15 per<abbr expan="Cent">Ct:</abbr> which is our Standard to make it Sterling I let a good <lb/>
Draft of <sic corr="these">ths</sic> small ones go for Currt. money what to do with the Cash <lb/>I Have not yet <sic corr="determined">determind.</sic> Denton is very much against remitting <lb/>any of it in Specie advises Strongly to offer 20 perCt. for bills of Exchange <lb/>which will be five per Ct. lost to you even upon our Sterling Sales nay <lb/>he is <sic corr="desirous">desireous</sic> I Should take Scotch bills rather than fail I Shall Consult <lb/>your Interest the best I can. I Serve him all that I am able towards his <lb/>Loading <sic corr="we">wee</sic> do not yet See he will Compass above 60 or 70 hogsheads <lb/>I purpose to Ship your <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> that Watkinson left out and reckon I <lb/>I Shall be able to make them up 40 hogsheads with my own,</p>

<p>Whats become of <note target="n12">Christian</note> <sic corr="we">wee</sic> dont hear Denton <lb/><sic corr="reckoned">reckond</sic> he would be here before him I Suppose he writes to you at <lb/>large himself I Shall give you no further trouble at present remain<lb/>ing 
</p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sir&mdash;<lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Yor: very humble Servt&mdash;<lb/>
per <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Trice<lb/>
Copy per Denton</seg>

<seg type="postscript">

<pb n="5"/><lb/><lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Added to Mr. Pembertons July the 26th: 1727<lb/>
Sir,	&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Rappahannock, &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Augst: the 23d: 1727<lb/><lb/>

<p>We are now come to the departure of the John &amp; <lb/>Betty herein comes a bill of Lading for 25 hogsheads of my own <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> <lb/>also for Sixteen hogsheads belonging to the last years Cargo and for 6 hogsheads <lb/>this years Purchase as for my own <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> my Desire is that it be sold <lb/>at the Mast as Soon as it gets home Its none of my crops and I do not <lb/>Expect an <note target="n13">Inland Sale</note> You are to observe I have deducted no Salary nor for these <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> <lb/>nor for those that went by <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Watkinson I am Con<lb/>tented to take it as I did before upon the Sales</p>

<p>herewith Comes a General Accot. of the <abbr expan="Negroes">Negs.</abbr> imported <lb/>this year in the John and Betty and how they have bin disposed <lb/>of Also thirty first bills of Exchange Amounting to Seventeen hundred <lb/>Twenty nine pounds Seventeen Shillings for this money I have <lb/>already taken my Salary In my bill <del>to Mr. Pemberton</del> <add place="supralinear">on You</add> I have <lb/>paid <del>him</del> the odd money of Thirteen pounds Fifteen Shillings &amp; nine <lb/>pence due upon the Exchange here is also an Accot: of the Cash <abbr expan="received">rec'd</abbr> 


<pb n="6"/><lb/><lb/>
<abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Dentons <abbr expan="receipt">rect.</abbr> for what <add place="supralinear">money</add> he had A Copy of h<add resp="editor">[is Letter?]</add> <sic corr="desiring">desire<lb/>ing</sic> me I would take the Cash at 20 <abbr expan="per cent">perCt</abbr>. Together wi<add resp="editor">[th the Acc]</add>ot <lb/>of the marks Numbers and weights of the Sixteen and Six hogsheads</p>
 
<p>I now Send away the Second bills of Exchange for the <lb/><sic corr="Aforesaid">Afforesaid</sic> Sum by the Carter bound out with your Ship <add resp="editor">[There]</add> are <lb/>three <add place="supralinear">sick</add> Negroes to sell and Several Debts yet to be <abbr expan="received">rec'd</abbr> I ca<add resp="editor">[nnot]</add> <lb/>Settle a Stated accot. at Present will Endeavr. to do it by a <sic corr="later">latter</sic> Ship</p>

<p><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Denton and I have had some words at parting <lb/>now at the Close of every thing he grumbles much at my Salary <lb/>of 10 <abbr expan="per Cent">perCt.</abbr> <sic corr="Although">Altho</sic> he knew all along I would take no less <add place="supralinear"><hi rend="italics">(as by <abbr expan="Several">Sevl:</abbr> Expressions of his appeard)</hi></add> he was <lb/>so Scrupulous to demand a Sight of your Letter to me to See whe<lb/>ther you had <sic corr="Ordered">Orderd</sic> the Ship to my dispose in case of her coming <lb/>hither he also was Offended that I had not <abbr expan="Endorsed">Endd.</abbr> the bills of Exchange to you <lb/>&amp; Company I should have pleased him in this but he Spoke too late <lb/>for I had <sic corr="Endorsed">Endorst</sic> the bills before he <sic corr="altered">alterd</sic> the mark of this year<add resp="editor">['s] </add> <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> <lb/>but that I am not at all <sic corr="disturbed">disturbd</sic> at Esteem the Sale to be so well <lb/>made that I please my Self with hopes you will be very well <sic corr="Satisfied">Satisfyed</sic> <lb/>with it and not <del>[illegible]</del> <add place="supralinear">Envy</add> <del>ing</del> me my Salary. If the Gentleman had had <lb/>the Sale himself which he Seems now to think himself capable of <lb/>I am Strongly of the Opinion (that his Salary be what it would) You <lb/>would have no reason to think the Commission I have taken too much <lb/>I am not <add place="supralinear">fond</add> of business of this nature <sic corr="It was">twas</sic> in Service to you an old <lb/>friend that I undertook it at first I have no fault to find with <lb/><abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Denton in respect to his business I take him to be an indus<lb/>trious diligent man and deserves his Employ but wh<del>th</del>en <add place="supralinear">ever</add> <del>as</del> I am <lb/><sic corr="Concerned">Concernd</sic> in business of this <del>[illegible]</del> <add place="supralinear">Sort</add> I will have no bargain to make <lb/>with the Master but will be above any <sic corr="Control">Controul</sic> of his I must<lb/> note to you I have bought his privilege Slaves and the Doctors <lb/>two men two women and a boy <note n="JG2">Mr. Grimes</note> had Shall not give <lb/>you any further trouble at Present Only to wish the Ship Safe to</p> 

You remaining<lb/><lb/> 

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sir&mdash;<lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Yor. very humble Servt.<lb/><lb/>

We have no news of <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Christian <lb/>have lately heard of the Arrival <lb/>of <note target="n6"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Morton</note>&mdash;

</seg>

</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copies consulted:</hi></hi> Original letter and first post script from Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. Second post script from Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. Carter has edited this draft as is indicated by the use of italics.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Watkinson was captain of the <hi rend="italics">Vine,</hi> a ship that may have been owned by Micajah Perry. (Carter to Pemberton, 1724 March 25)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] The <hi rend="italics">John &amp; Betty</hi> was a Liverpool ship owned by merchant John Pemberton; she often carried slaves into the colony. In 1726 the captain was John Gale, and in the next year, she was commanded by a Captain William Denton. The ship would be lost in 1729. (<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 18, n. 23</bibl></cit>; <cit><bibl><xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C30d15c.html">Carter to Pemberton,</xref> April 15, 1730;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl><xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27f28c.html">Carter to William Dawkins,</xref> June 28, July 26, and August 22, 1727, for Denton's first name.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3]  The <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi> may have been a Liverpool ship owned by prominent merchant Bryan Blundell of that city. She was taken by the Spanish in October 1730 off Havanna.  (Charles McLean Andrews. <title>Guide to the Materials for American History,</title>  [Washington, D.C.: Carnegie institution of Washington, 1912.]  Part I, Vol. I , p. 256, citing Board of Trade, Commercial Papers,  1716-17   Spanish depredations.)</note>

 <note id="n4"> [4] A bill of exchange is a kind of check or promissory note without interest.  It is used primarily in international trade, and is a written order by one person to pay another a specific sum on a specific date sometime in the future.  If the bill of exchange is drawn on a bank, it is called a bank draft.  If it is drawn on another party, it is called a trade draft.  Sometimes a bill of exchange will simply be called a draft, but whereas a draft is always  negotiable (transferable by endorsement), this is not necessarily true of a bill of exchange. (<cit><bibl><xref to="Ext6">"Dictionary of  Financial Scam Terms,"</xref> 8/22/2005</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] There  were several vessels with the name <hi rend="italics">Rappahannock</hi>. One was based in Liverpool and was commanded by a Captain Francis Etheridge in 1725; she was a 90 ton ship with 13 men. Another of which Charles Whate was captain was of 60 tons with 11 men in 1726/27. Carter's letters mention a Captain Brackhill in 1728, and Captain Loxum in 1733. (<cit><bibl>Adm. 68/194, ff.30, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] The <hi rend="italics">Content</hi> was a Liverpool ship owned by John Pemberton and commanded by various masters including captains Stephenson (1721) , Fowler (1723), and Morton (1727). (<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> pp. 92, 93, 102</bibl></cit>; and Carter to Pemberton, <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C21b14d.html">February 14, 1721,</xref> and this letter.)</note>

<note id="n7">[7] John Hallowes (Hallows) (1615-1657) had come to Maryland as an indentured servant, but later moved to Westmoreland County where he acquired extensive tracts of land. Some of that land was purchased in 1733 by Thomas Lee from Samuel Hallowes of County Lancaster, England, who "as a great nephew of Major John Hallowes," had acquired title in an important legal case decided in 1722. This land became part of Stratford. Carter may have hoped to acquire a tract from Samuel Hallowes to add to Nomini as John Hallowes had lived near that plantation of Carter's. ("Major John Hallowes. 1615-1657." <cit><bibl n="B38">Norris. <title>Westmoreland County, Virginia.</title></bibl></cit> pp. 99-103.)</note>

<note id="n8">[8]  Watkinson was captain of the <hi rend="italics">Vine,</hi> a ship that may have been owned by Micajah Perry. (<xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C24c25b.html">Carter to Pemberton</xref>, March 25, 1724.)</note><lb/>

<note id="n9">[9] The 140 ton <hi rend="italics">Welcome</hi> was owned by London merchant James Bradley to whom Carter would write about her <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27e17a.html">on May 17, 1727.</xref> John Trice (Frice) was her captain, 1723-1727. (<cit><bibl>Adm 68/195, 154r, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n10">[10] Mrs. Elizabeth Young was Carter's housekeeper. He had agreed  with her for one year's service in 1724 but found her satisfactory for a longer term. She went to England in May 1728. (DiaryJune 2,  1727, and <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27f28c.html">Carter to William Dawkins,</xref> June 28, July 26, and August 22, 1727, for her first name. <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C28e08a.html">Carter to Pemberton</xref>  May 8, 1728, for her sailing to England.)</note>

<note id="n11">[11] The <hi rend="italics">John &amp; Betty</hi> was a Liverpool ship owned by merchant John Pemberton; she often carried slaves into the colony. In 1726 the captain was John Gale, and in the next year, she was commanded by a Captain William Denton. The ship would be lost in 1729. (<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 18, n. 23</bibl></cit>; <cit><bibl><xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C30d15c.html">Carter to Pemberton,</xref> April 15, 1730;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl><xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27f28c.html">Carter to William Dawkins,</xref> June 28, July 26, and August 22, 1727, for Denton's first name.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n12">[12] James Christian was captain of the <hi rend="italics">Rose,</hi> a vessel owned by merchant John Pemberton of Liverpool. (See <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C30d15a.html">Carter to Pemberton,</xref> April 15, 1730.) </note>

<note id="n13">[13] Because English law allowed an English purchaser of imported tobacco to apply for rebates of the impost, or duty, if the tobacco was exported from the country, Carter would have expected a discount on the charges on his tobacco sold to English merchants, or inland sales. </note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2003, was revised January 28, 2013,  to strengthen the footnotes and modern language version text.</hi></note>







</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>