<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27g24b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Cary, July 24 and August 22, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 12 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27g24b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Cary, July 24 and August 22, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, and Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-07-24</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27g24bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-07-24"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C2g24b7.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Cary, July 24 and August 22, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Robert Cary, July 24, 1727, to cover a bill of lading (not present) for 12 hogsheads of tobacco and to inform him that he is sending the public papers for forwarding by him as he has received most recent public papers through him. In a post script on August 22, 1727, Carter deals with the problem of Thomas Evans' bankruptcy by informing Cary that he is sending his account with Evans (not present) and a "Short warrant" to empower Cary to act as his attorney in attempting to collect the money Evans owed Carter.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">Robert Cary,</note> July 24 and August 22, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-07-24">July the 27th 1727</date><lb/>
Mr. Robt Cary<lb/>
</dateline>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;to be Copyd&mdash;<salute>Sir&mdash;&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>I have now 12 hhds: of my own crop <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr>
 in the <lb/><note target="n2">Marlborrough</note> <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Buckeridge <sic corr="Consiigned">Consignd</sic> to you a bill of Lading for <lb/>them comes herewith. I hope my Credit with you will answer for the <lb/>Clearing of this <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> If I fall Short now it will be the only time that I <lb/>reckon will happen while our dealings Continue, You must do in the <lb/>matter as you please The Public Expresses I choose to give you the trouble <lb/>of having <abbr expan="received">rec'd</abbr> most of the <sic corr="public">publick</sic> packets under yor. <abbr expan="Cover">Covr:</abbr> I am Sir, </p>

<closer>Yor: most humble Servt:
<lb/><lb/><seg type="postscript">per Buckeridge</seg><lb/><lb/>

<seg type="postscript"><pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Added to Carys July 24th: per the Marlborrough<lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Rappahannock, <abbr expan="August">Augst:</abbr> 22d: 1727<lb/>
	Sir,	<lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;I have little more to Say to you at present only in <lb/>relation to <note n="TE">Mr. Evans</note> Affair a Second Copy of my Accot: against <lb/>him herewith I Send you I have bin in Such a hurry with the Publick <lb/>Affairs that I have not bin able to prepare a power of <sic corr="Attorney">Atturney</sic> in form <lb/>to have <sic corr="Siigned">Signd</sic> in the presence of <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Dove and his men to Qualify you <lb/>to act  in this Affair as you <del>' would</del>do for your Self however herein <lb/>Send you a Short warrant Attested which I hope will do the <lb/>business as well I Shall have no opportunity hereafter by a <abbr expan="London">Lond:</abbr> <lb/>Ship therefore must let the Affair take it<add resp="editor">['s]</add> fate as it will<lb/><lb/>
	&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;If I have Committed any Error in my Accot. Mr. <lb/>Evans books will make everything Clear I am <lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italics">Sir,</hi></hi> <lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italics">Yor. very humble Servt.</hi></hi><lb/><lb/></seg>

<seg type="postscript"><pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
Whereas Mr. Thomas Evans Merchant of London hath lately <lb/><sic corr="failed">faild</sic> in his Credit and a Statute of Bankrupt is taken out against <lb/>him and the Said Thomas Evans Standing Justly in my Debt according <lb/>to the best Calculation I can make by an Accot. Stated and now Sent in <lb/>the Sum of Three hundred ninety three pounds Sixteen Shillings and <lb/>a penny to the End I may <del>[illegible]</del> come in proportion into the <sic corr="benefit">benifit</sic> of the <lb/>Statute I Robert Carter of Virginia <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> have Constituted &amp; appoint<lb/>ed and do by these presents make ordain Constitute and Appoint Mr. <lb/>Robert Cary <abbr expan="Merchant">Mercht.</abbr> of London to be my true and <sic corr="llawful">lawfull</sic> <sic corr="Attorney">Atturney</sic> <lb/>for me and in my name and to my use to treat manage and <lb/>Transact the above Affair And to do and Prosecute at the Law or <lb/>Otherways for recovery of my Said Debt or any part thereof as fully <lb/>and <sic corr="Amptly">Amplely</sic> to all Intents and purposes as I my Self might or Could <lb/>do <sic corr="were">where</sic> I Personally Present Hereby satisfying allowing &amp; Confin<lb/>ing all and whatsoever my Said <sic corr="Attorney">Atturney</sic> Shall do or Cause to be <lb/>done in or about the premisses Witness my hand and Seal This <lb/>22d: day of <abbr expan="August">Augst:</abbr> 1727<lb/></seg>

</closer>
</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copies consulted:</hi></hi> Original letter is from Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. Carter has added in his hand the close to the post script as is indicated by the use of bold italics. The post script is from Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1"> [1] Robert Cary (1685-1751) was a London merchant and member of a family  of which many members were involved in colonial trade. Carter purchased lands from him in King George, Richmond, and Westmoreland counties; he is mentioned in Carter's will. (<cit><bibl>Jacob M. Price. "Who Was John Norton? A Note on the Historical Character of Some Eighteenth-Century Virginia Firms."  <title>William and Mary Quarterly. </title> 3rd. ser. 19[July 1962]:401.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] The <hi rend="italics">Marlborough</hi> was a vessel of 100 tons and 14 men, commanded by George Buckeridge (Buckbridge). (<cit><bibl>Admiralty 68/195, abstracted in Survey Report 6801, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>





</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>