<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; 

<!NOTATION html SYSTEM "HTML">
<!ENTITY Ext6 SYSTEM "http://www.fraudaid.com\/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms\/bill_of_exchange.htm" NDATA html>

]>
<TEI.2 id="C27g03a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Mann Page, July 3 and 15, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27g03a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003, 2013</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Mann Page, July 3 and 15, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-07-03</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27g03aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-07-03"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27g03a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Mann Page, July 3 and 15, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his son-in-law, Mann Page, July 3, 1727, to report that he has met with George Nicholas, husband of his daughter, Elizabeth, to settle accounts due Nicholas from the estate of Elizabeth's first husband, Nathaniel Burwell, for the years 1722 and 1723. (Carter and Page were the administrators of the Burwell estate.) With the assistance of Thomas Edwards, he has decided that Nicholas is due over &pound;367, for which he has drawn bills of exchange which Page must sign. He has sent orders for goods for the estate and the Burwell children. He concludes with affectionate good wishes to Page and his family. In a post script dated July 15th he tells Page that Nicholas also claims part of the  profits of the mill at Carter's Creek for which Carter has not given him an answer.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="MP1">Mann Page,</note> July 3 and 15, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<date value="1727-07-03">July the. 3d: 1727</date><lb/>
</dateline>

</opener>


<p><hi rend="italics">Colonel Page<lb/>Hon:ble Sir&mdash;</hi></p><lb/><lb/>

<p>Finding how unlikely it was for both of us to meet <lb/>together with <note n="ECB">Dr. Nicholas</note> about the Accot. of the profits of <note n="NB">Mr. Burwells</note> <lb/>Estate for the Years 1722 and 1723 I have Set about it with the Assistance <lb/>of <note target="n1">Mr. Edwards</note> and have brought it to a <sic corr="narrow">narro</sic> Compass <sic corr="In">Inn</sic> which I <lb/>hope we have Committed but few Errors Some of the particular Articles <lb/>remain unadjusted which you can most properly give light <sic corr="to,">too,</sic> The <lb/><abbr expan="Doctor">Doctr:</abbr> <sic corr="has">hath</sic> the Accounts with him to give you Satisfaction in the <lb/>Method we have taken,</p>

<p>The ballance we make due to him for these Years fo<add resp="editor">[r]</add> <lb/>a third of the Profits after all proper deductions is three hundred Sixty <lb/>Seven pounds Eighteen Shill<add resp="editor">[ings]</add> and two pence which I have given him 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
Bills of Exchange for and he will address to you for your hand to them also <lb/>he will for Two hundred and Fifty pounds on <note n="MP2">Mr. Perry</note> and for One <lb/>hundred and Seventeen pounds Eighteen Shillings on <note n="WD">Mr. Dawkins
</note></p>

<p>The money <abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> <note target="n3">Henry Willis</note> owed to the Estate coming <lb/>through your hands I desire it might be <sic corr="Lodged">lodgd</sic> with Mr. Dawkins, but <lb/>if I am right in Calculating Mr. Dawkins Accot. I think he will not <lb/>want it all and if it be not too late for you I could wish a hundred pou<add resp="editor">[nds]</add> <lb/>of that money were <sic corr="Ordered">Orderd</sic> to <note target="n4">Mr. Falconer</note> who I reckon will be the <lb/><add resp="editor">[be]</add>st of any of the Merchants unless <sic corr="we">wee</sic> may Conclude he will <lb/>be in Cash for the Ten hhds: Sent him by <note target="n5">Trevisa,</note> by the Time <note target="n6">Buck<lb/>eridge</note> will arrive</p>

<p>I have Sent to Mr. Perry for the large Invoice of goods <lb/>and to Mr. Dawkins for the Childrens things,</p>

<p>I hope this will find your family in good health <lb/>and your Self growing better every day This Family Salutes yours <lb/>with <add place="supralinear">our</add> proper respects I am&mdash;</p>

<closer><seg type="postscript">Added to Colonel Pages last Letter&mdash;&mdash;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;	July the 15th: 1727&mdash;<lb/><lb/>

Sir&mdash;<lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;The above Letter Dr: Nicholas by Some Accident <lb/>happend to loose I have little now to add to it only that the Doctor <lb/>makes a Claim in light of his wife of the third of the profits of the <lb/>Mill at <note n="CC">Carters Creek</note> <sic corr="alleging">alledgeing</sic> that by <add place="supralinear">the</add> will of old <note n="LB"><abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> Burwell</note> his <lb/>Son had a fee Simple in the Mill and that his wife is Dowable I <lb/>give him no answer at Present. It is high time I had my Mares out <lb/>of your Pasture Sometime next week propose to Send for them pray <lb/>God <add place="supralinear">send</add> this find you all in good health,</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. Carter has added the name of the addressee and the salutation to the clerk's draft which is indicated by the use of italics.</note>

<note>The name of Carter's home, the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this draft letter to his son-in-law.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] "Thos. Edwards, a little petty Fogging Lawyer the Clark of our County that hath as much Mettle and more cunning for Contention then his predecessor had" Carter wrote to Landon Jones, <xref to="/users/berkeley/public/C23g22b.xml">July 22, 1723.</xref> His opinion of Edwards later changed for there are more appreciative mentions of him in Carter's diary. Edwards was clerk of the Lancaster County court from 1720-1746. (<cit><bibl><title>Within the Court House at Lancaster.</title> Lively, VA: Lively Printing Services, Lively, VA: Lively Printing Services, [1976]. p. 15.</bibl></cit>; and "Thomas Edwards, Gentleman, Clerk of the Court" in <cit><bibl n="B43">Brown and Sorrells. <title>People in Profile.</title> pp. 94-103.</bibl></cit>)</note>

 <note id="n2"> [2] A bill of exchange is a kind of check or promissory note without interest.  It is used primarily in international trade, and is a written order by one person to pay another a specific sum on a specific date sometime in the future.  If the bill of exchange is drawn on a bank, it is called a bank draft.  If it is drawn on another party, it is called a trade draft.  Sometimes a bill of exchange will simply be called a draft, but whereas a draft is always  negotiable (transferable by endorsement), this is not necessarily true of a bill of exchange. (<cit><bibl><xref to="Ext6">"Dictionary of  Financial Scam Terms,"</xref> 8/22/2005</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Henry Willis (1691-1740) of Fredericksburg. ("Willis Family Genealogy"  (http://homepages.rootsweb.com/~marshall/esmd73.htm as of 5/21/02; and <cit><bibl>"Willis Family." <title>William and Mary Quarterly.</title> 1st ser. 5(1896): 24-27, 171-176; 6(1897): 27-29, 206-214.)</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] John Falconar (d. <hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1729) was a London merchant with whom Carter dealt. In 1728, Falconar and Henry Darnell formed an association of 29 London tobacco merchants to deal with the French tobacco purchasing agent as a group in order to keep the price as high as possible. The association lasted only lasted a year or two before dissolving because some of its members were dealing directly with the French agent and selling below the agreed-upon price. (See <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27g24d.html">Carter's letter to Falconar </xref> of July 24 and August 22, 1727, for details about the payment of &pound;200 to him. (See <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C30d16b.html">Carter to William Dawkins,</xref> for Falconar's death date. <cit><bibl>Arthur Pierce Middleton. <title>Tobacco Coast:  A Maritime History of the Chesapeake Bay in the Colonial Era.</title> Newport News, VA: Mariners' Museum, 1953. p. 129</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5]Carter noted in his diary July 29, 1726,  the arrival of the <hi rend="italics">Mansell,</hi> Captain  Trevisa, and in his letter of <xref to="http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/etcbin/browse-carter?id=C27a14a.xml&images=images/modeng&data=/web/data/users/berkeley&tag=public">January 14, 1727,</xref> to the Board of Trade, gives the captain's full name as James Trevisa.</note>

<note id="n6">[6] The <hi rend="italics">Marlborough</hi> was a vessel of 100 tons and 14 men, commanded by George Buckeridge (Buckbridge). In a letter to London merchant John Falconar<xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27g24d.html"> July 24,  1727,</xref> Carter refers to this vessel as "yor. Marlborrough." (<cit><bibl>Survey report 6801 summarizing Adm. 68/195, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>
 
<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2003, was revised April 12, 2013,  to strengthen the footnotes and modern language version text.</hi></note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>