<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27h22e">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Pratt, August 22, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27h22e.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003, 2013</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pratt, August 22, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-08-22</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27h22eT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-08-22"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27h22e.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pratt, August 22, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his old friend, London merchant John Pratt, August 22, 1727, to tell him that he has worked very hard to see that John Falconar's ship the <hi rend="italics">Marlborough</hi> was fully loaded and that he has shifted most of his business to Falconar from Micajah Perry. He gives Pratt information about the current crop estimates in the colony, and writes that he owes his daughter Elizabeth (Carter) Burwell Nicholas &pound;50 which she wishes to be paid in plate. She will write to Pratt herself asking for his assistance in choosing it. He mentions his grandson Lewis Burwell's many promises of greater attention to his studies in preparation for university, and his own health problems.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">John Pratt,</note> August 22, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
Mr. John Pratt&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<date value="1727-08-22">Augst: the 22d: 1727</date><lb/>
<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>My good Daddy&mdash;</salute>

</opener>



<p>Yor: <abbr expan="Entertainment">Entertainmt.</abbr> of the 7th: of <abbr expan="December">Decr.</abbr> now calls on me <lb/>for my Anniversary Answer by the <note n="CS">Carter</note> <note target="n2"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Buckeridge</note> who I hope <lb/>is now very near you will be able to give a good Accot. of himself <lb/>Sailed the Last of the last month when he came in both he and his friends <lb/>were very <sic corr="doubtful">doubtfull</sic> he wouild fall a great deal Short of his loading <lb/>however our Zeal amongst us was so great that your friend <note target="n3">Falconar</note> <lb/><sic corr="has">hath</sic> no dead freight to pay and you must allow me to tell you <lb/>he met with no <add place="supralinear"><add resp="editor">[o
]</add>ne</add> <del>friend</del> that Exerted himself more <sic corr="than">then</sic> I did for <lb/>which Service I hope Mr. Falconar will have a Suitable Concern <lb/>for my Interest who is now let into a great Share of my business <lb/>and your old friend <note n="MP2">Mr. Perry</note> with whom I have had a long Chain <lb/>of large Affairs <sic corr="has">hath</sic> not one hogsheads from me this year how the <lb/>Gentleman will resent it his next must tell me if he will pay <lb/>away my Estate in his hands with honour I Shall have no <lb/>other regard for his great ness <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add></p>

<p>You Speak of an Empty market and give us hopes <lb/><sic corr="we">wee</sic> Shall meet with better prices this year <sic corr="than">then</sic> we did the last. It will <lb/>be good news if your Conclusions proves true. The Carter falls Short <lb/>of her Loading between two and three hundred hogsheads purely because <lb/>She was a lag Ship there is little to be depended on from our Guesses <lb/>of a Crop at this Time of year but the General Opinion at present is <lb/>that this crop will be a great deal less <sic corr="than">then</sic> the last was Our <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr>
<lb/>are fired away prodigiously <del>but It</del> and <sic corr="has">hath</sic> bin <sic corr="hurried">hurryd</sic> to the houses <lb/>before it was fit to go there, I <sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> <sic corr="you'll">you'l</sic> hear the Same Story from the <lb/>rest of your friends</p>

<p>I have for a long time bin indebted to my <note n="ECB">Daughter <lb/>Nicholas</note> in a promise of &pound;50 to be laid <add place="supralinear">out</add> for her as She Should direct <lb/>She now <sic corr="Chooses">Chuses</sic> to have it in Plate and writes to you herself to be <lb/>Assistant in the buying of it my Instructions go to Mr.Falconar&mdash;<lb/>I am glad to hear your little family was so well and that the Nephew <lb/>proves so great a Comfort to you and am Sorry you have nothing good <lb/>to Say of my GrandSon <note target="n4">Lewis</note> but that he is well, he gives me migh<lb/>ty promises of reforming himself and <sic corr="taking">takeing</sic> to his book<add resp="editor">[s]</add> heartily <lb/>in order to <sic corr="Qualify">Qualifye</sic> him for the University Pray God Grant him such <lb/>a measure of his Grace that he may answer the great design of 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
his father in Sending him for an English Education</p>

<p><sic corr="We">Wee</sic> have had an <sic corr="Extreme">Extream</sic> hot August from the begining <lb/>If our <note n="WG"><abbr expan="Governor">Govr.</abbr></note> Should come in quickly whom <sic corr="we">wee</sic> Expect <sic corr="daily">dayly</sic> in the <lb/><name type="ship">Randolph</name> he will go near to be Saluted with trying weather I thank <lb/>God all your friends are in reasonable good health of my large fam<lb/>ily I know of none but are well <note n="MP1">Colonel Page</note> will give Accot. of himself <lb/>for my own part I am under an Afflicting distemper that I am afraid <lb/>will bear me company to my Grave I am Sir in the Catalogue of <lb/>one of your paternal care and </p>

<closer>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sir<lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Yor. most humble Servt:&mdash;</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] John Pratt was a London merchant and an old friend of Carter's who usually referred to him as "Daddy."</note>

<note id="n2">[2] The <hi rend="italics">Marlborough</hi> was a vessel of 100 tons and 14 men, commanded by George Buckeridge (Buckbridge). In<xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27g24d.htmlhttp://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27g24d.html"> a letter</xref> to London merchant John Falconar July 24, 1727, Carter refers to this vessel as "yor. Marlborrough." (<cit><bibl>Admiralty 68/195, abstracted in Survey Report 6801, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] John Falconar (d. <hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1729) was a London merchant with whom Carter dealt. In 1728, Falconar and Henry Darnell formed an association of 29 London tobacco merchants to deal with the French tobacco purchasing agent as a group in order to keep the price as high as possible. The association lasted only lasted a year or two before dissolving because some of its members were dealing directly with the French agent and selling below the agreed-upon price. (See <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27g24d.html">Carter's letter to Falconar </xref> of July 24 and August 22, 1727, for details about the payment of &pound;200 to him. (See <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C30d16b.html">Carter to William Dawkins,</xref> for Falconar's death date. <cit><bibl>Arthur Pierce Middleton. <title>Tobacco Coast:  A Maritime History of the Chesapeake Bay in the Colonial Era.</title> Newport News, VA: Mariners' Museum, 1953. p. 129</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Lewis Burwell (1711 or 1712-1756), Carter's grandson by Elizabeth Carter Burwell and her first husband, Nathaniel Burwell (1680-1721). He was educated at Eton and Cambridge, and inherited considerable property, living at "Fairfield," Gloucester County. He would be president of the Council in 1750-1751. (<cit><bibl n="B42">Kneebone <hi rend="italics">et al.</hi>,  <title>Dictionary of Virginia Biography.</title>  2:434-5.</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 114.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2003, was revised November 22, 2013,  to strengthen the footnotes and modern language version text.</hi></note>





</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>