<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27h17a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to the Board of Trade, [<hi rend="italics">post</hi> August 17, 1727]</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 8 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to the Board of Trade, [<hi rend="italics">post</hi> August 17, 1727]</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  CO5/1320, Public Record Office, London.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-08-17</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27h17aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>LS</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-08-17"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27h17a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to the Board of Trade, [<hi rend="italics">post</hi> August 17, 1727]</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to the Board of Trade, [<hi rend="italics">post</hi> August 17, 1727], to enclose the minutes (not present) of the recent Council meeting and to report the actions of the Indians on the frontier as well as those of the pirates in North Carolina who were captured, brought to Virginia for trial, sentenced to death, and are soon to be executed. He notes that the Council has prorogued the Assembly until the lieutentant governor, who is expected very soon, can handle more pressing matters.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to the Board of Trade, [<hi rend="italics">post</hi> August 17, 1727]</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-08-17"></date><lb/>

</dateline>
<salute>My Lords</salute>

</opener>



<p>According to what I had the Honour to write <lb/>you in my last, I here <sic corr="enclose">inclose</sic> the proceedings of the <lb/>Council on the 14th: and 15th. of June last which in <lb/>all probability would have <sic corr="completed">compleated</sic> the Account <lb/>of my Administration, had not Some new Incidents <lb/>occasioned my calling another Council on the 17th: <lb/>instant, the Minutes whereof I hope in a Short time <lb/>to forward to yr. Lordships. One thing which gave <lb/>occasion to this Council, is a threatned invasion <lb/>from the Western Indians. Their pretences at first <lb/>was to revenge themselves of Some of our <sic corr="Tributaries">Tributarys</sic> <lb/>and the <sic corr="Tuscaroras,">Tuscaruros;</sic> but having met with Some <lb/>Success in that Enterprize they begin to talk more <lb/>insolently &amp; to threaten our Frontier Inhabitants <lb/>but I hope the Measures projected will not only <lb/><sic corr="Disappoint">disapoint</sic> their designs, but remove them further <lb/><sic corr="off">of</sic> from our Frontiers. Another thing which <lb/>which hath lately happened here, is the hasty forming <lb/>

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
and as Speedy Suppression of a gang of Pirates in North <lb/>Carolina: One <name type="person">Vedell</name> a man of Desperate fortune <lb/>having got with him three or four others of the Same <lb/>Stamp, fitted out a <note target="n1"><sic corr="Pirogue;">Perriague;</sic></note> and took and plundered <lb/>Several trading <sic corr="Vessels">Vessells</sic> on that Coast, but before he <lb/>had <sic corr="increased">encreased</sic> his Gang he was <sic corr="Set">Sett</sic> upon by Some of <lb/>the Country people and taken with two more of his <lb/>first Gang and one <sic corr="pressed">press't</sic> man; they were Sent in <lb/>hither for <sic corr="Trial,">Tryall,</sic> and on the 17th: instant Vedell <lb/>and two of his People received Sentence of Death <lb/>and will be speedily executed. These are the principal <lb/><sic corr="Occurances">Occurrences</sic> since my last letter, except that upon  the <lb/>uncertainty of the <note n="WG">Lieutenant Governors</note> Arrival, I <lb/>have prorogued the General Assembly to the 16th: of <abbr expan="November">Novr. </abbr><lb/>judging that <sic corr="though">tho</sic> his arrival Should happen as Soon <lb/>as may be, the General Court and other Affairs of the <lb/>Government will not <sic corr="permit">permitt</sic> him to hold an <lb/>Assembly Sooner, nor indeed is their any imediate <lb/>necessity for <sic corr="its">it's </sic>Meeting. I am </p>

<closer>My Lords &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Yr. Lordships <lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Most Obedient humble Servt: <lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italics">ROBERT CARTER</hi></hi></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> CO5/1320, ff 205, Public Record Office, London.  This is the recipient's copy signed by Carter as is indicated by the use of bold italics. It is endorsed: "Virginia | Lre from Mr. Carter, President | of the Council &amp; Commander in | Chief of Virginia, without Date," and "Recd Octor: 9th | Read Decr: 6: } 1727." Marginal summaries of its contents have been added by a clerk in London. As noted in its endorsement, Carter and his clerk forgot to write the date line on this letter; it has been assigned this date on the basis of evidence in the letter and from Carter's diary entries of this period.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence to persons abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Pirogue is the West Indian term for a dugout canoe.</note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>