<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27i06a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Peter Leheup, September 6, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.7  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27i06a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Peter Leheup, September 6, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-09-06</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27i06aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-09-06"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27i06a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Peter Leheup, September 6, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Virginia's agent in London, Peter Leheup, September 6, 1727, to report that unofficial news has been received in the colony of the death of King George I but that he must await official word from Whitehall before proclaiming the new king. He speculates that the official news may come with the new governor.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">Peter Leheup,</note> September 6, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-09-06">Sepr. the 6th. 1727</date><lb/>
Treasury Chamber<lb/>Peter Leheup Esqr.<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>The last trouble I gave you was of the 24th of <lb/>July Since by the <note n="CS">Carter</note> the 23d: of last month I Sent away the <lb/><sic corr="publci">publick</sic> packets to the Secretary of State and to the <note target="n2">Lords of Trade</note> <lb/>I think it not amiss to acquaint you with the news we have <lb/>of the <note target="n3">King's Death</note> which came from new York about a fortnight ago <lb/><sic corr="Accompanied">Accompanyd</sic> with pretty Strong Circumstances last night <lb/>I was advised of a Sloop Just come from <name type="place">Barbadoes</name> into Jam<add resp="editor">[es]</add> <lb/>river the Master whereof reports The King was <sic corr="pproclaimed">proclaimd</sic> at <lb/>the Bridgetown before he came away by the name of George the <lb/>Second. here is no publick notification of this yet arrived to <lb/>this Government till I have directions from Whitehall I <lb/>must take no notice of these private advices By what way <lb/>I am to receive my Orders for proclaiming the King here or <lb/>whether our <abbr expan="Governor">Govr.</abbr> is at hand and bring brings them himself we are <lb/>yet to learn I am </p>

<closer>Sir<lb/>Yor: most humble Servt:<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>By the <sic corr="Cranfield">Cranfeild</sic> <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Venn&mdash;</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to persons abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Peter Leheup, an English Treasury clerk, was Virginia's  and other colonies' agent in England for some years. He was related by marriage to the Prime Minister's brother who was secretary of the Treasury. His influence would be greater near the end of Carter's life.(<cit><bibl n="B22">Price. <title>Perry of London. . . . </title> pp. 75-77, 80, 83.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Established in 1696 as successor to a similar body, the Lords Commissioners of Trade and Plantations was "an advisory group, subordinate to king and Privy Council, and with no executive, financial, or penalizing powers, the Board of Trade was nevertheless able . . . to exert a far reaching and often determining influence in colonial matters. . . . It prepared the royal instructions for the governors overseas. . . ." (<cit><bibl>Henry Hartwell, James Blair, and Edward Chilton. Hunter Dickinson Farish, <hi rend="italics">ed.</hi> <title>The Present State of Virginia, and the College.</title> [First published, 1940, by Colonial Williamsburg, Inc., and reprinted Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1964.] pp. xvi-xvii.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] George I (1660-1727) who reigned 1714-1727. (<cit><bibl>"The Royal English Monarchy." http://www.scotlandroyalty.org/kings.html. 11/12/03</bibl></cit>)</note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>