<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27i27a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, September 27, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27i27a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003 2014</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, September 27, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-09-27</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27i27aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-09-27"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27i27a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, September 27, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Liverpool merchant John Pemberton, September 27, 1727, to report on the progress of the sales of the merchant's ship's cargo of slaves, noting that he has had to take tobacco for most sales because many slaves have come into the colony the past year and money is exhausted. There should be tobacco to load the ship for the return voyage.  He also quotes the governor concerning the capture of seven ships by a Spanish privateer.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="JP">John Pemberton,</note> September 27, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
Mr. John Pemberton&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;
<date value="1727-09-27">Sepr. the 27th 1727</date><lb/>
<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>



<p>My last went by <note target="n1"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Tarleton</note> Dated the <lb/>16th: Instant then advised the Arrival of the Rose <note target="n2"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Christian</note><lb/><del>[illegible]</del> I have not time now to Copy Think it necessary to send <lb/>you this line Via Glasgow to advise how far the Sale is <sic corr="gone">gon</sic> <lb/>forward That you be <sic corr="apprised">apprized</sic> in time how to order yor. Affairs in <lb/>my hands Some of the bills of Exchange are not to be give<add resp="editor">[n]</add> me <lb/><sic corr="until">till</sic> <sic corr="April">Aprill</sic> I was glad to take them then Perhaps I may be able <lb/>to return you about Nine hundred pound by the Ship money <lb/>is become prodigious Scarce among us I have bin <sic corr="forced">forcd</sic> to <lb/>take <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> for a great many as you will See by the <sic corr="Enclosed">Inclosed</sic> <lb/>list of the Sale there remains Six and Twenty unsold one of them <lb/>Just dead half the rest Sick <sic corr="ashore">aShoar</sic> with Scurvys Lameness <lb/>Swellings and <add place="supralinear">other</add> disorders those that are <add place="supralinear">on</add> board the <add resp="editor">[ship]</add> refuse most <lb/>if not all of them must go for <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> I shall now Consider the <lb/>Circumstances of Freighting the Ship there will be <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> enough <lb/>due this year <add place="supralinear">near</add> to Load her all to be of mens own Crops and <lb/>made heavy I make it all payable the Tenth of next month <lb/>and yet you know the <sic corr="getting">geting</sic> our Commodity ready depends<lb/>ing so much upon weather there is no trusting to it therefore I <lb/>have thought it <sic corr="advisable">adviseable</sic> to take Freight at &pound;8 per <sic corr="Ton">Tunn</sic> <lb/><sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> <sic corr="we">wee</sic> are promised between Sixty and four Score hhds.<lb/>whether to let any more I am at a loss to determine I know you <lb/>have as much of your Concern home as you Could and yet I am <lb/>willing to Save your paying Dead Freight as much as possible <lb/>Your <note target="n3">Charter Party</note> does not Say whether your owners are to <sic corr="fit">tfit </sic>

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
the Craft for the fetching this <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> or <lb/>the Freighters but I   but I must not agree to that if I can help it <lb/>the Freight <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> will be <sic corr="Consigned">Consignd</sic> to you,</p>

<p>I am <sic corr="dooubtful">doubtfull</sic> my proceeding in this Affair <lb/>hardly met with your Approbation however I have done my <lb/>utmost to Serve you as much as if the Concern had bin my own <lb/>had it bin so I could not have taken more pains the money of <lb/>the Country is quite Exhausted <sic corr="we">wee</sic> have had above five thous<lb/>and Negroes imported this year I am told they Sell at York <lb/>the Choice of their Ships at &pound;35 &pound;31 per pair I hear <note target="n4">Colonel Tayloe</note> <lb/>makes but an indifferent hand of it in Maryland His <sic corr="notes">noats</sic> <lb/>are up <add place="supralinear">here</add> at Several <sic corr="public">publick</sic> places for the <sic corr="letting">leting</sic> of freight at <lb/>&pound;8 per <sic corr="Ton">Tunn</sic> Sterling If his Ship is to Load here I reckon <sic corr="we">wee</sic> Shall <lb/>be in better Circumstances for a dispatch than he will</p>

<p>I shall Send you a <sic corr="piece">peice</sic> of News I had from the <lb/><abbr expan="Governor">Govr.</abbr> Yesterday in his own words ("A Spanish privateer has <lb/>taken Seven Sail on this Coast <note target="n5">Vizt</note>: Captain Graham belonging <lb/>to London from James river Cockram of Glasgow from <note target="n6">Patap<lb/>ses</note> a <sic corr="Liverpool">Leverpool</sic> Ship from Maryland and a Sloop belonging to <lb/>Drummond of Accomack A Sloop of new York one of Am<lb/>boy and another of Boston which last they discharged with <lb/>the prisoners who are Arrived at Hampton I am </p>

<closer>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sir<lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Yor: very humble Servt:
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>per Nicholson</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1 ]Several vessels named <hi rend="italics">The Loyalty</hi> sailed to Virginia. One commanded by Francis Wallis cleared from Poole for Virginia in 1726. Captain Loxom commanded  a vessel of this name in 1729-1730 as did James Tarleton in 1731. (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 9727, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit> See Carter's letters to John Pemberton <xref to="/users/berkeley/public/C30d15c.xml">April 15,1730</xref> and <xref to="/users/berkeley/public/C31h04a.xml">August 4, 1731. </xref>.)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] James Christian was captain of the <hi rend="italics">Rose,</hi> another vessel owned by John Pemberton. (See Carter to Pemberton, <xref to="/users/berkeley/public/C30d15c.xml">April 15, 1730</xref>.) </note>

<note id="n3">[3] A "charter party" is "the charter or deed made between owners and merchants for hire of a ship, and safe delivery of the cargo. It contains the name and burden of the vessel, the names of the master and freighters, the price or rate of the freight, the place and time of lading and unlading, and stipulations as to demurrage." (<cit><bibl><xref to="http://www.oed.com.proxy.its.virginia.edu/view/Entry/30829?redirectedFrom=charter+party#eid"><title>Oxford English Dictionary</title></xref> online.</bibl></cit>)</note>


<note id="n4">[4] John Tayloe (1687-1747) of Richmond County, who served as justice, burgess, colonel of militia, and as a member of the Council after 1732. His son of the same naqme would build the handsome house known as <xref to="http://mountairyplantation.com/Home.html">Mt. Airy</xref>. (<cit><bibl n="B31">Ryland. <title>Richmond County Virginia. . . . </title> pp. 115-16.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] "Vizt." is the abbreviation for the Latin word "videlicet"; it means "that is to say; namely; to wit: used to introduce an amplification, or more precise or explicit explanation, of a previous statement or word. " (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary</title> online.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6]  Perhaps Carter meant "Patapsco," the river at the north end of Chesapeake Bay on which the city of Baltimore is located today.</note>


<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2003, was revised May 9, 2014,  to strengthen the footnotes and modern language version text.</hi></note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>