<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27i21b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Major George Eskridge, September 21, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 8 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27i21b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003, 2014</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Major George Eskridge, September 21, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-09-21</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27i21bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-09-21"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27i21b.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Major George Eskridge, September 21, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his friend, Major George Eskridge of Westmoreland County, September 21, 1727, concerning the sale of slaves that will prevent him from attending a survey, and calling on Eskridge to help him find buyers for the slaves. He informs Eskridge that the packet from the governor of Maryland that Eskridge has forwarded concerns a robbery committed in Virginia by Maryland citizens, and that he has forwarded it to the new governor of Virginia.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Major <note n="GE">George Eskridge,</note> September 21, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-09-21">Sepr: the 21st: 1727</date><lb/>
Majr. George Eskridge<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p><abbr expan="Your">Yor:</abbr> Son came to me last night on board <lb/>the Negro Ship and this morning I Send your Negroes away with <lb/>him to <note n="WB">Colonel Balls</note> one of them Since his coming <sic corr="ashore">a Shoar</sic> a fine <lb/>Youth proves a little lame in his knees as did two of my Sons <lb/>and one of my own which I reckon will Soon wear <sic corr="off">of</sic> I hope <lb/>they will please you to make you <sic corr="Easy">Easie</sic> in the Price I have <lb/>charged them, at &pound;42 per pair.</p>

<p>Under the Circumstances I am it is impossible <lb/>for me to attend the Survey I have met with a Slave Sale have <lb/>not yet disposed of Fifty of the Slaves I can by no means be ab=<lb/>sent from it and must Earnestly desire your utmost care in Car<lb/>rying on the Survey the best you can In which I have already <lb/>Given as full Instructions as I am Capable I know not many <lb/>of your Jury Several of them I take to be men of no great Experience <lb/>let them but do me Justice and I think I cannot fear of Success</p>

<p>I <add resp="editor">[do not]</add> doubt I must be forced to Sell a great many of the <lb/>Slaves for <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> your Assistance may be of Service to me if you <lb/>can recommend to me any buyers that are good men and will <lb/>make ready pay I will take four thousand a <sic corr="Piece">Peice</sic> for women and <lb/>four thousand five hundred for men so proportionably 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
for boys and Girls Be so kind to tell <note n="RM">Meeks</note> this <sic corr="Story">Storey</sic> and let him <lb/>recommend also I would have the <note target="n2"><abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> prized</note> to at least Eight <lb/>hundred neat and to be paid of mens own Crops I should be glad <lb/>to See you after the Survey is over can hardly think it possible <lb/>it Should be <sic corr="finished">finishd</sic> as Soon as you Say,</p>

<p>The Packet you Sent me is from the <sic corr="Governor">Gor.</sic> of Mary<lb/>land <sic corr="relating">relateing</sic> to a robbery Committed in this <abbr expan="Government">Govermt.</abbr> by <lb/>Some Inhabitants there I dispatch it away to our <sic corr="Governor">Gor.</sic> and <lb/>herewith comes a Letter to <note target="n1"><sic corr="Governor">Govr.</sic> Calvert</note> which I desire yor. care <lb/>in forwarding as Soon as you can his <sic corr="has">hath</sic> bin <sic corr="traveling">travelling</sic> to <lb/>me ever Since the 22d. of last month I am </p>

<closer>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Yor. <abbr expan="Affectionate">Affecte:</abbr> humble Servt:&mdash;
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>remember me to my Sons and <lb/>to your good family<lb/>Your Son will inform you how <lb/>likely the Slaves are if I could Sell <lb/>a Score in your Parts it would be a great <lb/>help to me</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. There is a 19th-century transcript of the letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.
</note>

<note>The name of Carter's home, "Corotoman," the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Benedict Leonard Calvert (1700-1732) was governor, 1727-1731, of the colony of Maryland. ( <cit><bibl><xref to="http://msa.maryland.gov/msa/mdmanual/01glance/chron/html/chron17.html#1700">"Maryland at a Glance. Historical Chronology, 1700-1799."</xref> Posted on the web by the Maryland State Archives.</bibl></cit>) </note>

<note id="n2">[2]  The online <title>Encyclopedia Virginia</title> has an <xref to="http://www.encyclopediavirginia.org/media_player?mets_filename=evm00003264mets.xml">illustration</xref> from  William Tatham, <title>An Historical and Practical Essay on the Culture and Commerce of Tobacco</title>, (published in 1800)  showing the steps in tobacco production, including prizing. There are many articles on tobacco and its production in the <title>Encyclopedia</title>.</note>



<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2003, was revised May 9, 2014,  to strengthen the footnotes and modern language version text.</hi></note>



</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>