<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27l12e">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, December 12, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 13 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27l12e.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, December 12, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-12-12</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27l12eT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-12-12"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27l12e.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, December 12, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Micajah Perry, December 12, 1727, complaining that he has not been allowed a discount upon the fees for 90 hogsheads sent for sale. He comments on Perry's charges for "Collo: Bolling's commission," for "Mr. Blew the lawyer," and on affairs of the estates of Nathaniel Burwell, Merchants Hundred, and the Lloyds. He concludes that he is pondering what to do with the &pound;1500 bank annuity which he assumes has come to Perry's hands because of the Act of Parliament. </p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="MP2">Micajah Perry,</note> December 12, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-12-12">Decembr: 12th: 1727</date><lb/>
Mr: Micajah Perry<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>



<p>I have the favour of your two letters of the 23d of <abbr expan="August">Augst</abbr> <lb/>&amp; 9th of <abbr expan="October">Octobr:</abbr> &amp; find I am not to have the Discounts upon my 90 hogsheads allowed <lb/>me without the satisfaction of meeting with a Convincing reason why <lb/>you deprive me of it. Admitting you are right in saying that the state of <lb/>my Cash in your hands at that time (which I can by no means agree to) <lb/>was too low yet seeing the circumstances of my Affairs hath been <lb/>larger both before &amp; since than the calls of my Occasions a much lon-<lb/>ger time than the <sic corr="disbursements">disburstments</sic> <abbr expan="you">yo:</abbr> were out of pocket for me I can <lb/>not in my way of reasoning see why I might not have <del><add place="supralinear">not</add></del> Expected the <lb/>same benefit from your money as you reap from mine this part of <lb/>my Argument you have not thought fit to give me any answer to <lb/>how <sic corr="far">farr</sic> this proceeding is consistent with the strictest justice &amp; <lb/>honour I Shall leave to your consideration</p>

<p><abbr expan="Colonel">Collo:</abbr> Bolling's commission you agree to allow me <lb/>I suppose before this <note n="JR">Mr. Randolph</note> hath <abbr expan="paid">pd</abbr> into your hands on my <lb/>Accot. the Effects of the 67 hogsheads which I am well satisfyed he was <lb/>ordered by <abbr expan="Colonel">Collo</abbr> Bolling to Do having in my hands the bills of La=<lb/>ding with such Directions upon them</p>

<p>I am under no apprehension but <abbr expan="you">yo:</abbr> <abbr expan="paid">pd</abbr> to Mr Blew 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
the lawyer all the money you charge me with &amp; am in no wa<add resp="editor">[nt of]</add> <lb/>sight of his receipt all that I observed was it seem'd <del>[illegible]</del> a great de<add resp="editor">[al]</add> <lb/>&amp; his Solicitation I had no Occasion of because the matter was deter<lb/>mined before by the Kings instruction which <note n="HD"><abbr expan="Colonel">Collo:</abbr> Drysdale</note> was <lb/>pleased to conceal to say no more of it</p>

<p>You are pleased to own Your Self mistaken in not <lb/>allowing the Discounts on the <note n="MH">Merchants hundred</note> <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr>
 &amp; to tell me <abbr expan="you">yo:</abbr> <lb/>had given <note n="NB">Mr. Burwells</note> Estate Credit for it thus <sic corr="far">farr</sic> in part I am <lb/><sic corr="satisfied">satisfyed</sic> but the broken Accot of Paget it seems is still to stand a dead <lb/>weight upon that Estate. You <del>are pleased to</del> Observe that some have <lb/>thought proper to bear that loss with a view to recommend themselves bu<add resp="editor">[t]</add> <lb/><abbr expan="you">yo:</abbr> think it will be paying too Dear for your commissions I cannot he<add resp="editor">[re]</add> <lb/>forbear to call to your remembrance the methods of <note n="MP">your father</note> &amp; Gra<add resp="editor">[nd]</add><lb/>father who never charged a broken Account to any man in the long course <lb/>of their business, one would think if other mens Examples are no rule for <lb/><abbr expan="you">yo:</abbr> to theirs at least you would pay a venerable regard. I am obliged to you <lb/>for your kind promises that in respect of the long correspondence that <lb/>I have had subsisting in your family <del>shall always prompt you</del> <add place="supralinear">You will be ready</add> to do <lb/>me all the good Offices in your power which as I receive them I shall <lb/>never fail in suitable acknowledgements</p>

<p>I shall now look forward herein I send you my Accot of <lb/>the <sic corr="disbursements">disburstments</sic> upon the <note n="LL">LL's </note>Estate for the Year 1726 it <add place="supralinear">is</add> larger <lb/><sic corr="than">then</sic> hath been Usual Occasioned by paying for Grounds &amp; housing for <lb/>a great many of <sic corr="the">them</sic> slaves &amp; I have told <abbr expan="you">yo:</abbr> often &amp; do now again that the <lb/>plantations belonging to that Estate will not Afford a <sic corr="tolerable berth">tollerable birth</sic> <lb/>for above 25 or at most 30 of the slaves &amp; this upon enquiry you may <lb/>learn from others <del>men</del> as well as from me</p>

<p>Herein I send you a bill of Exchange from Ed-<lb/>mund Bagg On <note n="RC">Mr Cary</note> for &pound; 200 it is Mr Burwells money &amp; must be <lb/>placed to his credit I also send you a bill of Exchange of my own <lb/>Wilson Cary Draws upon your self for &pound;54:13:9 this &amp; my Accot <lb/>of my <sic corr="Disbursements">Disburstments</sic> mentioned above I desire may be placed to my<lb/>Credit</p> 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>

	<p>By a former letter from you &amp; indeed by the Act <lb/>of Parliament for the paying of the <sic corr="Annuities">Annuitys</sic> I must conclude <lb/>my <sic corr="bank">banck</sic> Annuity of &pound;1500. is <del>now</del> <abbr expan="paid">pd</abbr> into your hands my next <lb/>consideration must be how to employ this money to Advantage I almost <lb/>doubt should I propose to let it <sic corr="lie">lye</sic> in your hands at an interest of 4 <abbr expan="percent">perct:</abbr> <lb/>you would reject it I will pause a while perhaps if <abbr expan="you">yo:</abbr> design to say any <lb/>thing to it <sic corr="Until">Untill</sic> I may have your Answer if you will not meddle with <lb/>it my present thoughts are to turn it into <sic corr="bank">banck</sic> Stock.</p>

<p>I am now to remember there is two years rent due <lb/>to the <abbr expan="Proprietors">Proprs:</abbr> if <abbr expan="you">yo:</abbr> have not <abbr expan="paid">pd</abbr> any since the last Accot: but I hope <lb/>you have <abbr expan="paid">pd</abbr> one half of it at least &amp; if you have <abbr expan="paid">pd</abbr> it all I shall not <lb/>be disturbed provided you have Deducted <note n="EJ"><abbr expan="Colonel">Collo:</abbr> Jennings's</note> debt <lb/><sic corr="although">altho</sic> if the last years rent be not <abbr expan="paid">pd</abbr> till March next the <abbr expan="proprietors">proprs:</abbr> will have no reason to complain <lb/>I shall Close here &amp; <del>now</del> go to Yours of the 9th of <abbr expan="October">Octor:</abbr> remaining </p>

<closer>Sir <lb/>Yor: most humble Servt
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>per <note target="n1"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Christian</note>
<lb/>Copyed</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] James Christian was captain of the <hi rend="italics">Rose,</hi> a vessel owned by merchant John Pemberton of Liverpool. (See Carter to Pemberton, 1730 April 15.) </note>





</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>