<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27l16b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Cary, December 16, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27l16b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Cary, December 16, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-12-16</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27l16bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-12-16"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27l16b.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Cary, December 16, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Robert Cary, December 16, 1727, requesting that he join with merchant William Dawkins in being Carter's son Robert's security as naval officer to the Commissioners of the Customs. He notes that Mr. Fitzwilliams, surveyor general of customs in the colony, has raised an objection to Robert's appointment wbich he hopes that Cary and Dawkins will fight. In a post script he notes that he has just had word that his son John intends to press for the vacant deputy auditors position.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Cary, December 16, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-12-16">Decr. the 16th. 1727</date><lb/>
Mr Robt Cary<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir</salute>

</opener>



<p>The Above a Copy Via Bristol I have little to <lb/>add <sic corr="only">onely</sic> to let you know that our <abbr expan="Governor">Govr</abbr> hath been so kind 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
to my son <note n="RC2"><abbr expan="Robert">Robt</abbr></note> to renew his commission for the Naval Officers <lb/>place of this river his <sic corr="securities">securitys</sic> are the same <note n="MP1"><abbr expan="Colonel">Collo:</abbr> Page</note> &amp; the <lb/><note n="JC1">Secretary</note> we reckon that he <add place="supralinear">must</add> give Security also to the Comissioners <lb/>of the Customs again &amp; it is my request to you that you will <lb/><sic corr="join">joyn</sic> with <note n="WD">Mr Dawkins</note> in being my sons security a second <lb/>time there</p>

<p><note target="n1">Mr Fitzwillams</note> our Surveyer General made some <lb/>Opposition to the place of my sons living for the Convenience of the <lb/>trade I <abbr expan="affirmed">affirm'd</abbr> in Answer he <abbr expan="lived">liv'd</abbr> a great Deal more Conven<lb/>ient than Urbana where the collector keeps his Office for thi<add resp="editor">[s]</add> <lb/>I appeal to your Masters that Use here I have written the Story at <lb/>length to Mr Dawkins if this gentleman should make any <lb/>representation to the Comissioners against my son in this ma=<lb/>tter I pray you will <sic corr="join">joyn</sic> Your interest with Mr Dawkins in <lb/>taking off the force of his objections <del>I am</del> in which you'll very <lb/>much oblidge 
</p>

<closer>Sir <lb/>Your most humble Servt<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>Decembr 16th. 1727 Last night I received a letter from the Secre<lb/>tary Advising me that he would push for the Auditors place with all <lb/>his strength and tells me his letters should come to my hand this day to go <lb/>by this ship which may be time enough if he is not too Dilatory
<lb/>to be copyed</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a 19th-century transcript of the letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] As Surveyor General of the Customs in the colonies in "South America," Richard Fitzwilliams was a member of the councils of Virginia, South Carolina, and Jamaica. He served with William Byrd on  the commission to survey the boundary between Virginia and North Carolina in 1728. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:93-4; 155-56. </bibl></cit>)</note>





</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>