<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27l12f">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, December 12, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 12 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27l12f.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, December 12, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-12-12</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27l12fT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-12-12"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27l12f.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, December 12, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Micajah Perry, December 12, 1727, to comment on the merchant's letter about the actions of the Board of Trade concerning the Northern Neck proprietary and complain that Lord Fairfax shows little interest in defending his property. He adds comments about the Lloyd estate, and William Dawkins' ship, the <hi rend="italics">Carter</hi> (in which he owns an interest), and in closing reminds Perry that he has never received any payment for his administration of the Lloyd estate since the time of the merchant's grandfather. </p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="MP2">Micajah Perry,</note> December 12, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[ Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-12-12">Decembr: 12th: 1727</date><lb/>
Mr: Micajah Perry<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>



<p>In yours of the 9th of <abbr expan="October">Octor:</abbr> you are pleased <lb/>to Advise me that After a great number of Attendance on the <note target="n1">Lords of <lb/>trade</note> <abbr expan="you">yo:</abbr> have at last got the Attorney's &amp; Solicitor Generals opinion <lb/>upon the Northern Neck Affair differing in some points from their <lb/>former Opinions, which <note n="JC">Mr Clayton</note> tells <abbr expan="you">yo:</abbr> proceeded from the different <lb/>Stating of the question; &amp; that the Lords have sent in their Opinions to-<lb/>gether with their instructions to the <note n="WG"><abbr expan="Governor">Govr:</abbr></note> I shall only Observe that <lb/>Mr Clayton hath all along been a strenuous enemy in this Affair <lb/>&amp; I am apt to think hath strongly pursued it in prevailing upon the <lb/>Lawyers to Alter their Opinions as for the state of the Case I am sure <lb/>they had it rightly before, The Grant &amp; all the words of it relating to <lb/>the <sic corr="Controversy">Controversie</sic> were nakedly laid before them But if the <abbr expan="Proprietors">Proprs </abbr><lb/>will sit still &amp; suffer their rights to be determined from them with<lb/>out ever <sic corr="strugglig">strugling</sic> in defence of them they must not lay the fault on 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
me, what Determination the Lords are come to in this <del>Affair</del> <add resp="editor">[...]</add> <lb/>is not yet come to my knowledge <sic corr="although">altho</sic> I Expect it soon will it seems <lb/>a little strange that my <note n="TF"><abbr expan="Lord">Ld.</abbr> Fairfax</note> who is the heir at law should not <lb/>at least have had the strength of some other lawyers in defence of <lb/>his Cause</p>

<p>Your next Paragraph relates to the <note n="LL">LL's</note> <lb/>affair Advising me of the little <sic corr="likelihood">likelyhood</sic> there is of bringing it <lb/>to an End &amp; desiring that this Crop may be <sic corr="shipped">shipt</sic> in <note target="n2">Keeling</note> &amp; tells me <lb/>he <add place="supralinear"><sic corr="informed">enform'd</sic></add> <abbr expan="you">yo:</abbr> I had kept back the <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> <sic corr="until">'till</sic> he was near loaded this Story <lb/>I have taxed Keeling with wch: he disowns if he did say it he wronged me <lb/>egregiously for instead of delaying him I sent the <abbr expan="tobacco">tobbo</abbr>
aboard in a <lb/>Sloop of my own &amp; instead of twelve hogsheads of that <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> that I put <lb/>into the <note n="CS"><name type="ship">Carter</name></note> I put twenty of my own into him beleiving it to <lb/>be safer for the Estate to ship it <add place="supralinear">in</add> two bottoms than one</p>

<p><note n="WD">Mr Dawkins</note> acquaints me he <del>is</del> <add place="supralinear">intends to</add>  send<del>ing</del> <lb/>the Carter to us <del>again</del> with all dispatch if he makes her a lag <lb/>Ship it may be <sic corr="doubtful">doubtfull</sic> she will still continue <add place="supralinear">to be</add> an unfortunate one, <lb/>for my own part I have little reason to Desire a continuance of <lb/>my interest in her it would have been a great Deal of money saved <lb/>in my pocket had she been sold seven Years <sic corr="ago">agoe</sic></p>


<p>	According to a former desire of yours I now send <lb/>you a Copy of your Mortgage &amp; an Accot of the <sic corr="mortalities">mortalitys</sic> <del>at  that estate</del> <add place="supralinear">for the slaves</add> <lb/>since the last Accot you had, you give me no <sic corr="intelligence">intelligance </sic>yet of any Goods co=<lb/>ming for the supply of <sic corr="those">them</sic> <sic corr="families">familys</sic> <abbr expan="you">yo:</abbr> will not Expect them to be sub=<lb/>sisted without <sic corr="Clothes">Cloaths</sic> &amp; tools. I must never treat of this Affair without pu<lb/>tting you in mind of the salary <sic corr="that's">thats</sic> due to me for the Care of this est=<lb/>ate I made my claim soon after it was put into my hands by <abbr expan="your">yr:</abbr> <lb/><note n="MP">Grandfather</note> &amp; I have continued that claim ever since &amp; not many <lb/>Years <sic corr="ago">agoe</sic> made my Demand as to the Quantum to this you <lb/>make me no Answer surely you do not intend to leave me to Carve <lb/>for my self before this Estate goes out of my hands&mdash;&mdash;</p>

<p>I shall <del>Expect</del> <add place="supralinear"><hi rend="italics">desire</hi></add> in your next you will <add place="supralinear"><sic corr="please">pleas </sic>to</add> speak plain <lb/>to me upon this last Subject I am </p>

<closer>Sir <lb/><abbr expan="Your">Yr</abbr> most humble servt
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>per <note target="n3">Christian</note>
<lb/>to be <sic corr="copied">copyed</sic></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note>Carter reviewed this draft and added one word in his hand as is indicated by italics.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Established in 1696 as successor to a similar body, the Lords Commissioners of Trade and Plantations was "an advisory group, subordinate to king and Privy Council, and with no executive, financial, or penalizing powers, the Board of Trade was nevertheless able . . . to exert a far reaching and often determining influence in colonial matters. . . . It prepared the royal instructions for the governors overseas. . . ." (<cit><bibl>Henry Hartwell, James Blair, and Edward Chilton. Hunter Dickinson Farish, <hi rend="italics">ed.</hi> <title>The Present State of Virginia, and the College.</title> [First published, 1940, by Colonial Williamsburg, Inc., and reprinted Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1964.] pp. xvi-xvii.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Captain William Keiling commanded the <hi rend="italics">Betty.
</hi> (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800 summarizing Adm. 68/194, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley  Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] James Christian was captain of the <hi rend="italics">Rose,</hi> a vessel owned by merchant John Pemberton of Liverpool. (See Carter to Pemberton, 1730 April 15.) </note>









</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>