<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C28a05a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to James Carter, January 5, 1728</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 11 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C28a05a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to James Carter, January 5, 1728</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1728-01-05</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C28a05aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1728-01-05"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C28a05a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to James Carter, January 5, 1728</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his agent James Carter, January 5, 1728, a resident of Stafford County, concerning certain persons' applications for land grants, the fees to be collected, and the procedure to be followed. He gives particular instructions concerning the lands of Robert Alexander.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">James Carter,</note> January 5, 1728</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1728-01-05">January the 5th 1727 [1728]</date><lb/>
Mr. James Carter&mdash;<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p>I have Settled an Accot. with John Wright <abbr expan="about">abt.</abbr> Waugh <lb/>Darnells Deed in Stafford <abbr expan="County">Co:</abbr> he hath paid me all to 49 <abbr expan="pounds">lb</abbr>. of <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr>
 when <lb/>he pays you this ballance you may let him have the Deed he Says that <lb/>besides the <abbr expan="composition">campos.</abbr> for the other deed of Waugh Darnells he paid the <note target="n2">Quit <lb/>rents</note> to John Allen your receiver and he has his receipt for it now <lb/>the <abbr expan="Quit">Qt.</abbr> rents of the Land I have no Credit for or is the Land put into any <lb/>rent <sic corr="roll">role</sic> either yours of King George's he also tells me that Tom Stone <lb/>his neighbour hath got his Deed in his whole Accot. is 1101 <abbr expan="pounds">lb.</abbr> of <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobb</abbr>
 <lb/>you have given me Credit but for 600, these mistakes  I hint to <lb/>you that you may set them to rights, You must always reckon <lb/>the <abbr expan="Quit">Qt.</abbr> rents are due from the Date of the Deed and not from the time <lb/>of the Delivery for the delay in keeping the Deeds is <sic corr="Occasioned">Ocasiond</sic> for <lb/>want of the payment of the <abbr expan="Composition">Compo:</abbr> which is properly due from <lb/>the Date of the Deeds <del>upon the Letters and noats</del> it hath bin the <lb/>practice upon the Letters and <sic corr="notes">noats</sic> of the upper Inhabitants for me <lb/>to Send them out <abbr expan="warrants">warrts.</abbr> for the taking up Lands many of which <lb/>have never bin Executed nor <sic corr="returned">returnd</sic> to me which hath bin a great <lb/>abuse to the <abbr expan="Proprietors">Proprs:</abbr> and I think for the future to Issue no no more <abbr expan="warrants">warrts.</abbr> <lb/><sic corr="until">untill</sic> the fees are paid which you know is 15/ for a <abbr expan="warrant">warrt.</abbr> &amp; Entry <lb/>and if you Send down to me for any <abbr expan="warrants">warrts.</abbr> to take care to let me <lb/>know that these fees are paid to you or if you know of any perons <lb/>coming for <abbr expan="warrants">warrts.</abbr> you may Acquaint them unless they bring <lb/>their money they will loose their labour&mdash;</p>

<p><abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> <note target="n3">Robert Alexander</note> you returnd a <sic corr="Deliquent">Delinquint </sic><lb/>as well as Several others of good Circumstances I am <sic corr="informed">informd</sic> by <lb/>Several ways that Mr. Alexander holds a great deal more Land <lb/><sic corr="than">then</sic> he ever paid <abbr expan="Quit">Qt.</abbr> rents for pray let him know this &amp; Desire <lb/>him in my name that he would Survey his lands that it may <lb/>be known in what Quantity he holds that the <abbr expan="Proprietors">Proprs:</abbr> may be no longer <lb/>abused or if he will not put himself to the Charge I hope he will <lb/>not be Offended if I order the Survey of it for him that I may grant <lb/>the Surplus to Some other person that will pay the <abbr expan="Quit">Qt.</abbr> rents more <lb/>Punctually than he hath done I will have you take care to 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
tell this <sic corr="Story">Storey</sic> to him in the presence of some Wittnesses and it is <lb/>my further order to you that you do not receive his Arrears of <lb/><abbr expan="Quit">Qt.</abbr> rents in <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> but if he refuses to pay money let him <lb/>know that I will not take it other ways and let me hear <lb/>from you as Soon as you can I am </p>

<closer>Yor. <sic corr="Friend">Freind</sic></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>The name of Carter's home, "Corotoman," the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] James Carter (1684-1743), of Stafford County, was the younger brother of Carter's dear friend and associate, Captain Thomas Carter of Lancaster County, and was one of Carter's chief managers. (<cit><bibl>Joseph Lyon Miller, "Captain Thomas Carter and His Descendants," <title>William and Mary Quarterly.</title> 1st ser., 17(1908-09): 275-285.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Quit rent was the term used for the payment due from the holder of land to the "lord of the manor," in this case, to the proprietors of the Northern Neck. Carter as the proprietor's agent, collected these payments. No services were required of the landholder as had been true in mediaeval times.</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Robert Alexander (d. 1735) was a resident of Prince William County who would become a justice in 1734. Carter used the title of "major" which probably meant that Alexander was a militia officer. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:239. </bibl></cit>)</note>





</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>