<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C28a22a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Samuel Smith, January 22, 1728</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 13 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C28a22a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Samuel Smith, January 22, 1728</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1728-01-22</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C28a22aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 p.</extent>
<date value="1728-01-22"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C28a22a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Samuel Smith, January 22, 1728</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to chide Samuel Smith of King and Queen County, January 22, 1728, for not making the required legal arrangements for Smith's brigantine, the <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi> to unload its cargo of rum and take on tobacco for its voyage back to England. Carter notes he is willing to post the required bond provided Smith will sign a counter bond to indemnify Carter.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">Samuel Smith,</note> January 22, 1728</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Coro<add resp="editor">[toma]</add>n: <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1728-01-22">Janry 22d: 1727/8</date><lb/>
Mr. Samuel Smith<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Price in your Brigantine got <lb/>into <note target="n2">my Creek</note> this afternoon the disasters she met with in <lb/><note target="n3">the Bay</note> from the late storm and what materials will <lb/>be wanting to refit her I shall leave to the relation of <lb/>your men and the <abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> who writes to you at large</p>

<p>Her stay hath been so long that I be=<lb/>gan to grow out of Expectation of seeing her upon <lb/>my proposals her burthen being so much larger than <lb/>my information and the damage she hath now sustained 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
will in consequence prolong the time of her loading howe<lb/>ver if Mr Burgess and some others that I have expecta<lb/>tions from will do anything considerable, I beleive we shall <lb/>be able to give her a tolerable good dispatch <del>you ha</del></p>


<p>	You have been very wrong in not sending <lb/>a permit from Your Off<add resp="editor">[ice]</add>rs of the goods you have removed <lb/>in her and a certificate of the Legal importation of <lb/>the rum and of the payment of the Duty there and without <lb/>such certificate no Officer here can permit the landing <lb/>of it without Obliging the payment of the Duty over ag=<lb/>ain and without Obliging the present Master to an oath <lb/>to the contents of his Cargo and that the Vessel was Lega=<lb/>lly entered in your district or else must enter her afresh. <lb/>you know all these things better than I and that it is <lb/>the plain direction of the law indeed I think <note n="RC">Mr Cary</note> <lb/>was too <sic corr="scrupulous">scrupilous</sic> in not giving you a certificate upon <lb/>your oath made to the goods before <abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> Newton <add place="supralinear">one of your Justices</add> and <lb/>you have not so much as sent up the oath you took <lb/>before him my son is not at home but I have thought <lb/>the shortest way for you would be for your M<add resp="editor">[ast]</add>er to <lb/>give bond for payment of the Duty over again and <lb/>leave you to <sic corr="relieve">releive</sic> your self by a Certificate from your <lb/>Off<add resp="editor">[ice]</add>rs hereafter but you will think of this and give all di<lb/>rections according to your own thoughts</p>

<p>Another thing is wanting the Off<add resp="editor">[ice]</add>rs here <lb/>cannot permit your Vessel to take in <abbr expan="tobacco">tobbo</abbr> until bond <lb/>is given to them in a <abbr expan="thousand">thousd</abbr> or two <abbr expan="thousand">thousd</abbr> pounds accor<lb/>ding to her burthen for her <sic corr="unloading">unlaiding </sic>her <abbr expan="tobacco">tobbo</abbr> in <sic corr="Brita">Britta</sic><lb/>in being an enumerated commodity your <add place="supralinear"><hi rend="italics">letter</hi></add> for this en<lb/>gaging your self to be <del>bound with</del> your masters <add place="supralinear"><hi rend="italics">security</hi></add> in the 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
proper sum for his legal delivery according to the act <lb/>of parliament and returning Certificate thereof with=<lb/>in the limited time <del>I shall </del> <add place="supralinear">will be a foundation <del>to me</del> for me </add> Adventure <del>to</del> <add place="supralinear">by</add> signing the bond <lb/>in your stead <add place="supralinear">upon</add> your Undertaking to give a counter bond <lb/>to indemnify me this must be done before your Vess=<lb/>el can proceed in taking in <abbr expan="tobacco">tobbo</abbr> and this I dare say <lb/>you are no stranger to I am </p>

<closer>Sir <lb/>Your most humble Servt.&mdash;</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. Carter review the clerk'd draft of this letter and added an occasional word in his hand as is indicated by the use of italics.</note>

<note>The county and colony have been added for clarity to the heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Samuel Smith was a resident of King and Queen County where he was a justice, and would be sheriff in 1730 and 1731.(<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:215, 235. </bibl></cit>) </note>

<note id="n2">[2] Robert Carter's home, "Corotoman," was located on the bank of the Rapphannock River in Lancaster County close to the present-day community of Weems. A creek known today as Carter's Creek ran inland near the house.</note>


<note id="n3">[3] Chesapeake Bay</note>



</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>