<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;

<!NOTATION html SYSTEM "HTML">
<!ENTITY Ext6 SYSTEM "http://www.fraudaid.com\/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms\/bill_of_exchange.htm" NDATA html>
 ]>
<TEI.2 id="C28b20a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton and Company, February 20, 1728</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C28b20a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004, 2014</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton and Company, February 20, 1728</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1728-02-20</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C28b20aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1728-02-20"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C28b20a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton and Company, February 20, 1728</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Liverpool merchants John Pemberton and Company, February 20, 1728, to cover additional accounts of the slaves he has sold for them, and to notify the firm that he is sending tobacco received from the sale on board a vessel bound for Liverpool. He also sends some bills of exchange.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="JP">John Pemberton</note> and Company, February 20, 1728</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<date value="1728-02-20">Febry: the 20th: 1727/8</date><lb/>
Mr.  Jno Pemberton &amp; Company<lb/>
Fr[eighte]rs: of the Ship Rose<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Gent&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>By <note target="n1"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Christian</note> I Sent you a full Accot. <lb/>how far I had <sic corr="gone">gon</sic> in the <sic corr="disposition">dispose</sic> of your Slaves and now I Send you <lb/>Copys of that Transaction. The three Slaves that were unsold lay <lb/>upon my hands <sic corr="until">till</sic> the middle of last month and at last was <lb/>forced to part with them to a mean man <add place="supralinear">for <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo.</abbr></add> who I must trust for <lb/>a good part <sic corr="until">till</sic> next year In my last advised you I was in prospect <lb/>of freighting of a Vessel for your port and if I did Should be <sic corr="inclin">incline</sic><lb/>able to put Some of your Tobbo: into her She is now taking in her <lb/>Loading in <note target="n2">my Creek</note> I shall put between 20 and 30 hogsheads of your <lb/><abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> on board her which I hope will not be disagreeable to you 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
She will be ready to leave us Sometime in March</p>

<p>herein Send you three first <note target="n3">bills of Exchange</note> paid to me <lb/>by <note n="GE">Mr. Eskridge</note> in part of his Debt to <sic corr="wit">witt</sic> <abbr expan="Archibald">Archd.</abbr> Hamilton on <note target="n4"><abbr expan="Lawrence">Law</abbr>. <lb/><sic corr="Dinwiddie">Dunwiddie</sic></note> &amp; Company of Glasgow for &pound;18"&mdash;"&mdash; <note n="JB1">James Blair</note> on James <lb/>Blair &amp; Company of Irvine for &pound;11"&mdash;"&mdash; John Leigh on Mr. Pemberton <lb/>for &pound;8"&mdash;"&mdash; Money is so very Scarce amongst us <sic corr="we">wee</sic> dare not refuse <lb/>it in any part of <del>Europe</del> <sic corr="Britain">Brittain</sic> I am </p>

<closer>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Gent <lb/>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Yor. most humble Servt.


<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/><del>per the Leopard</del><lb/>This Letter by Accident <lb/>per <note target="n5">Denton</note>&mdash;<lb/>was mislaid and did not go by the <lb/><note target="n6">Leopard</note> The Seconds of these bills went in <lb/><note target="n7">Price,</note> and I hope are with you&mdash;
</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] James Christian was captain of the <hi rend="italics">Rose,</hi> a vessel owned by merchant John Pemberton of Liverpool. (See <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C30d15a.html">Carter to Pemberton,</xref> April 15, 1730.)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Robert Carter's home, "Corotoman," was located on the northeastern bank of the Rapphannock River in Lancaster County close to the present-day community of Weems.  A stream called Corrotoman [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>] River ran inland west of the house. Carter built a fine house there in the mid 1720s, but it burned in January 1729. See the <xref to="http://www.christchurch1735.org/history/corotoman.html">"Corotoman" page</xref> of the web site of Historic Christ Church Foundation for more information about the house and excavation of its ruins.  ( See the <hi rend="italics">Maryland Gazette</hi> for February 4-11, 1728/29 for comment on Carter's loss. The Maryland Archives has placed its copies of the  <hi rend="italics">Maryland Gazette</hi> online. Unfortunately, page four of the issue of February 4-11, 1728/29 is missing, and that must be where the notice of the fire at Corotoman appeared; the text is quoted in secondary sources as reading: "The fine large house of Colonel Carter on the Rappahannock was also burnt lately. The particulars of his loss we can't give you, but we are inform'd it is very great." [<hi rend="italics">Garden Club of Virginia Journal</hi>, May-June 1983, p.8.])</note>

<note id="n3"> [3] A bill of exchange is a kind of check or promissory note without interest.  It is used primarily in international trade, and is a written order by one person to pay another a specific sum on a specific date sometime in the future.  If the bill of exchange is drawn on a bank, it is called a bank draft.  If it is drawn on another party, it is called a trade draft.  Sometimes a bill of exchange will simply be called a draft, but whereas a draft is always  negotiable (transferable by endorsement), this is not necessarily true of a bill of exchange. (<cit><bibl><xref to="Ext6">"Dictionary of  Financial Scam Terms,"</xref> 8/22/2005</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] "Lawrence Dinwiddie [1696-1764] of Germiston (Provost of Glasgow 1742/43) a merchant in Glasgow had wide commercial interests trading with Virginia, Canada and the West Indies and a Bank. He also founded the Delftfield Pottery, Glasgow in l748, of which his brother Robert Dinwiddie (Lieut Governor of Virginia) was a partner." (<xref to="http://wc.rootsweb.ancestry.com/cgi-bin/igm.cgi?op=GET&db=monkeys&id=I21434"> "Janet Ariciu family Bush"</xref> in a RootsWeb online posting, examined 9/5/2014)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] The <hi rend="italics">John &amp; Betty</hi> was a Liverpool ship owned by merchant John Pemberton; she often carried slaves into the colony. In 1726 the captain was John Gale, and in the next year, she was commanded by a Captain William Denton. The ship would be lost in 1729. (<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 18, n. 23</bibl></cit>; <cit><bibl><xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27l19b.html">Carter to P3mberton</xref>, December 18, 1727;</bibl></cit>  <cit><bibl><xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C30d15c.html">Carter to Pemberton,</xref> April 15, 1730;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl><xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27f28c.html">Carter to William Dawkins,</xref> June 28, July 26, and August 22, 1727, for Denton's first name.</bibl></cit>)</note>

 <note id="n6">[6]  The <hi rend="italics">Leopard</hi> was a Liverpool ship commanded by Matthew Hayes in 1727-1728. (See Carter to Pemberton <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27l19b.html">December 19, 1727</xref>,  and <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C28b20a.html">February 21, 1728</xref>.)</note>

<note id="n7">[7] The <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi> was a ship owned by King and Queen County resident Samuel Smith; she was commanded by Thomas Price. (See <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C28a22a.html">Carter to Samuel Smith</xref>, January 22, 1728.)</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2004, was revised September 5, 2014,  to add footnotes and strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>





</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>