<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; 

<!NOTATION html SYSTEM "HTML">
<!ENTITY Ext6 SYSTEM "http://www.fraudaid.com\/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms\/bill_of_exchange.htm" NDATA html>

]>
<TEI.2 id="C28d16a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to James Carter, April 16, 1728</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.7  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C28d16a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004, 2014</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to James Carter, April 16, 1728</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1728-04-16</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C28d16aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1728-04-16"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C28d16a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to James Carter, April 16, 1728</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Stafford County resident James Carter, one of his senior managers, April 16, 1728, to inform Carter that a sloop is coming for his and Ponton's tobacco, and wants to know from Carter how much tobacco he will be sending. He reports a protested bill of exchange  against Henry Fitzhugh, and two that he has drawn on Carter.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">James Carter,</note> April 16, 1728</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<date value="1728-04-16">April 16th. 1728</date><lb/>
Mr Jas. Carter<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>



<p>I <sic corr="wrote">writ</sic> to you a few days ago acquainted you that <lb/>a Sloop was coming for yours And Pontons tobacco desired you 


<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
will let me hear from you Specially that I may know how much <lb/><abbr expan="tobacco">tobo</abbr> I may <sic corr="reckon">reackon</sic> upon this year from you I told you Mr <note n="LCF">Henry <lb/>Fitzhughs</note> <note target="n2">bills of <abbr expan="Exchange ">Exch</abbr></note> that you took for &pound;14:8 were <abbr expan="returned">return'd</abbr> <lb/>me protested and that I would send them to you by the first safe Opp-<lb/>ortunity I had this is to let you know that I have this day drawn on you <lb/>for 800 pounds of tobacco payable to <note target="n3">John Ashley</note> and for 900 pounds of tobacco payable <lb/>to Owen Greenan which I desire you to Answer I should be mighty glad <lb/>to hear from you and <note target="n4">Charles Brent</note> too As soon as possible which is <lb/>the Needfull at present from your friend &amp;ca</p>




</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>The name of Carter's home, "Corotoman," the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] James Carter (1684-1743), of Stafford County, was the younger brother of Carter's dear friend and associate, Captain Thomas Carter of Lancaster County, and was one of Carter's chief managers. (<cit><bibl>Joseph Lyon Miller, "Captain Thomas Carter and His Descendants," <title>William and Mary Quarterly.</title> 1st ser., 17(1908-09): 275-285.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2"> [2] A bill of exchange is a kind of check or promissory note without interest.  It is used primarily in international trade, and is a written order by one person to pay another a specific sum on a specific date sometime in the future.  If the bill of exchange is drawn on a bank, it is called a bank draft.  If it is drawn on another party, it is called a trade draft.  Sometimes a bill of exchange will simply be called a draft, but whereas a draft is always  negotiable (transferable by endorsement), this is not necessarily true of a bill of exchange. (<cit><bibl><xref to="Ext6">"Dictionary of  Financial Scam Terms,"</xref> 8/22/2005</bibl></cit>)</note>

 <note id="n3">[3] Jack Ashley is mentioned a number of times in Carter's diary; he lived in Spotsylvania County and apparently was an overseer for Carter at one time although he does not appear in the 1733 inventory. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine, H. R., ed. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>.  4 [1721-1739]:254</bibl></cit>).</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Charles Brent (1695-1756) of Overwharton Parish, Stafford County, married to Hannah Innes. He acted as collector of quit rents for Carter in the county. (<xref to="http://www.mathewscommunications.com/mathews/mw1/mw1g18.htm">"Matthews-Williams Family Genealogy,</xref>" is as useful as any on the Brent family whose genealogy is complicated. )</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2004, was revised September12, 2014,  to add footnotes and strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>