<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;

<!NOTATION php SYSTEM "php">
<!ENTITY Ext4 SYSTEM "http://www.stratfordhall.org\/learn\/lees\/thomaslee.php" NDATA php>

 ]>
<TEI.2 id="C28d18a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to James Thomas, April 18, 1728</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 13 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C28d18a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to James Thomas, April 18, 1728</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1728-04-18</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C28d18aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1728-04-18"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C28d18a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to James Thomas, April 18, 1728</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to surveyor James Thomas, April 18, 1728, concerning work that he is to undertake in the western lands of the colony on Carter's behalf, and noting his displeasure with surveyor John Savage.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">James Thomas,</note> April 18, 1728</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1728-04-18">Apl: 18th: 1728</date><lb/>
Mr Jas Thomas<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>



<p>Your letter of the 15th came <del>to hand</del> last night I find you <lb/>have given in your deposition so there will be no Call upon you to <note target="n2">town</note> <lb/>but your staying so long from your Surveying business puts me out of all <lb/>hopes of your doing the work you have before you several warrants that <lb/>were directed to you <note target="n3">Savage</note> <sic corr="has">hath</sic> made surveys upon and now people <lb/>are desirous of having their warrants directed to him he <sic corr="has">hath</sic> <abbr expan="returned">return'd</abbr> me <lb/>some plats upon your warrants but I have sent them back again and let <lb/>the people know I will not grant deeds upon Surveys made without my Au=<lb/>thority but if you neglect the business at this rate I must employ such as will <lb/>go <sic corr="through">thro</sic> it I expected you down and then I could have <abbr expan="talked">talk'd</abbr> freely with you about<lb/> my own business but now I must leave you to the instructions you have already <lb/>had as for your employing of <note target="n4"><sic corr="Awbrey">Awbery</sic></note> and <note target="n5">Ashley</note> I am very well contented you <lb/>should do it and for the service that they do in my business and the pro=<lb/>vision that Awbery finds I will very readily pay for but I would have you <lb/>make an agreement with them both beforehand Awbery is <add place="supralinear">in</add> my debt <lb/>for <sic corr="negroes">negros</sic> but he must not expect to pay me any of that <sic corr="money">mony</sic> that <lb/>way that belongs to gentlemen in England and he must be punctual <lb/>in comply<add place="supralinear">ing</add> to the payment of it according to time and pray let him <lb/>know so from me Awbery has <sic corr="written">writ</sic> to my son <note n="CC1">Charles</note> for a commission <lb/>from me to take up wild horses you may tell him I will send him one in 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
a short time and if he takes up any in the mean time that he will let <lb/>me come in for a share of I will <sic corr="justify">justifye</sic> him in the doing of it</p> 

<p><note target="n6"><abbr expan="Thomas">Thos</abbr> Owsley</note> had a commission from me Several years ago at the <lb/>instance of <note target="n7"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Lee</note> but I never saw a horse hair by it yet</p>

<p>As for Ludwells being <abbr expan="removed">remov'd</abbr> I had but little <sic corr="dependence">dependance</sic> <lb/>of him he told me many a fine story about <note target="n8"><sic corr="Shenandoah">Chenandoah</sic></note> in which I <sic corr="belie">belei</sic><lb/>ve he shot very much beyond the truth however I send you a copy of his relation <lb/>it may be of some service to you when you are out upon the <lb/><sic corr="Shenandoah">Chenandoah</sic> lands I should be desirous that the <del>first</del> surveys <del>you</del> make <lb/>for <note n="MP1"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> Page</note> and my children at <sic corr="Shenandoah">Chenandoah</sic> be first made before <lb/>any upon the <note target="n9"><sic corr="blue">blew</sic> ridge</note> or the <note target="n10">bull run</note> which last will be attended <lb/>I <sic corr="reckon">reackon</sic> with a great deal less difficulty <sic corr="although">altho</sic> the more you do this <lb/>trip the better you will <sic corr="please">pleas</sic> me I foresee you will not be able to fin=<lb/>ish half your warrants before the summer is too far advanced up=<lb/>on you I <sic corr="believe">beleive </sic><note target="n11"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Barber</note> and <note target="n12">Mr Warner</note> will both be out in the <lb/>woods at the same time you are if you agree to let them survey some of <lb/>your warrants I shall not be displeased but I will not allow Savage <lb/>to Survey any of them nor do I intend further to make use of him <lb/><sic corr="Until">Untill</sic> he gives me satisfaction in some erroneous practices he <lb/><sic corr="has">hath</sic> been Guilty of I shall not say no more at present but am </p>

<closer>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Your friend to Serve You</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>The name of Carter's home, "Corotoman," the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft. </note>

<note id="n1">[1] James Thomas was surveyor of Lancaster County, and after 1727, of Westmoreland County. In 1736, he would be one of the surveyors involved in the work of the commission to determine the bounds of the Northern Neck proprietary. (<cit><bibl n="B8">Brown. <title>Virginia Baron. . . .</title> pp. 83, 92. See <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27l14a.html">Carter to Peter Beverley,</xref> December 14,  1727.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Williamsburg</note>

<note id="n3">[3] John Savage was a surveyor, later (1734) to be employed by Lord Fairfax while attempting to establish the boundaries of the proprietary. He had been appointed surveyor for King George County the year after that county was formed in 1720, and was referred to then as "gentleman." He was surveyor of Stafford County when he particpated in the Fairfax survey. (<cit><bibl><title><xref to="http://books.google.com/books?id=55I38FXWyPgC&pg=RA2-PA473&lpg=RA2-PA473&dq=%22John+Savage%22+surveyor+Virginia&source=bl&ots=MkmI2kK9-T&sig=3AynIvgowKj-6KoKVYcua8AJpWM&hl=en&ei=mUVyTojVEafx0gHI2c2PCg&sa=X&oi=book_result&ct=result&resnum=10&ved=0CF8Q6AEwCQ#v=onepage&q=%22John%20Savage%22%20surveyor%20Virginia&f=false">Genealogies of Virginia Families </xref>from Tyler's Quarterly Historical and Genealogical Magazine.</title>  [Genealogical Publishing Co, 1981] Vol. I [of 4]:473;</bibl></cit> <cit><bibl n="B8">Brown. <title>Virginia Baron. . . .</title> pp. 83, 86, 88, 92;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 619.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Frank Awbrey (1690?- 1741) was an active land speculator in the area that became Loudoun County, and was one of the first justices when Prince William County was organiized in 1731. He was sheriff of that county in 1739. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:239, 439;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title>pp. 148, 150, 153-54 ff. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] Jack Ashley is mentioned a number of times in Carter's diary; he lived in Spotsylvania County and apparently was an overseer for Carter at one time although he does not appear in the 1733 Inventory. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine, H. R., ed. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>.  4 [1721-1739]:254</bibl></cit>).</note>

 <note id="n6">[6] Thomas Owsley (ca. 1690-1750) was a large landholder in Stafford County, and had taken many trips into the back country. (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title>pp. 53, 83, 110. 609.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n7">[7]  Thomas Lee (1690-1750) of Westmoreland County was the son of Richard Lee II, and nephew of Edmund Jenings; he would build "Stratford," and succeed Carter on the Council. For a good article on Thomas Lee, see  "<xref to="http://www.stratfordhall.org/collections-research/staff-research/thomas-lee-of-stratford-1690-1750/">Thomas Lee of Stratford</xref> 1690-1750" by Jeanne A. Calhoun on Stratford plantation's website. (<cit><bibl>Burton J. Hendrick. <title>The Lees of Virginia: Biography of a Family.</title> [Boston: Little Brown, 1935]. pp. 48, 51, etc.</bibl></cit>)</note>


<note id="n8">[8]  "The Shenandoah River is a tributary of the Potomac River, 55.6 miles (89.5 km) long. . . .  The principal tributary of the Potomac, the river and its tributaries drain the central and lower Shenandoah Valley and the Page Valley in the Appalachians on the west side of the Blue Ridge Mountains, in [present day] northwestern Virginia and the Eastern Panhandle of West Virginia." (<cit><bibl><xref to="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shenandoah_River">"Shenandoah River"</xref> in Wikipedia</bibl></cit>.) </note>

<note id="n9">[9] The Blue Ridge is the chain of Appalachian mountains that lie on the western border of today's state of Virginia.  In Carter's time, explorers were pushing over the range into the Valley of Virginia where the Shenandoah River lies.</note>

<note id="n10">[10] Bull Run is a major tributary of the Occoquan River, forming the foundary between today's Prince William and Fairfax counties, and then between Prince  William and Loudoun counties. (<cit><bibl>Alexandria Drafting Company. <title>Regional Northern Virginia.</title> [Alexandria, VA: Alexandria Drafting Company, 2002.] </bibl></cit>  Coverage of Fairfax, Fauquier, Loudoun, and Prince William counties.)</note>

<note id="n11">[11] Thomas Barber of Richmond County was a surveyor, and would be appointed a justice of that county in 1730, tobacco inspector in 1734, and sheriff in 1736. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]: 215, 342, and 369.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n12">[12] John Warner was the surveyor of King George County in 1727; he
laid off the town of Falmouth in 1728. Later he worked for Lord Fairfax, and prepared an important map of his holdings. (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison,  <title>Landmarks of Old Prince William</title>, 626-628.</bibl></cit>)</note>   


<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2004, was revised September25, 2014, and January 26, 2015,  to add footnotes and strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>