<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C28e25h">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Edward Tucker, May 25 and July 9, 1728</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C28e25h.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Edward Tucker, May 25 and July 9, 1728</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1728-05-25</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C28e25hT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 p.</extent>
<date value="1728-05-25"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C28e25h.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Edward Tucker, May 25 and July 9, 1728</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Weymouth merchant Edward Tucker, May 25, 1728, to report the arrival of Captain Willson after a long voyage via Antigua, several bills of exchange, Captain Brett's inability to take his tobacco, and his hope that Willson will be able to carry it. The bulk of the letter is devoted to persuading Tucker, a member of the House of Commons, to support the colony's desire to repeal the act of Parliament probhibiting the importation of stemmed tobacco into England. In a post script dated July 8th, Carter notes that he plans to send 30 hogsheads of tobacco in Captain Willson's ship, reports bills of exchange, and orders beer, malt, and ale. </p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="ET">Edward Tucker,</note> May 25 and July 9, 1728</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1728-05-25">May the 25th: 1728</date><lb/>
Edward Tucker Esqr.<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>After a round about Voyage by the way of <lb/><name type="place"><sic corr="Antigua">Antego</sic></name> <note target="n1"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Willson</note> came Safe in at last, I had Some damage <lb/>in my Beer Necessity forced him in his long passage to refresh <lb/>his men and himself with Some of it; but that he and I shall <lb/>Accommodate,</p>

<p>Herein Send you a bill of Exchange of <note target="n1"><note target="n2"><abbr expan="Thomas">Thos:</abbr> Edwards </note></note><lb/>for &pound;13:12:3:d Also John Kirks for &pound;8"9:11 both on your Self <lb/>which desire Credit for,</p>

<p><note target="n3"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Brett</note> soon after his coming in Spoke to me <lb/>for Some freight, Accordingly I promised him, but the number of <lb/>hhds: I could not then tell, I was a long time kept from home at <lb/>our Assembly and General Court, he sent two Sloops into our <lb/>parts, the last was after I got home and might have taken in <lb/>Some of my <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> but he had Some better <sic corr="friends">freinds</sic> to pleasure <lb/>I Suppose and so left me totally out <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Willson I intend to <lb/>ship upon if he <sic corr="does">doth</sic> not Serve me as Brett <sic corr="has">hath</sic> done he <sic corr="has">hath</sic> <lb/>Sent me word he will be with me in a few days when we Shall <lb/>Adjust that matter,</p>

<p>It is the general Opinion of the <abbr expan="Gentlemen">Gent</abbr> in the Country <lb/>that the great Occasion of sending of so much Trash and under <lb/><abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr>
 is by the restraint <sic corr="we">wee</sic> are under from <sic corr="Stemming">Steming</sic> for now all <lb/>the ground leaves and under <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr>
 are <sic corr="tied">tyed</sic> up and go to market <lb/>none is so bad but the Outports <abbr expan="Merchants">Merchts.</abbr> and the North <sic corr="Britains">Brittains</sic> <lb/>will buy at Some Price or other which <sic corr="we">wee</sic> reckon Computing <lb/>through the Country amounts to Several thousand hogsheads and does <lb/>very much depress the market for the better Sort of <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> Whereas <lb/>if the good were <sic corr="picked">pickt</sic> out by <sic corr="Stemming">Steming</sic> it would be as <sic corr="Valuable">Valueable</sic> <lb/>as the best <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> <sic corr="we">wee</sic> make. <sic corr="We">Wee</sic> think so much of the Trash of our <lb/><abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr>
 going home is no advantage to the King in his Customs 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
and greatly to the damage of <abbr expan="Merchant">Mercht </abbr>as well as the Planter in depress<lb/>ing the Price of all <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> for we Conclude this under Scruby under <lb/><abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> is either Clandestinely run or Serves the Export trade either <lb/>way no Custom is paid for it. The Country in general is so deep<lb/>ly <sic corr="Sensible">Senseable</sic> of this great <sic corr="Evil">Evill</sic> that the <sic corr="Council">Councill</sic> and Burgesses <lb/>have <abbr expan="addressed">address'd</abbr> the King and made Application to the <abbr expan="Parliament">Parliamt</abbr> <lb/>for the repealing of the Clause in the <note target="n4">Act of <abbr expan="Parliament">Parliamt.</abbr></note> prohibit<lb/>ing <sic corr="Stemming,">Steming,</sic> And we have <sic corr="Employed">Employd</sic> Mr. <note n="JR">John Randolph</note> one <lb/>of our Eminentest Lawyers whose is <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> now going home to Solic<lb/><sic corr="it">ite</sic> this affair; <sic corr="we">wee</sic> are made to hope that the <abbr expan="London">Lond:</abbr> <abbr expan="Merchants">Merchts.</abbr> <lb/>&amp; the Outports will <sic corr="Join">Joyn</sic> their utmost Strength with us to get <lb/>it Effected, And we are promised by the North <sic corr="Britains">Brittains</sic> among <lb/>us that their representatives will give their helping hand, <lb/><del>And</del> if all this Interest go along with us <sic corr="we">wee</sic> have Strong <lb/>hopes <sic corr="we">wee</sic> cannot fail of Success, Our Agent is instructed <lb/>with our reasons to the <abbr expan="Parliament">Parliamt.</abbr> to prevail with them in <lb/>granting our Petition. You have the honour now to be a Member <lb/>of the house of Commons and in that respect a proper Person to be <lb/><sic corr="applied">applyd</sic> <sic corr="to">too</sic> for your Assistance Although I believe you are <lb/>already so well Acquainted with the great mischiefs <sic corr="we">wee</sic> <lb/><sic corr="lie">lye</sic> under by this gravious restraint <del>which
</del><add place="supralinear">that</add> you will want no <lb/>Arguments to Induce you to be hearty in this design I Ex=<lb/>pect it will be writ you by most of the <abbr expan="Gentlemen">Gent</abbr> you Correspond wth. <lb/>upon this <sic corr="Topic">Topick</sic> I am per Woodward
Copy per Trice--</p>

<closer>Sir&mdash;<lb/>Yor. most humble Servt:<lb/><lb/>
<seg type="postscript">per <note target="n5">Woodward
</note><lb/>Copy per <note target="n6">Trice</note>&mdash;</seg><lb/><lb/>

<seg type="postscript">
<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;To be Added to Mr. Tuckers Letter the 25th May<lb/><lb/>

Sir&mdash;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Rappahannock July 9th: 1728<lb/><lb/>

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;The Above is a Copy <note target="n1"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Willson</note> is now coming into <lb/>the <note target="n8">Indian Creek</note> and as soon as he <sic corr="has">hath</sic> taken in a little <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> there <lb/>he comes away to <note target="n7">our river</note> for the rest of his Load am afraid he will <lb/>hardly dispatch time Enough to get away with this Fleet I shall <lb/>have about 30 hogsheads in him,<lb/><lb/>

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Herein are three first bills of Exchange drawn upon<lb/>upon <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> your Self Richard Neal for &pound;2"-"- Peter Hack for &pound;3"-"- <lb/>William Jones for &pound;2 which I desire Credit for, I have had ill luck <lb/>with my Beer for these two years however I would desire you to <lb/>Send me 2 hogsheads of your best Dorchester Beer, well and Carefully <lb/>bottled <sic corr="off">of</sic> and <sic corr="packed">packt</sic> up Also two hogsheads of your best Malt I hope it <lb/>will be Cheaper <sic corr="than">then</sic> the last and if your Southham be right good <lb/>this year I would have a hogshead of it put into bottles with care I <lb/>will have no more of it come in hogsheads By Willson I Shall be more <lb/>Particular remain at present
Sir 
<lb/>Yor. most humble Servt.
<lb/>per <note target="n6">Trice</note>&mdash;
<lb/>per Willson



</seg>




</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. The word "Mr." has been struck before Tucker's name in the salutation, but the software will not allow it to be shown struck through as it will in the body of the text.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] No information about Captain Willson has been located.</note>

<note id="n2">[2] "Thos. Edwards, a little petty Fogging Lawyer the Clark of our
County that hath as much Mettle and more cunning for Contention then his predecessor had" Carter wrote
to Landon Jones, July 23, 1723. His opinion of Edwards later changed for there are more appreciate mentions of him in Carter's diary. Edwards was clerkof the Lancaster County court from 1720-1746. (<cit><bibl><title>Within the Court House at Lancaster.</title> Lively, VA: Lively Printing Services, Lively, VA: Lively Printing Services, [1976]. p. 15.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] John Brett was master of Weymouth merchant Edward Tucker's ship, the <hi rend="italics">Princess Amelia,</hi> which had been commanded by a Captain Lawrence until he was drowned. (Survey Report 9729 detailing the Weymouth Port Books, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Parliament had passed the act forbidding the importation of stemmed tobacco in 1722. Randolph would not leave for England until 1729; his mission would be successful.<corr resp="editor"></corr> (<cit><bibl>Arthur Pierce Middleton. <title>Tobacco Coast:  A Maritime History of the Chesapeake Bay in the Colonial Era.</title> [Newport News, VA: Mariners' Museum, 1953.] p. 116.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] Thomas Woodward commanded the <hi rend="italics">Providence,</hi> a ship owned by Captain John Hyde &amp; Company, during a number of voyages to the colony, 1723-1727. (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800 summarizing Adm. 68/194 and Survey Report 6801 summarizing Adm 68/195, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia,</bibl></cit> and Carter's letter to the firm, 1723 September 17.)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] The 140 ton <hi rend="italics">Welcome</hi> was owned by London merchant James Bradley to whom Carter would write about her on 1727 May 17.  John Trice (Frice) was her captain, 1723-1728. (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6801 summarizing Adm 68/195, 154r, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n7">[7] Carter may refer to the Indian Creek that is the boundary between Lancaster and Northumberland counties. "It lies between Bluff Point Neck and Fleets Bay Neck, flowing about 3.6 miles into Fleets Bay. . . . " (<cit><bibl n="B29">Miller. <title>Place-Names . . . . </title>p. 72.</bibl></cit>
)</note>

<note id="n8">[8] The Rappahannock</note>







</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>