<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C28e21b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to [Governor William Gooch,] May 21, 1728</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C28e21b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to [Governor William Gooch,] May 21, 1728</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent> p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1728-05-21</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C28e21bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1728-05-21"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C28e21b.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to [Governor William Gooch,] May 21, 1728</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to [Governor William Gooch,] May 21, 1728, to send by his son Charles a commission for the governor's signature that will renew Carter's post as escheator of the Northern Neck. He alerts the governor that the county courts of Stafford and Northumberland will not sit until they receive new commissions as more than six months have passed since the death of the king. He encloses a list (not present) in which he has listed the members of each court, their "abilitys," "Characters," and where they live, and offers to send new commissions to these courts should they be ready before Charles leaves town.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to [Governor <note n="WG">William Gooch,</note>] May 21, 1728</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Coro<add resp="editor">[toman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1728-05-21">May the 21st: 1728</date><lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>May it Please yor. Honr.&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>This waits upon yor. <abbr expan="honor">honr.</abbr> with my Son <lb/><note target="n1">Charles</note> who brings the Commission I had from <note n="HD">Colonel Drysdale</note> for be=<lb/>ing <note target="n2">Escheator,</note> of the Northern Neck which you were <sic corr="pleased">pleas'd</sic> to prom<lb/>ise to renew to me I have Sent another ready drawn for yor. <abbr expan="Honor's">Honrs.</abbr> <lb/>Signature and the Seal of the Colony. if you Shall please to give <lb/>your Sanction to <del>I think</del> it,</p>

<p>I think it my Duty to acquaint your <abbr expan="honor">honr.</abbr> <lb/>with the <note target="n3">Semple</note> that Some of our County Courts have taken up <lb/>that the Six months from the demise of the King being Expired they <lb/>have no longer Power to hold Courts till they receive new Com<lb/>missions from your <abbr expan="honor">honr.</abbr> Stafford Court <sic corr="has">hath</sic> declined Sitting so <lb/><sic corr="has">hath</sic> Northumberland. Our Court <sic corr="has">hath</sic> <sic corr="Sit">Sitt</sic> in Course hitherto <lb/>what the other three Courts intend to do have not yet heard; Three <lb/>of these Commissions <note n="WR">Mr. Robertson</note> had Orders from yor. <abbr expan="honor">honr.</abbr> <lb/>to make out when I was at the Council Board for <abbr expan="Stafford">Staff</abbr> &amp; <abbr expan="Northumberland">Northumd:</abbr> <lb/>at the <sic corr="rising">riseing</sic> of Assembly for Richmond at the last Council in the <abbr expan="General">Genl.</abbr> <lb/>Court, In respect to the other Commissions I give <del>to yor. honr.</del> my <lb/>Opinion in the Enclosed list In which I have had regard to the <lb/><sic corr="abilities">abilitys</sic> of the men their Characters and Places of abode, If yor. <abbr expan="honor">honr.</abbr> <lb/>Shall think fit to order these Commissions to be made ready while <lb/>my Son is in <note target="n4">Town</note> I Shall take care to have them Transmitted to <lb/>the several Countys with all the dispatch I can <del>so t</del> that Justice may <lb/><del>be no longer</del> <add place="supralinear">meet with no</add> Delay I pray for the Continuance of yor. <abbr expan="honor's">honrs.</abbr> health <lb/>and happiness As it is my Duty and am </p>

<closer>Sir&mdash;<lb/>Your Honours <lb/>Most obedient most <lb/>Obliged &amp; most <lb/>humble Servt:&mdash;</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. There is a 19th-century transcript of the letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note>

<note>The county and colony have been added for clarity to the heading on this draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Charles Carter (1707-1764) was Robert Carter's tenth child; his mother was Carter's second wife, Elizabeth (Landon) Willis Carter. Charles would live at "Cleve," King George County, and inherit a number of properties in that area from his father. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 340;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B32">Morton. <title>Robert Robert Carter of Nomini Hall.</title></bibl></cit> Numerous references.)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] An escheat is the reversion of land to the lord of the manor, or in this case,
to the proprietors of the Northern Neck, because of the death without heirs of the holder of the lands.
Anyone wishing to patent escheated lands had to pay a fee to Carter as the agent of the proprietors.</note>

<note id="n3">[3] According to the <hi rend="italics">Oxford English Dictionary,</hi> "semple" is an "obsolete form of sampler,"  as "to give a Semplar or Specimen of what may be done." </note>

<note id="n4">[4] Williamsburg</note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>