<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C28h08b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, August 8, 1728</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 8 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C28h08b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, August 8, 1728</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1728 August 8-1730 May 15,  Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1728-08-08</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C28h08bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1728-08-08"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C28h08b.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter toWilliam Dawkins, August 8, 1728</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant William Dawkins, August 8, 1728, to set out his long-standing dissatisfaction with the management of the <hi rend="italics">Carter</hi> and that his friend, Captain Thomas Dove, is beyond his ability with this ship.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="WD">William Dawkins,</note> August 8, 1728</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1728-08-08">Augst: 8th: 1728</date><lb/>
Mr. Wm: Dawkins<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>I am taking my leave of the <note n="CS"><name type="ship">Carter</name></note> a final on<corr resp="editor">[e]</corr> <lb/>I almost think concluding the Owners will never have the patience <lb/>to undergo any more <sic corr="losing">looseing</sic> Voyages, poor D<corr resp="editor">[ove]</corr> can best tell <lb/>you the misfortunes he <sic corr="has">hath</sic> bin under him<corr resp="editor">[self and]</corr> of the Gout <lb/>that kept him \Confined to the Ship I think <corr resp="editor">[...]</corr> 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
and the baseness of the Officers he has had under him, worse I <sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> <lb/>Master was never plagued withall you had better given Young <lb/>Baggwell &pound;50 <sic corr="than">then</sic> let him Set his foot into her, they Seem all to <lb/>be pretty much of a piece. The Boatswain, Seems to be the best among <lb/>them I think in my Conscience had the Ship bin under brisk man=<lb/>agement and a lively brisk <add place="supralinear">Driving</add> leader She would have fared abundance <lb/>better and her dispatch bin a great deal quicker I have a very good <lb/>Friendship for <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Dove and would Say nothing to his disadvan=<lb/>tage I esteem him an honest man and that he <sic corr="has">hath</sic> Exerted his <lb/>utmost in the Service he is in and yet I cannot but be of Opoinion <lb/><del>but</del> the Ship too <sic corr="big">bigg</sic> for him, This I do not Say with any design to <lb/>displace the man. The <del>Stoory</del> <add place="supralinear">report</add> that has bin raised of her Leakiness <lb/>whoever was the author <sic corr="has">hath</sic> bin mightily improved to her disad=<lb/>vantage and by none more <sic corr="than">then</sic> Some of the Masters, who have <lb/>found their Ends in it here was <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr>
 Enough in this river <lb/>Several hundreds of hogsheads <sic corr="have">hath</sic> bin <sic corr="carried">carryed</sic> to York, which I am <lb/>not capable to give a <sic corr="Reason">Reesen</sic> for when so good a Ship in the river <lb/>was ready to Serve them, pray God Send her well home and <corr resp="editor">[I]</corr> <lb/>Shall <abbr expan="Endeavor">Endeavr.</abbr> to be <sic corr="easy">asie</sic> let what will become of her, for I shall <lb/>never desire to See her again unless She comes under a better prospect <lb/>If She be <sic corr="really">realy</sic> a Sound firm ship could be made an Early one <lb/>and put under vigorous <abbr expan="management">managemt.</abbr> there might be hopes <del>of her</del> <lb/><del>doing better</del> but as things have run I can Entertain nothing but <lb/><sic corr="discouraging">discourageing</sic> thoughts and I am Sure my Pocket affords no<add place="supralinear">ne</add> <del>better</del> <lb/><sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> I have Said more <sic corr="than">then</sic> is Convenient but Sufferers will take <lb/>the Liberty to Speak <add place="supralinear">though I have made but a dull heavy tale of it, being</add> <del>I am</del> <sic corr="hugely">hughly</sic> unwilling to glance with any harsh<lb/>ness upon an honest mans livelihood, I am </p>

<closer>Sir&mdash;<lb/>Yor. humble Servt:&mdash;
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>per Carter</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. The leaf of the letter book on which this letter was written has some marginal damage and a missing portion at the bottom.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>