<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C28h08d">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Pratt, August 8, 1728</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C28h08d.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pratt, August 8, 1728</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1728-08-08</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C28h08dT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1728-08-08"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C28h08d.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pratt, August 8, 1728</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his old and dear friend London merchant John Pratt, August 8, 1728, to complain mildly about the arragements mechant John Falconar has made in the purchase of silver plate for his daughter, Elizabeth (Carter) Burwell Nicholas. He asks Pratt to have him sent Bristol water as he understands it is good for a "cheerfull clear Temper." Affectionate greetings to another friend and to Pratt conclude the letter.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">John Pratt,</note> August 8, 1728</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1728-08-08">Augst: 8th. 1728</date><lb/>
My Good Daddy Pratt<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>



<p>I have already answerd <abbr expan="yours">yors:</abbr> of the 28 <abbr expan="November">Novr.</abbr> <lb/>and have told yo<corr resp="editor">[u]</corr> <sic corr="although">altho</sic> you underwent all the trouble <abbr expan="your">yor.</abbr> Friend <lb/><note target="n2">Falcon<corr resp="editor">[ar has c]</corr>harged</note> me with commission for the Plate <lb/><corr resp="editor">[...]</corr> the favour you <sic corr="designed">designd</sic> both to me &amp; my <abbr expan="Daughter">Dar.</abbr> 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
and I do not find he hath allowd me the drawback at the custom house <lb/>as you tell me I ought to have,</p>

<p>Our Barren <del>Country</del> <add place="supralinear">Wilderness</add> affords little news My Children <lb/>I thank God for what I know are all well <note n="MP1">Colonel Page's</note> milk Diet <lb/>agrees so well with him that makes me hope he will prolong <lb/>his Life to gray hairs, I have the blessings of Seeing my Childrens <lb/>Children before me and as far as Matrimony is <sic corr="gone">gon</sic> every one <lb/>has the comforts of descendents. My <note n="ECB">Daughter Nicholas</note> is now wth <lb/>me and gives you her kind Service I have lived to <sic corr="Taste">Tast</sic> of the Infir<lb/>mitys of old age every day brings its uneasienesses along with it <lb/>I am advised nothing will contribute more to a <sic corr="Cheerful">Cheerfull</sic> clear <lb/>Temper <sic corr="than">then</sic> the use of the Bristol waters I <sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> Colonel Page has his <lb/>from you and they may be had to a <sic corr="trifle">triffle</sic> as cheap at <name type="city">Lond<lb/>on</name> and ,as good as at <name type="city">Bristol</name> if it be so I would desire you to ac=<lb/>quaint Mr. Falconar <del>to Se</del> I would have him Send me in 2 <abbr expan="dozen">doz:</abbr> <lb/>Flasks, or if the differnce in price be any thing Considerable <lb/>I would have him Employ some friend of his to Send so much from <lb/>Bristol, I am glad to hear that worthy Gent Mr. Toace is Still <lb/><corr resp="editor">[a]</corr>live pray give my kind love and Service to him I wish him <lb/>a happy old age as I do to you Accept the Services and proper respects <lb/>of this family and at the Front of them his who as <sic corr="it is">tis</sic> right <lb/>Expects a double portion in your benedictions and is </p>

<closer>Sir&mdash;<lb/>Yor. most humble servt:&mdash;<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>per <note n="CS">Carter</note></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. The foot of the first leaf of this letter has lost a portion affecting three lines.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note>See Carter's letter to Pratt <xref doc="C27h22e">1727 August 22</xref> for information about the purchase of the plate for his daughter Elizabeth (Carter) Burwell Nicholas. </note>

<note id="n1">[1] John Pratt was a London merchant and an old friend of Carter's who usually referred to him as "Daddy."</note>

<note id="n2">[2] John Falconar (d. <hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1729) was a London merchant with whom Carter dealt. In 1728, Falconar and Henry Darnell formed an association of 29 London tobacco merchants to deal with the French tobacco purchasing agent as a group in order to keep the price as high as possible. The association lasted only lasted a year or two before dissolving because some of its members were dealing directly with the French agent and selling below the agreed-upon price. (See Carter to William Dawkins, and Carter to Falconar's executors, both 1730 April 16, for Falconar's death date. <cit><bibl>Arthur Pierce Middleton. <title>Tobacco Coast:  A Maritime History of the Chesapeake Bay in the Colonial Era.</title> Newport News, VA: Mariners' Museum, 1953. p. 129</bibl></cit>)</note>





</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>