<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C28j18a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to James Thomas, October 18, 1728</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 11 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C28j18a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to James Thomas, October 18, 1728</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1728 August 8-1730 May 15,  Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1728-10-18</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C28j18aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1728-10-18"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C28j18a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to James Thomas, October 18, 1728</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to surveyor James Thomas, October 18, 1728, to chastise him for his idleness and poor conduct of his work in preparing 20 surveys of lands for which Carter has given him warrants, and threatening to take the work away. He sends a paper (not present) of his observations on 12 of the surveys, and especially berates Thomas for forwarding an out-of-date warrant from a Mr. Barns when Thomas knows very well that he has one for that land in the name of Robert Carter II.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">James Thomas,</note> October 18, 1728</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1728-10-18">Octobr: 18th 1728</date><lb/>
Mr. Jams: Thos:<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute></salute>

</opener>

<p>I <abbr expan="received">receiv'd</abbr> yours by <note n="GE"><abbr expan="Major">Majr:</abbr> Eskeridge</note> the 14th of this month <lb/>wth 20 Surveys <abbr expan="returned">return'd</abbr> I send you here a paper of my Observations upon 12 of them <lb/>you Ask new Instructions of me but I find it no purpose to give you any <lb/>If you look into the instructions you had from me you will find I direct you to keep <lb/>strictly to my <abbr expan="Warrants">Warnts:</abbr> both as to quantity &amp; place And have often <corr resp="editor">[been]</corr> told you <lb/>did not I should not Care to grant Deeds upon such Surveys After I come <lb/>from <note target="n2">Town</note> you must come down &amp; mend your Works or I shall be at a full <lb/>stop from granting Deeds upon <abbr expan="your">yr:</abbr> Erroneous <del>Warrts.</del>  Surveys You have not <lb/>only neglected the warrants you have of mine in your hands I mean those in the name<corr resp="editor">[s]</corr> <lb/>of my Sons But you have <abbr expan="served">serv'd</abbr> a great many other people in the same <sic corr="Manner">Mannor</sic> keep=<lb/>ing their <abbr expan="Warrants">Warrts:</abbr> by you <sic corr="Until">Untill</sic> they are worn out of Date Idling Away the pro=<lb/>per time of Surveying both in the Spring and this last fall on one silly pretence <lb/>or other Some say it proceeds form Laziness others from Sottishness All agree <lb/>your Circumstances are very narrow you have a Numerous family when you 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
keep in a very ordinary condition one would think a Sufficient <sic corr="spur">spurr</sic> upon <lb/>you to lay aside <sic corr="slothfulness">slothfullness</sic> and to rouse you up to do your business while <lb/>you have it your power to be getting something for them&mdash;&mdash;</p>

<p>You tell me you are going up into Stafford to work I hope when you <lb/>are there you will Survey all the <abbr expan="Warrants">Warrts</abbr> that you have yet Undone <sic corr="Otherwise">Otherways</sic> <lb/>I must be so plain that I must be forced to Call for them out of <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> hands and put them <lb/>or new ones in their <sic corr="Room">Rooms</sic> in the hands of others that will Execute them I <abbr expan="designed">design'd</abbr> <lb/>you a great deal of kindness and it <sic corr="lies">lyes</sic> in my power with yor: Diligence to help <lb/>you out of your poor Circumstances but if you have not the heart to bestir your self while <lb/>you have the Opportunity you must thank yourself &amp; not blame me</p>

<p>Among Your Surveys you have sent one made by <note target="n3">Savage</note> for <note target="n4">Mr. <lb/>Barns</note> in Which I reackon is a great deal of trick the <abbr expan="Warrants">Warrts</abbr> dated in <abbr expan="October">Octobr</abbr> 17<corr resp="editor">[...]</corr> <lb/>the Survey made in the same Month now sent to me in <abbr expan="October">Octobr:</abbr> 1728 how you c<corr resp="editor">[ame]</corr> <lb/>by it I dont know Savage <sic corr="has">hath</sic> played me many A Villanous Trick and I <corr resp="editor">[am]</corr> <lb/>Apt to think this is a link of the same Chain Which you may Let Mr. Barn<corr resp="editor">[s]</corr> <lb/>know The first time you see him I shall not think it <del>fit to Allow</del> proper to g<corr resp="editor">[ive]</corr> <lb/>him any Deed upon this Survey This land or some thereabouts was f<corr resp="editor">[irst]</corr> <lb/>pretended to By <note target="n5"><abbr expan="Francis">Franc:</abbr> Awbry</note> and then by <note target="n6"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> Mason</note> and now at La<corr resp="editor">[st]</corr> <lb/>Barns and Savage together think they have got me in A Noose what re<corr resp="editor">[ason]</corr> <lb/>hath made them to keep this Survey so long by them <sic corr="until">till</sic> the <del>Warrts</del> time of the <lb/>Warrt was <abbr expan="Expired">Expir'd</abbr> for Several months I Cant tell and at last to make you <lb/>the <abbr expan="Instrument">Instrumt:</abbr> of sending it to me when you know very Well you havd a <lb/><abbr expan="Warrant">Warrt</abbr> of my <note n="RC2">Son Roberts</note> Subsisting in <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> hands for these several years <lb/>together for the very same piece of Land before Any of the Above persons made <lb/>any pretentions to it You may be Able to Unfold this <sic corr="Mystery">Mistery</sic> but I can't <lb/>tell what to make of it I am </p>

<closer><seg type="postscript">Your friend</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. The right margin of the second page of the draft has suffered some damage.</note>

<note>The name of Carter's home, "Corotoman," the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] James Thomas was surveyor of Lancaster County, and after 1727, of Westmoreland County. In 1736, he would be one of the surveyors involved in the work of the commission to determine the bounds of the Northern Neck proprietary. (<cit><bibl n="B8">Brown. <title>Virginia Baron. . . .</title> pp. 83, 92. See Carter to Peter Beverley, 1727 December 14.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Williamsburg</note>

<note id="n3">[3]  John Savage was a surveyor, later (1734) to be employed by Lord Fairfax in his  attempt to establish the boundaries of the proprietary. (<bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 619.</bibl>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] This may be Richard Barnes who would be appointed tobacco inspector at Nailors Hole in Richmond County in 1732. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:286. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] Francis (Frank) Awbrey (1690?- 1741) was an active land speculator in the area that became Loudoun County, and was one of the first justices when Prince William County was organized in 1731. He was sheriff of that county in 1739. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:239, 439;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title>pp. 148, 150, 153-54 ff. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] George Mason III (c. 1690-1735), justice, sheriff, burgess, and county lieutenant of Stafford County, father of the constitutional theorist. (<cit><bibl n="B24">Copeland and MacMaster, <title>The Five George Masons.</title> pp. 50-86</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl>George Harrison Sanford King, <title>The Register of Overwharton Parish Stafford County Virginia 1723-1758 And Sundry Historical and Genealogical Notes</title>. [Fredericksburg, VA: privately printed, 1961.]</bibl></cit>)</note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>