<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C28l04a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Jones, December 4, 1728</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.16 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C28l04a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Jones, December 4, 1728</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1728 August 8-1730 May 15,  Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1728-12-04</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C28l04aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 p.</extent>
<date value="1728-12-04"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C28l04a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Jones, December 4, 1728</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his manager, Robert Jones of Prince William County, December 4, 1728, to chastise him for his "abundance of words" and lack of action, and to let Jones know that he has a good candidate to replace him. He will give Jones one more year but if Jones is planning to move, he wishes to know at once so that he may hire the candidate. He then turns to the disappointing wheat crop and poor quantities of tallow. He gives specific instructions for the herding of his hogs down from plantation to plantation, noting that he has promised certain of the hands that they may come "down" at Christmas, and they could herd the hogs. He writes of the need  to present the deeds for lots in Falmouth to the county court, and hopes that Jones and two other witnesses to the deeds will be present. </p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="RJ">Robert Jones,</note> December 4, 1728</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman,Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1728-12-04">Decr. 4th. 1728</date><lb/>
Mr Robt Jones<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p>I am now upon yours of the 7th of <abbr expan="November">Novr:</abbr> if abundance of <lb/>words would Answer the want of Deeds I must Allow you would pass for one <lb/>of the best managers I ever had to do with but where there wants performan=<lb/>ces this wordy talent is of little value in my esteem I shall only tell you upon <lb/>your huge promises I Shall adventure to make a <sic corr="trial">tryal</sic> of you one year long<lb/><corr resp="editor">[e]</corr>r that is to enter into Fresh Articles with you when your last year is up <lb/><sic corr="although">altho</sic> I have now the offer of a very good man to come into your place <lb/><corr resp="editor">[who]</corr> has <abbr expan="behaved">behav'd</abbr> himself very well in business of the same nature with <lb/>yours And is clear of A Burthensome family which you know is no sm<lb/>all charge to me in yours being so large so that it is very much in consider<lb/>ation of the straights you would be under that brings me into the humor <lb/>of continuing you Another year And therefore if you will be so <sic corr="cheerful">chearfull</sic> &amp; <lb/>easy Under a present remove as you seem to hint I am very willing you sho-<lb/>uld take your leave of me as soon as you have <sic corr="performed">performd</sic> the conditions <lb/>of your last years <abbr expan="Agreement">Agreemt.</abbr> and this I would have you Advise me of by the <lb/>first <sic corr="Opportunity">Oppertunity</sic> that I may close with the person now Offering himself <lb/>of whose both industry and Ability I have a very good Opinion</p>

<p>I shall now take into consideration the Accot you <lb/>send me of the Wheat and other things you tell me of Seven Bushels and <lb/>one half I spent which was very great House keeping considering I was so <lb/>Much of my time at the Out quarters but that I do not Much mind it <lb/>more Concerns me that you have sowed no more certainly there might <lb/>have four or five bushels been sowed there as well as At the Other <abbr expan="quarters">qrs:</abbr> <lb/>especially considering How convenient the Wheat there is the crops <lb/>at the Other <abbr expan="quarters">qrs:</abbr> fall a great deal short of what the overseers told me <lb/>some of them at Least Sabin <sic corr="talked">talkd</sic> of a hundred Bushels so did Willia<corr resp="editor">[ms]</corr> <lb/>at the least and So did Cassety the Butter pots are a pretty many in <lb/>number they are most of them but small I wish you had Added the 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<abbr expan="weights">wts</abbr> Upon your Tickets and I wish that the small quantities of butter <lb/>made may not be the Occasion of the Loss of several of the Calves several <corr resp="editor">[of]</corr> <lb/>them were so poor and Small that without a great deal of care const<lb/>ant housing and good feeding they will not be <abbr expan="wintered">winter'd</abbr> <sic corr="Although">Altho</sic> with <lb/>good care I am <sic corr="satisfied">satisfyed</sic> they may for from my own Experience this very <lb/>year several poor Calves by housing and feeding with the benefit of <lb/>the Corn fields are grown to be likely &amp; lusty and no fear of <sic corr="wintering">wintring</sic> <lb/>them</p>

<p>The number of <sic corr="Hogs">Hoggs</sic> you tell me you <abbr expan="reckoned">reckon'd</abbr> upon to be <lb/><sic corr="fattened">fattned</sic> at the several <abbr expan="quarters">qrs:</abbr> amount to 86 Out of these After the over=<lb/>seers have their Share some for the people and what will be for your <lb/>provision I hope you will be able to Afford me Fifty or at Least near it <lb/>And I would have of the best of them too Some meat must be kept for <lb/><note target="n1">Hurst</note> while he is at work Upon the Town houses Now I am upon <lb/>that Subject <abbr expan="it is">tis</abbr> proper to let you know that I have got a promise of <note n="RC1">Mr <lb/>Chichester</note> to get what Fraiming Stuff I have Occasion for off of h<corr resp="editor">[is]</corr> <lb/>Land for my buildings at the Town which will save a great deal of La<corr resp="editor">[bour]</corr></p>

<p>The Tallow you send me Down is of very different <abbr expan="weights">wts:</abbr> your beef <lb/>yielded 31 pounds the <note n="RF1">RichLand</note> 33 pounds and one half the <note n="PQ">Park</note> 18 3/4 pounds and the <note n="PQ1">Pop<lb/>lar</note> but 14 1/4 pounds. your and RichLand is a great deal short of what I <lb/><sic corr="Used">Usd</sic> to have but Certainly Williams &amp; Sabin have <abbr expan="played">play'd</abbr> the rogue <lb/>egregiously in their Tallow</p>

<p>What <sic corr="Hogs">Hoggs</sic> I am to have I must have them Drove down to me <lb/>and I would have them come in Two <sic corr="parcels">parcells</sic> as <note target="n2">Roger Oxford</note> indeed pro<lb/><abbr expan="posed">pos'd</abbr> to Me to be the best way its very common to the Southward to drive <lb/><sic corr="Hogs">Hoggs</sic> as far they put them into Large enclosures three or four days be<lb/>fore they set off with them and Drive them about with Horses and <lb/>then they tell me they manage them with a great deal of ease there are <lb/>Several Gentlemen in the way that I dare say would Afford them con<lb/>veniencys for <add place="supralinear">a </add>Night As <note target="n3"><abbr expan="Major">Majr:</abbr> Thornton</note> <note n="NS"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Smith</note> there is <note n="MP1"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> <lb/>Pages </note><abbr expan="Quarter">Qr</abbr> at Nansatico where particular Orders are given to give enter=<lb/><abbr expan="tainment">tainmt</abbr>. to my Overseers and <sic corr="Hogs">Hoggs</sic> then there is the head of <lb/><note n="NH2">Nomini</note> Next to that my <note n="FP">Fieldings</note> and my <note n="MF1"><sic corr="Morattico">Merattico</sic></note> <abbr expan="quarters">qrs:</abbr> and so down to the <lb/><note n="OF">Office</note> these Stages in My thoughts will make the Matter Easy I have <lb/><abbr expan="promised">promis'd</abbr> Ben and Jacob and the Carpenter boys that they shall come <lb/>down this Christmas to see their relations I reckon about that 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
time these <sic corr="Hogs">Hoggs</sic> will be fit to come away You may Contrive to let the <lb/>Carpenters come at the same time and to make them Help down <lb/>with the <sic corr="Hogs">Hoggs</sic> which will save <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> sending Others</p>

<p>I have bought <note target="n4">Innis's</note> land the Deeds are executed I had <lb/>once intended to send them to you to get them Acknowledged but I was exp<lb/>ecting to be up at this Court I thought it more proper to send them to <abbr expan="Major">Majr:</abbr> <lb/>Thornton I have also sent to him mine and my familys Deeds for the <note target="n5">town</note> <lb/>Lots in Order to their being Acknowledged our best Lawyers Assure me <lb/>it is Absolutely necessary to be done three of the Witnesses Appearing and giv<lb/>ing their <sic corr="testimony">testamony</sic> to the Execution of the Deeds confirms the title and no<lb/>thing less will do you that are the Evidences at least three of you I hope will <lb/>not fail to Appear at the Court for this purpose and I reckon all that have <lb/>bought Lots will be willing to have the same Security</p>

<p>I hope the Overseers <note target="n6"><sic corr="Shelton">Shilton</sic></note> and <note target="n7"><sic corr="Threadkill">Threalkild</sic></note> are with you <lb/>before now and roundly at their business I hope they will prove a Couple <lb/>of brisk fellows in your next you will be Able to give me a near Accot. of <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> <lb/>Crops both of corn and <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobo:</abbr> my crops of Corn here are Considerable Lar<lb/>ger <sic corr="than">then</sic> they were Last year I shall be glad to find yours so too</p>

<p>I have sent by <note target="n8">Charles Brent</note> Murdocks Deed to be delivered <lb/>with your Approbation the Charges of it I shall make you <abbr expan="Debtor">Dr:</abbr> for</p>

<p>I hope Hurst is upon my Town house Ding dong I have <lb/>bought Innis's land for money Am Under no Obligation of building anything <lb/>for him</p>

<closer><seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note> The name of Carter's home, "Corotoman," the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] John Hust (or Hurst) was the overseer of "Hamstead Quarter," Stafford County, in the 1732 inventory, supervising  sixteen slaves with the assistance of one horse. Hust apparently was a carpenter because Carter mentions his doing carpentry work in various letters. (<cit><bibl n="A26">Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Roger Oxford was the overseer at Norman's Ford.</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Major William Thornton (d. 1742/43) of King George County. (<cit><bibl><title>King George County Virginia Will Book A-1 1721-1752 And Miscellaneous Notes.</title> [Fredericksburg, VA: Privately Printed, 1978], p. 277.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Carter acquired this Richmond County property toward the end of 1728. Enoch Innis inherited it from his father, James, who died in 1709. (<cit><bibl>Lucy Jane Brent Palmer, "Charles Brent of Stafford County and Some of His Descendants," <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography</title>, 34(1926): 280-85 and 378-84</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl>"Abstracts From Records of Richmond County, Virginia," <title>William and Mary Quarterly</title>, (1)17(1908-09): 176-177, which cites records of Richmond County concerning this will, probated 25 December 1709, as from Will Book 3</bibl></cit>).</note>

<note id="n5">[5] The new town of Falmouth was created by the Assembly in February 1727. Carter, Mann Page, Nicholas Smith, William Thornton, John Fitzhugh, Charles Carter, and Henry Fitzhugh the younger were the "directors and trustees." The land chosen for the site of the new town lay in King George County, and deeds would have been recorded in its court records.  (<cit><bibl>William Waller Hening, <title>The Statutes at Large; Being a Collection of the Laws of Virginia . . . . </title>[Richmond, 1820. reprint, 1969]. IV, 234-39.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] Henry Shelton was one of Carter's overseers, and they settled in December 1722 on terms for his employment for the coming year as Carter noted in his diary.</note>

<note id="n7">[7] William Threalkill (Threalkild) is mentioned in the inventory of Carter's estate as the overseer at Poplar Quarter, Stafford County. (<cit><bibl n="A26">Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>.)</note>

<note id="n8">[8] Charles Brent (d. 13 January 1756) of Overwharton Parish, Stafford County, married to Hannah Innes. He acted as collector of quit rents for Carter in the county.</note>







</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>