<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C29e26a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Captain John Hyde and Company, May 26, 1729</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C29e26a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005, 2015</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Captain John Hyde and Company, May 26, 1729</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1728 August 8-1730 May 15,  Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1729-05-26</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C29e26aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1729-05-26"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C29e26a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Captain John Hyde and Company, May 26, 1729</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchants Captain John Hyde and Company, May 26, 1729, to enclose a bill of lading (not present) for 40 hogsheads of his own tobacco on board their ship the <hi rend="italics">Providence,</hi> and reporting that he had prevailed upon Captain Woodward to give him a pipe of madeira that was on board the ship because he had lost his wines when his house burned. He orders two more pipes.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Captain <note n="JH2">John Hyde</note> and Company, May 26, 1729</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1729-05-26">May 26th. 1729</date><lb/>
Capt John Hyde &amp; Compa.<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p><note target="n1"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Woodward</note> now leaving <del>our river </del> <add place="supralinear">us</add> wth design to <lb/><sic corr="lie">lye</sic> in the <note target="n2">freshes</note> of James river <sic corr="until">till</sic> the fleet sails I give you this <lb/>short <abbr expan="entertainment">entertainmt</abbr> reserving my self for <abbr expan="Enlargement">Enlargemt </abbr><sic corr="until">till</sic> my next</p>

<p>This Encloses a <note target="n3">bill of Lading</note> for forty hogsheads of my <lb/>own Crop <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobo</abbr> on board the <name type="ship">Providence</name> you will be <sic corr="informed">informd</sic> from <abbr expan="your">yr:</abbr> <lb/><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> how kind I have been to him in filling him up when he was <lb/>at a Loss to make up his load any otherway <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> upon the <note target="n4">loss of my house </note><lb/>and destruction of all the Old wines I had <sic corr="prevailed">prevaild</sic> wth Woodward <lb/>Upon his not bringing me in Any wine by the order you had send to <lb/><name type="place"><sic corr="Madeira">Maderas</sic></name> to spare me a Pipe of the wine he had taken on board <lb/>for your S<corr resp="editor">[e]</corr>lf which I daresay you will not be <sic corr="disatisfied">disatisfyed</sic> 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
at leaving it to you to Charge me for it as you shall think Proper <lb/>and <sic corr="lest">least</sic> I should forget it hereafter I now desire you to send fresh <lb/>orders by <sic corr="Correspondents">Corrispondts</sic> in <sic corr="Madeira">Maderas</sic> to send me Two Pipes of their <lb/>best wines if <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> Ship comes that way again I had rather have <lb/>it by her than any Other</p>

<p>I have <note target="n5">drawn upon you</note> &pound;40"12"3 payable to <lb/><abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> <abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> which I desire may be Answered on my Accot who Am <lb/></p>

<closer>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sirs <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<abbr expan="Your">Yr:</abbr> most Humble Servt.<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>

per Wooodward</seg>
</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Thomas Woodward commanded the <hi rend="italics">Providence,</hi> a ship owned by Captain John Hyde &amp; Company, during a number of voyages to the colony, 1723-1729. (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800 summarizing Adm. 68/194 and Survey Report 6801 summarizing Adm 68/195, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia,</bibl></cit> and Carter's letter to the firm, 1723 September 17.)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] The <title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title> defines "freshes" as " containing fresh as opposed to salt water."  Carter means that Captain Woodward planned to anchor his ship at the point in the James River where the salt water turned to fresh.</note>

<note id="n3"> [3] A bill of lading is "an official detailed receipt given by the master of a merchant vessel to the person consigning the goods, by which he makes himself responsible for their safe delivery to the consignee. This document, being the legal proof of ownership of the goods, is often deposited with a creditor as security for money advanced."  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title>. Oxford University Press.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4]  Robert Carter's home, "Corotoman," was located on the northeastern bank of the Rapphannock River in Lancaster County close to the present-day community of Weems.  A stream called Corrotoman [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>] River ran inland west of the house. Carter built a fine house there in the mid 1720s, but it burned in January 1729. See the <xref to="http://www.christchurch1735.org/history/corotoman.html">"Corotoman" page</xref> of the web site of Historic Christ Church Foundation for more information about the house and excavation of its ruins.  ( See the <hi rend="italics">Maryland Gazette</hi> for February 4-11, 1728/29 for comment on Carter's loss. The Maryland Archives has placed its copies of the  <hi rend="italics">Maryland Gazette</hi> online. Unfortunately, page four of the issue of February 4-11, 1728/29 is missing, and that must be where the notice of the fire at Corotoman appeared; the text is quoted in secondary sources as reading: "The fine large house of Colonel Carter on the Rappahannock was also burnt lately. The particulars of his loss we can't give you, but we are inform'd it is very great." [<hi rend="italics">Garden Club of Virginia Journal</hi>, May-June 1983, p.8.]) </note>

<note id="n5"> [5] A bill of exchange is a kind of check or promissory note without interest.  It is used primarily in international trade, and is a written order by one person to pay another a specific sum on a specific date sometime in the future.  If the bill of exchange is drawn on a bank, it is called a bank draft.  If it is drawn on another party, it is called a trade draft.  Sometimes a bill of exchange will simply be called a draft, but whereas a draft is always  negotiable (transferable by endorsement), this is not necessarily true of a bill of exchange. (See <cit><bibl><xref to="http://www.fraudaid.com/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms/bill_of_exchange.htm">"Bill of Exchange"</xref> in the online Dictionary of Financial Scam Terms: the Truth vs. the Scam.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2005, was revised February 24, 2015,  to add footnotes and strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>



</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>