<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C29e24a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Major [John] Holloway, May 24, 1729</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 11 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C29e24a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Major [John] Holloway, May 24, 1729</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1729-05-24</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C29e24aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1729-05-24"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C29e24a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Major [John] Holloway, May 24, 1729</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Major [John] Holloway, May 24, 1729, to ask his legal opinion of Carter's right to make grants of land in the western areas of Virginia which Carter believes to be part of the holdings of the proprietor of the Northern Neck for whom he is agent.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Major <note n="JH">[John] Holloway,</note> May 24, 1729</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Corotoman, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1729-05-24">May the 24th. 1729</date><lb/>
Majr Holloway<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>



<p>It will not be improper for me to give you the best Scheme I <lb/>can <add place="supralinear"><abbr expan="according">accordg.</abbr> to my Informations</add> how the river of <sic corr="Potomac">Patowmack</sic> branches <add place="supralinear">take their <sic corr="Courses">Cours's</sic></add> above the falls thereof</p>

<p>There are many runs making into the Northern Neck which <lb/>all of them are Inhabited more or less, One of them about 30 mil<corr resp="editor">[e]</corr>s above the Falls is &amp;<lb/>Called <note target="n1">Goose Creek</note> <add place="supralinear">up to this Creek and above it is inhabited</add> the branches of this is <sic corr="reckoned">reckond</sic> to lock into the Northern branches <lb/>of the North Stream of Rappahannock as <add place="supralinear">you</add> will observe by Savage's <sic corr="Plat,">Platt,</sic> beyond Goose <lb/>Creek about 15 Miles comes down a ridge of <del>Small</del> mountains from Rappahannock <lb/>Almost to the very side of <sic corr="Potomac">Patowmack</sic> river and is Called by the hunters the blue <lb/>ridge beyond this blue ridge about a Mile up the run of <sic corr="Potomac">Patowmack</sic> the river <lb/>forks, the main river which the <add place="supralinear">Indians</add> call <note target="n2">Cohunkaruta </note>keeps up to the Westward <lb/>the other branch which makes this fork runs away to the South West <sic corr="Called">Calld</sic> by <lb/>the Indians <sic corr="Shenandoah">Chenandoa</sic> and by the Inhabitants Jerundo, This branch is Sup<lb/>posed to run above the branches of Rappahannock after it has left the great Stream of <lb/><sic corr="Potomac">Patowmack</sic> a Considerable way it may be 40 or 50 Miles it forks again &amp; in <lb/>this fork as I am <sic corr="informed">informd</sic> <note target="n3">Larkin Chew</note> and his Company made their <lb/>Surveys I must own below this fork of <sic corr="Shenandoah,">Chenandoa</sic> on the upper Side of it, not <lb/>far from the mouth of it where it leaves the main river Cohunkaruta I have <lb/>had lately 2 or 3 Surveys made but have <sic corr="passed">pas'd</sic> no Deeds for Lands there <lb/>not that I can See any the least reason to doubt these Lands being Expressly <lb/>within <note target="n4">the Grant,</note> If the words of it have any plain meaning even from the <lb/>Doctrine that <sic corr="has">hath</sic> taken awy the lower fork <add place="supralinear">of Rappad<corr resp="editor">[an]</corr></add> from the <abbr expan="Proprietors">Proprs.</abbr> where the only <lb/>reason pretended is that the Northern branch is the bigger &amp; larger Stream,</p>

<p>The Maryland Grant bounds it self <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> by Cohunkaruta <lb/>and is inhabited a great way above the mouth of <sic corr="Shenandoah,">Chenandoa</sic></p>

<p>I Send you this <abbr expan="entertainment">entertainmt.</abbr> for yor. Consideration and to <lb/>have yor. Opinion whether by any fair Interpretation these Lands above <lb/><sic corr="Shenandoah">Chenandoa</sic> can be Construed out of <abbr expan="proprietors">propriers.</abbr> Grant and <add place="supralinear">to</add> belong to the Crown It <lb/>Seems my passing a Deed or two in the <abbr expan="Second">Secd</abbr> fork of the Northern <add place="supralinear">branches</add> of Rappahannock under my <lb/>presumption in making Some Surveys upon the upper side of <sic corr="Shenandoah">Chenandoa</sic> <lb/>is <sic corr="looked">lookd</sic> upon as a Crime so heinous That nothing less is threatned then the <lb/>Destruction of the <abbr expan="proprietors">propriers.</abbr> Grant for it.</p>

<p>Its the wise mans Saying in the multitudes of <sic corr="Counselors">Counsellors</sic> <lb/>there is Safety and I Always have a very great dependance upon yor. Opinion <lb/>in these <sic corr="Perplexed">Perplexd</sic> Cases <sic corr="Although">Altho</sic> I think this cannot properly be called a <lb/><abbr expan="Perplexed">Perplex'd</abbr> Case,</p>

<closer></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a 19th-century transcript of the letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.
</note>

<note>The county and colony have been added for clarity to the heading on this draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Goose Creek flows into the Potomac River just east of Leesburg in modern Loudoun County.</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Cohunkaruta is probably what we continue to call the Potomac today.</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Larkin Chew (ca. 1708-1770) and his brothers John and Thomas were born in Spotsylvania County and speculated  in land there when the county was huge. "But for the twelve years from 1722 to 1734 it contained within its bounds the present Piedmont counties of Orange, Culpeper, Madison, Rappahannock and Greene, as well as the
Valley counties of Rockingham, Page and Warren." Both Larkin and Thomas served as sheriff at various times.  (<cit><bibl>http://www.ronulrich.com/rfuged/fam04050.htm, 1/10/2005 citing Spotsylvania County 1721-1800; Will Book D 1761-1772; page 25: Chew, Larkin Spotsylvanla Co., d. Mar. 27, 1770, Executors Bond dated Sept. 21, 1770;</bibl></cit>  <cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]: 66, 86, 173, 439. </bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl>Nathaniel Mason Pawlett. <title>Spotsylvania County Road Orders 1722-1734.</title> [Charlottesville, VA: Virginia Highway &amp; Transportation Research Council, 1985], 2.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Carter refers to the grant to the proprietors of the Northern Neck.</note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>