<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C29f25c">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas, Lord Fairfax, June 25, 1729</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C29f25c.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas, Lord Fairfax, June 25, 1729</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1729-06-25</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C29f25cT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1729-06-25"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C29f25c.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas, Lord Fairfax, June 25, 1729</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Thomas, Lord Fairfax, June 25, 1729, to inform him of the latest actions of the Council regarding the Northern Neck proprietary, and urging him to find as many suporters of the proprietary in England as he can.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Thomas, <note n="TF">Lord Fairfax,</note> June 25, 1729</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1729-06-25">June the 25th. 1729</date><lb/>
To the Right honble. the Ld. Fairfax<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>My Lord&mdash;</salute>

</opener>



<p>Upon Considering the orders of Council lately made <del>on</del><add place="supralinear">upon</add><lb/>
my puting in Caveats in your Lordships behalf I <abbr expan="cannot">cant</abbr> but observe that there <lb/>
appears to me to be a wide diference between former <abbr expan="Governors">Govrs.</abbr> Granting away the <lb/>
Lands in the <note target="n1">little Fork</note> when there was no Caveat put in against them &amp; those <lb/>
back woods was then very little known and the <note n="WG">Present <abbr expan="Governors">Govrs.</abbr></note> <sic corr="Continuing">Continueing</sic> these Grants <lb/>
after a Caveat is <sic corr="Entered">Enterd</sic> and Such Plain Proof <abbr expan="offered">offer'd</abbr> that these Lands are within <lb/>
your Lordships bounds. Perhaps my reasoning may have no force in it. I have had<lb/>
Some private hints <add place="supralinear">from my Lawyers that they thought</add> the Govr. was not very forward in going into this order <lb/>
but the Opinion of the Major part of the Council <sic corr="prevailed">prevaild</sic> however it was your <lb/>
Lordship may Conclude it to be highly necessary for your Lordship to make as <lb/>
many friends as Possibly you can in England for I doubt the Grant will meet <lb/>
with but few friends here unless Some folks are made to know that the Estate <lb/>
is above their reach. In the other order you will meet with a great many new <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Invented

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>

names Such as Happy Creek. Cape Leanock. and the fork of Leanock ri<corr resp="editor">[ver]</corr><lb/>
and the fork of Cape Leanock Run and all <sic corr="laid">layd</sic> down to lye in <sic corr="Spotsylvan">Spotsilvan</sic><corr resp="editor">[ia]</corr><lb/>
County Contrived under these names never heard of before but in reality <lb/>
According to all <sic corr="Information">Informations</sic> I can get they are only streams Issuing <lb/>
out of <sic corr="Shenandoah">Chenandoa</sic> and discharge themselves <sic corr="through">thro</sic> it and if <sic corr="Spotsylvania">Spotsilvania</sic> <lb/>
County be to be Extended to all the Lands on the upper side of <sic corr="Shenandoah">Chenandoa</sic> the <lb/>
great stream of <sic corr="Potomac">Patowmack</sic> which I have often <sic corr="Called">Calld</sic> Cohunkoruta <lb/>
the Indian name will be its Boundary and will surround to the Westward <lb/>
all your Lordships Grant I have Said Enough to give your Lordship a Right <lb/>
Idea of the nature of the place And it may be more then was necessary</p>

<closer><seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a 19th-century transcript of the letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to persons abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] The Fry-Jefferson map shows the Little Fork as a tributary of the Hedgman (now the Rappahannock) River. It lies in what is probably Culpeper County today, not far from the Blue Ridge. </note>





</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>