<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C29f27g">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to [John] Pratt, June 27, 1729</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 11 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C29f27g.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to [John] Pratt, June 27, 1729</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1728 August 8-1730 May 15,  Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1729-06-27</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C29f27gT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1729-06-27"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C29f27g.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to [John] Pratt, June 27, 1729</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his old friend London merchant [John] Pratt, June 27, 1729, detailing his illnesses and the remedies of Pratt's that he has adopted, and hoping Pratt will continue to advise him.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">[John] Pratt,</note> June 27, 1729</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1729-06-27">June 27th. 1729</date><lb/>

</dateline>
<salute>My good Daddy Pratt&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>I am indebted to you for your Letter of the 24th. of <abbr expan="October">Octobr.</abbr><lb/>
 a very kind one it is.  Your advice in relation to my health and management of<lb/>
 my self in my infirmities is most <sic corr="Obliging">Obligeing</sic> I have followed your advices in <lb/>
several respects I have drunk a great deal of <sic corr="Spa">Spaw</sic>  water. I had some of the <lb/>
Bristol water sent me from thence in which I have soaked myself very Plen=<lb/>
=tifully and I have also taken a preat deal of <add place="supralinear">your</add> receipt and Intend to Continue it <lb/>
but your directions to refrain Eating Butter every manner of way I think imposs<lb/>
ible to follow there being nothing <sic corr="we">wee</sic> eat but must have butter to make it savou<lb/>
ry and I dare say <abbr expan="Doctor">Doctr.</abbr> Bave himself can much Easier give this advice <sic corr="than">then</sic> <lb/>
take it, however I follow it as.much as reasonably I can with abundance of <lb/>
regularity and a great deal of Exercise with the use of frequent Purges of <note target="n2">And=<lb/>
=ersons pills</note> I make a shift to keep my distemper at a tolerable Bay the time of <lb/>
my greatest disturbance is about midnight when I am so frequently oppresed <lb/>
that I know not how to live the greatest of my Malady proceeds from wind Occ=<lb/>
=<sic corr="asioned">asiond</sic> I conceit by a difficult and bad  digestion of my food sometimes my <lb/>
<sic corr="fits">fitts</sic> are so violent heaving me into so much Confusion which makes me un<lb/>
fit for any business take away all my resolution distracts my mind &amp; <lb/>
fills me with ungovernable thoughts <sic corr="rendering">rendring</sic> all the <sic corr="Ideas">Idie's</sic> of my soul in dark <lb/>
and <sic corr="discouraging">discourageing</sic> Colours.which I have not the power to <sic corr="dispel">dispell</sic> by the Consid<lb/>
<sic corr="erations">eracions</sic> of all the liberal mercys I am under which by the good hand of Providence<lb/>
I must own are not a few and when ever I transgress a little either in Eating <lb/>
or drinking to be sure that night I am to be miserably tormented.</p>

<p><corr resp="editor">[I tell you]</corr> so much the history of my <sic corr="Maladies">Maladys</sic> being in hopes

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
you may be able to give me some further advice, for my distemper I thank you <lb/>
kindly for you <sic corr="putting">puting</sic> <note target="n3">Mr. Falconar</note> upon sending me some German <sic corr="Spa">Spaw</sic> water <lb/>
I have already sent away my Invoice to him and have forgot to send for any <lb/>
more of it, but I will write to him about it hereafter and request you to put him <lb/>
in mind to send me the same Quantity next Year as he did this. <del>I heart</del></p> 

	<p>I heartily congratulate you upon your recovery after <sic corr="we">wee</sic> had <lb/>
several letters <sic corr="advising">adviseing</sic> us that <add place="supralinear">the</add> Doctors. had given you over as a <sic corr="gone">gon</sic> man, May <lb/>
you and I make use of the remaining time God shall please to allow us to the<lb/>
best Purposes for his glory and our Comfort. I thank God as far as I hear at <lb/>
this time all our <sic corr="families">familys</sic>  are in tolerable health. My <note n="ECB">Daughter Nicholas</note> <lb/>
is a very crazy ailing body. All this family salutes you In the Quality of a <lb/>
most <sic corr="Esteemed">Esteemd</sic> Daddy Particularly him who heartily prays for your happiness <lb/>
&amp; is, 
</p>

<closer>Sir<lb/>
Yor. most obliged humble Servt.
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>Another Affliction I am under I <lb/>
have had sore running Eyes for near <lb/>
two Year and cant find any remedy. <lb/><lb/>

per <note target="n4"><sic corr="Bailey">Baily</sic></note>
</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] John Pratt was a London merchant and an old friend of Carter's who usually referred to him as "Daddy."</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Anderson's Scots Pills, a product of the 1630's, had been invented by Patrick Anderson, a Scot, who wrote in a book published in 1635 that he had learned the secret of the pills in Venice. He passed the formula to his daughter Katherine who in turn passed it to a doctor named Thomas Weir in 1686. Weir obtained letters patent on the formula from James II in 1687. (<cit><bibl>George B. Griffenhagen and James Harvey Young, "Old English Patent Medicines in America," in <title>Contributions From the Museum of History and Technology</title> (Washington, D.C.: Smithsonian Institution, 1959), paper 10, 156-183.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] John Falconar (d. <hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1729) was a London merchant with whom Carter dealt. In 1728, Falconar and Henry Darnell formed an association of 29 London tobacco merchants to deal with the French tobacco purchasing agent as a group in order to keep the price as high as possible. The association lasted only lasted a year or two before dissolving because some of its members were dealing directly with the French agent and selling below the agreed-upon price. (See Carter to William Dawkins, and Carter to Falconar's executors, both 1730 April 16, for Falconar's death date. <cit><bibl>Arthur Pierce Middleton. <title>Tobacco Coast:  A Maritime History of the Chesapeake Bay in the Colonial Era.</title> Newport News, VA: Mariners' Museum, 1953. p. 129</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] The <hi rend="italics">Bailey</hi> was a London ship owned by William Dawkins and commanded at various times by Adam Graves (1725-1730) and by Thomas Dove (1731-1732). She was a vessel of some 250 tons and carried 15-17 crew members. (<cit><bibl>Survey report 6801 summarizing Adm. 68/195, 156v, and other data in Adm. 68/194 and /196, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small  Special Collections Library, University of Virginia;</bibl></cit> A letter of Carter's executors to Dawkins 1738 May 10 refers to "your ship Bailey.")</note>
 



</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>