<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C29f30b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Major George Eskridge, June 30, 1729</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C29f30b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Major George Eskridge, June 30, 1729</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1729-06-30</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C29f30bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1729-06-30"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C29f30b.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Major George Eskridge, June 30, 1729</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his friend and agent in Westmoreland County, Major George Eskridge, June 30, 1729, about his pressing need for cash and urges Eskridge to press the collection of quit rents.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Major <note n="GE">George Eskridge,</note> June 30, 1729</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Corotom<add resp="editor">[an, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1729-06-30">June 30. 1729</date><lb/>
Majr. George Eskridge<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>



<p>when you were here I know you intended to<lb/>
be at our July Court &amp; I hope you will but <sic corr="lest">least</sic> you should fail<lb/>
I can't for bear to put you in mind how poor I am how few bills of<lb/>
Exchange I have <abbr expan="received">receiv'd</abbr> this year and how low my stock of Cash is so tht.<lb/>
I am hardly Able to Pay my debts which I Expect Every day will be<lb/>
Called for and how little money I <abbr expan="received">receiv'd</abbr> for my <note target="n1">Quit rents</note> this year<lb/>
not a third of what has been paid me for several years Past</p>

<p>Upon Consideration of these my Uncommon ne:<lb/>
cessitys I press you strongly to get me all the money you Can I hope<lb/>
you have begun prosecutions for my fines against those you have<lb/>
any reason to suspect will not pay without</p>

<p><note target="n2">Mr Downman</note> you told me owns to have<lb/>
twenty pounds of the money in his hands pray take a right method

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
to get it of him that I may have it to Answer my Present<lb/>
Calls And sure of my Other debts will be got this year for me</p>

<p>Mr <note n="JC2">James Carter</note> tells me he was promised by the<lb/>
gentlemen of Stafford to pay their rents to the Value of &pound;100<lb/>
who now shuffle with him and tell him they must Pay <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobo</abbr> at<lb/>
last I order him to sue for the money Upon their <note target="n3">Assumpsits</note><lb/>
thinking my self not Obliged to take <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobo:</abbr> so late in the year<lb/>
for their last years rents and I dare say you will be of the same<lb/>
of Opinion</p>

<p><note n="WR1"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Robinson</note> for All his fine promises to you hath<lb/>
never yet paid his rents to Mr Carter I am
</p>

<closer>Your Affectionate Humble Servt.</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.There is a nineteenth-century copy of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note>

<note>The county and colony have been added for clarity to the heading on this draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Quit rent was the term used for the payment due from the holder of land to the "lord of the manor," in this case, to the proprietors of the Northern Neck. Carter as the proprietor's agent, collected these payments. No services were required of the landholder as had been true in mediaeval times.</note>

<note id="n2">[2] William Downman was a justice of Richmond County from 1718, sheriff  in 1722 and 1723, and a tobacco inspector in 1731 and 1732. (<cit><bibl n="B31">Ryland. <title>Richmond County Virginia. . . . </title> p. 504.</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]: 12, 34, 238, 286.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] An assumpsit is "an agreement or promise made orally or in writing not under seal; a contract." (<cit><bibl>"Answers.com." http://www.answers.com/assumpsits&r=67. 7/21/2005</bibl></cit>)</note> 




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>