<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C29h26a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to James Bradley, August 26, 1729</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C29h26a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005, 2015</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to James Bradley, August 26, 1729</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1729-08-26</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C29h26aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1729-08-26"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C29h26a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to James Bradley, August 26, 1729</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant James Bradley, August 26, 1729, to order additional goods including a "close stool," "Mill brasses," nails, stockings, etc., and a suit and accessories for himself. He writes of the heavy rains during the spring that have damaged the crops. In a post script, he asks Bradley to be one of the securities for his so Charles as naval officer of the Rappahannock.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">James Bradley,</note> August 26, 1729</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1729-08-26">Augst 26. 1729</date><lb/>
Mr: James Bradley<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir</salute>

</opener>



<p>The chief occasion of this is to desire a Small addition<lb/>
of Goods may be made to those I have already sent to you for. <note target="n2">(Vizt)</note><lb/>
a <note target="n3">close stool</note> <add place="supralinear">(besides that <del>[illegible]</del> in my former invoice</add> for a Chamber  to be round all of Wood Except the pan to have<lb/>
a lock to it of this sort I have seen very handy ones;) A Set of <note target="n4">Mill brasses</note><lb/>
one for the Spindle two for the Gudgeons) Six <abbr expan="dozen">doz:</abbr> Strong mens plains<lb/>
<sic corr="Common">Carmen</sic> Shoes. 2 <abbr expan="dozen">doze:</abbr> 14s: 2 <abbr expan="dozen">doze.</abbr> 12s: 2 <abbr expan="dozen">doze:</abbr> 10s,) Six <abbr expan="dozen">doz</abbr> large Irish Sto:<lb/>
<sic corr="ckings">ckins</sic>.) fifty thousand 8s nails 30 thousand 10s nails;) 500 <abbr expan="pounds">lbs:</abbr> of Iron for hoes in flat<lb/>
<sic corr="Bars">Barrs</sic> 1/2 for weeding hoes) Half a dozen pound of Powder for <note target="n5"><sic corr="periwigs">periwiggs</sic></note><lb/>
One quart <abbr expan="perfumed">perfum'd</abbr> <sic corr="oil">oyle</sic> for Ditto:) And a fashonable suit of broad<lb/>
Cloth <sic corr="Clothes">Cloths</sic> for my self for the Winter of a grave Colour lined with <note target="n6"><sic corr="Shalloon">Shaloon</sic></note><lb/>
Mr: How has my measures and knows how to fit me he took it in<lb/>
Virginia and <sic corr="has">hath</sic> also made me <sic corr="Clothes">Cloaths</sic> since I am become <del>a great</del> <add place="supralinear">much</add> sm<lb/>
aller in Bulk than I was at that time, Also a <abbr expan="pair">pr:</abbr> of <abbr expan="Milled">Mill'd</abbr> <sic corr="Stockings">Stockins</sic><lb/>
and a pair of <note target="n7"><sic corr="Worsted">Worstead</sic></note> <sic corr="Stockings">Stockins</sic> to suit the <sic corr="Clothes">Cloths</sic> I hope this letter will<lb/>
get <corr resp="editor">[to you in]</corr> time Enough for the <add place="supralinear">goods</add> to come away with the rest</p>
	
<p>You will have an <abbr expan="Account">Accot</abbr> from all hands of the great<lb/>
destruction in our Crops by the continual floods of rain we have had<lb/>
this Summer which will make them much short of what they were last<lb/>
year some reckon a third some a fourth some More I shall make no guess.<lb/>
es this with our <note target="n8">Liberty of Stemming</note> must of Necessity influence the<lb/>
Market Considerably and we hope for that already gone I am 

</p>

<closer>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sir <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Your most humble <abbr expan="Servant">Servt:</abbr>

<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>A Clause to be added to Mr. Bradleys letter <abbr expan="August">Augst.</abbr> 26th. 1729<lb/>
Sir<lb/>
	not many days <sic corr="ago">agoe</sic> our <note n="WG"><abbr expan="Governor">Govr</abbr></note> <sic corr="has">hath</sic> been so kind to give<lb/>
my Son <note n="CC1">Charles</note> (who is now at Mans Estate and I <sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> of whom you<lb/>
have some Remembrance) a Commission for the <note target="n9"><abbr expan="Naval Officer's">N Offr</abbr> place</note><lb/>
of <note target="n10">our river</note> he <sic corr="has">hath</sic> given Security here but Security must<lb/>
Also be given to the Commissioners of the Customs for the due<lb/>
discharge of this office I have <sic corr="writxten">writ</sic> to <note n="WD">Mr. Dawkins</note> to be one<lb/>
of his Securitys and he hath <sic corr="writxten">writ</sic> to <note n="EA">Mr Athawes</note> to be the Other<lb/>
I tell Mr. Dawkins any of the <abbr expan="Merchants">Merchts</abbr> that <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> I Correspond with<lb/>
I <sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> will be <sic corr="joined">joyned</sic> with Him particularly naming you<lb/>
If there be Occasion I request it of you and I will be <abbr expan="your">yr. </abbr><lb/>
Counter Security</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a nineteenth-century copy of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note>

<note>Thhe numerous parens seem to havve been entered by Carter's clerk, but probbably for some other reason than parenthetical expressions because they are not used to enclose sets of words.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] James Bradley was a London merchant with whom Carter dealt from at least 1723 until his death. As noted in his letter to Bradley of <xref to="/users/berkeley/public/C27e17a.html">May 17, 1727,</xref> Bradley owned the <hi rend="italics">Welcome,</hi> but little information about Bradley has been located. (There is a listing of the firm of Bradly &amp; Griffin, Merchants, Fenchurch-street, opposite the Mitre Tavern, on page 13 of <cit><bibl><title><xref to="freepages.history.rootsweb.com/~frpayments/KD1740/AB.htm">Kent's Directory </xref>For the Year 1740 Containing An Alphabetical List of the Names and Places of Abode of the Directors of Companies, Persons in Publick Business, Merchants, and other Eminent Traders in the Cities of London and Westminster, and the Borough of Southwark.</title>  [London: Printed and Sold by Henry Kent in Finch-Lane, near the Royal Exchange: and by the Booksellers and Pamphlets Shops of London and Westminster, 1740]. p. 39. Online, examined 8/12/2005 and 6/14/2012. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Vizt. is the abbreviation for the Latin word "videlicet";  it means "that is to say; namely; to wit: used to introduce an amplification, or more precise or explicit explanation, of a previous statement or word." (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary</title> online.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] "A <xref to="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Close_stool">close stool</xref>, used from at least the sixteenth century until the introduction of indoor plumbing, was an enclosed cabinet or box at sitting height with an opening in the top, which might be disguised by a folding outer lid. The close stool contained a pewter or earthenware chamberpot. . . ." (Wikipedia. 5/15/2015.  The <title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title> states that it is "a seat enclosing a chamber utensil; a commode; more explicitly stool of ease.) </note> 

<note id="n4">[4] By the term "mill brasses," Carter means the <xref to="https://millsarchive.org/explore/glossary/b">bearings</xref>. (See the <xref to="https://millsarchive.org/about">"Mills Archive"</xref> online.</note>

<note id="n5">[5] A periwig is "any highly stylized wig of a kind formerly worn by men and women, and (esp. in Britain and parts of the British Commonwealth) retained by judges and barristers as part of their professional dress. More generally: a wig of any kind."  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title>. Oxford University Press.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] Shalloon is "a closely woven woollen material chiefly used for linings.   (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title>. Oxford University Press.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n7">[7] Worsted is "a woollen fabric or stuff made from well-twisted yarn spun of long-staple wool combed to lay the fibres parallel."  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title>. Oxford University Press.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n8">[8]Parliament had passed an act forbidding the importation of stemmed tobacco in 1722. John Randolph was sent to England in 1728 as agent for Virginia to try to have the act overturned; his mission was successful, and he was home in the colony by <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C29f02a.html">June 2, 1729</xref>, when Carter wrote to welcome him home. (<cit><bibl>Arthur Pierce Middleton. <title>Tobacco Coast:  A Maritime History of the Chesapeake Bay in the Colonial Era.</title> [Newport News, VA: Mariners' Museum, 1953], 116.</bibl></cit>)</note>

 <note id="n9">[9] The naval officer was an official in the colony that reported to the Commissioners of Customs, a body that had first been established in 1663; the group was reorganized several times, especially after 1688. The board was "intrusted with collection of customs both in England and the colonies." The board helped write many of the instructions for colonial governors in collaboration with the Privy Council. "Their direct connection with the colonies was through the governors, who were instructed to correspond with the commissioners, and to send them, every three months, lists of clearances, and also reports of illegal trading. The governor's agent in matters of trade was the naval officer whom he was empowered to appoint, but who was required by the 7th and 8th William III to give security to the commissioners of customs." (<cit><bibl>Louise Phillips Kellogg. <title>The American Colonial Charter. A Study of English Administration in Relation Thereto, Especialy after 1688.</title>  [Annual Report, American Historical Association. Vol. 1, Govt. Print. Off., 1904], p. 226.</bibl></cit> For a recent study, see <cit><bibl>Alvin Rabushka. <title>Taxation in Colonial America</title> [Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2008.]</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n10">[10] the Rappahannock</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2005, was revised May18 , 2015,  to add footnotes and strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>



</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>