<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C29h26e">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Messrs. Haswell &amp; Brooks, August 26, 1729</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C29h26e.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Messrs. Haswell &amp; Brooks, August 26, 1729</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1729-08-26</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C29h26eT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1729-08-26"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C29h26e.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Messrs. Haswell &amp; Brooks, August 26, 1729</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchants Messrs. Haswell &amp; Brooks, August 26, 1729, to thank them for their accounts of the passage through Parliament of the act repealing the prohibition against the importation of stemmed tobacco, and to report the damage to the colony's crops from heavy rains.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Messrs. <note target="n1">Haswell &amp; Brooks,</note> August 26, 1729</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1729-08-26">Augst. 26.1729</date><lb/>
Messrs. Haswell &amp; Brooks<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Gent</salute>

</opener>



<p>I thank you for the frequent Accots. <lb/>
you gave me of the Several Steps the <note target="n2">Act of <abbr expan="Parliament">Parliamt</abbr></note> <add place="supralinear">took</add> For <lb/>
releasing us from the bondage we were under in being prohibited <lb/>
from putting our Staple Commodity  into such Shapes as we ap<lb/>
prehended would prove most advantageous to Our Support now <sic corr="it is">tis</sic> <lb/>
a law as We reckon (<sic corr="although">altho</sic> I donot <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> yet hear any person has the news of its <lb/>
passing The Royal assent) We have great hopes that our Crops nicely <lb/>
managed will never fail to return us prizes that we may live by</p>

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<p>You will have from all hands the Accot. how the Violent and <lb/>
incessant rains this Summer have damaged our <abbr expan="present">prest.</abbr> Crops wch <lb/>
must of necessity be very much Short of what we made last and some <lb/>
preceeding years all these things raise our Crests to Expect better <lb/>
markets for the Tobo now gone home than we have met with for some <lb/>
years past</p>

<p>In my former letter I have already write the <sic corr="needful">needfull</sic> I shall <lb/>
Conclude at <abbr expan="present">prest.</abbr> 
</p>

<closer>Gent. <lb/>
Your most Humble Servt:</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Haswell and Brooks was a London firm listed in 1740 directories of that city. Samuel Haswell was a London Assurance director in Suffolk Lane. There are several men of the name "Brooks" in the directories including a Christopher Brooks, a ship broker, also located in Suffolk Lane. (<cit><bibl><title>A Compleat Guide to All Persons who have any Trade or Concern with the City of London and Ports adjacent. . . .</title> London: Printed for J. Osborn, at the Golden Ball in Pater-noster-row, MDXXXL</bibl></cit>; and  <cit><bibl><title>Kent's Directory For the Year 1740 Containing An Alphabetical List of the Names and Places of Abode of the Directors of Companies, Persons in Publick Business, Merchants, and other Eminent Traders in the Cities of London and Westminster, and the Borough of Southwark.</title>  London: Printed and Sold by Henry Kent in Finch-Lane, near the Royal Exchange: and by the Booksellers and Pamphlets Shops of London and Westminster, 1740. http://freepages.history.rootsweb.com/~frpayments/KD1740/AB.htm. 8/12/2005. p. 39.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Parliament had passed an act forbidding the importation of stemmed tobacco in 1722. John Randolph was sent to England in 1729 as agent for Virginia to try to have the act overturned; his mission would be successful.<corr resp="editor"></corr> (<cit><bibl>Arthur Pierce Middleton. <title>Tobacco Coast:  A Maritime History of the Chesapeake Bay in the Colonial Era.</title> [Newport News, VA: Mariners' Museum, 1953.] p. 116.</bibl></cit>)</note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>