<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C29h29b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, August 29, 1729</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.9  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C29h29b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005, 2015</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, August 29, 1729</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1729-08-29</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C29h29bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1729-08-29"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C29h29b.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, August 29, 1729</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Liverpool merchant John Pemberton, August 29, 1729, to report that he is sending 25 hogsheads of tobacco on Captain Ireland's Liverpool ship, and enclosing (not present) a bill of lading. He comments on the damage to crops done by the heavy rains of the summer.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="JP">John Pemberton,</note> August 29, 1729</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1729-08-29">Augst. 29th 1729</date><lb/>
Mr John Pemberton<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>



<p><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Ireland of your Port from James riv<lb/>
er Came <sic corr="here">hither</sic> seeking freight I made a <sic corr="Positive">Possitive</sic> <abbr expan="agreement">agreemt.</abbr> with <lb/>
him for Forty hogsheads he pretends he could not meet with a Sloop big eno:<lb/>
ugh so I have got but 25 in him the rest of my <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobo</abbr> is left <lb/>
Herein comes a <note target="n1">bill of Lading</note> for 20 hogsheads of my own Concern You <lb/>
will have the accot from all parts of the Abundance of rains <lb/>
that we have had this Summer all along many of the lowlands <lb/>
quite drowned all great Sufferers the high lands Tobacco will be <lb/>
very thin and light we reckon in General the Crops this year <lb/>
will be very much Short of the last Which gives us hope Even the <abbr expan="tobacco">tobo</abbr> <lb/>
<sic corr="already">allready</sic> gone will meet with a Much better market than the last did <lb/>
the Liberty of Stemming for which we have now an <note target="n2">Act of <abbr expan="parliament">parliamt</abbr></note> 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
we are in Expectation will Contribute a great deal to <sic corr="lessening">lessning</sic> the <lb/>
Quantity as well as mending the Quality</p>

<p>If you Can meet with an Early ship to let my goods <lb/>
Come by it will be very Acceptable for the Supply of my <sic corr="families">family's</sic> <lb/>
before this Winter sets in too hard I am 
</p>

<closer>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sir  your most humble Servt.</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

 <note id="n1"> [1] A bill of lading is "an official detailed receipt given by the master of a merchant vessel to the person consigning the goods, by which he makes himself responsible for their safe delivery to the consignee. This document, being the legal proof of ownership of the goods, is often deposited with a creditor as security for money advanced."  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title>. Oxford University Press.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Parliament had passed an act forbidding the importation of stemmed tobacco in 1722. John Randolph was sent to England in 1728 as agent for Virginia to try to have the act overturned; his mission was successful, and he was home in the colony by <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C29f02a.html">June 2, 1729</xref>, when Carter wrote to welcome him home. (<cit><bibl>Arthur Pierce Middleton. <title>Tobacco Coast:  A Maritime History of the Chesapeake Bay in the Colonial Era.</title> [Newport News, VA: Mariners' Museum, 1953], 116.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2005, was revised June 9, 2015,  to add footnotes and strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>