<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C29i17a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Richard Hickman, September 17, 1729</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C29i17a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Richard Hickman, September 17, 1729</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1728 August 8-1730 May 15,  Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1729-09-17</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C29i17aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1729-09-17"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C29i17a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Richard Hickman, September 17, 1729</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes toWilliamsburg resident Richard Hickman, September 17, 1729, to ask for Hickman's  assistance in protecting his rights in his house there because his tenant, Dr. Lewis Contesse, has recently died owning Carter many years' rent.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">Richard Hickman,</note> September 17, 1729</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1729-09-17">Sep. 17. 1729</date><lb/>
Mr Richard Hickman<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir</salute>

</opener>

<p>I have this day heard by <note n="CS1">Mr Stagg</note> that <note target="n2">Lewis <sic corr="Contesse">Countess</sic></note> <note target="n3">my Tenant </note><lb/>
is lately dead, tht his Widow is removed hath left all his Goods &amp; <sic corr="has">hath</sic> <lb/>
locked up into the House, &amp; as she <sic corr="says">sayes</sic> for me He owed me on the <lb/>
ninth of August last for seven Years Rent at eight pounds per <abbr expan="Annum">An.</abbr> of &mdash;<lb/>
which he <sic corr="has">hath</sic> paid me but eight pounds fifteen shillings so that there <lb/>
remains due to me forty seven pounds five Shillings, this I can make&mdash;<lb/>
appear by a Writing under his Hand to which <note n="JC3">Mr <sic corr="Attorney">Atturney</sic></note> is Witness</p>

<p>I cannot think of any person so proper to be of use to me in this <lb/>
Matter as yourself. Rents are a Debt so sacred a Nature tht I think <lb/>
the Law will allow them to be served before any others. The Widow is <abbr expan="ordered">order'd</abbr> to <lb/>
have removed none of her Husbands Goods, leaving them for me to be <lb/>
served out of them. I desire you would take Advice what Method is <lb/>
proper for you to proceed in. To be sure the Goods ought to be valued, <lb/>
My Request is, &amp; I do hereby impower you to act for me in all Respects <lb/>
as fully as if I were present</p>

<p>It <sic corr="seems">seem's</sic> there is a Woman &amp; her Daughter that have pos=<lb/>
sessed themselve of my Kitchen, &amp; have been desired by Mr <sic corr="Contesse">Countess</sic> <lb/>
to take Care of my dwelling House. I must leave it to you either to continue <lb/>
these people there or else if you can meet with a person whom you like <lb/>
better to place there in the Room to remove them. The Furniture in <lb/>
my dwelling House cost me above fifty pounds Sterl. The Care of them <lb/>
&amp; the Housing, I am mighty desirous should be put into the hands of <lb/>
some honest Body. Your kindness in the Affair will very much oblige 
</p>

<closer>Your Friend &amp; <lb/>
humble Servt
</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>The name of Carter's home, "Corotoman," the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note>

<note id="n1"> [1]  Richard Hickman (d. 1732) had been deputy clerk of Middlesex County in 1709. After Governor Hugh Drysdale's death, the Council appointed him to manage the Governor's house and its gardens.  His name appears a number of times in the Council minutes as he was the doorkeeper, and as he took out land patents. From Carter's letter to William Robertson 1727 July 15, in which he complains that "Mr. Hickman is very dilatory with his probatted Administrations," it seems that Hickman must have done other work for the colonial government. (Edward W. James.  "Libraries in Colonial Virginia."   <title>William and Mary Quarterly.</title> 3[1,#4, Apr. 1895]:248-51 for Hickman's inventory recorded 1732 May 15  listing many books; "Notes from the Journal of the House of Burgesses, 1712-1726." <title>William and Mary Quarterly.</title> 21[1,#4, April 1913]:257 mentions his being Council doorkeeper; "Notes from the Journal of the House of Burgesses, 1727-1734, <title>William and Mary Quarterly.</title>22[1, #1, July 1913]:54,56-58, mentions his being clerk of the Committee of Propositions and Grievances; and <cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]:114. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] "Dr. Lewis Contesse lived and practised medicine in Williamsburg during the  first quarter of the 18th century. His daughter, married John Tyler. Contesse  was a French Huguenot."  (Mary A. Stephenson. "Robert Carter House Historical Report, Block 30-2 Building 13 Lot 333, 334, 335." [1956 Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Library Research Report Series - 1604. Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Library. Williamsburg, Virginia. 1990]  
http://www.pastportal.com/Archive/Research%20Reports/Html/RR1604.htm; 8/25/2005)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Carter owned pproperty in Williamsburg  from early in his life. "Carter was one of the trustees or feoffees of the city [from 1705], appointed to assign  lots." He sold a lot in 1718 to Edmund Jenings, and owned a house there that he bequeathed in his will to his son George. Because early records are missing, it is not certain that this is the property designated today by Colonial Williamsburg as the Carter-Saunders House, but it probably is the one in which Dr. Contesse had been living. (Mary A. Stephenson. "Robert Carter House Historical Report, Block 30-2 Building 13 Lot 333, 334, 335." [1956 Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Library Research Report Series - 1604. Colonial Williamsburg Foundation Library. Williamsburg, Virginia. 1990]  
http://www.pastportal.com/Archive/Research%20Reports/Html/RR1604.htm; 8/25/2005)</note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>