<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C29j22a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Jones, October 22, 1729</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 18 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C29j22a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Jones, October 22, 1729</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>4 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1728 August 8-1730 May 15,  Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1729-10-22</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C29j22aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>4 p.</extent>
<date value="1729-10-22"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C29j22a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Robert Jones, October 22, 1729</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to a senior manager, Robert Jones of Prince William County, October 22, 1729, to give him very specific instructions about the distribution of bedding, caps, and clothes for slaves on the quarters under his supervision, the breaking and training  of oxen for carts for which wheels and other gear are being sent, rounding up of hogs, cider, beef, and butter for Carter's use, and to chide Jones for his inattention to Carter's affairs.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="RJ">Robert Jones,</note> October 22, 1729</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Corotoman, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1729-10-22">Octobr 22d. 1729</date><lb/>
Mr. Robert Jones<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<p>By the Sloop I send you a great many things you have <lb/>
a particular invoice of them Inclosed, the Bed clothing there are Labels <lb/>
upon with the Names of Every Negro they are for, the bedding for the Overseer<lb/>
of <note n="RF1">Richland</note> and for the Overseer at the <note n="MF2">Mountain</note> are particularly <sic corr="marked">markd</sic> <lb/>
the Frocks for the Children are all <sic corr="marked">markd</sic> Also another <sic corr="Pettiicoat">petty Coat</sic> for <lb/>
Grace my son <note n="CC1">Charles</note> is very Certain that he sent one before for her knowing <lb/>
her to be a large Woman &amp; Cowkeeper he was particularly <sic corr="Careful">Carefull</sic> to choose <lb/>
a <sic corr="petticoat">pettyCt</sic> for her and set her name Upon it and it was one of the <sic corr="Petticoats">PettyCts</sic> <lb/>
that the things were <abbr expan="sewed">sow'd</abbr> up in, I hope you will be more <sic corr="Careful">Carefull</sic> in the right <lb/>
delivery of these goods than you were in the <sic corr="Clothes,">Cloths,</sic> for what I <abbr expan="Observed">Observ'd</abbr> <lb/>
you never so much as <abbr expan="Looked">Look'd</abbr> into the Packs to see whether Everything was <lb/>
there <add place="supralinear">before</add> you sent them away so that it is in the breast of any Overseer <lb/>
to take What they <sic corr="please">pleas</sic> out and deny that they Came to them this is like <lb/>
the rest of the care you Use about Other things, the way <abbr expan="used">us'd</abbr> to be Either <lb/>
to have all the People down from the Several <abbr expan="Quarters">Qrs</abbr> and fit them at the <lb/>
<note n="FQ">Falls <abbr expan="Quarter">Qr:</abbr></note> or Else to have the furthest overseers down and to open <lb/>
the packs before them and let them see that Every thing was right for <lb/>
their Gangs, this is the method I observe with <note n="NH2">Nomini</note> and Richland <lb/>
people every Overseer comes down for his peoples <sic corr="Clothes">Cloths</sic> and sees <lb/>
that everything is right and this is the method that I Will have <abbr expan="Observed">Observ'd</abbr> <lb/>
By the person that lives in your Station</p>

<p>I have sent you two <abbr expan="pair">pr</abbr> of <sic corr="Wheels">Wheals</sic> with <sic corr="Axletrees">Axtrees</sic> Well <lb/>
<abbr expan="Boxed">Box'd</abbr> and Well <sic corr="Clamped">Clampt</sic> with Clouts Washers and <sic corr="Link">Linck</sic> pins with an Iron <lb/>
to be at the End of the tongue of Each Cart 4 Chains <sic corr="Yokes">Yeokes</sic> Well fitted <lb/>
for two teams of oxen of six in a teem <sic corr="Complete">Compleat</sic>, so that you have nothing <lb/>
to do but to make the Carpenters make two Carts, I have Also sent you <lb/>
three Ropes for the managing the Oxen one <sic corr="team">teem</sic> I would have Broke <lb/>
Between <note target="n1">Threalkild</note> &amp; <note target="n2">Jimmy Peters,</note> <note target="n3">Tim Dargon</note> has <abbr expan="promise">promis'</abbr><corr resp="editor">[d]</corr> 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
me to Break a Yoke of Oxen for himself</p>

<p>I have agreed with an Overseer for Richland And have <abbr expan="obliged">oblig'd</abbr> <lb/>
him in his Conditions to Break me a Yoke of Oxen, he will Be up <lb/>
before christmas and I intend to send up two <abbr expan="pair">pr</abbr> of Wheels more wth <lb/>
Yokes &amp; Chains &amp;ca. one for <note target="n4">Oxford</note> and Mountain the Other for <lb/>
Richland, the two first <sic corr="teams">teems</sic> I would hope if you were a person <lb/>
of life &amp; resolution would be soon got ready for your use and <lb/>
While the Other are getting ready for you you might Break more <lb/>
young Oxen that might be ready for the two Carts that I intend <lb/>
to provide Wheels for by the next Sloop When we get these 5 <sic corr="teams">teems</sic> <lb/>
of Oxen <sic corr="Equipped">Equipt</sic> and Well managed I think all business will go <lb/>
on with a great deal of Ease And Wheat &amp; Corn &amp;ca. will be Easily <lb/>
brought down <del>without</del> and removd from one plantation to ano<lb/>
ther without The sad <sic corr="spectacle">specticle</sic> of Sore <sic corr="backed">backt</sic> horses &amp; poor Jades <lb/>
and the people where the Plantations are large may have <lb/>
their fencing stuff drawn into place their Firewood got to <lb/>
their doors their Corn removed to their home houses their <lb/>
<abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobo</abbr> Carried from their fields <sic corr="though">tho</sic> never so <sic corr="remote">remoat</sic> and abundance <lb/>
of other benefits not to be <abbr expan="mentioned">mention'd</abbr></p>

<p>I have sent you a Cask to put the <note n="PQ1">poplar</note> <sic corr="Cider">Cyder</sic> <lb/>
in that which I brought down pleases me and agrees <lb/>
with me so Extraordinary Well that I set a great Value <lb/>
Upon it purposely for my Own drinking therefore you <lb/>
will take Very great Care that it be not <abbr expan="abused">abus'd</abbr> I think <lb/>
the best way will be that the Cask be <abbr expan="Carried">Carry'd</abbr> there &amp; <lb/>
that there the <sic corr="Cider">Cyder</sic> be drawn of from the <note target="n5">Lees</note> much <lb/>
Better than to bring it down to the Falls with 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
the Lees in</p>
	
<p>You must send me all the Wheat possibly you Can get down <lb/>
for the Sloop <note n="NB">Burwells</note> wheat may Come down I have sent 20 Empty <lb/>
hogsheads I would have you send me 4 <sic corr="Beaves">Beeves</sic> by All means if Possible two <lb/>
from  the <note target="n6"><sic corr="Ford,">Foard,</sic></note> the <sic corr="Pied">Pide</sic> Ox at the Falls I think may be one I think <lb/>
Oxfords Beeves must be <sic corr="killed">killd</sic> there and Carted down the other Beef I <lb/>
would have a Very good one you may take him from what <abbr expan="Quarter">Qr.</abbr> you think <lb/>
best, <note target="n7">John Hust</note> I have <sic corr="Written">Writ</sic> to by <note n="JC2">James Carter</note> about doing <del>your</del> <add place="supralinear">the</add> <sic corr="Jobs">Jobbs</sic> <lb/>
<add place="supralinear">at <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> Quarter</add> making these 2 Carts and about the Buildings at the falls&mdash;I <lb/>
have sent a great many Caps and the names of the people that are to <lb/>
<add place="supralinear">have them </add> I have sent you 20 yards of <note target="n9"><sic corr="Osnaburg">Oxnabuggs</sic></note> as you desire My New hands are all <lb/>
down in <note target="n10">their Seasoning</note> Except one I must wait with Patience till they <lb/>
recover their strength before I can send them.</p>

<p>I have a great many Observations to make of your ill <lb/>
<sic corr="management">managemt</sic> but I will take another time for it I am told you said you do <lb/>
a great deal of Work for a little money I am of the Contrary Opinion I <lb/>
think you do but very little for a great deal of money I am sure reckon <del>[illegible]</del><lb/>
<del>[illegible]</del> the Expenses of your living and your salary there is never a ten hands I<lb/>
 have Under you with all They make will answer what you have if you <lb/>
can find a way to mend your self I shall be very Easy you have a mighty <lb/>
Itch of retailing a little rum by <abbr expan="quarts">qts.</abbr> and pints you know This is What I peremp<lb/>
<sic corr="torily">toryly</sic> forbid and <add place="supralinear">if</add> you get my Overseers into your debt by these practices I shall <lb/>
send you some where Else to look for your Pay you are Very forward in <lb/>
drawing out your Salary before you have Earned it you know when we last <lb/>
<add place="supralinear">settled</add> We were pretty Even I owe you nothing <sic corr="until">till</sic> your year is up were it to <lb/>
stock you with negroes <sic corr="it would">twould</sic> do you good I should not Grudge <del>-t</del> it but <lb/>
<abbr expan="you had">you'd</abbr> Best have a Care of being too free with your <sic corr="notes">noats</sic> least I refuse<lb/>
	&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<sic corr="Payment">Paymt</sic>
 
<pb n="4"/><lb/><lb/>he is an honest man that pays for his Work after <sic corr="it is">tis</sic> done the <lb/>
proverb is he is a Bad paymaster Who pays not at all <lb/>
or Who pays beforehand&mdash;I shall take me Leave of you at <del>[illegible]</del><lb/>
Present I am 

	</p>

<closer>your friend to Serve you
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>
I Expect you will begin to look about <lb/>
you for <sic corr="Hogs">Hoggs</sic> they must be put <lb/>
up When the <note target="n11">Mast</note> is Over as soon as <lb/>
the corn is in or at least got into the Corn <lb/>
fields I shall never Endure to have such <lb/>
<sic corr="intolerable">intollerable</sic> Accots for the <sic corr="fattening">fattning</sic> of <sic corr="hogs">hoggs</sic> <lb/>
as the Overseers gave me the last year and you Were at the wonder<lb/>
<sic corr="ful">full</sic> pains of Writing down from their mouths <note n="JB4">Dr: Bell</note> I intend <lb/>
to let have the same allowance of provision he <sic corr="has">hath</sic> had in former years <lb/>
the Overseers <sic corr="talked">talkt</sic> of a great many outlying <sic corr="hogs">hoggs</sic> that have not <lb/>
been seen of late I hope they Will be got in, The Butter I Expect you <lb/>
will send down in the Sloop you have 12 Calves at the <abbr expan="Quarter">Qr</abbr> Where <lb/>
you live some of them very near <sic corr="killed">killd</sic> with the Churn stick I <lb/>
<sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> I shall have hardly butter Enough from <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> dairy to Answ:<lb/>
er the life of one of them I hope by that time this sloop Comes away <lb/>
you may be Able to let me know how many <sic corr="hogs">hoggs</sic> I may Expect from you <lb/>
I Expect you will take Care that I have all the tallow of these Beeves &amp; <lb/>
of the Cow sent to me if you let Dr Bell have half a dozen pound I <lb/>
shall not be against it. The last thing to be done for the Sloop must <lb/>
be the killing the <sic corr="Beaves">Beeves</sic> and I hope you will take Care to see them well <lb/>
aboard and hung up as Usual I have always had my meat Come down well <lb/>
hitherto</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note>This letter was published in <cit><bibl n="A8">Berkeley. "Robert Carter as Agricultural Administrator: . . .", 291-295.</bibl></cit>  
</note>

<note id="n1">[1] William Threalkill is mentioned in the <xref to="/users/berkeley/public/C33inven.xml">1733 inventory</xref>  of Carter's estate as the overseer at Poplar Quarter, Stafford County. (<cit><bibl n="A26">Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>.)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Jimmy Peters was an overseer who would be at Hinson's Quarter in Stafford County in <xref to="/users/berkeley/public/C33inven.xml">the1733 inventory.</xref> (<cit><bibl n="A26">Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>.)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] "In 1724, Robert Carter took out patents for, among others: the Licking Run tract of 10,227 acres which lay along and east of Licking Run above Germantown and across Owl and Turkey Runs, to what was then supposed to be the western boundary of the vast Brent Town Tract. Here Carter seated the Lodge Quarter mentioned in his will."   Timothy Dargan was its overseer in the <xref to="/users/berkeley/public/C33inven.xml">1733 inventory.</xref>  (<cit><bibl>Carl F. Cannon, Jr., "Robert ("King") Carter of "Corotoman." Unpublished doctoral dissertation, Duke University, 1956, p. 274;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="A26">Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Roger Oxford was the overseer at Norman's Ford.</note>

<note id="n5">[5] The lees are the dregs or the sediment.</note>

<note id="n6">[6]  Norman's Ford was an important Rappahannock River (earlier Hedgeman's River) crossing on the old Iroquois trail, later called the Carolina Road. Fairfax Harrison states that it received its name because Isaac Norman patented the land in June 1726, but Carter refered to it by this name four years earlier. It is located where U.S. 29 and U.S. 15 cross the Rappahannock between Culpeper and Fauquier counties. (<cit><bibl n="B4">"The Old Roads and the Ordinaries," in Harrison, <title>Landmarks of Old Prince William,</title> pp. 441-517, esp. fn. 37 on p. 500.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n7">[7] John Hust (or Hurst) was the overseer of "Hamstead Quarter," Stafford County, in the <xref to="/users/berkeley/public/C33inven.xml">1733 inventory,</xref>  supervising  sixteen slaves with the assistance of one horse. Hust apparently was a carpenter because Carter mentions his doing carpentry work in various letters. (<cit><bibl n="A26">Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n8">[8]</note>

<note id="n9">[9] Osnaburg is a coarse fabric named for the region of Germany in which it was first produced. It was commonly used for sacking and bagging. (<cit><bibl>18th Century Trade Terms (Fabrics), "<xref to="http://www.18cnewenglandlife.org/18cnel/ofsilk.htm">Of Silk, Terms Of Silk</xref>, Cotton, Linen and Wool,"[Compiled from] <title>The Beekman Mercantile Paper</title> 1746 - 1799. 5/ 4/2007; 6/18/2015</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n10">[10]  Seasoning is "the process by which a person becomes hardened or inured to a strange climate, acclimatization," and was the term colonial Virginians used to refer to the sicknesses that affected new immigrants, black and white, to the colony, until they developed immunities.  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title>. Oxford University Press.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n11">[11] Mast is "the fruit of beech, oak, chestnut, and other woodland trees, esp. when fallen and used as food for pigs, etc."  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title>. Oxford University Press.</bibl></cit>)</note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>