<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C29k13a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, November 13, 1729</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.7  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C29k13a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, November 13, 1729</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1728 August 8-1730 May 15,  Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1729-11-13</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C29k13aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1729-11-13"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C29k13a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Micajah Perry, November 13, 1729</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Micajah Perry, November 13, 1729, to notify Perry that he is unable to locate the most recent accounts that Perry had sent for his own and the Burwell estate, and requesting new copies. He adds that his clerk, John Harvey, has recently completed his indenture, and Carter, who does not think much of his honesty, suspects he may  have taken the missing accounts. He orders some goods.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="MP2">Micajah Perry,</note> November 13, 1729</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1729-11-13">Novr: 13th. 1729</date><lb/>
Alderman Perry<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir</salute>

</opener>

<p>I have already <abbr expan="advised">advis'd</abbr> you of the receipt of <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> last <lb/>
accot Currt. and also of the Accot Currt of <note n="NB">Mr Burwells Estate</note> by <abbr expan="what">wht </abbr><lb/>
accident I know not these two accots are so Mislaid that I cannot Af<lb/>
ter the strictest search find them by any means I Earnestly desire <lb/>
you will send me <sic corr="Copies">Copys</sic> of them</p>

<p>My <sic corr="servant">servt</sic> <note target="n1">John Harvey</note> whom you sent me from <lb/>
the Hospital is lately free he is a fellow of no good principles <lb/>
I am not without Suspicion That these Accots may be fallen into <lb/>
some bad hands that may Endeavour to make an ill use of them <lb/>
have therefore thought it necesary to <sic corr="signify">signifye</sic> this much to <abbr expan="you">yo.</abbr> <lb/>
that you may be upon <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> Guard you may be sure I neither have nor <lb/>
shall draw any money out of <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> hands in haste I am 
</p>

<closer>Sir &amp;ca
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>
<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
I <sic corr="desire">disire</sic> you will send 2 pounds of the best <note target="n2">India Rhubarb</note> and 6 pounds of <note target="n3">Je<lb/>
suits Bark</note> and if you make a present to me of a box of <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobo</abbr> <lb/>
for my own Smoking it will be Accptable</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1]  Carter had a clerk named John Harvey, and there are notes on some of his letters, "Harvey to copy." A John Harvey witnessed his will, and some of its codicils, which is logical if Harvey had written it out for Carter.</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Jesuit's bark "is the most celebrated specific remedy for all forms of malaria. It is obtained from several species of the genus cinchona . . . that have been discovered at different times and are indigenous in the Western Andes of South America. Formerly the bark itself, prepared in different forms, was used as a drug. . . " (<cit><bibl>"Jesuit's Bark," in <title>The Catholic Encyclopedia </title>online at  http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/08372b.htm. 8/29/2005.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2]  "The root of several species of Rheum, used much as a cathartic medicine," and also in cooking.  (<cit><bibl><title>On-line Medical Dictionary. </title>Published at the Dept. of Medical Oncology, University of Newcastle upon Tyne. http://cancerweb.ncl.ac.uk/cgi-bin/omd?rhubarb.</bibl></cit>)
</note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>