<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C29l24a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from William Dawkins to Charles Carter, December 24, 1729
</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Dawkins, William</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C29l24a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005, 2015</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from William Dawkins to Charles Carter, December 24, 1729</title>
     <author>William Dawkins</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, VA</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1729-12-24</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C29l24aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1729-12-24"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C29l24a</idno>
<title>Letter from William Dawkins to Charles Carter, December 24, 1729</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Letter from London merchant William Dawkins to Charles Carter, December 24, 1729, to inform Carter that he and his partner, Edward Athawes, have posted security for Carter's good performance of his duties as naval officer, and giving Carter advice on the handling of his business and accounts.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from <note n="WD">William Dawkins</note> to <note n="CC1">Charles Carter,</note> December 24, 1729</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">London</name><lb/>
<date value="1729-12-24">Decemr 24th 1729</date><lb/>
Charles Carter<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir</salute>

</opener>

<p>I have received your <sic corr="several">severall</sic><lb/>
letters and congratulate you on your<lb/>
<note target="n1">NavaL Office</note> place. <note n="EA">Mr <sic corr="Athawes">Athaws</sic></note><lb/>
and I have given security for you<lb/>
here at our <add resp="editor">[omission in text]</add> and hope you<lb/>
will take care that there shall never<lb/>
be any mistake or error.</p>

<p>I also desire you will be very <lb/>
punctual and exact in doing all<lb/>
your business as a Merchant to be<lb/>
sure to endorse all <note target="n2">your bills</note><lb/>
regular and to  give advice to what<lb/>
Account they are to be placed; for<lb/>
I shall keep your Naval Office<lb/>
Account distinct; and to advise<lb/>
whenever you draw any bills:<lb/>
for I will pay no bills without<lb/>
advice <abbr expan="although">altho'</abbr> I believe it may be

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
your hand. Also, draw your bills <lb/>
at sixty days, which gives time to <lb/>
be in cash if it should be otherwise. <lb/>
I desire you will write to me often. <lb/>
Your place gives you great opportu=<lb/>
nity of conveyance.</p>

<p>As to the Tobacco Trade, it continues<lb/>
 bad&mdash;the price low. Notwithstand<lb/>
-ing the advices we have of the dam<lb/>
-age the great rains have done to the last <lb/>
crop in Virginia, our buyers <lb/>
will not believe any thing until <lb/>
they <add resp="editor">[omission in text]</add> a real security, which is <lb/>
far from with us at present.</p>

<p>As to your <note target="n3">Copper mine</note>, it is <lb/>
likely to be a very good thing; but <lb/>
Mr <sic corr="Athawes,">Athaws,</sic> who has taken a great <lb/>
deal of pains in having it proved by <lb/>
the greatest artist, will give you a <lb/>
full account of what <add resp="editor">[omission in text]</add> he knows <lb/>
of it.</p>

<p>	As I have had some small share in your <lb/>
education, so I <abbr expan="cannot">can't</abbr> forbear giving you advice <lb/>
and recommending to you strict virtue and <lb/>
integrity in every action of your life.</p>

<p>You know <note target="n4">Mr. Heath</note> has a <lb/>
Country Seat. If you meet with <lb/>
any rarity of trees of plants, it <lb/>
will be an acceptable present; <lb/>
which is all I shall trouble you <lb/>
with at present, but assure you <lb/>
I am
</p>

<closer>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Your real friend &amp; humble servant.<lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr> Dawkins
</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:  </hi></hi>  Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia. These texts are all nineteenth-century copies. Apparently there was in existence a letter book of Robert Carter's&mdash;now lost&mdash; and some incoming letters, from which the unknown copyist recorded these texts. As they are the only texts, the punctuation and "corrections" obviously supplied by the copyist have been retained.</note><lb/>

<note>Robert Carter had written to Dawkins on  <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C29h26c.html">August 26, 1729</xref>, to request his support in Charles's becoming naval officer.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] The naval officer was an official in the colony that reported to the Commissioners of Customs, a body that had first been established in 1663; the group was reorganized several times, especially after 1688. The board was "intrusted with collection of customs both in England and the colonies." The board helped write many of the instructions for colonial governors in collaboration with the Privy Council. "Their direct connection with the colonies was through the governors, who were instructed to correspond with the commissioners, and to send them, every three months, lists of clearances, and also reports of illegal trading. The governor's agent in matters of trade was the naval officer whom he was empowered to appoint, but who was required by the 7th and 8th William III to give security to the commissioners of customs." (<cit><bibl>Louise Phillips Kellogg. <title>The American Colonial Charter. A Study of English Administration in Relation Thereto, Especialy after 1688.</title>  [Annual Report, American Historical Association. Vol. 1, Govt. Print. Off., 1904], p. 226.</bibl></cit> For a recent study, see <cit><bibl>Alvin Rabushka. <title>Taxation in Colonial America</title> [Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2008.]</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2"> [2] A bill of exchange is a kind of check or promissory note without interest.  It is used primarily in international trade, and is a written order by one person to pay another a specific sum on a specific date sometime in the future.  If the bill of exchange is drawn on a bank, it is called a bank draft.  If it is drawn on another party, it is called a trade draft.  Sometimes a bill of exchange will simply be called a draft, but whereas a draft is always  negotiable (transferable by endorsement), this is not necessarily true of a bill of exchange. (See <cit><bibl><xref to="http://www.fraudaid.com/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms/bill_of_exchange.htm">"Bill of Exchange"</xref> in the online Dictionary of Financial Scam Terms: the Truth vs. the Scam.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3]  In 1728, Carter, his sons Robert and Charles, and his son-in-law Mann Page,  organized a company they named Frying Pan to mine for copper on a tract of some 27,000 acres that Louis Morton describes as lying "near the present boundary of Fairfax and Loudoun counties." Fairfax Harrison wrote that the tract was "on the  Horsepen of Broad." Today, there is a Frying Pan Park just east of the border of the Dulles Airport reservation, and there are other things with the name in the area. The company was not successful. (<cit><bibl n="B32">Morton. <title>Robert Robert Carter of Nomini Hall.</title> pp. 18-19;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 342. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] This may be Edmund Heath, husband of Katherine (Bailey) Heath, grandaughter and daughter of the Carter family's old English friends, <note n="AB1">Arthur Bailey</note> and his son, <note n="AB2">Arthur Bailey</note>, as Alan Simpson has speculated. (<cit><bibl n="A3">Simpson. "Robert Carter's Schooldays." p. 173, fn. 29.)</bibl></cit>)</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2005, was revised July 21, 2015,  to add footnotes and strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>