<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C30">

<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from [the Proprietors of the Frying Pan Copper Mining Company] to James Bradley, May 15, 1730</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.9  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C30e15a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from [the Proprietors of the Frying Pan Copper Mining Company] to James Bradley, May 15, 1730</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1728 August 8-1730 May 15,  Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1730-05-15</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C30e15aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1730-05-15"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C30e15a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from [the Proprietors of the Frying Pan Copper Mining Company] to James Bradley, May 15, 1730</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter represennting the Proprietors of the Frying Pan Copper Mining Company writes to London merchant James Bradley, May 15, 1730, directing the merchant to coordinate finding miners for the Virginia company with Edward Athawes.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from [the Proprietors of the Frying Pan Copper Mining Company] to <note target="n1">James Bradley,</note> May 15, 1730</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1730-05-15">May 15th. 1730</date><lb/>
Mr James Bradley<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir</salute>

</opener>

<p>	On the 15th of <abbr expan="September">Sepr</abbr> last we Acquainted you  <del>with an</del><lb/>
that <add place="supralinear">in</add> our adventure after a <note target="n2">Copper mine</note> we <del>found it absolutely</del> <add place="supralinear">were advised that it was</add> <lb/>
necessary to get some labouring men <sic corr="skilled">skilld</sic> in digging and raising <lb/>
these ores and <abbr expan="applied">apply'd</abbr> to you to oblige us in sending in two persons <lb/>
that were <abbr expan="qualified">qualify'd</abbr> for this Work to this Letter we have had no Ans<lb/>
wer from you which makes us Conclude you have done nothing in&mdash;<lb/>
this matter <note n="EA">Mr: Athawes</note> hath taken a great deal of pains and hath <lb/>
given us a very particular accot of the Several <sic corr="trials">tryals</sic> he has had <lb/>
made of the Ores we sent him from whose Encouragement We have <lb/>
now <sic corr="written">writ</sic> to him to provide us with proper Persons for the business <lb/>
therefore <sic corr="it is">tis</sic> our Request <del>now</del> to you that you Will <sic corr="please">pleas</sic> to let him&mdash;<lb/>
know what Steps you have taken in this Affair if you have <sic corr="procured">procurd</sic> <lb/>
Us any men that then he <add place="supralinear">may</add> desist otherwise that he will proceed in ser<lb/>
ving us According to our directions this We desire of you that We may <lb/>
Avoid a double Charge We are 
</p>

<closer>Sir&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Your most humble Servants
</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] James Bradley was a London merchant with whom Carter dealt from at least 1723 until his death. As noted in his letter to Bradley of 1727 May 17, Bradley owned the <hi rend="italics">Welcome,</hi> but little information about Bradley has been located. (There is a listing of the firm of Bradly &amp; Griffin, Merchants, Fenchurch-street, opposite the Mitre Tavern, on page 13 of <cit><bibl><title>Kent's Directory For the Year 1740 Containing An Alphabetical List of the Names and Places of Abode of the Directors of Companies, Persons in Publick Business, Merchants, and other Eminent Traders in the Cities of London and Westminster, and the Borough of Southwark.</title>  London: Printed and Sold by Henry Kent in Finch-Lane, near the Royal Exchange: and by the Booksellers and Pamphlets Shops of London and Westminster, 1740. p. 39. http://freepages.history.rootsweb.com/~frpayments/KD1740/AB.htm. 8/12/2005. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2]  In 1728, Carter, his sons Robert and Charles, and his son-in-law Mann Page,  organized a company to mine for copper on a tract of some 27,000 acres that Louis Morton describes as lying "near the present boundary of Fairfax and Loudoun counties." Fairfax Harrison wrote that the tract was "on the  Horsepen of Broad." Horsepen Run joins Broad Run on the northern border of Dulles airport. The company was not successful. (<cit><bibl n="B32">Morton. <title>Robert Robert Carter of Nomini Hall.</title> pp. 18-19;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 342. </bibl></cit>)</note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>