<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C31f22a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Colonel John Tayloe, June 22, 1731</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C31f22a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2005, 2015</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Colonel John Tayloe, June 22, 1731</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1731-06-22</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C31f22aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1731-06-22"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C31f22a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Colonel John Tayloe, June 22, 1731</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Colonel John Tayloe of Richmond County, June 22, 1731, concerning terms for employing  Tayloe's brick mason, and the possible purchase of Mr. Champ's land.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Colonel <note target="n1">John Tayloe,</note> June 22, 1731</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Corotoman. <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1731-06-22">June 22d. 1731</date><lb/>
Colo John Tayloe<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir</salute>

</opener>



<p>Your letter of the 27 of May <sic corr="has">hath </sic>been with me for some <lb/>
time all along I <abbr expan="designed">design'd</abbr> an Answer to it by the return of my Son <lb/>
his stay at <note target="n2">Fryingpan</note> being longer than I Expected <sic corr="has">hath </sic><lb/>
made me more dilatory than I intended.</p>

<p>The wages you demand for your Bricklayer if <lb/>
he be a master Workman is a diligent quick fellow and posses<corr resp="editor">[es]</corr> <lb/>
with those good qualities you mention I think is not much <del>out</del> <lb/>
<del>of the way</del> <add place="supralinear">amiss</add> only the word Sterling scares me if you will be <lb/>
contented to take Cash I will come into that readily I have no <lb/>
present occasion for him I would have his time Commence <lb/>
from the first or middle of September he may carry on <note target="n3"><sic corr="Rubbed">Rubd</sic></note> <lb/>
work all the Winter and be ready when the Summer comes to <lb/>
lay Bricks if this pleases you and I suppose it will not be ag=<lb/>
ainst the inclinations of the fellow I will stand concluded by the <lb/>
Bargain</p>

<p>As to your other Offer about <note target="n4">Mr Champs</note> land <lb/>
were the times as easy to get money in as I have known them <lb/>
I would not make two words about the Price but the word ster=

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
ling is frightful to me. there also the buildings further than <lb/>
houses to cure tobacco <del>or</del> put Corn <add place="supralinear">or lodge negroes</add> in you know will be of Little<lb/>
Advantage to me and the Old fields and <abbr expan="cleared">clear'd</abbr> grounds which <lb/>
must be <abbr expan="presumed">presum'd</abbr> to have been out of the best of the Land accor<lb/>
ding to my information are much larger than you suppose <lb/>
And the Lands to be <sic corr="Cleared">Cleard</sic> chiefly hilly and upon Swamp sides <lb/>
however if there be eight hundred Acres and Mr. Champ can make <lb/>
me an indisputable Title I will adventure to give one hundred &amp;<lb/>
fifty Pounds for it With that terryfying word Sterling added <lb/>
to it and will give my <note target="n5">bills of Exchange</note> immediately upon <lb/>
passing proper Assurances for the Land this is within ten <lb/>
pounds of <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> proposal which I fancy will hardly turn away <lb/>
a good Customer&mdash;You will particularly oblige me in being <lb/>
the instrument of handing the papers that relate to <note n="LL">Lloyds</note> <lb/>
Land to me I am </p>

<closer>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sir&mdash;&mdash;<lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;your most humble Servant
</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1728 August-1731 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>The county and colony have been added for clarity to the heading on this draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] John Tayloe (1687-1747) of Mt. Airy, Richmond County, who served as justice, burgess, colonel of militia, and as a member of the Council after 1732. (<cit><bibl n="B31">Ryland. <title>Richmond County Virginia. . . . </title> pp. 115-16.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2]  In 1728, Carter, his sons Robert and Charles, and his son-in-law Mann Page,  organized a company they named Frying Pan to mine for copper on a tract of some 27,000 acres that Louis Morton describes as lying "near the present boundary of Fairfax and Loudoun counties." Fairfax Harrison wrote that the tract was "on the  Horsepen of Broad." Today, there is a Frying Pan Park just east of the border of the Dulles Airport reservation, and there are other things with the name in the area. The company was not successful. (<cit><bibl n="B32">Morton. <title>Robert Robert Carter of Nomini Hall.</title> pp. 18-19;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 342. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Rubbed brick is "a soft clay brick with a smooth polished surface, chiefly used for ornamental and high-quality brickwork. . . ." "Because of the uneven edges of hand-made bricks, rubbed bricks were used at corners and at window and door jambs to give a building sharp edges and snug fits around its openings. Rubbed bricks were selected for their density and even color, and were rubbed to precise shapes with smooth faces using a special stone or hard brick. The rubbed bricks' rich red color lent a wall surface handsome articulation."  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title>. Oxford University Press,</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl>Calder Loth. "<xref to="http://blog.classicist.org/?p=3931">Flemish Bond:</xref> A Hallmark Of Traditional Architecture" posted to the Classicist Blog, December 1, 2011.</bibl></cit></note>

<note id="n4">[]4 This may have been John Champ of King George County who had been appointed a justice and sheriff of that county in April 1731. (<cit><bibl n="B10">McIlwaine. <title>Executive Journals of the Council. . . .</title>, 4[1721-1739]: 235-36. </bibl></cit> )</note>

<note id="n5"> [5] A bill of exchange is a kind of check or promissory note without interest.  It is used primarily in international trade, and is a written order by one person to pay another a specific sum on a specific date sometime in the future.  If the bill of exchange is drawn on a bank, it is called a bank draft.  If it is drawn on another party, it is called a trade draft.  Sometimes a bill of exchange will simply be called a draft, but whereas a draft is always  negotiable (transferable by endorsement), this is not necessarily true of a bill of exchange. (See <cit><bibl><xref to="http://www.fraudaid.com/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms/bill_of_exchange.htm">"Bill of Exchange"</xref> in the online Dictionary of Financial Scam Terms: the Truth vs. the Scam.</bibl></cit>)</note></div1>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2005, was revised September 29, 2015,  to add footnotes and strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>


</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>