<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C31g29a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins &amp; Company, July 29, 1731</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 13 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C31g29a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2006, 2016</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins &amp; Company, July 29, 1731</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>4 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1731 July 9-1732 July 13 , Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1731-07-29</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C31g29aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>4 p.</extent>
<date value="1731-07-29"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C31g29a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins &amp; Company, July 29, 1731</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchants William Dawkins &amp; Company, July 29, 1731, concerning tobacco he has shipped on board the <hi rend="italics">Bailey</hi> for himself, his son Robert, and the Burwell and Mann Page estates. He encloses an invoice (not present) for goods, mentions his claims against merchant John Falconar's estate and the affairs of the Frying Pan copper mine, his and Dawkins'  problems in being part-owner of trading ships, and Tom Dove's hard work in the colony this year as master of the <hi rend="italics">Bailey.</hi> He adds that should Dawkins decide to build a new ship for Dove, he would be willing to own a portion of her, and alerts them to several bills of exchange. He presses the merchants to return to a former method in their accounts, and of his need for a new clerk to replace Richard Chapman.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="WD">William Dawkins</note> &amp; Company, July 29, 1731</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1731-07-29">July 29&mdash;1731</date><lb/>
Mr. William Dawkins &amp; Company<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Gentlemen,</salute>

</opener>



<p>This I intend as the Concluding stroke to my <lb/>
business Per <corr resp="editor">[the ]</corr> <note target="n1"><name type="ship">Bailey</name></note> Brings to <abbr expan="you"><abbr expan="you">yo</abbr></abbr> the <note target="n2">Bills of Lading</note> for the tobacco on <lb/>
board her <note target="n3">Vizt</note> thirty hogsheads of my own tobacco three of them leaf.<lb/>
Purchase <abbr expan="tobacco">tobo</abbr> all the rest <abbr expan="stemmed">stemm'd</abbr> &amp; my own Crops 6 hogsheads belonging to <lb/>
my <note n="RC2">Son Robert</note> also <abbr expan="stemmed">stemm'd</abbr> and of as good a Crop as Any I have 8 hogsheads <lb/>
<abbr expan="stemmed">stemm'd</abbr> belonging to <note n="NB">Mr. Burwells</note> Estate which <note n="JH2"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Hyde</note> <sic corr="has">hath</sic> always <lb/>
sold very well also 22 hogsheads belong to <note n="MP1"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> Pages</note> Estate stemmed likewise <lb/>
of which <abbr expan="you">yo</abbr> have already had an <abbr expan="Account">Acct</abbr><lb/>
My own consignmt of my own tobacco this Year in the whole is 102 hogsheads</p>
 
<p>Besides the Invoice of goods I have already<lb/>
<sic corr="written">writ</sic> for for the Use of my <sic corr="families">familys</sic> I now send another small invoice <lb/>
which I would have Come in as Early as <abbr expan="you">yo</abbr> can and by no means to <del>Come</del> <add place="supralinear">be <sic corr="shipped">shipt</sic></add>in <lb/>
the same Ship with my other Invoice that I may <add place="supralinear">not</add> <sic corr="risk">risque</sic> both in the same<lb/>
<del>both in the same</del> <note target="n4">bottom</note></p>

<p>I have already <sic corr="Written">Writ</sic> so fully and so frequently <lb/>
about the Several Sums of money due to me from <note target="n5">Mr Falconars</note> Executors <lb/>
and have so fully <sic corr="Lodged">Lodgd</sic> that Matter within your Power that to me there <lb/>
seems no reason for doubt the Payment of those <sic corr="Balances">Ballances</sic> into <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> hands witho<corr resp="editor">[u]</corr>t <lb/>
any further trouble either to <abbr expan="you">yo</abbr> or to myself before this will reach you</p>

<p>I find you throw the whole Affair of our <note target="n6">Copper <lb/>
design</note> upon the Sholders of <note n="EA">Mr. Athawes</note> just as it is with him sometimes <lb/>
I find <sic corr="our">or</sic> hopes the next news ready to <sic corr="despair">dispair</sic> in the same manner <sic corr="has">hath</sic> been <lb/>
<corr resp="editor">[no ?]</corr> entertainments since we have got the Miners to Work Mr. Athawes <lb/>
<corr resp="editor">[<sic corr="has">hath</sic>]</corr> a full history of these matters therefore I shall not give <abbr expan="you">yo</abbr> the <lb/>
<corr resp="editor">[trouble ?]</corr> of repetition</p> 


<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
<p>I observe you make heavy Complaints of <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> Concerns in <lb/>
Shipping and are design'd to wear out those you have and to have to do <lb/>
with no more if this be your Case who have the consignments to lick <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> <lb/>
Losses Whole you will easily make a judgement what little reason we <lb/>
have to run into such Adventures that have none of those sweet <sic corr="Morsels">Morsals</sic> <lb/>
to make up our Losses you know what a great Sufferer I was for many <lb/>
years together by the <note n="CS"><name type="ship">Carter</name></note> never <sic corr="failed">faild</sic> in filling up my quota every year<lb/>
and yet always brought in to bear a share in the <note target="n7">dead Freight</note> After <abbr expan="you">yo.</abbr> <lb/>
Have <abbr expan="pleased">pleas'd</abbr> yourself in saying all the disadvantagious things of <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> <lb/>
Shipping I believe you will find it absolutely necessary while you <lb/>
are desirous to Support your interest in the trade <del>. . . will be necessary</del><lb/>
<del>for</del> to continue an owner</p>

<p>I reckon <note target="n1">Tom Dove</note> is <sic corr="ppretty">pritty</sic> secure on an <sic corr="employ">imploy</sic> under <abbr expan="you">yo.</abbr> <lb/>
The Bailey is grown <sic corr="ppretty">pritty</sic> old how long you will think her fit to <lb/>
Continue in the trade is none of my business to given an opinion in&mdash; <lb/>
<del>But</del> from Mr. Doves Silence (for he <sic corr="has">hath</sic> not said one Word to me <lb/>
about a New Ship) <add place="supralinear">I reckon</add> he is very well <abbr expan="satisfyied">satisfy'd</abbr> to Continue in the old one <lb/>
as I am that he <sic corr="has">hath</sic> made to me no <del>new</del> <add place="supralinear">fresh</add> Solicitations If my <abbr expan="stemmed">stem'd</abbr> <lb/>
tobacco Sent <abbr expan="you">yo</abbr>u last year and this would turn out at about 10&pound; Per hogshead <lb/>
and <abbr expan="you">yo.</abbr> and Mr Athawes inclination were <del>turnd</del> <add place="supralinear"><sic corr="fixed">fixd</sic> so much in his favour&mdash;</add> to build a new <lb/>
Ship for him to be appropriated for <note target="n8">this River</note> I would upon these <lb/>
Conditions Adventure to be <abbr expan="Concerned">Concern'd</abbr> in her as <add place="supralinear">far as</add> two or three hundred <lb/>
Pounds will go. Tom Dove <sic corr="has">hath</sic> <sic corr="shown">shew'd</sic> so much life and dexterity <lb/>
in his business this Year that I have taken up a better opinion of him <lb/>
than I <abbr expan="Used">Us'd</abbr> to have which was when he was made a master there was a <lb/>
good Mate <abbr expan="spoiled">spoil'd</abbr></p>

<p>Herein comes the following Small <note target="n9">bills of Exchange</note> <lb/>
<del>Vizt</del> <note target="n10">Mr. Thomas Edwards</note> on <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> Selves for 11"18"2<lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Capt Thomas Dove on <abbr expan="ditto">do</abbr>&mdash;&mdash;                  &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;9"14"0&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Carried to the next<lb/>
	&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;John Lees on Hugh Arburthnot&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;3"6"3&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Page but one<lb/>

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&pound;24"18"5</p>
<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
<p>Brought from the forgoing Page but one</p><lb/>
<p>I will once more beg of <abbr expan="you">yo</abbr> to take up <abbr expan="your">yr</abbr> old method in the Invoice <lb/>
you send me that is not to give me the plague of the Shop <sic corr="notes">noats</sic> I must <lb/>
confess it is the method of the other <abbr expan="Merchants">Merchts</abbr> and I believe it saves <lb/>
them some trouble but it is not much and I hope <abbr expan="you">yo</abbr> will please me in this <lb/>
matter.</p>

<p>As for <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> own business you have it at large in a <sic corr="joint">joynt</sic> letter <lb/>
from <note target="n11">Mr. Lee</note> and my self which I Expect will be to <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> Satisfaction&mdash; </p>

<p>I heartily wish <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> Health and all the imaginable <sic corr="Happiness">Happyness</sic> which <lb/>
this World has to bestow upon us Wretched mortals while we are in our <lb/>
Veil of Pilgrimage combating with the <add place="supralinear"><sic corr="daily">dayly</sic></add> tr<del>oubles</del> <add place="supralinear">yals</add> of it and am 
</p>

<closer>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sirs<lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;with abundance of Sincerity,<lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<abbr expan="Your">Yr.</abbr> Most humble Servt.&mdash;
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>
<pb n="4"/><lb/><lb/>
A Postscript to Mr. Dawkins last letter<lb/>
Gint <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add><lb/>
<p>In a former letter I have <sic corr="written">writ</sic> to <abbr expan="you">yo</abbr> both very Pressing&mdash;<lb/>
ly to use <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> Utmost endeavours to send me in a Person of Proper qualifi<lb/>
cations to be a Clerk to me in the Room of <note target="n12">Richard Chapman</note> whose time of <lb/>
Service is near Expirig I cannot forbear repeating this request to <lb/>
you with all imaginable Earnestness. I am to Advise I have just now a <lb/>
<note target="n9">bill of Exchange</note> on <abbr expan="you">yo</abbr>. Payable to the said Richard Chapman which I <lb/>
request <abbr expan="you">yo</abbr> to Answer</p></seg>



</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1731 July 9-1732 July 13 , Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity. The lower corner portion of the first leaf has bee3n affected by a water stain thast has faded the ink making reading difficult.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] The <hi rend="italics">Bailey</hi> was a London ship owned by William Dawkins and commanded at various times by Adam Graves (1725-1730) and by Thomas Dove 1730-1732. She was a vessel of some 250 tons and carried 15-17 crew members. (<cit><bibl>Survey report 6801 summarizing Adm. 68/195, 156v, and other data in Adm. 68/194 and /196, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small  Special Collections Library, University of Virginia;</bibl></cit> A letter of Carter's to Dawkins <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C32e12b.html">May 12, 1732,</xref> refers to "your ship Bailey." as does a letter of August 10, 1733, from Carter's executors to Dawkins. [<cit><bibl>Lloyd T. Smith, Jr., <hi rend="italics">ed.</hi> <title>The Executors' Letters of Robert Carter of Corotoman, 1732-1738. </title> (Irvington, VA: Foundation for Historic Christ  Church, 2010) p. 76].</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2"> [2] A bill of lading is "an official detailed receipt given by the master of a merchant vessel to the person consigning the goods, by which he makes himself responsible for their safe delivery to the consignee. This document, being the legal proof of ownership of the goods, is often deposited with a creditor as security for money advanced."  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title>. Oxford University Press.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Vizt. is the abbreviation for the Latin word "videlicet";  it means "that is to say; namely; to wit: used to introduce an amplification, or more precise or explicit explanation, of a previous statement or word." (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary</title> online.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Carter uses the word "bottom" in the sense "bottom (of a ship): generally . . .  'the part of the hull of a ship which is below the wales' . . . ; also, the hull as a whole; hence, a ship, boat, or other vessel."  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title>. Oxford University Press.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[5] John Falconar (1677-1729) was a London merchant with whom Carter dealt. He apparently was in  New Jersey and Maryland, 1699-1705. In 1728, Falconar and Henry Darnell formed an association of 29 London tobacco merchants to deal with the French tobacco purchasing agent as a group in order to keep the price as high as possible. The association lasted only lasted a year or two before dissolving because some of its members were dealing directly with the French agent and selling below the agreed-upon price. (See <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C27g24d.html">Carter's letter to Falconar </xref> of July 24 and August 22, 1727, for details about the payment of &pound;200 to him. See <xref to="http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/html/C30d16b.html">Carter to William Dawkins,</xref> for Falconar's death date.  <cit><bibl>"<xref to="http://archiver.rootsweb.ancestry.com/th/read/GEN-MEDIEVAL/2010-11/1289784273">GEN-MEDIEVAL</xref>-L Archives" on Rootsweb, 8/10/2015</bibl></cit>; and  <cit><bibl>Arthur Pierce Middleton. <title>Tobacco Coast:  A Maritime History of the Chesapeake Bay in the Colonial Era.</title> Newport News, VA: Mariners' Museum, 1953. p. 129</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6]  In 1728, Carter, his sons Robert and Charles, and his son-in-law Mann Page,  organized a company to mine for copper on a tract of some 27,000 acres that Louis Morton describes as lying "near the present boundary of Fairfax and Loudoun counties." Fairfax Harrison wrote that the tract was "on the  Horsepen of Broad." Today, there is a Frying Pan Park just east of the border of the Dulles Airport reservation, and there are other things with the name in the area. The company was not successful. (<cit><bibl n="B32">Morton. <title>Robert Robert Carter of Nomini Hall.</title> pp. 18-19;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 342. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n7">[7] Dead freight is "the amount paid for that part of a vessel not occupied by cargo, when the vessel is chartered for a lump sum."  (<cit><bibl><title>Oxford English Dictionary Online</title>. Oxford University Press.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n8">[8] the Rappahannock</note>

<note id="n9"> [9] A bill of exchange is a kind of check or promissory note without interest.  It is used primarily in international trade, and is a written order by one person to pay another a specific sum on a specific date sometime in the future.  If the bill of exchange is drawn on a bank, it is called a bank draft.  If it is drawn on another party, it is called a trade draft.  Sometimes a bill of exchange will simply be called a draft, but whereas a draft is always  negotiable (transferable by endorsement), this is not necessarily true of a bill of exchange. (See <cit><bibl><xref to="http://www.fraudaid.com/Dictionary-of-Financial-Scam-Terms/bill_of_exchange.htm">"Bill of Exchange"</xref> in the online Dictionary of Financial Scam Terms: the Truth vs. the Scam.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n10">[10]"Thos. Edwards, a little petty Fogging Lawyer the Clark of our County that hath as much Mettle and more cunning for Contention then his predecessor had" Carter wrote to Landon Jones, <xref to="/users/berkeley/public/C23g22b.xml">July 22, 1723.</xref> His opinion of Edwards later changed for there are more appreciative mentions of him in Carter's diary. Edwards was clerk of the Lancaster County court from 1720-1746. (<cit><bibl><title>Within the Court House at Lancaster.</title> Lively, VA: Lively Printing Services, Lively, VA: Lively Printing Services, [1976]. p. 15.</bibl></cit>; and "Thomas Edwards, Gentleman, Clerk of the Court" in <cit><bibl n="B43">Brown and Sorrells. <title>People in Profile.</title> pp. 94-103.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n11">[11]  Carter may refer to Thomas Lee (1690-1750) of Westmoreland County, the son of Richard Lee II, and nephew of Edmund Jenings; he would build "Stratford," and succeed Carter on the Council. For a good article on Thomas Lee, see  "<xref to="http://www.stratfordhall.org/collections-research/staff-research/thomas-lee-of-stratford-1690-1750/">Thomas Lee of Stratford</xref> 1690-1750" by Jeanne A. Calhoun on Stratford plantation's website. (<cit><bibl>Burton J. Hendrick. <title>The Lees of Virginia: Biography of a Family.</title> [Boston: Little Brown, 1935]. pp. 48, 51, etc.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n12">[12] As Carter's clerk, Chapman had written out and signed as a witness to Carter' will and several of its codicils.</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2006, was revised February 18, 2016,  to add footnotes and strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>