<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C32c02a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Philip Perry, March 2, 1732</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.11  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C32c02a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2006</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Philip Perry, March 2, 1732</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1731 July 9-1732 July 13 , Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1731-03-02</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C32c02aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>3 p.</extent>
<date value="1731-03-02"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C32c02a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Philip Perry, March 2, 1732</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Philip Perry, March 2, 1732, brother to and partner of 
Micajah Perry, to comment the need for a tailor for the Burwell estates, on tobacco sales, and on the debts of the Page estate to the recently deceased merchant John Pratt.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note target="n1">Philip Perry,</note> March 2, 1732</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1731-03-02">March 2d, 1732</date><lb/>
Mr. Philip Perry<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sr</salute>

</opener>



<p>By this conveyance I have already writ<lb/>
pretty largely to <del>your brother</del> <add place="supralinear"><note n="MP2">Mr. Alderman</note></add> however having received various<lb/>
Letters from <add place="supralinear">you</add> I shall think it proper to give you a Short entertain<lb/>
ment.</p>

<p>In your of the 27th. of July you give me hopes<lb/>
of procuring a <sic corr="tailor">taylor</sic> for <note n="NB">Mr. Burwells</note> Estate <del>and in answer a . . .</del> <add place="supralinear">which I shall be glad</add> <lb/>
 you Succeed in  we have always been <abbr expan="Supplyied">Supply'd</abbr> in by You hitherto <abbr expan="although">altho</abbr><lb/>
he were one of an inferiour rank he might Serve to make up Servants<lb/>
<sic corr="clothes">cloths</sic> As to the Servant I writ for on Accot of <note n="MP1">Colonel Pages</note> affairs<lb/>
a proper Well <abbr expan="disposed">dispos'd</abbr> Person that could write a good hand 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
and had some Small knowledge in Surgery such as I have met with<lb/>
in Barbers boys would be of great Use in that estate I had the luck<lb/>
some years agoe to get one of this Sort at the rate of &pound;5. Per annum<lb/>
but how to Limit you I cannot tell I should not think it proper to<lb/>
exceed &pound;8" Per annum the highest wages I think that you have sent<lb/>
any <sic corr="Tailor">Taylor</sic> was 7&pound; or 8&pound;. it may not be amiss here to Acquaint You<lb/>
the Shoemaker that came away in <note target="n2">Loney</note> one of his Convicts which You<lb/>
recommended to my favour <sic corr="died">dyed</sic> in his passage else I should <add place="supralinear">not</add> have<lb/>
<del>endeavour</del> <add place="supralinear"><sic corr="failed">faild</sic> to use my endeavour</add> to <del>[illegible]</del> answer your desire</p>

<p>In yours of the 10 of November is included<lb/>
the steps you had taken in the sales of my <abbr expan="tobacco">tobo</abbr> Last Year 12 of the <corr resp="editor">[tobacco mark]</corr><lb/>
by <note target="n3">Malbon</note> Sold at 8 1/4 and 22 of the <corr resp="editor">[tobacco mark]</corr> by do Ship at the same price <lb/>
they were all <abbr expan="stemmed">stemm'd</abbr> <abbr expan="tobacco">tobo</abbr> and your brother speaks in favour of the<lb/>
goodness of the first mark I shall not complain of this mean sale<lb/>
but Allow me to tell you a story I met with this very day a Neigh <lb/>
bour of mine sends 38 <abbr expan="hogsheads">hhds.</abbr> of <sic corr="stemmed">stemmd</sic><add place="supralinear"> in a ship that did not sail so soon as Malbon</add> to Mr. Forward which I cannot<lb/>
<sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> under better management than mine Was 22 of them are Sold<lb/>
the top sort at 9 1/2 <abbr expan=" pence">d</abbr>  the middling at 9 <abbr expan=" pence">d</abbr>. and the <note target="n4"><sic corr="lugs">luggs</sic></note> at 81/2 <abbr expan=" pence">d</abbr>  he is a new<lb/>
broom indeed <add place="supralinear">but</add> by the pleasing accounts he sends to his Customers<lb/>
he engroses a great many consigments he <sic corr="has">hath</sic> now three ships<lb/>
in his interest and how can you blame men for running into him<lb/>
upon this great difference in <sic corr="prices">prizes</sic> he finds ways to give them</p>

<p>Your letter directed to the <abbr expan="Executors">Exrs</abbr> of <note n="MP1"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> Page </note>about <note target="n5">Mr. Pratts</note> affairs tells us<lb/>
you had given Account by the <name type="ship">Dolphin</name> bound to <note target="n6"><sic corr="Nansemond">Nancimond</sic></note> of his death<lb/>
<del>This letter never came to hand that I know of</del>  <add place="supralinear">another of the 24th of July by Lony I suppose is much</add> to the same purpose</p>
 
<p>You tell us in Mr. <sic corr="Pratt's">Prat's</sic> books <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> Page stood indebted upon his own<lb/>
Accot 164"7"6 and as Attorney for Mr. <sic corr="Pratt">Prat</sic> 189"7"1 I cannot take<lb/>
upon me to answer to these things till I meet the <note n="JC1">Secretary</note> I believe no<lb/>
thing of All this appears from <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo</abbr> Pages books or papers which I must <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;let 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
you <add place="supralinear">know</add> appear to be kept in a very <abbr expan="Confused">Confus'd</abbr> negligent manner but more of<lb/>
this another time We shall endeavour to give you the best light<lb/>
we Can into this affar and conclude at present 
</p>

<closer>Sir<lb/>
Your most humble Servant</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1731 July 9-1732 July 13 , Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a nineteenth-century copy of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Philip Perry (1703-1762) was partner with his brother Micajah III in the family business after the death of their father Richard in 1720 and grandfather Micajah in October 1721. (<cit><bibl n="B22">Price. <title>Perry of London. . . . </title> pp. 24-27.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] The <hi rend="italics">Forward</hi> was a London ship of 150-200 tons  commanded in1728-29 by William Loney, and in 1731 by George Buckridge. (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800 summarizing Adm. 68/194 and Survey Report 6801 summarizing Adm 68/195, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit> )</note>

<note id="n3">[3] The <hi rend="italics">Rebecca </hi> was probably a London ship; she was of 300 tons, had a crew of 11, and was commanded by Samuel Malbon in 1731-32. (<cit><bibl>Adm. 65/195, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4]  "The lowest grade [of tobacco] was known as lugs as early as 1686. . . ." (Philip A. Bruce. <title>Economic History of Virginia in the Seventeenth Century: An Inquiry into the Material Condition of the People, Based on Original and Contemporaneous Records.</title> [New York: MacMillan and Co., 1896]. p. 422 online at "Classics of American Colonial History." http://www.dinsdoc.com/bruce-1-1.htm) </note>

<note id="n5">[5] John Pratt was a London merchant and an old friend of Carter's who usually referred to him as "Daddy."</note>

<note id="n6">[6] The Nansemond is a tributary of the James River flowing into it on the south side of Hampton Rhoads along the west side of present-day Suffolk.</note>

</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>