<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C32f07a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, June 7, 1732</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 11 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C32f07a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2006</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, June 7, 1732</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1731 July 9-1732 July 13 , Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1732-06-07</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C32f07aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1732-06-07"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C32f07a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, June 7, 1732</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant William Dawkins, June 7, 1732, to report on the stories in the country that the tobacco crop is small and that ships are having a hard time finding complete cargoes which, he hopes, may affect prices for the tobacco already on its way to England. Mr. Bradley's ship has not arrived, and there are many rumors of Bradley's financial difficulties. The assembly is working on amending the tobacco inspection law.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="WD">William Dawkins,</note> June 7, 1732</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1732-06-07">June 7, 1732</date><lb/>
Mr William Dawkins,<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir,</salute>

</opener>



<p>I writ to you at some length by <note target="n1">Captain Malbon</note> &amp; added a Line <lb/>
by <note target="n2">Brooks.</note> I have little to say now only to mention the Reports that are <lb/>
very hot among us. <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Bradby of the <note target="n3"><name type="ship">Spotswood</name></note> tells me he does not <lb/>
expect to get above four hundred hogsheads, &amp; speaks of several more of the York <lb/>
ships under his Circumstances &amp; Reports from James River as much the <lb/>
same. <note target="n4">Captain Dove</note> gives you an accot himself of his Circumstances. The <lb/>
Outport Ships make heavy Complaints of the Want of Tobaco. I must not pre= <lb/>
tend to guess how these Things will end; but We cannot forbear entertaining <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;our


<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
ourselves with some Hopes that these Reports will have a Good Influence upon the <lb/>
Markets even for that <sic corr="Tobacco">Tobaco</sic> that is already gone. We have no news yet of <lb/>
<note target="n5">Mr. Bradleys</note> Ship for our River. If she <sic corr="does">doth</sic> not come it will be some ad= <lb/>
vantage to your <name type="ship">Bailey.</name> I have already hinted to you the harsh stories that are <lb/>
spread about all the <sic corr="Country">Countrey</sic> of Mr. Bradley's Circumstances. I <sic corr="cheer">chear</sic> myself <lb/>
up with Hopes they are not true. If any such thing <abbr expan="should">shou'd</abbr> happen I shall be a <lb/>
great Sufferer; and I believe many Gentlemen in James River will have their <lb/>
Share. I have already told you how fond our Countrey is of the <note target="n6"><sic corr="Tobacco">Tobaco</sic> Law.</note> The <lb/>
Burgesses are now upon mending of it. What they will make of it at last you <lb/>
will know in time. I am 
</p>

<closer>Your very humble Servant,</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1731 July 9-1732 July 13 , Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] The <hi rend="italics">Rebecca </hi> was probably a London ship; she was of 300 tons, had a crew of 11, and was commanded by Samuel Malbon in 1731-32. (<cit><bibl>Adm. 65/195, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Christopher Brooks commanded the <name type="ship"><hi rend="italics">Cambridge,</hi></name> a vessel of 100 tons and 11 men owned by London merchants Haswell and Brooks in 1729. (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6801 summarizing Adm. 68/195, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] The <hi rend="italics">Spotswood</hi> was a  London ship commanded by James Bradby,  1727-1732, and was owned by Micajah Perry.  (<cit><bibl>Adm 68/195, 70r ff., found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. See Carter to Micajah Perry 1730 April 16.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] The <hi rend="italics">Bailey</hi> was a London ship owned by William Dawkins and commanded at various times by Adam Graves (1725-1730) and by Thomas Dove (1731-1732). She was a vessel of some 250 tons and carried 15-17 crew members. (<cit><bibl>Survey report 6801 summarizing Adm. 68/195, 156v, and other data in Adm. 68/194 and /196, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small  Special Collections Library, University of Virginia;</bibl></cit> A letter of Carter's to Dawkins 1732 May 12 refers to "your ship Bailey." as does a letter of 1738 May 10 from Carter's executors to Dawkins 1738 May 10.)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] James Bradley was a London merchant with whom Carter dealt from at least 1723 until his death. As noted in his letter to Bradley of 1727 May 17, Bradley owned the <hi rend="italics">Welcome,</hi> but little information about Bradley has been located. (There is a listing of the firm of Bradly &amp; Griffin, Merchants, Fenchurch-street, opposite the Mitre Tavern, on page 13 of <cit><bibl><title>Kent's Directory For the Year 1740 Containing An Alphabetical List of the Names and Places of Abode of the Directors of Companies, Persons in Publick Business, Merchants, and other Eminent Traders in the Cities of London and Westminster, and the Borough of Southwark.</title>  London: Printed and Sold by Henry Kent in Finch-Lane, near the Royal Exchange: and by the Booksellers and Pamphlets Shops of London and Westminster, 1740. p. 39. http://freepages.history.rootsweb.com/~frpayments/KD1740/AB.htm. 8/12/2005. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] The tobacco inspection act of  1730 was introduced and steered through the legislature by Lieutenant Governor Sir William Gooch. " The "bill called for the inspection and bonding at public warehouses of all tobacco shipped abroad; for the destruction of all unacceptable tobacco; for standardization of the size of hogsheads . . . ; for maintenance of detailed records to prevent smuggling; and for the circulation of warehouse receipts as legal tender in lieu of tobacco iteself. . . ." Gooch also managed to obtain approval of the act in England. It went into effect 1731 August 1.(<cit><bibl n="B27">Billings. <hi rend="italics">et al. </hi> <title>Colonial Virginia: A History. </title></bibl></cit> pp. 236-39.)</note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>