<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;

 ]>
<TEI.2 id="C32f14a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">

             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Robert Carter's General Assembly bill re the estate of Mann Page, June 14-23, 1732</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia
Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 7 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C32f14a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL:
http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2016</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Robert Carter's General Assembly bill re the estate of Mann Page, June 14-23, 1732</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: McIlwaine, H. R., <hi rend="italics">ed</hi>. <title>Journals of the House of Burgesses of Virginia 1727-1734 1736-1740.</title> Richmond, Va. : [Library Board, Virginia State Library], 1910.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic
Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text
Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject
Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1732-06-14</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term
type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C32f14aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1732-06-14"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C32f14a.xml</idno>
<title>Robert Carter's General Assembly bill re the estate of Mann Page, June 14-23, 1732</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>These are the minutes of the Virginia House of Burgesses consideration of a bill brought by Robert Carter concerning his handling of the estate of Mann Page.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Robert Carter's General Assembly bill re the estate of Mann Page, June 14-23, 1732</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Williamsburg, Virginia</name><lb/>
<date value="1732-06-14">June 14-23, 1732</date><lb/>
<lb/>
</dateline>


</opener>

<hi rend="italics">Wednesday, June 14, 1732</hi>:   

<p>A Bill, to enable Robert Carter, Efq; One of the<lb/> Executors of the laft Will and Teftament of Mann Page,<lb/> Efq; deceased, to pay the Debts of the faid Mann Page; <lb/>and to entitle him to receive Interest for the Money he<lb/> hath advanced or shall advance for that Purpose; and to<lb/> charge the Estate of the aid Mann Page with the<lb/> Repaiment of the Principal and Interest; was read a<lb/> fecond Time.</p>

<p>Ordered, That the Bill be committed to a<lb/> Committee; and that they do examine the Allegations<lb/> thereof; and report the Matter, as it shall appear to them,<lb/> to the House: And it is referr'd to Mr Eskridge, Mr<lb/> Meriwether, Mr Blair, Mr Conway, Mr Attorney, Mr<lb/> Tayloe, Mr Lee, Mr Robinson, and Mr Francis Willis.</p><lb/>

<hi rend="italics">Friday, June 16, 1732:</hi>   

<p>Mr Eskridge reported, That the Persons appointed,<lb/>had (according to Order) examined the Allegations of<lb/> the Bill to enable Robert Carter, Esq; one of the<lb/> Executors of the last Will and Testament of Mann Page,<lb/> Esq; deceased, to pay the Debts of the said Mann Page;<lb/> and to entitle him to receive Interest for the Money he<lb/> hath advanced, or shall advance for that Purpose; and to<lb/> charge the Estate of the said Mann Page, with the<lb/> Repaiment of the Principal and Interest: And that they<lb/> were of Opinion, it was reasonable to pass the Bill.</p>

<p>Ordered, That the Bill be ingrossed.</p><lb/>

<hi rend="italics">Tuesday, June 20, 1732:</hi>  
<p>A Bill, intituled, An Ad to enable Robert Carter,<lb/> Esq; one of the Executors of the last Will and Testament<lb/> of Mann Page, Esq; deceased, to pay the Debts of the<lb/> said Mann Page; and to entitle him to receive Interest for<lb/> the Money he hath advanced or shall advance for that<lb/> Purpose; and to charge the Estate of the said Mann Page,<lb/> with the Repaiment of the Principal and Interest; was read the third Time.<lb/></p>
<p>Resolved, That the Bill do pass.</p>

<p>Ordered, That Mr Eskridge do carry the Bill to the<lb/> Council; and desire their Concurrence.</p><lb/>

<hi rend="italics">Friday, June 23, 1732: </hi> <p>A Mesfage from the Council:</p>

<p>That they have agreed to the Bill, intituled, An Act<lb/> to enable Robert Carter, Esq; One of the Executors of<lb/> the last Will and Testament of Mann Page, Esq;<lb/> deceased, to pay the Debts of the said Mann Page: and<lb/> to entitle him to receive Interest for the Money he hath<lb/> advanced, or shall advance for that Purpose: and to<lb/> charge the Estate of the said Mann Page, with the<lb/> Repaiment of the Principal and Interest.</p>

</div1>

</body>
<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> McIlwaine, H. R., <hi rend="italics">ed</hi>. <title>Journals of the House of Burgesses of Virginia 1727-1734 1736-1740.</title> Richmond, Va. : [Library Board, Virginia State Library], 1910.
</note>

<hi rend="italics"><lb/><lb/>This text was created for addition to the project June 14, 2016.</hi>

</div1>
</back>


</text>

</TEI.2>

