<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C32g10a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Alderman [Micajah] Perry, July 10, 1732</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 10 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C32g10a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2006</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Alderman [Micajah] Perry, July 10, 1732</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1731 July 9-1732 July 13 , Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1732-07-10</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C32g10aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1732-07-10"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C32g10a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Alderman [Micajah] Perry, July 10, 1732</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Alderman [Micajah] Perry, July 10, 1732, to comment on the tumult in the General Assembly over an Act of Parliament concerning the recovery of debts in the colonies which was considered unfair.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Alderman <note n="MP2">[Micajah] Perry,</note> July 10, 1732</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappa<add resp="editor">[hannock, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1732-07-10">July 10.. 1732</date><lb/>
Alderman Perry<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sr</salute>

</opener>



<p>In your letter of the 12th of April by the Man of <sic corr="War">Warr</sic> <lb/>
which I have in some measure already answered you are <abbr expan="pleased">pleas'd</abbr> to take <lb/>
into your view some <sic corr="public">publick</sic> affairs and among the rest to excuse your <lb/>
Self from any further Concern in that Severe act of Parliament which you <lb/>
were so kind to send me wearing the title, for the better Recovery of Debts in the <lb/>
British plantations than what relates to proving Merchants accounts if it 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
had stopt there it would not have <abbr expan="alarmed">alarm'd</abbr> us in the manner it has done but <lb/>
what with that and the prodigious Oppressions we labour under in other <lb/>
Respects it has <sic corr="raised">raisd</sic> so general a fury in the Assembly that <sic corr="has">hath</sic> <sic corr="Carried">Carryed</sic> <lb/>
them into measures which I heartily wish from getting out of one <sic corr="extreme,">extream,</sic> <lb/>
we may not be <abbr expan="involved">involv'd</abbr> in another the particulars you will hear enough of <lb/>
from other pens A months time of the assembly was run out before I was <lb/>
got to it and all the <sic corr="Schemes">Scheams</sic> were laid long before I came and the Current <lb/>
so Strong there was no Stemming the tide if some had had never had so great an <lb/>
inclination to do it <note n="JR">Mr. Randolph</note> the Agent of the Country Embarks in <lb/>
the <note target="n1">Burwell</note> to prosecute the great designs upon the Anvil from him you will <lb/>
have a Copious account what steps have been taken for the <sic corr="relief">releif</sic> of this <lb/>
poor Oppressed Country <add place="supralinear">in Addressing</add> to his majesty. Representing to the Lords of the Treasu <lb/>
ry and petitioning to the house of Commons what will be the consequence <lb/>
of these grand undertakings must be left to time to disclose </p>

<p>As for an <note target="n2">Excize</note> which most men wish for to <sic corr="relieve">releive</sic> us from <lb/>
the Oppression of the Merchants from the danger of Broken accounts and <lb/>
from the many destructive articles that have of late years been found out <lb/>
to deprive us of the greatest part of the Profit of our Labours I must profess <lb/>
is beyond my comprehension to forsee what will be the Consequence of this <lb/>
<sic corr="prodigous">prodigeous</sic> Change upon our trade but the general <sic corr="cry">crye</sic> that <sic corr="has">hath</sic> <sic corr="borne">bore</sic> down <lb/>
all before it <sic corr="has">hath</sic> been <abbr expan="it is">'tis</abbr> <add place="supralinear">more</add> <note target="n3">illigible</note> to <sic corr="rely">relye</sic> on the mercy of our Prince <lb/>
than to be subjected to the tyranny of the merchants who are daily <sic corr="increasing">encreasing</sic> their <lb/> Oppressions upon us it is an old <sic corr="Adage">Adagy</sic> that Oppressions make a wise <lb/>
man mad what our Madness will produce I can hardly promise myself <lb/>
<note target="n4">to live</note> to see the end of </p>

<p>As for the news from the Shipping there is no doubt but the <lb/>
masters let <sic corr="fly">flye</sic> their batteries to their owners I shall Conclude this Epistle <lb/>
with Sincere wishes for <abbr expan="your">yr.</abbr> health and happyness being really 
</p>

<closer><abbr expan="Sir">Sr:</abbr> <lb/>
Your most Humble Servant
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>
via <name type="city"><sic corr="Liverpool">Leverpoole</sic></name> <note target="n5">Loxum</note> </seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1731 July 9-1732 July 13 , Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a nineteenth-century copy of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] This vessel was commanded by Captain Constantine Cant and may have been owned by William Dawkins and Micajah Perry as Carter reported her December 1723 arrival to each of them. (<cit><bibl>Adm. 68/194-195, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Carter may refer to an excise tax which the colonists favored because of a variety of problems with the taxes on their tobacco, and particularly because of the act of parliament to which Carter refers earlier in his letter. Collecting debts owed by colonists to merchants in Great Britain was difficult for the merchants because of restrictive laws about proof of debts in Britain, and because there were two sets of books 3,000 miles apart, that carried the details of each transaction. In 1732 British merchants got through the act of parliament that made it much easier for them to collect these debts "merely on their own oaths" and which allowed them "to attach both real estate and slaves to secure them."  (<cit><bibl n="B27">Billings. <hi rend="italics">et al. </hi> <title>Colonial Virginia: A History. </title> pp. 242-43.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] The editor has been unable to determine what word Carter meant from what the clerk wrote down.</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Carter's remark was prophetic for he had less than a month to live.</note>

<note id="n5">[5] Captain Loxom commanded  a vessel named the <hi rend="italics"> Loyalty</hi>in 1729-1730. (Survey Report 9727, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. See Carter's letters to John Pemberton 1730 April 15 and 1731 August 4.)</note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>