<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech;

<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "jpg">   
<!ENTITY church SYSTEM "http://etext.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/public/church.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

 ]>

<TEI.2 id="RCwill">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Robert Carter's will, October 16, 1732</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 151 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">RCwill.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/users/berkeley/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Robert Carter's will, October 16, 1732</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>51 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter will, 1732 October 16, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1732-10-16</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="RCwillT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AD</abbr>
<extent>51 p.</extent>
<date value="1732-10-16"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">RCwill.xml</idno>
<title>Robert Carter's will, October 16, 1732</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter makes disposition in his will begun in 1726 (with codicils in October 1726, September 1728, and June and July 1730) of his extensive lands, slaves, investments, and other property to his children with small bequests to his trustees and friends, his minister, and the parish poor.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="document" n="1">
<head>Robert Carter's Will and Codicils, 1726-1732, Admitted to Probate in the General Court, October 16, 1732</head>
<opener>
<dateline>

<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman,] Lancaster County, Virginia</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1732-10-16">August 22, 1726</date><lb/>

</dateline>


</opener>

<pb n="page (1)"/><lb/><lb/>

<p>In the name of God Amen I Robert Carter <lb/> 
of Lancaster County in the colony and Dominion of <lb/> 
Virginia <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> being in a sickly declining state of Body <lb/>
but of sound mind and memory (to God be the praise) <lb/>
and being now in the sixty third year of my age do make <lb/>
this my last will and Testament.</p>



<p>I resign my soul to God as into the hands of a Faithfull <lb/>
Creator and my Body (when it shall please him to take <lb/>
me out of this World to the earth) trusting in and through <lb/>
the merits and Mediation of my ever blessed redeemer our <lb/>
great and only high priest at the right hand of the Father <lb/>
to have my sins pardoned and <sic corr="washed">washt</sic> away and to attain <lb/>
to the resurection of the Just disclaiming any righteousness <lb/>
of my own and firmly believing in the ever blessed Trin-<lb/>
-ity Father Son and holy Ghost placing my only hopes in <lb/>
in the Satisfaction and propitiation of my dear Lord and <lb/>
Saviour Jesus Christ I order my body <del>body</del> to be laid in <lb/>
the yard of Christ Church near and upon the right hand <lb/><lb/><lb/>
<figure entity="church" style= "float :right">
<figDesc><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Photograph of Christ Church, Lancaster County; <lb/>the Carter tombs are to the right of the building.</hi></hi> </figDesc></figure>
<lb/><lb/><lb/>
of my Wives a decent funeral to be kept at my interment <lb/>
a monument or tombstone to be sent for to be erected over <lb/>
my grave of about the value of my last wives Tombstone <lb/>
with a proper Inscription at the discretion of my son John <lb/>
or of my other executors in case of his Mortality and I <lb/>
do dispose of that worldly estate which God hath <lb/>
blessed me with <add place="supralinear">in</add> manner following.</p>


<p>I give unto my son <note n="JC1">John Carter</note> <abbr expan="Esquire"><abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr></abbr> and to his heirs Male <lb/>
all my lands Houses and appurtenances, and all my slaves <lb/>
and real Estate whatsoever lying and being in Lancaster <lb/>
County (excepting such Land slaves and real estate as <lb/>
I shall otherwise dispose of in this my will) likewise <lb/>
my water Mill and the lands I bought of Richard <lb/>
Sattimore adjoining whether lying in Lancaster or <lb/>
Northumberland County.</p><lb/>


<pb n="page (2)"/><lb/><lb/>

<p>I give unto my said son John and to the heirs male issue of <lb/>
his body lawfully begotten all that tract of Land I bought <lb/>
of Mr John Spicer in Essex County <add place="supralinear">containing</add> seven and twenty<lb/>
hundred acres with all housing Members and appurtenances  <lb/>
with all the slaves and real estate thereon excepting the <lb/>
slaves in this my will hereafter excepted.</p>

                    
<p>I give unto my said son John and to the heirs Male issue <lb/>
of his Body Lawfully to be begotten my tract of Ten thou-<lb/>
sand acres of Land upon the branches of <note target="n1">Occaquan,</note><lb/>
upon Cedar run, Owl run &amp; <note target="n2">Licking run,</note> adjoining to <lb/>
the Germans, granted to <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr><note n="GT"> George Turbervile,</note> and by <lb/>
him conveyed to me, unto him my said son John, and <lb/>
to the heirs male issue of his Body and for want of such <lb/>
unto my son Charles, and to the heirs male issue of his <lb/>
Body, and for want of such unto my son <note n="RC2">Robert</note> and to <lb/>
the heirs male issue of his Body and for want of such  <lb/>
unto my own right heirs forever.</p>

<p>I give unto my said son John and to the heirs male issue of <lb/>
of his Body Lawfully to be begotten, one moyety or half <lb/>
part of all those lands I lately bought of <note target="n3">Robert Cary</note> <lb/>
of London Merchant with their and every of their ap-  <lb/>
-purts lying in Richmond &amp; Westmoreland Counties to <lb/>
be equally divided as followeth. The division to begin <lb/>
somewhere near the plantation of Peter Smith where <lb/>
the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> Smith lives and so to run away towards <abbr expan="Rappahannock">Rappa.</abbr>  <lb/>
River in such manner <add place="supralinear">so</add> as to make pretty near equal <lb/>
Quantities in each part consideration being had to <lb/>
the conveniences of both parts of these lands and that <lb/>
the <note target="n4">Fork of Totees Key</note> come in to the lower division the <lb/>
lower half of this Land I given unto my said son <lb/>
John and to the heirs male issue of his Body <lb/>
and for want of such unto my son <lb/> <lb/>



<pb n="page (3)"/><lb/><lb/>

Robert and to the heirs male issue of his Body and for <lb/>
want of such unto my son <note target="n5">Charles</note> and to the heirs male <lb/>
of his Body and for want of such unto my own right heirs <lb/>
forever.</p>

<p>I give unto my said son John and to the heirs male <lb/>
issue of his Body that tract of Land in King George County <lb/>
that I bought of the said Cary, called the <note target="n6">round hills</note> being <lb/>
esteemed to contained five hundred acres together with the <lb/>
appurtenances thereunto belonging. All these Lands Tenements <lb/>
Houses and appurtenances  slaves and real estate I devise will <lb/>
and bequeath unto my said son John and the heirs male issue <lb/>
of his Body lawfully begotten and if my said son John <sic corr="die">dye</sic> <lb/>
without issue male or his issue male <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male <lb/>
then my will is that these lands House Slaves and real <lb/>
estate given to my  said son John do go to my son Robert <lb/>
and to his heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten <lb/>
and if my son Robert <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male or his issue <lb/>
male <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my will is that these <lb/>
lands House Slaves and real estate given to my son John <lb/>
do go to my son Charles and his heirs male issue of his <lb/>
Body lawfully begotten and if my son Charles <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without <lb/>
issue male or his issue male <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then <lb/>
my will is that these Lands houses slaves, and real estate <lb/>
given to my son John do go to my son <note target="n7">Landon</note> and his heirs male <lb/>
issue of his Body lawfully begotten and if he <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male <lb/>
or his issue male <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male that then these Lands <lb/>
houses slaves and real estate given unto my said son <lb/>
John do go unto my son <note target="n8">George,</note> and his heirs male issue of his <lb/>
Body lawfully begotten and if he <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male <lb/>
or his issue male <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male that then these lands <lb/>
Houses slaves and real estate given unto my said son John do go <lb/>
unto my Grandson <note target="n9">Carter Burwell</note> second son of my <lb/>
daughter <note n="ECB">Elizabeth Nicholas</note> and to the heirs <add place="infralinear">male</add>  <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (4)"/><lb/><lb/>

male issue of his Body lawfully begotten and if my said Grandson <lb/>
Carter Burwell do <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male or his issue male <lb/>
<sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male that then these lands, houses slaves <lb/>
and real estate do go to my Grandson <note target="n10">Robert Burwell</note> and to <lb/>
the heirs male issue of his body lawfully begotten and if my <lb/>
said Grandson <abbr expan="Robert">Robt..</abbr> Burwell do <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male <lb/>
or his issue male <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male that then these lands <lb/>
,houses, slaves and real estate given to my son John do go to <lb/>
my Grandson <note target="n11">Lewis Burwell</note> and to the heirs male issue of <lb/>
his body lawfully begotten and if my said Grandson Lewis <lb/>
do <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male of his body that then these Lands <lb/>
houses slaves and real estate shall go to my Grandson <lb/>
<note target="n12">Mann Page</note> the son and heir of my daughter <note n="JCP">Judith <lb/>
Page</note> and the heirs male issue of his body lawfully begotten <lb/>
and if my said Grandson Mann Page <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue <lb/>
male or his issue male <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male that then <lb/>
these lands, house slaves and real estate given to my <lb/>
son John do go unto my said daughter Pages second <lb/>
or living son if any such there be, to be baptized <lb/>
Carter and to the heirs male issue of his Body lawfully <lb/>
begotten and if such Second or living son of my said <lb/>
daughter Judith Page do <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then <lb/>
I give these lands, slaves, houses and real estate <lb/>
given unto my said son John unto my own right <lb/>
heirs forever</p>

<p>I give and bequeath unto my son Robert <lb/>
and <add place="supralinear">to</add> his heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten <lb/>
all my lands houses slave appurtenances  and real estate what-  <lb/>
soever lying and being in Westmorland <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add>County and <lb/>
likewise the M <hi rend="underline">ill,</hi> and lands adjoining in <lb/>
Richmond County commonly called and known by the <lb/>
name of <note n="DM">Dickersons Mill</note> also all my lands houses slaves appur-  <lb/>
-tenances and real estate I have upon the branches of Wicocomoco <lb/>
River in Northumberland County known by the name <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (5)"/><lb/><lb/>

of <note n="FP">Fieldings Plantation</note> and necks containing between eighteen <lb/>
hundred and two thousand acres or thereabouts likewise all <lb/>
my tract of land I bought of <abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> <note n="JH">John Holloway</note> lying upon <lb/>
Chappawamsick in <note target="n12.5">Hartford county</note> and also all my lands <lb/>
lying upon the Branches of Ottaquan in the same County and <lb/>
likewise the slaves tht. went from Middlesex since my <lb/>
wifes death up to <note n="PE">pewmens Emd</note> which I have <add place="supralinear">likewise</add> before ex-  <lb/>
-cepted  <add place="supralinear">out</add> of my gift to my said son John I give and de <lb/>
-vise unto my son Robert and to the heirs male issue <lb/>
of his Body lawfully begotten as also the following negroe <lb/>
slaves (to wit) my negroe George the cooper and his wife <lb/>
and Children The two negroes I have now bound out <lb/>
as apprentices to Wm. Garland Also the Negroe Boy that <lb/>
is an apprentice to George the Cooper also my negroe boy <lb/>
David Tom Gumby's Brother and likewise my Cook <lb/>
wench Priss her husband Old Robin and her children <lb/>
all that she hath or shall have These lands houses <lb/>
slaves appurtenances  and real estate I do give and devise unto my <lb/>
said son Robert and his heirs male issue of his Body <lb/>
lawfully begotten And if my son Robert <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without <lb/>
issue male then my will is that these lands houses <lb/>
slave appurtenances  and real estate given unto my said <lb/>
son Robert do go to my son Charles and to the heirs <lb/>
male issue of his Body lawfully begotten and if my son <lb/>
Charles <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my will is that these <lb/>
lands house slave appurtenances and Real estate <lb/>
given unto my son Robert do go to my son John and  <lb/>
the heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten and if my <lb/>
son John <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my will is that <lb/>
these lands house slave appurtenances  and real estate <lb/>
given unto my son Robert do go to my son Landon and to the heirs <lb/>
male issue of his Body lawfully begotten and if my said son Lan-  <lb/>
-don <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my will is that these lands <add place="infralinear">houses slaves appurtenances </add>  <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (6)"/><lb/><lb/>

 and real estate given unto my son Robert do go to my <lb/>
son George and the heirs male issue of his Body lawfully <lb/>
begotten and if my said son George <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male <lb/>
then my will is that these lands house slave <abbr expan="appurtenances">appurts</abbr>,  <lb/>
given unto my son Robert do go to right heirs <add place="supralinear">forever</add> I give unto <lb/>
my son Robert and to the heirs male issue of his Body all <lb/>
that other <note target="n13">moiety</note> and half of the lands and appurtenances <lb/>
that I bought of <abbr expan="Robert">Robt.</abbr> Cary lying in Richmond <lb/>
and Westmoreland Counties being the upper Moiety of <lb/>
these lands according to the division directed as afore-  <lb/>
-said and in case of the death of my said son Robert <lb/>
without issue male then this Moiety of the lands I bought <lb/>
of Mr Robert Cary to go to my son John and to his issue <lb/>
male and for want of issue male of the body of my son <lb/>
John to go to my son Charles &amp; to the heirs male issue <lb/>
of his Body lawfully begotten and for want of such <lb/>
to my son Charles <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add>and to the heirs male issue of his <lb/>
Body lawfully begotten and if my said son Landon  <sic corr="die">dye</sic> <lb/>
without issue male then to my son George and to the <lb/>
heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten and if <lb/>
my said son George <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my <lb/>
will is that this <sic corr="moiety">Moyety</sic> of these lands and <abbr expan="appurtenances">appurts</abbr>  <lb/>
given to my said son Robert do go to my right heirs forever &mdash;  <lb/>
I give unto my said son Robert that tract or parcel of <lb/>
land I lately bought of William rust lying in Hartford <lb/>
County upon the branches of Bull Run to him and <lb/>
his heirs forever.</p>

<p>I give these lands houses slaves Appurtenances and real estate <lb/>
I do give and bequeath unto my said son Robert and to his heirs <lb/>
male issue of his Body lawfully begotten and if my son Robert  <lb/>
<sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my will is that (excepting the <lb/>
lands I bought of Mr Cary which are settled on my son John <lb/> 
in remainder as aforesaid and the lands I bought of <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<add place="infralinear">of </add><lb/>  <lb/> 

<pb n="page (7)"/><lb/><lb/>

William Rust, which I have given unto my sad son Ro-  <lb/>
bert in Fee simple) these lands houses slaves appurtenances  <lb/>
real estate given unto my said son Robert do go <lb/>
unto my son Charles and to the heirs male issue of his Body <lb/>
lawfully begotten and if my said son Charles <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without <lb/>
issue <add place="supralinear">male</add> then my will is that these lands house slaves &amp;  <lb/>
real estate do go to my son John and to the heirs male issue of <lb/>
his Body lawfully begotten and if my said son John <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without <lb/>
issue male then my will is that these lands house and real <lb/>
estate do go to my son Landon to the heirs male issue <lb/>
of his Body lawfully begotten and if my said son Landen <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add><lb/>
<sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my will is that all these <lb/>
lands houses slaves and real estate do go to my son <lb/>
George and to the heirs male issue of his Body lawfully be-  <lb/>
-gotten and if my son George <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male <lb/>
then it is my will that all these Lands house slaves and <lb/>
real estate do go to my right heirs forever. &mdash;</p>

<p>I give and bequeath unto my son Charles and to all the <lb/>
heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten All my lands houses  <lb/>
plantations and appurtenances in Lancaster and Northumber-  <lb/>
-land Counties which formerly belonged to <abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> William  <lb/>
Lister as also the plantation and lands I bought of  <lb/>
Mr <note target="n14">Robert Jones</note> commonly called <note target="n15">old plantation</note> <lb/>
and likewise the plantation and Lands I <lb/>
bought and purchased of John Sudley the Father <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add>  <lb/>
and the son called <note target="n16">Blough point plantation</note> on where  <lb/>
<note target="n17"><abbr expan="Thomas">Thos.</abbr> West</note> now lives and also I give unto said son <lb/>
Charles and to the heirs male issue of his Body law-  <lb/>
-fully begotten all lmy lands in King George and <lb/>
Spotsylvania Counties lying above the falls of <lb/>
Rappahannock River and also my Great tract of <lb/>
land <add place="supralinear">lying</add> upon the Branches of Potomack whereon <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (8)"/><lb/><lb/>

I have three plantations now seated likewise I give <lb/>
unto my said son Charles all the slaves that are upon <lb/>
the said plantations Lands &amp; settlements herein given <lb/>
to him and all the slaves that shall be upon the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr>  <lb/>
plantations at the time of my death and I also give <lb/>
unto my said son Charles my negroe Tom Gumby <lb/>
and his wife &amp; children and also my negroe Frank the <lb/>
Carpenter &amp; his wife and children &amp; my two negroes that <lb/>
are apprentices to John Hurst and my negroe boy called <lb/>
Cesar I also and devise to my said son Charles and <lb/>
to the heirs male issue of his body apiece of Land about <lb/>
two hundred acres lying between the line of the Great <lb/>
Tract I live upon and the lands that were <lb/>
where the brick store stands and joining upon the Glebe <lb/>
being a piece of Land on which John Bradley lived also <lb/>
the lands I bought of John Wale the son <add place="supralinear">of</add> Elizabeth Waugh <lb/>
the relict of <note n="WW">William Waugh</note> also the lands I have lately <lb/>
agreed for with <note target="n18">Simon Sallard</note> and Blanch his wife <lb/>
for the executing deeds for the same I have Sallards bond <lb/>
which deeds in case of my death before exempted it is <lb/>
my will shall be past to my said son Charles and the <lb/>
heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten.</p>
<p>I give these lands plantations houses slaves appurtenances  <lb/>
and estate I give unto my said son Charles and the  <lb/>
heirs male of his Body lawfully begotten and if my son <lb/>
Charles <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my will is that <lb/>
these lands plantations houses slaves and appurtenances and <lb/>
estates given unto my said son Charles do go to my son Robert <lb/>
&amp; the heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten and if my son <lb/>
Robert <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my will is that these lands plantations <lb/>
houses slaves <abbr expan="appurtenances">appurts</abbr>	&amp; estates given unto my son Charles do <lb/>
go to my son John and the heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (9)"/><lb/><lb/>

And if my son John <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my will is <lb/>
that these lands plantations houses <add place="supralinear">slaves </add> appurtenances and estates <lb/>
given unto my son Charles do go to my son Landon <lb/>
and the heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten <lb/>
and if my son Landen <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my <lb/>
will is that these Lands plantations houses slaves <lb/>
appurtenances and estate given unto my son Charles do go <lb/>
to my son George and the heirs male issue of his Body <lb/>
lawfully begotten and if my son George <sic corr="die">dye</sic> with-  <lb/>
-out issue male then my will is that these lands <lb/>
houses slaves appurtenances &amp; estates given unto my son <lb/>
Charles do go to my right heirs forever.</p>
<p>My will is that the respective stocks of Cattle horses <lb/>
sheep and hoggs that are upon my several plantations,  <lb/>
shall go to such of my sons as the Lands are given to according <lb/>
to my aforesaid will and to be and be continued as an <lb/>
appurtenace to the several plantations to which they belong. &mdash;</p>

<p>My will is that all my lands slaves stocks of cattle &amp; hoggs <lb/>
houses plantations and appurtenances to the said lands and real <lb/>
estate belonging, lying upon <note n="MH">merchants hundred</note> in James river <lb/>
beheld <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> &amp; enjoyed by my Daughter <note n="ECB">Elizabeth</note> formerly the relict <lb/>
of <abbr expan="Nathaniel">Nathl.</abbr> Burwell <abbr expan="Gentleman">Gen.</abbr> <abbr expan="deceased">decd</abbr> and now the wife of Doctor George <lb/>
Nicholas for and during the time of her natural life and the <lb/>
profits of the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> estate to belong to her and after her <lb/>
decease my will is that these lands houses slaves <abbr expan="appurtenances">appurts</abbr> <lb/>
stocks of Cattle &amp; hogs do go to my Grandson Carter Burwell &mdash;  <lb/>
&amp; to the heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten, and for want <lb/>
of such unto my Grandson <abbr expan="Robert">Robt.</abbr> Burwell, and the heirs <lb/>
of his Body lawfully begotten and for want of such unto my Grand-  <lb/>
-son Lewis Burwell &amp; to the heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten <lb/>
and if my <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> Three Grandsons should <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male, Then my <lb/>
will is that these lands slaves, houses, appurtenances stocks of Cattle and hogs do go to <lb/>
my Grandaughter <note target="n19">Elizabeth Burwell</note> and to the heirs male issue of her Body, and <lb/>
if all my <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> grandchildren should <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (10)"/><lb/><lb/> 

Will is that these lands &amp; estate of <note n="MH">Merchant hundred</note> with the <lb/>
slaves and <abbr expan="appurtenances">appurts</abbr> do go to my son John and the heirs male issue  <lb/>
of his Body and for want of such unto my <add place="supralinear">all</add> sons in tail male <lb/>
with the remainder over according to the disposition I have <lb/>
already made of the rest of my lands slaves and real estates <lb/>
in this my will, and my further will is that this estate in all <lb/>
time to be called &amp; <add place="supralinear">to</add> go by the name of Carter Grove provided <lb/>
<hi rend="underline"><sic corr="always">alwaies</sic></hi> &amp; it is my and meaning that the number of slaves <lb/>
that are now upon the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> plantation shall always be kept up <lb/>
and that the mortalitys shall be still supply'd of the profits <lb/>
of this estate, and that the number of Cattle and other <lb/>
stocks shall always be kept up for the use and manure <lb/>
of the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> plantation to the same number they are at my demise <lb/>
and that the  <add place="supralinear"><abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> plantation</add> be always kept in good repair and that the contin-  <lb/>
-gent charges of the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> estate be born out of the profits ;&mdash;</p>
<p>That whereas I have bought two tracts of Land of <abbr expan="Major">Maj.</abbr> <note n="JH">John <lb/>
Holloway</note> lying in King &amp; Queen County which cost me <lb/>
seven hundred pounds sterling six negroes of Mr. <note target="n20">Augus-  <lb/>
-tine Moore</note> which cost me <del>[illegible]</del> <add place="supralinear">one</add> hundred &amp; twenty <lb/>
pounds sterling and sundry negroes in number <lb/>
twelve of Mr John Pratt which cost me one hundred <lb/>
and eighty pounds ten shillings which <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> two tracts of <lb/>
of <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> Land &amp; negroes are now in the possession of <note n="MP1">Mann Page</note> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr>  <lb/>
and my daughter <note n="JCP">Judith Page</note> his wife and no settlement <lb/>
thereof made and having also given orders to the said Mann <lb/>
Page to lay out a Debt due from him to me upon an ac-  <lb/>
-count amounting to one hundred and six pounds <lb/>
Eighteen shillings and two pence in slaves for a <lb/>
further settlement upon the afore<abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> Lands I do <lb/>
therefore give and devise the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> Lands &amp; slaves <lb/>
that shall be bought with the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> money unto my <lb/>
said daughter Judith Page for and during the <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (11)"/><lb/><lb/>

Term of her natural life and the profit of the said land and <lb/>
slaves and after the decease of my said daughter Judith Page <lb/>
the said land &amp; slaves do go to my Grandson <note target="n21">Carter Page</note> &amp; to the <lb/>
heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten and for want <lb/>
of such to my Grandson <note target="n22">John Page</note> and to the heirs male issue of  <lb/>
his Body lawfully begotten and for want of such to my <lb/>
grandson <note target="n23">Mann Page</note> and to the the heirs male issue of his  <lb/>
Body lawfully begotten and if the said Three Grandsons <lb/>
should <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then my will is that these <lb/>
lands and slaves &amp; appurtenances  do go to my Daughter Page's <lb/>
issue Female and the heirs of their Bodies lawfully begotten <lb/>
and in case of failure of heirs of the Body of my daughter <lb/>
Judith, first by her present husband in whose posterity by my said <lb/>
daughter my design is that this estate be <sic corr="fixed">fixt</sic> and for want of issue <lb/>
by him then upon the issue of her Body by any other husband,  <lb/>
but if no such issue be, to take this estate according to my intent <lb/>
then it is my will that this estate after the death of my said <lb/>
daughter's husband Mann Page <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> who is to enjoy the profits of <lb/>
it during his natural life these lands slaves Houses &amp; appurtenances  <lb/>
do go to my son John and his heirs male and <add place="supralinear">so</add> to my other sons in <lb/>
Tale male with the remainder over <abbr expan="according">accordg</abbr> <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> to the order and dis-  <lb/>
-position of this my will as afore said and after the entail is <lb/>
spent to revert And go to my own right heirs and my will <lb/>
is that this estate be called and go by the name of Carter's Dale <lb/>
in all times to come provided <sic corr="always">alwaies</sic> and it is my will and <lb/>
meaning that the number of slaves that are <add place="supralinear">now</add> upon the <add place="supralinear">sd</add> plan-  <lb/>
-tation, shall always be kept up and that the mortalitys shall be <lb/>
still supplied out of the profits of this estate and the number <lb/>
of Cattle and other stocks shall <hi rend="underline">alwaies</hi> be kept up for the <lb/>
use and manner of the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> plantation to the same number <lb/>
they are at, at my decease and that the said plantation <lb/>
be always kept in good repair and that the contingent Charges <lb/>
of the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr>  estate be <sic corr="bourne">born</sic> out of the profits.</p>

<pb n="page (12)"/><lb/><lb/>

<p>That whereas I have bought a tract of Land of <abbr expan="Major">Maj:</abbr> Thomas <lb/>
Randolph in henrico County with the <abbr expan="appurtenances">appurts</abbr> &amp; stocks <lb/>
thereon which cost me two hundred and fifty pounds ster-  <lb/>
-ling and another Tract of Lands in Surry County of Mr. Wil-  <lb/>
-liam Macon and <add resp="editor">[gap in text]</add> his Wife which <lb/>
cost me five hundred and sixty pounds sterling and also <lb/>
Ten negroes which I bought of Mr Augustin More which cost <lb/>
me Two hundred pounds sterling and three negroes more of <lb/>
the said More which cost me sixty six pounds sterling all <lb/>
which lands and negroes being now in the possession of Maj.  <lb/>
<abbr expan="Benjamin">Benja.</abbr> Harrison &amp; my Daughter Anne his wife it is my will <lb/>
&amp; so I do give and bequeath all these lands &amp; the said slaves and <lb/>
stocks that now are and shall be upon the said lands of my <lb/>
purchase unto my said Daughter Anne for and during <lb/>
her natural life and to her second son to be christened Carter,  <lb/>
and to the heirs male issue of his Body and for want of such to a <lb/>
third son and to a the heirs male issue of his Body and for want <lb/>
of such to the eldest son of my Daughter Anne and to the <lb/>
heirs male issue of his Body and for want of <del>such</del> issue male <lb/>
of my Daughter Anne's body to her my said Daughter's heirs <lb/>
female and for want of issue male &amp; female of my said <lb/>
Daughter these lands and slave to go to my son Robert and <lb/>
to heirs male issue of his Body and for want of such to  <lb/>
my son Charles and the heirs male issue of his Body and <lb/>
for want of such to my son Landon and the the heirs male issue <lb/>
of his Body and for want of such to <del>revert to</del> my son George <lb/>
and the heirs male issue of his Body and for want of such <lb/>
to revert to my right heirs forever provided always &amp; it is my <lb/>
will that the number of slaves that I have now bought for the <lb/>
settlement as aforesaid be made up by executors to the <lb/>
number of Twenty five workers within three years after my de-  <lb/>
-cease provided always and it is my will &amp; meaning that the <lb/>
number of slaves that are now upon the said plantations or that shall be placed <lb/>
there according to the intent of this my will shall always be kept up and that the <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (13)"/><lb/><lb/>

mortalitys shall be still supplied out of the profits of this estate <lb/>
and the number of Cattle &amp; other stocks shall always be kept up for <lb/>
the use and manner of the said plantations to the same number <lb/>
they are at <add place="supralinear">at</add> my decease, and the said plantations be always <lb/>
kept in good repair and the contingent Charges of the <lb/>
said estate be <sic corr="bourne">born</sic> out of the profits.</p>
<p>And it is my further will that if my said Daughter Anne be <lb/>
living at the time of my decease there be five hundred <lb/>
pounds sterling paid to her by my executors three years after my <lb/>
decease And I do also given unto my said daughter Anne <lb/>
forty pounds sterling to be in lieu &amp; satisfaction for her <lb/>
claim to my negro wench Martha being unwilling she <lb/>
shall be parted from her husband, The said forty pounds <lb/>
to be laid out in negroes to be <note target="n32"><sic corr="entailed">intailed</sic></note> upon her my said <lb/>
Daughter Anne &amp; upon her daughter <note target="n23">Betty.</note></p>
<p>It is my will then when my Daughter Anne's Daughter Betty <lb/>
shall arrive to the age of Twenty one years or to be Married there <lb/>
shall be paid to her the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of five hundred pounds sterling <lb/>
by my executors and that when my said daughter Anne's Daugh-  <lb/>
-ter <note target="n24">Anne</note> shall arrive at the age of Twenty one years or to be <lb/>
married there shall be paid to her the <hi rend="underline"> </hi> of five hundred  <lb/>
pounds sterling by my executors and in case of the death of  <lb/>
either of my said Grandaughters the whole ten hundred pounds <lb/>
to be paid to the survivor when she arrives at the age of Twen-  <lb/>
-ty one years or is married and if both of my <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr>  Grandchild-  <lb/>
-dren should <sic corr="die">dye</sic> before they arrive at such ages or marriage <lb/>
then the said ten hundred pounds to be paid to such other son <lb/>
or Daughter as shall be born of the body of my said Daughter <lb/>
Anne when he or she shal <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> arrive at the age of twenty <lb/>
one years or marriage. My will is that if my Daughter <note n="MCB">Mary</note> shall <lb/>
live to the age of twenty one years unmarried or if she should <lb/>
marry before with the consent and approbation of <abbr expan="Colonel">Col:</abbr> Mann Page <abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr>  <lb/>
<note n="BH1">Benjamin Harrison</note> my son John &amp; her brothers Robert &amp; Charles or the major <lb/>
part of them or the survivors of them that then there be paid to her by my <lb/>
<abbr expan="executors''">extors</abbr> the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of two thousand pounds sterling to be paid in manner following (that is to say)  <lb/>  <lb/>


<pb n="page (14)"/><lb/><lb/>

at three yearly equal successive payments the first payment to be made <lb/>
in eight months after my said Daughter's marriage with consent <lb/>
as aforesaid or her coming to the age of twenty one, And my will <lb/>
is that my said Daughter Mary have a genteel maintenance <lb/>
out of my estate until she arrive at such age or marriage <lb/>
and that she live with her sister <note n="JCP">Page </note>or her sister <note n="ACH">Har-  <lb/>
-rison</note> as they shall agree to be best and <sic corr="most proper">properest</sic> for her <lb/>
I also give to my said Daughter Mary thirty five pounds <lb/>
sterling to be paid to my son John to be in lieu and sa-  <lb/>
-tisfaction for her claim to my Mulatto Girl Molly and <lb/>
her child <del>being</del> being unwilling she should be parted <lb/>
from her husband also the spinning Girl phillis <lb/>
and the Girl Nanny which she already calls hers to <lb/>
her the said Mary, and to the heirs of her Body and <lb/>
if she dies without such heirs unto my daughter Harri-  <lb/>
-son, and the heirs of her Body forever. And I do order my <lb/>
executors to send for, for my said Daughter Mary a gold <lb/>
watch of thirty pounds price, and a pearl necklace of <lb/>
twenty five pounds price when she arrives at sixteen <lb/>
years of age, and it is my further will that if my said <lb/>
Daughter Mary shall marry before she attains to the age <lb/>
of twenty one years without the consent and approbation <lb/>
of her brothers as aforesaid or the major part of the sur-  <lb/>
-vivors of them that in such case I do revoke &amp; make <lb/>
void all the aforesaid Legacies &amp; then order my executors to <lb/>
pay to her my said Daughter Mary the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of Five hun-  <lb/>
-dred pounds sterling and no more.</p>
<p>My will is that if my Daughter <note n="LCF">Lucy</note> shall live to the age of twenty one years <lb/>
unmarried or if she shall marry before with the consent and approbation of <lb/>
<abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> Mann Page, <abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr>. <abbr expan="Benjamin">Benja.</abbr> Harrison my son John and her brothers Robert <lb/>
and Charles that then there be paid to her by my Executors the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of eight-  <lb/>
-een hundred pounds sterling to be paid in manner following (that is to <lb/>
say) at three yearly equal successive payments the first payment to <lb/>
be made in eight months after my said daughter's marriage with consent <lb/>
as aforesaid, or her coming to the age of twenty one years and my <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (15)"/><lb/><lb/>

Will is that my said Daughter Lucy have a genteel maintenance <lb/>
out of my estate until she arrive at such age or marriage, and <lb/>
that she live with her sister Page, or her sister Harrison as <lb/>
as they shall agree to be best and properest for her, I also give <lb/>
unto my said daughter Lucy, the Madagascar Girl Belinda <lb/>
and her child and Nausau's Girl Bridgett, and Toby's <add place="supralinear">Girl</add> Pricilla,  <lb/>
to her the said Lucy, and the heirs of her Body and if she <sic corr="die">dye</sic> <lb/>
without heirs of her Body unto my son Robert and the heirs of <lb/>
his Body forever. And I do order my executors to send for, for my <lb/>
said Daughter Lucy a gold watch of thirty pounds price, <lb/>
and a pearl necklace of twenty five pounds price when she arrives  <lb/>
at sixteen years of age. And it is my further will that <add place="supralinear">if</add> my said <lb/>
Daughter Lucy shall marry before she attains to the age <lb/>
of twenty one years without the consent and approba-  <lb/>
-tion of her brothers as aforesaid, or the major part of the sur-  <lb/>
-vivors of them that in such case I <sic corr="revoke">revoak</sic> &amp; make <lb/>
void all the aforesaid Legacys and then order my executors to  <lb/>
pay to her my said Daughter Lucy the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of five <lb/>
hundred pounds sterling and no more.&mdash; </p> 

<p>My will is that if either of my two youngest daughters <lb/>
<del>dye</del> <sic corr="die">dye</sic> before she comes of age or is married <add place="supralinear">so that</add> she doth not  <lb/>
come to enjoy the Legacies designed by this said will then <lb/>
my will is there be paid by my executors to each of my sur-  <lb/>
-viving daughters the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of two hundred pounds sterling <lb/>
and if the other of my two youngest Daughters <sic corr="die">dye</sic> before <lb/>
she come to enjoy the Legacies designed her by this will <lb/>
then two hundred pounds more a peice to my surviving <lb/>
Daughters, and in case of the death of my surviving daugh-  <lb/>
-ters or either of them leaving Child or children <add place="supralinear">such child or children</add> to enjoy <lb/>
the mothers part And Whereas I have in <sic corr="England">england</sic> in <note n="MP2">Mr.  <lb/>
Perry's</note> &amp; <note n="WD">Mr. Dawkin's</note> hands Four thousand two hundred &amp; fifty pounds <lb/>
Capitol Bank stock &amp; in Mr. Perry's hands a bank annuity of fifteen hun-  <lb/>
-dred pounds and whereas I have sundry valuable debts due unto me in <lb/>
Virginia upon Mortgage bonds &amp; Interest it is my will <add place="supralinear">that</add> these Bank Stocks and this Bank <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (16)"/><lb/><lb/>

annuity shall be kept upon the same foot they now are and also two <lb/>
thousand pounds of my best debts, that are now out upon mortgage Bond and <lb/>
interest as aforesaid still as the money shall be paid into my <abbr expan="executors''"><abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr></abbr> <lb/>
hands shall be let out again unto me or more substantial person or <lb/>
persons in Virginia with good security according to the discretion <lb/>
of my executors upon mortgage or Bonds at interest &amp; so to be contin<add resp="editor"> [u]</add>-  <lb/>
-ed at interest until my son George shall arrive at the age of twenty one <lb/>
years, and that the interest for the first two years after my death to be <lb/>
raised out of these bank stocks the bank annuity and the said  of <lb/>
two thousand <add place="supralinear">pounds</add> shall go to my three elders son my executors &amp; shall <lb/>
contribute to the payment of my Legacies the discharging the <lb/>
incumbrances of this my will &amp; to the maintenance &amp; educat-  <lb/> 
-tion of my Children <add place="supralinear">in</add> Britain and Virginia. </p> 

<p>It is my will that when my son Landon shall arrive at the age <lb/>
of twenty one years there shall then be paid to him &amp; delivered <lb/>
by my executors one moiety or half part of my said Capitol Bank <lb/>
stocks &amp; one moiety of my said Bank annuity and one moiety <lb/>
or half part of the said two thousand pounds to be kept out at <lb/>
interest as aforesaid and likewise one half part or moiety of <lb/>
the interest that shall arise from the said Bank stocks <lb/>
Bank Annuity and the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> two thousand pounds after the afore-  <lb/>
-said two years shall be run out &amp; expired.</p>
<p>It is my will that when my son George shall arrive at the <lb/>
age of one and twenty years the other moity <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> or half part <lb/>
of my said Capitol Bank stocks the other moiety or  <lb/>
half part of my said Bank annuity, and the other <lb/>
moiety of half part of my <add place="supralinear">said</add> two thousand pounds ordered <lb/>
to be placed out at interest as aforesaid together <lb/>
with the interest that shall arise out of <del>out of</del>  <lb/>
the said moiety of the said Capitol Bank stocks <lb/>
<del>and</del> <add place="supralinear">&amp; </add> of the said Bank annuity and of the said<lb/>two thousand pounds after the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr>  two years <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (17)"/><lb/><lb/>

are expired and run out as aforesaid, shall be paid delivered and <lb/>
assigned over to my executors or the survivors of them unto my said <lb/>
son George.</p>
<p>It is my will that if my son Landon <sic corr="die">dye</sic> before he arrives at the <lb/>
age of one &amp; twenty years, so that according to the intent of this my will,  <lb/>
he my son Landon will have no right to these Legacys designed him <lb/>
when <add place="supralinear">he</add> comes to the age of one &amp; twenty years &amp; not before, that then <lb/>
that moiety or half part of my said Capitol Bank stocks of <lb/>
my said Bank annuity and of my said two thousand <lb/>
pounds together with the interest that shall arise therefrom,  <lb/>
after the expiration of the aforesaid two years (ordered to be <lb/>
paid to my said son Landon by my said executors when he comes <lb/>
to the age of one and twenty years) shall be also paid to my <lb/>
son George when he shall arrive to the age of one &amp; twenty <lb/>
years &amp; not before or otherwise.</p>
<p>My will is that if my son George do <sic corr="die">dye</sic> before he arrives at the <lb/>
age of one &amp; twenty years, so that the moiety or half part of my <lb/>
said Capitol Bank Stock, the moiety of my said Bank Annuity <lb/>
and the moiety or half of the said two thousand pounds with the <lb/>
interest arrising therefrom as aforesaid after the said two <lb/>
years are expired, ordered to be paid <del>to be paid</del> to my son George <lb/>
when he comes to the age of one &amp; twenty years as aforesaid he my <lb/>
said son George will have no right to, according to the intent <lb/>
of this my will that then that moiety or half part of my said <lb/>
Capitol Bank Stocks of said Bank Annuity and of my said two <lb/>
thousand pounds together with the interest that shall arrise <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add><lb/>
therefrom after the expiration of the aforesaid two years <lb/>
(ordered to be paid by my <add place="supralinear">said</add> executors to my said son George when <lb/>
he comes to the age of one &amp; twenty years) shall be also paid &amp; assign-  <lb/>
-ed over by my executors or the survivours of them unto my son Landon <lb/>
when he shall arrive to the age of one &amp; twenty years <del>years</del> &amp;  <lb/>
not before or otherwise.</p>

<p>Whereas that if my said sons Landon &amp; George <sic corr="die">dye</sic> before they arrive at their <lb/>
respective Ages of one &amp; twenty years so that in such case my said Bank <lb/>  <lb/>


<pb n="page (18)"/><lb/><lb/>

stocks my said Bank annuity &amp; my said two thousand pounds with <lb/>
the Interest arising therefrom as aforesaid according to the <lb/>
intent of this my Will will go and belong unto my three elder <lb/>
<add resp="editor"> [sons]</add> John Robert &amp; Charles my <abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> &amp; to the survivor or survivors<lb/>
of them it is in such case my will that when this <lb/>
contingency does happen if any of my three elder sons <lb/>
should be dead John, Robert or Charles having legitimate <lb/>
child or Children then alive that then such Child <lb/>
or Children have and e <add resp="editor"> [n]</add>joy his or their Father's part <lb/>
But it is my further Will that if my said three elder <lb/>
sons or their Children as aforesaid come to have <lb/>
and enjoy my aforesaid Bank stocks my aforesaid <lb/>
Bank Annuity &amp; my aforesaid two thousand pounds <lb/>
according to the intent of my will It shall be <lb/>
upon this condition that they my three elder sons,  <lb/>
John, Robert &amp; Charles &amp; the executors &amp; administrators of my said <lb/>
Sons, if either of my said sons should <sic corr="die">dye</sic> before <del>be</del>  <lb/>
<del>fore</del> the time shall be answerable for &amp; make <sic corr="payment">paiment</sic> <lb/>
of the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of Four hundred pounds sterling to each <lb/>
of my daughters that shall be then alive and if any <lb/>
of my daughters should <sic corr="die">dye</sic> leaving Child or Children <lb/>
the said Four hundred pounds designed for the Mother <lb/>
shall be paid to such Child or Children and this will <lb/>
be but an <sic corr="easy burden">easie burthen</sic> upon my said three Elder Sons <lb/>
when this large addition comes to their estates provided al-  <lb/>
<sic corr="-ways">-waies</sic> &amp; it is my will &amp; intent that my executors my sons <lb/>
John, Robert &amp; Charles or the survivors of them or the major <lb/>
part of them with the consent and approbation of my trustees and <lb/>
more especially with the consent of Mann Page Esq.. if he shall be then <lb/>
alive taking all prudent care for the security of these estates these Bank Stocks <lb/>
this Bank annuity &amp; this two thousand pounds and the interest thereof <lb/>
as aforesaid if any loss or lasses <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> do happen in any of these estates my <abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> <lb/>
shall not be answerable for any such loss or losses out of their own Estates.</p><lb/>


<pb n="page (19)"/><lb/><lb/>

<p>I give unto my son Landon, and to the heirs of his body &amp; for want of such <lb/>
issue unto my son George and the heirs of his body forever Smith Robins <lb/>
Girl Joan &amp; Nausaus two eldest Children (Bridget which was given <lb/>
away before excepted) and my will is that Landon be kept <lb/>
at school in his Education until he is seventeen years of age <lb/>
&amp; then be disposed of in such <add place="supralinear">a</add> manner as my executors his brothers <lb/>
shall judge most condusive to his future well being.  </p>

<p>I give unto my son George and to the heirs of his body &amp; for <lb/>
want of such issue unto my son Landon &amp; the heirs of his body <lb/>
forever my Negroe Boy Scipio &amp; the mulatto boy Talbert &amp; the <lb/>
girl Mary that is now in for a share at the old house &amp; her <lb/>
Children &amp; increase and it is my will that my son George be <lb/>
kept in Virginia &amp; that he be educated at the College of Wil-  <lb/>
-liam and Mary so long as my sons his brothers shall think <lb/>
fit to continue him there and then to be disposed of <add resp="editor"> [in]</add>  such <lb/>
manner as my executors his Brothers shall judge most <lb/>
conducive to his future well being.&mdash;</p>

<p>I give unto my said two sons Landon &amp; George and to the <lb/>
heirs male issue of their bodies lawfully begotten all my Estate <lb/>
both real and Personal in Williamsburg &amp; if both my sons <lb/>
<sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then to my son John &amp; his issue male <lb/>
And if my son John <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male then to my son Robert <lb/>
&amp; his issue male and if my son Robert <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male, then <lb/>
to my son Charles &amp; his issue male and in case of the Death of all sons with-  <lb/>
-out issue male then to go to my own right heirs forever. And I do here-  <lb/>
-by oblige my <del>my</del> son John to keep the said estate in good re-  <lb/>
-pair out of the profits of the said estate. My will is that the <lb/>
mortgage I have of Edmund Jennings <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> of <note target="n25">Rippon hall</note> in <lb/>
York County the Ten following negroes be placed upon the said plan-  <lb/>
-tations immediately after my decease (to wit) Tom at the <note n="IT">indian <lb/>
town</note> with his wife &amp; children, Sambo at <note n="CF">Changlings</note> with his wife <lb/>
&amp; child or Children Nick Read's Jos at <note n="CO">Co<add resp="editor">[ro]</add>toman</note>  &amp; his wife and Children if <lb/>
any a negroe Man &amp; his wife and Children if any from <note target="n26">Clough point</note> a negroe man <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (20)"/><lb/><lb/>

&amp; his wife &amp; Children if any from old plantation and also that there <lb/>
be bought five more chase <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> working slaves to be seated &amp; settled there-  <lb/>
-on, for the improvement of the said estate and that the stock of Cat-  <lb/>
-tle thereon be made up at least to sixty head for manuring <lb/>
the grounds and it is my will and meaning that the profits of these <lb/>
lands and slaves do go and belong to my two sons Landon &amp; George <lb/>
for and until my son George shall arrive to the age of twenty one <lb/>
years and that then it is my will that upon my son George's pay-  <lb/>
-ment of two hundred pounds Sterling to my son Landon that <lb/>
this estate Lands slaves and stocks, I do will and devise to <lb/>
my said son George the said mortgage Lands the said slaves <lb/>
&amp; stocks in the following manner (that is to say) to my son <lb/>
George &amp; the heirs male issue of his body and for want of such <lb/>
to my son Landon and to the heirs male issue of his Body &amp;  <lb/>
for want of such to my son John &amp; the heirs male issue of his Body <lb/>
&amp; for want of such to my son Robert &amp; the heirs male issue of <lb/>
his Body &amp; for want of such to my son Charles &amp; the heirs male issue of <lb/>
his Body and for want of such to my own right heirs forever.<add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add>  <lb/>
provided <sic corr="always">alwaies</sic> and it is my will and meaning that the num-  <lb/>
-ber of slaves appointed by this my will shall always be kept <lb/>
up to the number fifteen workers upon the said Lands <lb/>
and that the <sic corr="mortalities">mortalitys</sic> <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> shall still be <sic corr="supplied">supplyed</sic> out of <lb/>
the profits of the said estate until my said son George <lb/>
comes to the age of twenty one years And it is my will <lb/>
&amp; meaning that this mortgage of Rippon hall shall be taken <lb/>
and understood to be in payment of one thousand <add place="supralinear">pounds</add> Virgin-  <lb/>
-ia Debts given to my sons Landon &amp; George And my will <lb/>
is that the houses upon the said rippon Hall planta-  <lb/>
-tion be well repaired and kept in good repair <lb/>
out of the profits of the said estate that is the <lb/>
repairs to be immediately made by my son John <lb/>
&amp; he to be repaid out <del>out</del><lb/><lb/>

<pb n="page (21)"/><lb/><lb/>

of the profits of the said estate as they shall arise and my will <lb/>
is that the stock that is in Mr <note n="WD">Wm. Dawkins's </note>hands <abbr expan="merchant">Mercht.</abbr>  <lb/>
in London there be bought into it two hundred &amp; fifty <lb/>
pounds more than now it is by my executors in three years <lb/>
after my decease to belong to my said two younger sons <lb/>
Landon &amp; George in the same manner and under the <lb/>
same direction that my stocks given to my said two <del>sons</del>  <lb/>
younger sons are directed to be. </p>

<p>It is my will that there be a true full &amp; perfect Inventory made <lb/>
of all my estate as Slaves, Stocks, Goods Chattles moneys Debts &amp;  <lb/>
both in Virginia &amp; Great Brittain <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add>&amp; be recorded in the General <lb/>
Court &amp; that no valuation or appraisement be made of my <lb/>
estate &amp; that my <abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> named and appointed in this my <lb/>
will be not obliged to give security for my estate when they <lb/>
take probate of my will.</p>

<p>It is my will that the tobacco now to ship &amp; the crops both of <lb/>
corn &amp; Tobo. that shall be made this year shall <add resp="editor"> [be]</add> accounted as <lb/>
part of my estate &amp; shall be <abbr expan="shipped">ship'd</abbr> to Great Britain in <lb/>
such probation as my <abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> shall think <sic corr="fit">fitt</sic> &amp; to the Mer-  <lb/>
-chants that I at present deal with if <del>if</del> my <add resp="editor"> [executors]</add> have no reason <lb/>
to vary the consignments however leaving them at liberty <lb/>
to whom to consign, taking care to trust substantial Men <lb/>
and it is my will that the aforesaid Tobo. be <abbr expan="shipped">ship'd</abbr> in the <lb/>
name of my executors And it is my will that the Crops of all <lb/>
my slaves both of Tobacco and Corn that shall be made in <lb/>
the next two succeeding years that is in one thousand seven hun-  <lb/>
-dred &amp; twenty seven &amp; one thousand seven hundred and twenty <lb/>
eight &amp; when my son Charles will come to age shall be <lb/>
held deemed &amp; taken as my estate &amp; the Crops of Tobacco to <lb/>
be shiped <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add>in the name of my 
09:49 12/4/2002
executors as aforesaid and the produce <lb/>
thereof to be accounted for to my estate for and towards the discharge of <lb/>
my debts Legacies &amp; other incumbrances of this my will provided al-  <lb/>
-ways there be allowed out of the produce of the said two years Crops two <lb/>
hundred pounds sterling a piece per <abbr expan="annum">Ann:</abbr> to each of my three eldest sons for their <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (22)"/><lb/><lb/>

maintenance likewise that the family have suitable <sic corr="supplies">supplys</sic> for their <lb/>
maintenance for the said two years &amp; the contingent charges of the <lb/>
said estate to be <sic corr="bourne">born</sic> &amp; that my younger Children also have <lb/>
a <sic corr="decent">descent</sic> maintenance and it is my will that the money <lb/>
that is and shall be raised in Britain by the profits of my <lb/>
plantations or by any other <sic corr="ways">waies</sic> than what will answer <lb/>
my Debts Legacies Bequests &amp; orders made in this my will <lb/>
be divided into three equal parts my two younger sons <lb/>
Robert and Charles to have a thousand pounds more <lb/>
apiece than my son John towards building &amp; Settling their <lb/>
plantations And whereas several of my legacies are made <lb/>
payable at some distance of time &amp; some of them upon <lb/>
such Contingencies which perhaps may never happen It <lb/>
is my will that upon the division of the money that shall <lb/>
belong to my estate as aforesaid that my three elder sons <lb/>
&amp;  <abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> enter into reciprocal Bonds to one and the other <lb/>
to be answerable in proportion for the respective Legacies <lb/>
and bequests in this my Will when they shall become due &amp; payable.&mdash;</p>

<p>It is my will that the charge maintenance &amp; education of <lb/>
my two youngest sons Landon &amp; George <sic corr="according">acording</sic> to the direc-  <lb/>
-tion &amp; intention of this my will shall be equally <sic corr="bourne">born</sic> <lb/>
by my three eldest sons John Robert &amp; Charles, out of <lb/>
the profits of their estate, during their minority.</p>

<p>It is my will that if my <note n="JCP">daughter Page</note> shall be alive on <lb/>
the Tenth day of May In the year seventeen hundred and <lb/>
twenty nine that then there be paid to her my said Daughter <lb/>
Page the sume of three hundred pounds sterling by my <lb/>
three eldest sons my <abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> out of the estates &amp; profits there-  <lb/>
-of I have given them And it is my further Will that my <lb/>
<abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> shall pay to my Grandson Mann Page when he <lb/>
arrives to the age of twenty one years the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of <lb/>
three hundred pounds Sterling and it is my further Will <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (23)"/><lb/><lb/>

that my executors shall pay to my Grandson Carter Page when he <lb/>
arrives at the age of Twenty one years the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of three hundred <lb/>
pounds sterling and my further Will is that my Executors <lb/>
shall pay to my Grandson John Page when he arrives at <lb/>
the age of twenty one years the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of three hundred <lb/>
pounds Sterling And my Will is that if one of my said <lb/>
grandsons should <sic corr="die">dye</sic> before he comes to said age of Twenty <lb/>
one years the whole nine hundred pounds shall be paid <lb/>
to the two surviving Brothers when they arrive at the said <lb/>
age of twenty one years And if two of my said Grandsons <lb/>
should <sic corr="die">dye</sic> before they arrive to their respective ages <lb/>
of twenty one years then the nine hundred pounds shall <lb/>
be paid to the last surviving Brother when he shall  <lb/>
arrive at the age of twenty one years.  </p>

<p>It is my further will that if the large brick house now building by <lb/>
<note n="MP1"><abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Page</note> in the room of the house that was unfortunately con-  <lb/>
-sumed by fire shall be <sic corr="finished">finisht.</sic> and completed during <lb/>
the life time of my said Daughter Page so that she shall <lb/>
come to enjoy it &amp; to have her Tithe of Dower in it then it <lb/>
is my Will and I do lay it as a charge upon my three eldest <lb/>
sons John Robert and Charles my executors out of the profits of <lb/>
the estates I have hereby given to them the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of one<lb/>
hundred pounds one hundred pounds <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> apiece to be paid <lb/>
to my son in Law Mann Page <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> if he be then alive,<lb/>
or else to my Daughter his now Wife towards furnishing <lb/>
the said house. It is my Will that if <add resp="editor"> [my]</add> <note n="ECB">Daughter Elizabeth</note> <lb/>
the wife of Doctor <abbr expan="George">Geo</abbr> Nicholas shall be alive on the <lb/>
tenth day of May seventeen hundred and twenty nine <lb/>
that then there be paid to my said Daughter Elizabeth the  <sic corr="sum">sume</sic><lb/>
of three hundred pounds sterling by my Executors And I do also <lb/>
give to my said Daughter a pair of Diamond Ear rings to cost <lb/>
fifty pounds sterling, to be bought by such person as she shall <lb/>
desire the money to be paid by <add resp="editor"> [my]</add> Executors And it is my Will that<lb/><lb/>

<pb n="page (24)"/><lb/><lb/>

when her eldest Son she hath by her <add place="supralinear">said</add> husband shall come to the age <lb/>
of Twenty one years that there shall be paid to him by my <lb/>
<abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> one hundred pounds Sterling and when her youngest <lb/>
son she hath by her said husband shall come to the age <lb/>
of twenty one years that there shall be paid to him by my <lb/>
<abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> one hundred pounds sterling and if either of them <lb/>
<sic corr="die">dye</sic> the whole  to be paid to the Survivor. </p>

<p>It is my Will then <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> when my Grandson Lewis Burwell arrives <lb/>
to the age of twenty five <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> years there shall be paid to him by <lb/>
my Executors the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of three hundred pounds Sterling and <lb/>
it is also my Will that my Executors shall pay to my Grandson <lb/>
Carter Burwell when he arrives at the age of twenty one <lb/>
years the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of three hundred pounds Sterling and it is <lb/>
also my Will that my Executors shall pay to my Grandson <lb/>
<abbr expan="Robert">Robt.</abbr> Burwell when he arrives to the age of twenty one <lb/>
years the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of three hundred pounds Sterling and it <lb/>
is my Will that if either of my three Grandsons should <sic corr="die">dye</sic> <lb/>
before they come to the aforesaid ages in this my Will that <lb/>
the whole nine hundred pounds shall be paid to <lb/>
the two surviving Brothers when they arrive to their respec-  <lb/>
-tive ages by this my Will And if two of my said Grandsons <lb/>
should <sic corr="die">dye</sic> before they come to the ages aforesaid then the <lb/>
said nine hundred pounds shall be paid to the last <lb/>
surviving Brother when he comes to the age aforesaid in <lb/>
this my said Will And it is my Will that there shall be <lb/>
paid by my Executors to my Grandaughter Elizabeth Burwell <lb/>
the sum of three hundred pounds Sterling when she shall <lb/>
arrive at the age of twenty one years.&mdash;&mdash;</p>

<p>I give unto my son John all my furniture in the new <lb/>
house and half of the rest of the Furniture in my Kitchen &amp; other <lb/>
houses about my mansion Dwelling the other half of my Furniture <lb/>
I do give unto my sons Robert &amp; Charles to be <lb/>
valued by four of the most substantial of my neighbours <lb/><lb/>

<pb n="page (25)"/><lb/><lb/>

and my son John to pay for them to my said Sons Robert &amp; Charles ac-  <lb/>
-cording to the valuation unless it be the desire of my sons <lb/>
Robert &amp; Charles to have them in kind.</p>

<p>My Will is that my plate both old &amp; new be equally divided be-  <lb/>
-tween my three elder Sons John Robert &amp; Charles my books to <lb/>
be divided into four parts, my son John to have two parts <lb/>
of them my sons Robert &amp; Charles to have the other two parts <lb/>
my pictures each Child to have his own picture my son <add resp="editor"> [John]</add><lb/>
to have my first picture and his mothers also my gold watch <lb/>
and diamond ring my Son Robert to have my other picture &amp; his <lb/>
mothers picture &amp; one half of my other rings &amp; watches my son Charles <lb/>
to have the other half my sons Robert and Charles to have each of <lb/>
them a gold watch sent for at the Charge of my estate to cost <lb/>
to cost <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> thirty pounds each all my Goods that are coming in for <lb/>
my <sic corr="families">familys</sic> to be disposed of among the <sic corr="families">Familys</sic> for their Sup-  <lb/>
-ply as they were intended all my new Goods Tools nails <lb/>
utensils &amp; not already disposed of to belong to my said three <lb/>
sons, John Robert and Charles to be equally divided between them <lb/>
or appraised and the Value answered to my <add place="supralinear">two</add> younger <lb/>
sons as my Executors shall agree</p>

<p>My Will is that thirty mourning rings be sent for to be distri-  <lb/>
-buted by my <abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> among my friends and relations and it <lb/>
is my will that all the rest of my estate personal or real <lb/>
not herein disposed of in Virginia or elsewhere do belong &amp; I do <lb/>
give it unto my said three eldest sons John Robert and Charles <lb/>
and their heirs forever. </p>

<p>It is my Will that in regard those negroes which went from Middlesex <lb/>
are now seated and settled upon my son John's plantation called <lb/>
<note n="PE">pewmonds End</note> in Essex which slaves notwithstanding I have given <lb/>
unto my son Robert It is my Will and desire that my son John <lb/>
let my son Robert have other slaves of their Value either new <lb/>
or old &amp; that after such Change made to the satis-  <lb/>
faction of both my said sons <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;such<lb/><lb/>

<pb n="page (26)"/><lb/><lb/>

such slaves be then deemed &amp; taken to be within the perview <lb/>
of the intails aforesaid of my respective sons slave &amp; real estates.  </p>

<p>I give my wearing apparel &amp; Cloths the best of them and what are <lb/>
coming in for my own wearing &amp; my <sic corr="wigs,">wiggs,</sic> swords canes pistols <lb/>
&amp;<add resp="editor"> [c]</add> to be divided among my three elder sons &amp; my other Cloths I <lb/>
would have given to my good friends <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> <note target="n28">Thomas Carter </note><lb/>
&amp; Mr John Turbervile.&mdash;&mdash; </p>

<p>I give unto my Son in Law <abbr expan="Colonel">Collo.</abbr> Mann Page twenty pounds <lb/>
Sterling to buy him mourning also <abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> <abbr expan="Benjamin">Benja.</abbr> Harrison <lb/>
Twenty pounds for the same use And to Doctor George Nicholas <lb/>
Ten pounds for the same use And I do order all my Children <lb/>
<add place="supralinear">&amp; Grand Children</add> to go into decent mourning at the Charge of my estate.  </p>

<p>It is my Will that what selling Goods I have coming in this <lb/>
shipping when they arrive shall be delivered to <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Thomas <lb/>
Carter to be by him sold &amp; disposed of together with the <lb/>
Goods already under his care for good tobacco and money <lb/>
or Bills of exchange to be accounted for as also all the <lb/>
Tobaccos &amp; Debts due in the said Carters hands upon <lb/>
the sales of Goods already sold out of the said Store <lb/>
unto my said three eldest sons equally or the <lb/>
survivors of them.</p>

<p>It is my Will that my son John have &amp; enjoy the <lb/>
Lease I have lately taken &amp; am now in possession of <lb/>
the northern neck from <del>from</del> the proprietors &amp; he to <lb/>
have and receive in his own right the profits of <lb/>
the same and the management thereof and that my <lb/>
son John out of his own estate do pay the yearly <lb/>
rents for the said Lease that I stand engaged for <lb/>
to the said proprietors, It is my request to my son <lb/>
John that he release to his brothers Robert &amp;  <lb/>
Charles the rents of their Lands during the <lb/>
term of the said Lease.&mdash;<lb/></p>

<pb n="page (27)"/><lb/><lb/>

<p>I do name constitute and appoint my three elder sons John,  <lb/>
Robert &amp; Charles to be Executors of this my will and to be guar-  <lb/>
dians of my younger Children &amp; their estates and I do re-  <lb/>
quest constitute and appoint &amp; make my honorable &amp; good <lb/>
friends &amp; relations the aforesaid Mann Page <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> of Gloces-  <lb/>
-ter County <abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> <abbr expan="Benjamin">Benja.</abbr> Harrison of Charles City County <lb/>
<abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> <note n="GE"><abbr expan="George">Geo.</abbr> Eskridge </note>&amp; <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> <note n="GT"><abbr expan="George">Geo.</abbr> Turbervile</note> of We <add resp="editor"> [s]</add>moreland <lb/>
County Mr. <note n="RL">Richard Lee</note> of Northumberland County &amp;  <lb/>
<abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Thomas Carter of Lancaster County to be Assist-  <lb/>
-ant to my Executors &amp; to be my trustees to see this my Will <lb/>
performed &amp; to be consulted and advised with upon all <lb/>
emergent occasions more especially the said Mann Page <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> </p>

<p>It is my Will and I do ordain that whenever the Vestry of <lb/>
Christ Church Parish shall undertake to build a <lb/>
brick Church in the place where the present Church <lb/>
stands that there be paid out of my estate by my <lb/>
three elder sons <add place="supralinear"> &amp; </add> Executors the sum of two hundred pounds <lb/>
sterling money one half part of this money is to be paid <lb/>
out of my son John's estate the other half is to be equal-  <lb/>
-ly paid by my son Robert &amp; my son Charles out of <lb/>
their part of my estate this money to remain in my <lb/>
Executors hands until one half <del>one half</del> of the work is <lb/>
<sic corr="completed">compleated</sic> provided <sic corr="always">alwaies</sic> the <hi rend="underline">Chancel</hi> be preserved <lb/>
as a burial place place <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> for my family as the present <lb/>
Chancel is, and that there be preserved to my family a <lb/>
commodious pew in the new Chancel and it is my <lb/>
further Will that the bricks that are now made &amp; bu<add resp="editor"> [r]</add>nt shall be <lb/>
appropriated to the Building of the said BrickChurch <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> or as many <lb/>
thereof as will perfect the building and likewise the bricks that <lb/>
shall be made and be there at my decease and if my Son <lb/>
John shall have occasion to make use of any of the said <lb/>
bricks then he be obliged to make &amp; burn as many more for the use afore <lb/>
said. I give twenty pounds Sterling to be laid out in a piece of plate for the <lb/>
use of our Church to be sent for and engraved according <lb/><lb/>

<pb n="page (28)"/><lb/><lb/>

to the direction of my son John.</p>

<p>My Will is that my white servants that are about my house <lb/>
that are not tradesmen be divided amongst my three sons <lb/>
John, Robert and Charles &amp; those that are tradesmen to be-  <lb/>
-long to my said three sons and to be made use of as they <lb/>
shall agree, in their respective trades and that the white <lb/>
Servants that are abroad seated upon my plantations <lb/>
belong to such of my said sons as the plantations are given to.  </p>

<p>I give unto my son John, my Coach and four Coach horses also <lb/>
my barge &amp; furniture, my own riding horse, my Chariot &amp;<add resp="editor">[c.]</add>  my <lb/>
other two Coach horses my Will is my son Robert shall have <lb/>
when he removes to live on his own Lands <add resp="editor"> [.]</add> my two youngest <lb/>
daughters to have each of them a riding horse &amp; side <lb/>
saddle provided for them out of my estate and that <lb/>
my sons Landon &amp; George have found for them Constant-  <lb/>
-ly a good riding horse &amp; saddle out of my estate until <lb/>
they come to their respective ages of twenty one years.</p>

<p>My Will is that my son John have four of my best Cart <lb/>
horses &amp; tht. all the rest of my horses &amp; mares be equally di-  <lb/>
vided between my three sons John Robert &amp; Charles.</p>

<p>Whereas there are sundry debts &amp; ballances due to me from <lb/>
some of my friends &amp; poor neighbours to whom I have a <lb/>
mind to be kind I do therefore ordain as followeth &amp;  <lb/>
give the following directions that Robert Gordon be discharg-  <lb/>
-ed of his whole debt he paying ten pounds Sterling to my <lb/>
Executors that <note target="n29">John Hutchins</note> be discharged of his whole debt <lb/>
he paying ten pounds sterling to my Executors. <abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr>  <lb/>
<abbr expan="George">Geo.</abbr> Eskridge's Debt upon obligations &amp; all other <lb/>
accounts between us he having lately paid me <lb/>
a bill of Exchange of seventy pounds it is my <lb/>
Will that all accounts <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (29)"/><lb/><lb/>

for his <sic corr="quit">Quitt</sic> Rents &amp; stand ballances between us the <lb/>
debt he has of mine in his hands upon account of sales <lb/>
of negroes out of the ship <note target="n30"><name type="ship">Mercury</name></note> he stands answera-  <lb/>
-ble for, Mr. <note n="RL"><abbr expan="Richard">Richd.</abbr> Lee's</note> obligation I remitt.</p>

<p>Whereas <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Thomas Carter hath gone through a series <lb/>
of Business for me for several years together in selling <lb/>
<sic corr="diverse">divers</sic> cargoes of Goods and upon other accounts of <lb/>
whose honesty &amp; integrity I have always had a very <lb/>
good opinion It is my Will that such accounts of my <lb/>
afairs <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> as he can make up be received as satisfac-  <lb/>
-tory from him by my Executors and that he be to no <lb/>
trouble at law upon my account. </p>

<p>That Whereas in this my Will I have given the lands I <lb/>
bought of Mr. Robert Cary which cost me above Two thou-  <lb/>
-sand pounds Sterling to my sons John &amp; Robert it is my <lb/>
Will that they my said sons John &amp; Robert do pay unto <lb/>
my estate some time within five years after my <lb/>
decease each of them the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of five hundred <lb/>
pounds out of their own estates to be accounted as <lb/>
part of my estate to go towards the discharge of <lb/>
my legacies &amp; incumbrances of this my Will. </p>

<p>Whereas I have paid for my son John several <sic corr="sums">sumes</sic> of money <lb/>
amounting to between twelve &amp; fourteen hundred pounds in <lb/>
discharge of <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> <note target="n31">Edward Hills</note> debts &amp; Legacies for the securi-  <lb/>
-ty of the <sic corr="repayment">repaiment</sic> of part of the said money my said son John <lb/>
hath mortgages certain negroes and for the payment of the rest <lb/>
hath given me Bond and is obliged to pay me Interest for all <lb/>
the said money until repayment thereof It is my Will that  <lb/>
in Lieu and satisfaction of this money due to me upon my <lb/>
said sons mortgage &amp; Bond that he my said son his Executors or <lb/>
administrators shall repay unto my estate the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of eight hundred pounds <lb/>
Sterling of the said money to be accounted as part of my estate &amp; to go <lb/>
towards the discharging my Legacys &amp; incumbrances of this <lb/>
my Will and that my executors my sons <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (30)"/><lb/><lb/>

Robert &amp; Charles have power to recover this said  <lb/>
of eight hundred pounds sterling from my said son John his <lb/>
Executors and <abbr expan="administrators">admors</abbr> under their Quality of their being my <abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr>.  </p>

<p>Whereas I have given power to Mr <note n="MP2">Micajah Perry</note> of <abbr expan="London">Londo.</abbr>  <lb/>
Merchant to purchase for me the whole estate of John L.  <lb/>
Boyd <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> deceased lying in Richmond &amp; Westmoreland <lb/>
Counties the lands the negroes &amp; the stocks &amp; to give for the <lb/>
same four thousand pounds Sterling Now if the said <lb/>
Perry should make the said purchase which must <lb/>
come out of the Estate of my three sons John Robert <lb/>
and Charles <del> &amp; to be</del> <add place="supralinear">in case of my Death it is therefore my will and I do desire the said estate in common between my said two</add>  <lb/>
<add place="supralinear">sons Robert and Charles </add> &amp; to be divided equally between them <lb/>
as they shall agree upon division each son to hold his <lb/>
part both of Land &amp; slaves to him &amp; his heirs Male of <lb/>
his Body lawfully begotten and so to be continued in Tail <lb/>
Male as the rest of my said respective Sons Lands are to go <lb/>
(excepting the Lands I bought of Mr Cary) which are under <lb/>
a diferent <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> devise in respect of the remainders And where-  <lb/>
-as the <sic corr="entail">intail</sic> of the lands bought of Mr. Cary is carried <lb/>
<sic corr="down">dound</sic> no further than to the issue male <del>of male</del> of my <lb/>
son Charles my further Will is that in case of failure <lb/>of issue male of my <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> son Charles that then these <lb/>
lands bought of Mr Cary do go to my son Landon &amp; to <lb/>
the heirs male issue of his body &amp; for want of such to <lb/>
my son George &amp; the heirs male issue of his Body &amp; for <lb/>
want of such to my right heirs forever.</p>

<p>Whereas in the former part of <add place="supralinear">this</add> my Will <lb/>
I have given <add place="supralinear">to</add> my son John Ten thousand acres <lb/>
of Land upon the branches of Occaquan binding <lb/>
upon the Germans conveyed to me by deed from <lb/>
<abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Geo Turbervile which said tract of Land I have <lb/>
								
<pb n="page (31)"/><lb/><lb/>

intailed upon my said son John and his male issue <lb/>
I do now <sic corr="revoke">revoak</sic> that part of my said Will and do <lb/>
give the said tract of Land conveyed to me as <lb/>
aforesaid unto my son John and his heirs forever <lb/>
in Fee Simple desiring him to give Two thousand <lb/>
acres <add place="supralinear">out of the said tract unto my Grand son <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> Robert Burwell and two Thousand</add> unto my Grandson John Page out of such <lb/>
parts of the Land as he my said son John shall <lb/>
think <sic corr="fit.">fitt.</sic></p>

<p>Whereas I am now in possession of the Negroes &amp; personal <lb/>
estate of <note target="n33">Thomas Glascock</note> which was forfeited to me as <lb/>
the proprietors Agent upon the conviction of the said <lb/>
Thomas Glascock for murder these negroes and per-  <lb/>
-sonal estate I give to my son John &amp; his heirs desiring <lb/>
him to be kind to the Children of the said Glascock <lb/>
such of them as he shall think deserves it in some <lb/>
proportion to the value of the estate as whereas there <lb/>
is an outlawry prosecuting at the General Court in <lb/>
order to attaint the said Glasc<add resp="editor">[oc]</add>k  that his lands may <lb/>
be escheated which are also now in my possession my <lb/>
Will is that if my son John comes to enjoy the said <lb/>
Glascocks Lands under a good title that then he fur-  <lb/>
-ther consider the said Glascocks Children in such <lb/>
proportion as he shall think fitt or otherwise <sic corr="gratify">gratifie </sic><lb/>
them according to his discretion.</p>

<p>That whereas in the second item in the eighth sheet <lb/>
in this my Will I have directed tht Merchants hundred <lb/>
plantation with the slaves and Stocks to be held &amp; enjoyed  <lb/>
by my daughter <note n="ECB">Elizabeth</note> for and during the term of <lb/>
her natural life my intent &amp; meaning is <add place="supralinear">that</add> my Stocks <lb/>
of Cattle &amp; hoggs &amp; other personal Goods belonging to the <lb/>
said plantation be only lent to my said daughter Eli-  <lb/>
zabeth during her life and no property Vested in <lb/>
her, and she my said daughter to enjoy the profits of  <lb/>

<pb n="page (32)"/><lb/><lb/>

of the said stocks still keeping up the number that they shall <lb/>
be at the time of my decease And my Will and meaning is the <lb/>
same in respect of the other settlements I have made to my <lb/>
daughter<add resp="editor">[s]</add> Page &amp; Harrison.</p>

<p>It is my will that forty pounds worth of Coarse good be <lb/>
sent for and to be distributed amongst the poor necessitous <lb/>
people of the parish I live <add resp="editor">[in]</add> at the discretion of my executors.</p>

<p>It is my Will and I do give to Mr. <note n="JB4">John Bell</note> our minister <lb/>
Ten pounds sterling for mourning.</p>

<p>It is my Will and I do give to my several friends my Trustees <lb/>
in this my <add resp="editor"> [Will]</add> Ten pounds sterling a piece as an acknowledge-  <lb/>
-ment for the trouble they will be at.</p>

<p>I do hereby revoke all other and former Wills &amp; testaments heretofore by <lb/>
me made &amp; do publish utter &amp; declare this to be my last will &amp; testament.  <lb/>
In Witness whereof I have hereunto set my hand &amp; seal this twenty <lb/>
second day of August one thousand seven hundred &amp; twenty six.</p>

<p>NB the words in the Twelfth sheet, of this my Will (or the ma-  <lb/>
-jor part of them or the survivors of them) &amp; the Words (to be <lb/>
paid by my son John) and in the seventeenth sheet the <lb/>
Words (so long as my sons his Brothers shall think fitt to <lb/>
continue <add place="supralinear">him</add> there) interlined before signed.  <lb/>

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<hi rend="bold">Robert Carter</hi> (LS) <lb/>

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Signed sealed &amp; published in <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;presence of us<lb/><lb/>

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<note target="n34">John Turbervile</note> <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;1726 <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<note n="RL"><abbr expan="Richard">Rd.</abbr> Lee </note><lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<note target="n35">Thomas Edwards</note> <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<note target="n36">John Harvey</note> <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Solomon Aashead <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;I the aforesaid Robert Carter <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;being of sound mind and <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;memory.&mdash;&mdash;</p>

<pb n="page (33)"/><lb/><lb/>

<p><add resp="editor">[First Codicil, 1726 October 1]</add></p>

<p>Twenty Eighth sheet of my Will.  </p>

<p>I do this day make this my further addition &amp; alteration in my <lb/>
aforegoing Will dated the twenty second day of August last to make <lb/>
my son Robert equal to his other Brothers in number of slaves I <lb/>
do give unto my said son Robert and the heirs male issue of his body <lb/>
lawfully begotten under the same limitation as the rest of the <lb/>
negroes are given the following slaves (to Wit) all those slaves Men <lb/>
Women and Children that I bought and purchased of Mr  John Pratt <lb/>
which were brought home to my house also the negroe called Harry Bacon <lb/>
and the negroe Boy called Sam both which run away from my <note n="NH2">Nomini</note> <lb/>
plantation likewise four good Negroes out of these I have given to my son <lb/>
Charles two young men &amp; two young women also as many more slaves <lb/>
out of these I have given to my son John half Males &amp; half Females not to be  <lb/>
under the age of twelve years as will make up the number I have given to <lb/>
him my said son Robert one hundred working slaves above the age of twelve years.</p>

<p>My will and meaning is that my Negroe Harry one of Georges sons <lb/>
shall be deemed to belong to my son Charles he now <del>he now</del> living at <lb/>
my falls plantation.</p>

<p>Whereas I have ordered <add place="supralinear">a</add> Quarter to be seated upon the Land I lately <lb/>
bought of Mr Cary with Ten or twelve slaves from my Westmoreland <lb/>
plantations which Quarter will belong to my son John by this my Will It <lb/>
is notwithstanding my Will &amp; intent that these slaves as many of them as <lb/>
shall be seated on the said new plantation at the time of my <lb/>
Death shall be held and taken to belong to my  said son Roberts <lb/>
number of slaves</p>

<p>In Witness that this is a part of my will &amp; to be construed as <lb/>
such I have hereunto set my hand and seal this eleventh day <lb/>
of October one thousand seven hundred and twenty six.;&mdash;  <lb/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;	<hi rend="bold">Robert Carter </hi>(L.S.)  <lb/>
Signed sealed &amp; published in presence <lb/>
of <note n="RL"><abbr expan="Richard">Rd</abbr> Lee</note> <lb/>
John Harvey <lb/>
L Austin &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Twenty ninth sheet of my will.  <lb/>
Solomon Ashead </p>

<pb n="(34)"/><lb/><lb/>
<p><add resp="editor">[Second Codicil, 1728 September 12 ]</add></p>


<p>In the name of God Amen I Robert Carter <lb/>
aforesaid since the making of my abovesaid Will consisting of twenty <lb/>
nine sheets of paper having undergone several Changes and altera-  <lb/>
-tions in my circumstances in relation to my temporal Estate <lb/>
and for as much as by a late Act of Assembly made since the <lb/>
making of my said Will to explain &amp; amend the act declar-  <lb/>
-ing the negro mulatto &amp; Indian slaves within this Dominion <lb/>
great alterations are made in the said act making negroes <lb/>
a real estate under the consideration of which former Act <lb/>
of Assembly I made my said Will being &amp; continuing to this <lb/>
day thro' the mercy of God of sound mind &amp; memory do <lb/>
make the following additions alterations <sic corr="revocations">Revokations</sic> <lb/>
&amp; declarations in &amp; concerning my said Will as aforesaid.&mdash;  </p>

<p>Whereas I have entailed upon my three eldest sons John <lb/>
Robert &amp; Charles all my slaves belonging to my several <lb/>
plantations in Virginia with several remainders over <lb/>
which under the former Law I had power to do <lb/>
giving all my said slaves in such Words unto my said <lb/>
three sons as will give the property in all my said <lb/>
slaves according to the interpretations &amp; meaning <lb/>
of the said <note target="n37">late Law</note> which was never my purpose <lb/>
or intent to do. I do hereby utterly <sic corr="revoke">revoak</sic> all those <lb/>
gifts to my said three sons John Robert &amp; Charles here-  <lb/>
-by declaring it is my full intent &amp; meaning that no <lb/>
property shall be vested in any of my said three <lb/>
sons to any of my said slaves and I do hereby de-  <lb/>
-clare that it is my intent &amp; meaning that my said <lb/>
three sons shall have only the use and profits of <lb/>
my said slaves &amp; their increase for during and Continu-  <lb/>
-ing their respective natural lives the said slaves and their <lb/>
increase however to be annexed to my respective Lands and planta-  <lb/>
-tions for the improvements of my said several plantations &amp;  <lb/>
Lands according to the directions of my said Will.  </p>

<pb n="page (35)"/><lb/><lb/>

<p>It is my will that my several slaves that are to be annexed <lb/>
according to the intent of my will to the lands and plantations <lb/>
where I live which I hold as tenant in tail under the will <lb/>
of <note n="JC">my Father</note> &amp; also all the slaves which <del>which</del> are to be <lb/>
annexed to all the rest of the lands &amp; plantations which I <lb/>
have given to my said son John in Tail the property in <lb/>
all my said slave &amp; their increase lent to my said son <lb/>
John as aforesaid I give unto my <note target="n38">Grandson John</note> my said <lb/>
son John's son however to be annexed both <del>to</del> all the said <lb/>
slaves and their increase unto the Lands &amp; plantations <lb/>
that are intailed upon my said son John &amp; to continue <lb/>
annexed &amp; to go with the Lands according to the intent <lb/>
&amp; meaning of my said Will.&mdash;  </p>

<p>It is my will that my several slaves that are to be annexed <lb/>
according to the intent of my said Will to the Lands &amp; planta-  <lb/>
tions which I have given to my son <note n="RC2">Robert</note> in Tail the property <lb/>
in all my said slaves &amp; their increase lent to my said son <lb/>
Robert as aforesaid I give unto my <note target="n39">Grandson Robert</note> my <lb/>
said son Robert's son however to be annexed both all the <lb/>
said slave &amp; their increase unto the Lands &amp; plantations <lb/>
that are in tailed upon my said son Robert and to Contin-  <lb/>
ue annexed <add place="supralinear">&amp;</add> to go with the Lands accord <add resp="editor"> [ng]</add> g to the intent &amp;  <lb/>
meaning of my said Will.... </p>

<p>p>It is my will that my several slaves that are to be annexed <lb/>
according to the intent of my said Will to the Lands &amp; plantations <lb/>
which I have given to my son Charles in Tail the property in<lb/>
all my said slaves and their increase lent to my said son Charles as <lb/>
aforesaid I do give unto my said son Charles, in trust to be by him <lb/>
conveyed and made over unto the heirs male of my said son <lb/>
Charles and to be continued annexed to the said <del>said</del> lands <lb/>
entailed upon my said son Charles as aforesaid. </p>

<p>That Whereas I have bought sundry tracts of Land for my three mar-  <lb/>
-ried daughters And have bought sundry slaves for the improving <lb/>
and working the said Lands which they are annexed unto <lb/><lb/>

<pb n="page (36)"/><lb/><lb/>

And whereas in the disposition of the said slaves I have used the <lb/>
words [I give the said slaves unto my said Daughters respectively <lb/>
for and during their natural lives or to this purpose] I do <lb/>
<sic corr="revoke">revoak</sic>e the said Clauses and do only give the profits of the said <lb/>
slaves &amp; their increase unto my said three Daughters for and <lb/>
during their natural lives under the conditions aforesaid And <lb/>
it is my further Will that <note n="MP1">Mann Page</note> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> do enjoy the pro-  <lb/>
-fits of the lands &amp; negroes settled upon his Wife for and du-  <lb/>
-ring the term of his natural life according to the intenti-  <lb/>
-on of my afore said <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> Will under the conditions mentioned as <lb/>
afore<abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr> And it is my further Will that <abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> <note n="BH1">Benjamin Har-  <lb/>
-rison</note> do enjoy the profits of the lands &amp; negroes settled upon <lb/>
his Wife for and during the term of his natural life accord-  <lb/>
-ing to the the intention of my aforesaid Will under the Conditi-  <lb/>
-ons mentioned as aforesaid And I do give the property of the <lb/>
said slave &amp; their increase unto my said Daughter's sons <lb/>
&amp; the heirs of their Bodies to continue annexed to the said <lb/>
lands and to go &amp; descend according to the intent of my said Will.</p>

<p>And Whereas at the making of my said Will I had only <add place="supralinear">a</add> mort-  <lb/>
-gage of Rippon Hall in York County &amp; the lands thereto belonging <lb/>
upon the forfeiture whereof by the Judgement of the General <lb/>
Court in Chancery the redemption of the said estate hath <lb/>
been since foreclosed and I am now <sic corr="seized">seised</sic> in the said estate <lb/>
as of an inheritance in fee simple &amp; have also seated the <lb/>
said Estate <add place="supralinear">with</add> fourteen slaves It is my will that the profits <lb/>
of the said estate and slaves do go and belong to my two <lb/>
sons Landon &amp; George until my said son George arrives <lb/>
to the age of twenty one years that then the said <add place="supralinear">slaves</add>  <lb/>
&amp; their increase to belong to my said son George <lb/>
he paying to my son Landon the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of one <lb/>
hundred &amp; fifty pounds sterling And I do hereby <lb/>
give and devise unto my son George the said estate of Rippon Hall <lb/><lb/>

<pb n="page (37)"/><lb/><lb/>

with the lands &amp; appurtenances thereunto belonging to him &amp;  the <lb/>
heirs of his body lawfully begotten &amp; for want of such to my <lb/>
son Landon &amp; the heirs of his body lawfully begotten &amp; for <lb/>
want of such to my son John &amp; the heirs of his body lawfully <lb/>
begotten &amp; for want of such to my son Robert &amp; the heirs of <lb/>
his body lawfully begotten &amp; for want of such to my son Charles <lb/>
&amp; the heirs <del>heirs</del> of his body lawfully begotten &amp; for want of <lb/>
such to my right heirs forever.</p>

<p>And Whereas I have given my estate in Williamsburg to  <lb/>
my two sons Landon &amp; George It is now my Will &amp; I do here-  <lb/>
-by devise unto my said son George all my said estate in <lb/>
<abbr expan="Williamsburg">Wms.burg</abbr> to him &amp; the heirs of his body lawfully begotten &amp;  <lb/>
for want of such to my son Landon &amp; the heirs of his body <lb/>
lawfully begotten and for want of such to my son John <lb/>
&amp; the heirs of his body lawfully begotten &amp; for want of such <lb/>
to my son <abbr expan="Robert">Robt.</abbr> &amp; the heirs of his body lawfully begotten <lb/>
&amp; for want of such to my son Charles &amp; the heirs of his <lb/>
body lawfully begotten &amp; for want of such to my right <lb/>
heirs forever.&mdash; </p>

<p>And whereas in my said Will I have given to my two sons Landon <lb/>
&amp; George my bank annuity of Fifteen hundred pounds which <lb/>
hath since been paid into the hands of <note n="MP2">Micajah Perry</note> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr>  <lb/>
It is my Will that this Fifteen hundred pounds be paid to my <lb/>
said son Landon when he shall come to <add place="supralinear">the</add> age of twenty one <lb/>
years in three equal yearly payments in the following <lb/>
manner <note target="n40">Viz.</note> the first payment to be made the first <lb/>
shipping after my said <add resp="editor"> [son]</add> Landon arrives at his age of <lb/>
twenty one the second payment the shipping after that &amp; the <lb/>
third payment to be made the shipping after that &amp; that <lb/>
he also have one moiety of my bank stocks in the hands <lb/>
of the said Perry &amp; Mr. <note n="WD">William Dawkins</note> the other moiety <lb/>
of my said Bank stocks to belong to my son George <lb/>
according to the directions and in the manner of my said Will <lb/><lb/>


<pb n="page (38)"/><lb/><lb/>

And that there be further paid by my <abbr expan="executors">Extors</abbr> unto my said <lb/>
son Landon when he shall arrive at the age of twenty one <lb/>
years the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of eight hundred &amp; seventy five pounds <lb/>
Sterling in three equal yearly payments according to <lb/>
the manner afore<abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr>&mdash;  </p>

<p>And it is my Will that my Executors do pay unto my <lb/>
son George when he shall arrive at the age of twenty <lb/>
one years the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of three hundred pounds sterling <lb/>
to be paid in three years successively in three equal <lb/>
payments after he comes of age And that they my <lb/>
said sons Landon &amp; George have no further claim of <lb/>
my debts due to me in Virginia notwithstanding <lb/>
any thing contained before in my said Will.&mdash; </p>

<p>I give unto my son Landon my new Negroe boy Called Tom that I <lb/>
bought out of the <note target="n41"><name type="ship">John &amp; Betty</name></note> last year &amp; also my two <lb/>
new Negroe Girls Named <add resp="editor"> [gap in text]</add> which I bought <lb/>
of Colo. Braxton last year. </p>

<p>I give to my son George my negroe Girl named Cloe <lb/>
which I bought of <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Tayloe this year. </p>

<p>I give to my daughter <note n="MCB">Mary</note> my new negroe Girl named <lb/>
Venus that I bought of <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Tayloe. </p>

<p>I give to my Daughter <note n="LCF">Lucy</note> my new negroe Girl named <lb/>
<add resp="editor"> [gap in text]</add> which I bought last year of <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Braxton</p>

<p>I give to my son Charles my Mulatto Girl named Mary <lb/>
Tom Gumbo's Wife's Daughter. </p>

<p>It is my Will that five of the men &amp; two of the Women &amp;  three Boys <lb/>
which I bought of <abbr expan="Colonel">Colo.</abbr> Tayloe, &amp; are now placed at my son Charles <lb/>
plantations in Northumberland County be removed to my <lb/>
son Roberts plantation in Westmoreland County &amp; be annexed to some <lb/>
of the said plantations the profits of the said slave I give to my <lb/>
son Robert during his life &amp; the property to my Grandson Robert <lb/>
to Continue annexed to the said plantations them &amp; their increase <lb/><lb/>

<pb n="page (39)"/><lb/><lb/>

forever Item in Consideration hereof I do hereby <sic corr="revoke">revoak</sic> the <lb/>
Clause in my will ordering two mean &amp; two Women slaves to <lb/>
belong to my said son Robert from <add place="supralinear">of</add> <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> the plantations entailed <lb/>
upon my said son Charles. </p>

<p>It is my Will that when my <note target="n42">Grandaughter Elizabeth</note> my son Roberts <lb/>
Daughter shall arrive at the age of twenty one years or marriage <lb/>
that then there be paid her by my <abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> equally between them <lb/>
out of my estate given them the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of Five hundred pounds sterling <lb/>
and whereas I have given by <add place="supralinear">my</add> will to my two Gransons <note target="n43">George</note> &amp;  <lb/>
<note target="n44">John Nicholas</note> the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of one hundred pounds sterling a piece <lb/>
under the Condition of their coming to age It is my Will that <lb/>
there shall be paid to each of them by my Executors out of my  <lb/>
estate instead of the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of one hundred pounds apiece <lb/>
the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of three hundred pounds sterling a piece when <lb/>
they shall arrive at their respective ages of twenty one years.  </p>

<p>It is my Will that when my Grandsons <note target="n45"><sic corr="Matthew">Matthers</sic></note> <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add>Page &amp; <note target="n46">Robert <lb/>
Page</note> shall arrive at their respective Ages of twenty one years that <lb/>
then there shall be paid to them by my <abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> in equal por-  <lb/>
-tions the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of three hundred pounds sterling a <sic corr="piece">peice.</sic> </p>

<p>It is my Will that this addition to my said Will Contained in <lb/>
five sheets of paper <sic corr="comprising">comprizing</sic> in the whole thirty four <lb/>
sheets shall be taken as a part of my said Will &amp; shall be <lb/>
interpreted as a declaration of my intent &amp; meaning and <lb/>
shall be taken as a <sic corr="revocation">revokation</sic> to such parts and as an <lb/>
addition to others &amp; as explanatory of the whole so that my <lb/>
real &amp; true intent may be answered. In Witness whereof <lb/>
I have hereunto set my hand &amp; afixed my seal this <lb/>
twelfth day of September in the year of our Lord God one <lb/>
thousand seven hundred &amp; twenty eight <lb/>
Signed sealed &amp; published in presence of.  </p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<hi rend="bold">Robert Carter</hi> (L.S.)  </p>

<pb n="page (40)"/><lb/>
<p>

R. Lee <lb/>
John Harvey <lb/>
<note target="n47">Barnabus Burch</note> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Thirty fourth sheet of my Will<lb/>
<abbr expan="Richard">Richd.</abbr> Talent <lb/>
<note target="n48">John Conner </note><lb/>
Arthur Neale<lb/>

<lb/><add resp="editor">[Third Codicil, 1730 June 9]</add> </p>

<p>In the name of God Amen I Robert Carter <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> of <lb/>
Lancaster County being of sound mind <add resp="editor"> [and]</add> memory but in a Crazy <lb/>
disordered Condition respecting my health do make this addition <lb/>
alteration &amp; <sic corr="revocation">revokation</sic> to several parts of my Will which is <lb/>
contained in four &amp; thirty sheets of paper, being made at <lb/>
three several times the first bearing date the two and twentieth <lb/>
day of August seventeen hundred &amp; twenty six the second <lb/>
bearing date the eleventh day of October seventeen hundred <lb/>
&amp; twenty six the third bearing date the twelfth day of Oc-  <lb/>
-tober seventeen hundred and twenty eight all intended to be one <lb/>
entire Will as far as can be made consistent and when altera-  <lb/>
-tions are made the latter Clauses alway<add resp="editor">[s]</add>  to be understood to <sic corr="control">controul</sic> <lb/>
&amp; revoke the former this Will under these circumstances I do now <lb/>
revive &amp; republish so far as it will stand &amp; consist with the <lb/>
alterations additions &amp; <sic corr="revocation">revokation</sic>s that I am now about to make.  </p>

<p>Notwithstanding the devises in my said Will I do now give <lb/>
unto my son Landon all my lands &amp; plantations in <lb/>
Northumberland County excepting the lands at the up-  <lb/>
-per end of the said County called <note n="FP">Fieldings</note> which I <lb/>
have given to my son Robert to him my son Landon <lb/>
&amp; the heirs male issue of his body &amp; for want of such <lb/>
unto my son Charles &amp; the heirs male issue of his <add resp="editor"> [body]</add>  <lb/>
&amp; for want of such the Tail to be continued <lb/>
according to the directions of my Will &amp; I also do <lb/>
lend unto my said son Landon all the slaves that shall <lb/>
belong to the said plantations now given him for and during <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (41)"/><lb/><lb/>

the Term of his natural life the property of the slaves to remain <lb/>
and be in trust to my said son Landon to and for the use of <lb/>
the heirs male issue of his body and I do give unto my said <lb/>
son Landon all the stocks of Cattle hoggs &amp; sheep that are <lb/>
upon the said plantations.&mdash;  </p>

<p>Whereas I have been for some time upon a bargain for the <lb/>
whole estate of Mr John L. Boyd Lands slaves stocks &amp;c <lb/>
in Richmond County for which I have bin in the  <lb/>
Court of Chancery  <add place="supralinear">in</add> Great Britain by the hands of <note n="MP2">Alder-  <lb/>
man Perry</note> of London the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of three thousand eight <lb/>
hundred pounds sterling five hundred pounds of which <lb/>
money is already paid as a depositum into the said <lb/>
Court of Chancery &amp; the remaining three thousand three <lb/>
hundred pounds now lies in the hands of the said <lb/>
Alderman Perry ready to consumate the said bargain,  <lb/>
if the said bargain be concluded then my Will is, and I do <lb/>
devise &amp; bequeath all the said lands plantations housing <lb/>
&amp; appurtenances unto my said son Landon and to the  <lb/>
heirs male issue of his Body lawfully begotten forever and <lb/>
I do also lend unto my said son Landon for and during <lb/>
the term of his natural life all the slaves contained in the <lb/>
said purchase excepting only the slaves of the said estate that <lb/>
are now seated upon my plantations above the falls of Rappaha-  <lb/>
-nock the property of the said slaves to be in trust with my said <lb/>
son Landon &amp; to be vested in him for the use of his issue male <lb/>
after his decease I do also give unto my said son Landon Carter <lb/>
all the stocks of Cattle hoggs houshold stuf<add resp="editor">[f]</add> &amp;c that do belong to the <lb/>
said estate whether upon the said plantations or upon any other <lb/>
lands and if my said son Landon should <sic corr="die">dye</sic> without issue male <lb/>
then I do give and devise the said Lands slaves plantations  <lb/>
stocks &amp;c contained within the said purchase unto my son <lb/>
George &amp; the heirs male issue of his Body &amp; for want of the Tail <lb/>
to <lb/>

<pb n="page (42)"/><lb/><lb/>

to be continued according to the direction of my Will but if <lb/>
notwithstanding the proceedings that have been had towards <lb/>
this bargain &amp; purchase of L. Boyds estate as aforesaid, it should <lb/>
happen to be defeated &amp; not perfected then my Will is and I do <lb/>
give unto my said son Landon, if he shall be alive to receive <lb/>
the same at the several times of paymt hereby directed to be <lb/>
made to him the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of three thousand pounds out of the <abbr expan="said">sd.</abbr>  <lb/>
purchase money Lying in the hands of the said Perry as aforesaid <lb/>
(to wit) one thousand pounds to be paid when he comes to the <lb/>
ago of one &amp; twenty years one thousand pound <add resp="editor"> [s]</add> two years after <lb/>
and one thousand pounds two years after that provided if <lb/>
he dies before these times of payment shall come leaving <lb/>
Child or Children behind him such Child or Children to <lb/>
have a right to this money. </p>

<p>I give unto my <add place="supralinear">said</add> son Landon the plantation that is now seated <lb/>
with some of the said slaves of this purchase called <note n="HT">Hickory <lb/>
thicket</note> plantation &amp; a thousand acres of Land adjoining to <lb/>
the said plantation part of the Land I bought of Mr. Robert <lb/>
Cary to be laid <sic corr="off">of</sic> Contiguous to the said plantation so <lb/>
that it shall not hurt the <note target="n49">Bridge Quarter</note> this thousand <lb/>
acres of Land give unto my said son Landon &amp; the heirs male <lb/>
issue of his Body lawfully begotten forever &amp; for want of such <lb/>
the Tail to continue to my son Robert &amp; the heirs male issue <lb/>
of his Body this devise of this thousand Acres of Land is intend-  <lb/>
-ed to take effect upon Condition that this purchase be <lb/>
made of Loyds estate but if my said son Landon Comes <lb/>
to enjoy this Legacy of three thousand pounds then this <lb/>
devise of this thousand acres of Land is not to subsist but <lb/>
to be void and the Land to go with the rest of Carys Land <lb/>
according to the directions of my Will excepting the peice of <lb/>
Land called the <note target="n50">round hills</note> in King George County which <lb/>
I do devise and give unto my said son Landon &amp; to the heirs male issue <lb/>

<pb n="page (43)"/><lb/><lb/>

of his Body &amp; for want of such unto my son Robert &amp; his heirs male.</p>

<p>Whereas I have given unto my son Landon and my son George <lb/>
my bank stock in the hands of Alderman Perry &amp; Mr. Dawkins <lb/>
&amp; also other debts due to me in Virginia &amp; likewise the mortgage <lb/>
of Rippon Hall I do revoke and alter my Will in these respects <lb/>
&amp; do direct as followeth first I do give and devise unto my <lb/>
son George all my lands and estate of Rippon Hall and the <lb/>
Lands adjoining thereto which were mortgaged to me by <lb/>
Colonel <note n="EJ"><sic corr="Jenings">Jenyings</sic></note> and also the mill that I have bought since <lb/>
likewise the Lands I bought of Joseph Wade &amp; my houses <lb/>
&amp; estate in Williamsburg &amp; also the Lands I lately bought <lb/>
of <abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> <abbr expan="Benjamin">Benja.</abbr> Robinson &amp; his Wife at Arnolds Ferry lying <lb/>
lying <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> in King &amp; Queen County, all these Lands plantations hous-  <lb/>
-es &amp; real estate I give and devise unto my said son George and <lb/>
to the heirs Male issue of his Body forever, as also the slaves <lb/>
that belong to &amp; are now seated upon Rippon plantation &amp; in case <lb/>
of failure of issue male of my son George then I do give these <lb/>
houses Lands &amp; slaves unto my son Landon, &amp; the heirs male <lb/>
issue of his Body &amp; for want of such to my son Robert &amp; his heirs male.&mdash;</p>

<p>It is my Will that my bank stock in the hands of Mr. Perry &amp; Mr.  <lb/>
Dawkins be kept at Interest as it is until my son George <lb/>
comes to the age of one &amp; twenty years that the Interest of the <lb/>
said money be carried to the credit of my Executors for the <lb/>
answering my Legacies &amp; incumbrances &amp; maintenance of <lb/>
my younger Children particularly my son George three <lb/>
thousand pounds of my said Bank <add resp="editor"> [stock]</add> it is my Will be paid <lb/>
&amp; delivered unto my son George when he comes of age the <lb/>
remaining twelve hundred &amp; fifty pounds of Bank stock <lb/>
if the said bargain takes effect for L Boyds estate as <lb/>
aforesaid so that the said Landon doth not enjoy any of the said three <lb/>
thousand pounds pounds, <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> but comes to the estate upon the bar-  <lb/>
-gain as aforesaid then it is my will that one moiety <lb/>
of the said twelve hundred &amp; fifty pounds <lb/>  <lb/>


<pb n="page (44)"/><lb/><lb/>

Bank stock do go unto my son Landon the other moiety to belong to <lb/>
my three eldest sons for discharging my Legacies &amp; incumbrances.</p>

<p>I do give and devise unto my son Charles the lands I bought <lb/>
of <note target="n51">John Mercer</note> &amp; his Wife adjoining to the Lands of my <note n="FQ">Falls <lb/>
Quarter</note> to him my son Charles &amp; the heirs male issue of <lb/>
his Body lawfully begotten &amp; for want of such to accord=  <lb/>
-ing to the intail of the rest of the Lands given unto my <lb/>
said son Charles.</p>

<p>I do give and devise unto my son George three thousand <lb/>
acres of Land part of my Great Tract upon the Branches <lb/>
of Potomac Creek in Stafford County to be laid off at the <lb/>
upper end of the said Tract to include and take in the <lb/>
plantation called <note n="PQ">Carters Park</note> the negroes however who are <lb/>
upon the said Park Quarter plantation to belong to my son <lb/>
Charles accord<add resp="editor"> [in]</add>g to the direction of my Will these three thousand <lb/>
acres of Land I devise to my said son George &amp; the heirs male <lb/>
issue of his Body lawfully begotten &amp; for want of such unto <lb/>
my son Landon &amp; the heirs male issue of his Body lawfully <lb/>
begotten &amp; for want of such to go according to the intail <lb/>
o f my Will.</p>

<p>I do give unto my son George the negroes I lately bought out of <lb/>
<note n="MP1">Mr. Pages</note> estate being in number twenty six to be seated <lb/>
&amp; planted &amp; kept upon the said three thousand acres of <lb/>
Land for the use &amp; profit of my said son George.</p>

<p>Whereas I have given unto my son John my tract of Land <lb/>
called the <note target="n52">lodge</note> upon Cedar run, it is my Will that he <lb/>
my son John have &amp; enjoy the slaves &amp; stocks that are <lb/>
upon the said Land.&mdash;</p>

<p>It is my will that my son George be kept at school at the College <lb/>
of <abbr expan="William">Wm.</abbr> &amp; Mary two years longer and that then he be sent to the <lb/>
university of Cambridge for an education the Charge of his edu-  <lb/>
-cation to be <sic corr="bourne">born</sic> by my executors and out of the interest of my said  <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (45)"/><lb/><lb/>

son Georges Bank stock &amp; if my executors his Brothers see it so <lb/>
fitting that he my son George may be entered first at the <lb/>
Inns of Court, that if his inclination &amp; capacity Lead <lb/>
that way he may be bred to the Law. </p>

<p>It is my Will and I do appoint my son Landon to be <lb/>
one of the <abbr expan="executors">extors</abbr> of this my Will. </p>

<p>Whereas I have given to my son Charles my negroe man <lb/>
Tom Gumby his Wife and Children I revoke that part of <lb/>
my Will &amp; I do give them to my son Robert excepting the<lb/>
Girl Mary which I leave to my son Charles.</p>

<p>It is my Will that some young negroes of those I have given <lb/>
to my son George be bred up Trades men Carpenters &amp; Coopers <lb/>
for the use of his plantations.</p>

<p>It is my Will that when my Grandson <note target="n53">Robin Carter Nicholas</note> <lb/>
arrives to the age of ten years there be paid to his Father <lb/>
by my executors the sum of three hundred pounds sterling to <lb/>
be by him put out to interest for the use &amp; benefit and <lb/>
toward the maintenance of my said Grandson.</p>

<p>Whereas in the dispose of those slaves that are to belong to my son Robert <lb/>
I have done my endeavour to annex them so to his Lands to prevent his <lb/>
sale and dispose of them from his posterity, however notwithstanding, in <lb/>
Regard his present <note n="RC2">Wife</note> brought to her husband my said son Robert <lb/>
a considerable fortune, I think it but justice to declare that it is my <lb/>
Will that she my said son Roberts Wife, if she survive her said hus-  <lb/>
band, shall have her right of Dower out of the said slave during <lb/>
her natural life. </p>

<p>Whereas Mann Page <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> my sons Robert &amp; Charles with myself <lb/>
are in a company for the Working &amp; Carrying on a Copper Mine upon a Cer-  <lb/>
tain tract of Land going &amp; known by the name of <note target="n54">Frying pan</note> &amp; that we <lb/>
have already seated the said Land being at great Charges in taking up <lb/>
large Quantities of Lands contiguous and are under several contracts <lb/>
to one another for the working and carrying on the said Cop-  <lb/>
per mine it is my Will and desire that the subsisting <lb/>
contract shall all be <lb/>  <lb/>

<pb n="page (46)"/><lb/><lb/>

performed &amp; I do Will and devise all my part in the said estate <lb/>
as Lands slaves servants &amp;c unto my son John &amp; to <add resp="editor"> [the]</add> heirs male <lb/>
issue of his body lawfully begotten for want of such unto my <lb/>
son Landon and to the heirs male issue of his Body lawfully <lb/>
begotten &amp; for want of such unto my son George &amp; to the <lb/>
heirs Male issue of his Body lawfully begotten, &amp; for want of <lb/>
such to be a joint estate unto my sons Robert &amp; Charles <lb/>
&amp; their heirs forever.</p>

<p>It is my Will that if my daughters <note n="MCB">Mary</note> &amp; <note n="LCF">Lucy</note> shall be alive five <lb/>
years after my decease that then there be paid to each of them <lb/>
the <sic corr="sum">sume</sic> of two hundred pounds sterling more than the Legacies <lb/>
I have given them by this <add place="supralinear">my</add> Will, and that <add resp="editor"> [if]</add>  either of my said <lb/>
daughters should <sic corr="die">dye</sic> before that time leaving Child or <lb/>
Childred <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> behind them that then such sum be paid to such <lb/>
Child or Children when the said term of time is expired by <lb/>
my Exetors out of the estate I have given to them.</p>

<p>It is my Will that notwithstanding any thing contained in my <lb/>
aforesaid Will my debts in Virginia shall belong to and be deed-  <lb/>
-ed a part of my estate for the satisfying my legacies &amp;  <lb/>
incumbrances.</p>

<p>It is my Will that the aforesaid Writing contained in four sheets <lb/>
of Paper be constructed deemed &amp; taken to be a part of my said Will <lb/> 
&amp; to be a revocation of so much of it as it contradicts In Witness <lb/>
whereof I have hereunto set my hand &amp; seal this ninth day <lb/>
of June in the year of our Lord one thousand seven hundred  <lb/>
&amp; thirty. </p>

<p>It is my earnest desire to my sons &amp; to every one of them respectively <lb/>
that they always &amp; upon all occasions behave themselves as loving <lb/>
brethren to one another &amp; that upon any controversies or diferences <lb/>
that may arise between them they <sic corr="always">alwaies</sic> submit the deter-  <lb/>
mination thereof to their Friends &amp; relations &amp; that they do <lb/>
not haul one another to the Law.</p>

<pb n="page (47)"/><lb/><lb/>

<p>Signed sealed &amp; published <lb/>
in presence of us &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Robert Carter (L.S.)  <lb/>
Richard Chapman <lb/>
<abbr expan="Richard">Richd.</abbr> Talent &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Fourth sheet of this addition to my Will <lb/>
John Conner &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Robert Carter <lb/>
John Toulton <lb/><lb/>

<add resp="editor">[Fourth Codicil, 1730 July 23]</add></p>

<p>In the Name of God amen I Robert Carter of Lancaster <lb/>
County being in a declining state of Body but of sound mind <lb/>
&amp; memory Whereas I have made my last will &amp; Testa-  <lb/>
ment at sundry periods of time to wit on the twenty <lb/>
second day of August seventeen hundred &amp; twenty <lb/>
six on the eleventh day of October seventeen hundred <lb/>
&amp; twenty six on the twelfth day of September seventeen <lb/>
hundred &amp; twenty eight &amp; on the ninth day of June <lb/>
seventeen hundred &amp; thirty since which time by  <lb/>
losses, the great fall of Tobacco &amp; various other misfortunes <lb/>
my circumstances are very much reduced at this day <lb/>
And Whereas in my said Will I have given &amp; ordered <lb/>
large legacies to my Children &amp; Grand Children which <lb/>
my estate is no <sic corr="ways">waies</sic> able to support to prevent the <lb/>
ruin &amp; undoing of my sons I do revoke &amp; reduce the said  <lb/>
Legacies in the following manner,</p>

<p>My <note n="ACH">Daughter Harrison's</note> Legacy of Five hundred pounds <lb/>
I reduce to two hundd.. &amp; fifty pounds.</p>

<p>Her daughter Betty's Legacy of Five hundred pounds <lb/>
I reduce to two hundred pounds.</p>

<p>Her daughter Ann's Legacy of Five hundred pounds <lb/>
I reduce to two hundred pounds.</p>

<p>My <note n="JCP">daughter Page's</note> Legacy of three hundred pounds <lb/>
I reduce to two <add resp="editor">[hundred?]</add> &amp; fifty pounds.</p>

<p>Her son Mann Page's Legacy conditionally as my Will directs of three<lb/><lb/>

<pb n="page (48)"/><lb/><lb/>

hundred pounds I reduce to one hundred pounds.</p>

<p>My Legacy of three hundred pounds to Carter Page payable <lb/>
as my Will directs I reduce <add resp="editor"> [to]</add> one Hundred &amp; fifty pounds.</p>

<p>The Legacy to John Page payable as aforesaid of the three <lb/>
hundred pounds I reduce to one hundred pounds.</p>

<p>My Legacy of three hundred pounds to my daughter Ni-  <lb/>
-cholas I reduce to two hundred &amp; fifty pounds.</p>

<p>Memorandum the fifty pounds given to my daugh-  <lb/>
-ter Nicholas for ear rings I have already paid her in plate.</p>

<p>Her son John's Legacy after the manner I have expressed <lb/>
in my Will, first mentioned <add resp="editor"> [as]</add> a hundred pounds &amp; then <lb/>
three hundred pounds I reduce to one hundred pounds.&mdash;</p>

<p>My said daughter's son George's Legacy in the manner as <lb/>
is exprest <abbr expan="although">altho'</abbr> it's twice mentioned is to be but a <lb/>
hundred pounds.</p>

<p>My Grandson Lewis Burwell's Legacy instead of three <lb/>
hundred pounds is to be but one hundred pounds under <lb/>
the condition mentioned.</p>

<p>Carter Burwells Legacy under the Condition mentioned <lb/>
of three hundred pounds I reduce to one hundred <lb/>
pounds.</p>

<p>Robert Burwell's Legacy of three hundred pounds under <lb/>
the condition mentioned I reduce t one hundred &amp;  <lb/>
fifty pounds.</p>

<p>Elizabeth Burwell's Legacy of three hundred pounds <lb/>
under the condition mentioned I reduced to one hundred <lb/>
pounds The Legacy of fifteen hundred pounds to my son <lb/>
Landon &amp; the Legacy of eight hundred &amp; seventy five pounds to <lb/>
him both these legacies I reduce to five hundred pounds to be <lb/>
paid at two successive yearly payments after he comes of age.</p>

<p>The half of my Bank stock, first given to him my son <lb/>
Land I have already <sic corr="revoke">revoak</sic>ed.</p>

<pb n="page (49)"/><lb/><lb/>

<p>The Legacy of three hundred pounds, given to my son George <lb/>
at his age I make payable at three yearly payments.</p>

<p>The Legacy of Five hundred pounds to my son Roberts <lb/>
Daughter Elizabeth under the Condition mentioned I  <lb/>
reduce to three hundred pounds. </p>

<p>The three hundred pounds Legacy to my Grandson Mathew <lb/>
Page I reduce to one hundred pounds. </p>

<p>The Legacy of three hundred pounds to my Grandson Robert <lb/>
Page I reduce to one hundred pounds under the Condition <lb/>
mentioned. </p>

<p>The legacy of three thousand pounds bank stock to my <lb/>
son George I reduce to fifteen hundred pounds. </p>

<p>The legacy of half the remaining part of my Bank stock <lb/>
to my son Landon I <sic corr="entirely">intierly</sic> revoke having made other <lb/>
provision for him. </p>

<p>The Legacy of three hundred pounds to my Grandson <lb/>
Robert Carter Nicholas under the Condition mentioned <lb/>
I reduce to two hundred pounds. </p>

<p>The Legacies of two hundred pounds apiece to my Daughters <lb/>
<note n="MCB">Mary</note> &amp; <note n="LCF">Lucy</note> payable five years after my decease I re-  <lb/>
duce to <add place="supralinear">a</add> hundred pounds to each </p>

<p>And instead of my daughter Lucy receiving the portion <lb/>
I have given her in three yearly equal payments my <lb/>
Will is it be paid to her in six yearly equal payments. </p>

<p>And also my Will is that my Executors have five years to <lb/>
pay my daughter Mary's portion in by equal payments <lb/>
from her age or marriage.</p> 

<p>And Whereas I have given in several parts of my <lb/>
Will the use &amp; profits of my slaves only to my sons <lb/>
and have endeavoured to vest the property in their <lb/>
sons &amp; heirs to prevent their Fathers selling or <lb/>
disposing of them all the Clauses of this nature <lb/><lb/>

<pb n="page (50)"/><lb/><lb/>

I do absolutely &amp; intirely revoke &amp; I do give my slaves to my re-  <lb/>
-spective sons according to my designation in my Will unto my <lb/>
said respective sons &amp; to their heirs forever as a real estate &amp;  <lb/>
descendible according to the terms of our late Negroe Law.</p>

<p>And Whereas I have ordered my son George an University educa-  <lb/>
-tion I have seen such bad effects of it, that I leave the care <lb/>
of him to the disposal of his Brothers particularly my son <lb/>
John and after a years stay more at the College, if he <lb/>
thinks <sic corr="fit">fitt</sic> to breed him up in the secretary's office.</p>

<p>My Will is that if my Grandson <abbr expan="Benjamin">Benja.</abbr> Harrison live to the age <lb/>
of ten years there be paid to him by my Executors the sum of two <lb/>
hundred pounds to be laid out in young Negroes between the <lb/>
ages of ten &amp; fifteen years one half of them to be females. </p>

<p>My Will is that if my Grandson Robert Carter live to the <lb/> 
age of ten years there be paid to him by my Executors the <lb/>
 of two hundred pounds to be laid out in young negroes be-  <lb/>
-tween the ages of ten &amp; fifteen years one half of them to be females. </p>

<p>It is my Will that this Writing contained in two sheets of <lb/>
paper be deemed &amp; taken to be a part of my Will &amp; to be a <lb/>
revocation of my Legacies as far as it goes as also an <lb/>
alteration of my Will as far as it is cointradictory to it. </p>

<p>In Witness whereof I have hereunto set my hand &amp; seal this <lb/>
three &amp; twentieth day of July in the years of our Lord one <lb/>
thousand seven hundred &amp; thirty </p>

<p>signed sealed &amp; published in <lb/>
the presence of us .............................Robert Carter (L.S.)  <lb/>
<abbr expan="Richard">Rich.</abbr> Chapman <lb/>
<abbr expan="Richard">Rich.</abbr>Talent <lb/>
John Conner <lb/>
John Toulton <lb/><lb/>

<pb n="page (51)"/><lb/><lb/>

Virginia &amp;c. </p>

<p>Memorandum that the General Court of this <lb/>
dominion begun and held at his Majesty's Royal Capitol <lb/>
in the City of Williamsburg the sixteenth day of October <lb/>
in the year of our Lord MDCCXXXii this Will con-  <lb/>
-tained in forty sheets of Paper was presented in Court <lb/>
&amp; proved by diverse of the witnesses thereto that is to say <lb/>
the former part thereof contained in twenty eight sheets <lb/>
of Papers was proved by the Oaths of <note n="RL">Richard Lee</note> and <lb/>
Thomas Edwards Other part thereof Contained in the <lb/>
next sheet by the oath of the said Lee other part of <lb/>
the same contained in the five next sheets by the Oaths  <lb/>
of the said Lee and John Conner and the rest of the  <lb/>
Will contained in the six last sheets by the Oaths <lb/>
of Richard Chapman and the said Conner &amp; <note n="JC1">John  <lb/>
Carter</note> <abbr expan="Esquire">Esqr.</abbr> Charles Carter &amp; Landon Carter Gen<add resp="editor">[tlemen]</add> Ex<add resp="editor">[ecu]</add>-  <lb/>
-tors therein named made oath thereto according to law <lb/>
and there upon the same was by the Court ordered to be <lb/>
recorded And certificate for obtaining a probate there-  <lb/>
-of in form was granted to the said Executors &mdash;  </p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Test Matt: Kempe C &amp;: Cwd.&mdash;</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Copy </p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Teste </p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<hi rend="underline">Wilson Allen</hi> C.G.C.<lb/><lb/>



 
 


</p>



</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter will, 1732 October 16, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. The text is contained in a bound volume and is a copy of a copy of the original probated in the General Court whose records were destroyed in the Richmond fire at the end of the Civil War. This copy was prepared and is attested to by Wilson Allen, Clerk of the General Court. Its source was a copy of the original made and attested to by Matthew Kemp, appointed clerk of the General Court about 1731. Given the number of duplicated words and other errors in this text, one must be sympathetic to the boredom of Allen in transcribing this long and tedious text. </note>

<note>The will was published in the <cit><bibl><title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography,</title> 5(May 1898):408-428; 6(July 1898):1-32.</bibl></cit></note>

<note id="n1">[1] The Occaquan River is a tributary of  the Potomac River that lies in what was Stafford County until Prince William County was formed in 1730. Much of the river today is known as the Bull Run, and forms the boundary between Fairfax and Prince William counties, and to the west, between Loudoun and Prince William  counties. Cedar and other runs converge to form it </note>

<note id="n2">[2] Licking Run is a tributary of Cedar Run lying in today's Fauquier County south of Germantown, but which, in Carter's day, lay in Stafford County.</note>

<note id="n3"> [3] Robert Cary (1685-1751), a London merchant and member of a family  of which many members were involved in colonial trade. Carter purchased lands from him in King George, Richmond, and Westmoreland counties. (<cit><bibl>Jacob M. Price. "Who Was John Norton? A Note on the Historical Character of Some Eighteenth-Century Virginia Firms."  <title>William and Mary Quarterly. </title> 3rd. ser. 19[July 1962]:401.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Totuskey Fork farm lay "in the fork between the two branches of Totuskey Creek at the hill of the same name" in Richmond County. After 1806 the property would be known as "Richmond Hill." (<cit><bibl n="B29">Miller. <title>Place-Names . . . . </title>pp. 135, 158.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] Charles Carter (1707-1764), Robert Carter's tenth child with his second wife, Elizabeth (Landon) Willis Carter. He would live at "Cleve," King George County, and inherit a number of properties in that area from his father.</note>

<note id="n6">[6]  Round Hills was a tract of about 500 acres in King George County which, as Carter notes here, he had purchased from London merchant Robert Cary. While Carter here bequeathes the property to John, he would later giive it to Landon.</note>

<note id="n7">[7] Landon Carter (1710-1778) was Carter's seventh child by his second wife, Elizabeth (Landon) Willis, and was the second child to bear the name Landon, the first having died shortly after his birth in 1708. Landon would live at "Sabine Hall," Richmond County, and marry three times, leaving many descendants, some of whom own "Sabine Hall" today. As an adult, he would keep a very interesting and useful diary. (<cit><bibl n="B30">Greene. <title>The Diary of Colonel Landon Carter. . . .</title></bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n8">[8]  George Carter (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1718-<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi>1741-42) was Carter's fifteenth child; his mother was Betty Landon Willis Carter. He attended the College of William and Mary and was sent to London after his father's death to study law. He died there unmarried. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 457.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n9">[9]  Carter Burwell (1716-1756) was Robert Carter's grandson by his daughter Elizabeth (Carter) Burwell and her first husband, Nathaniel Burwell (1680-1721). Carter Burwell would live at "Carter's Grove," and would marry Lucy Grymes in 1738. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 128.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n10">[10]  Robert Carter Burwell (1720-1777) was Robert Carter's grandson by his daughter Elizabeth (Carter) Burwell and her first husband, Nathaniel Burwell (1680-1721). Robert Burwell would live in Isle of Wight County, and marry twice, first in 1742 to Sally Nelson, and later Mary Blair Braxton.(<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 174.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n11">[11] Lewis Burwell (1711 or 1712-1756) was Carter's grandson by Elizabeth Carter Burwell and her first husband, Nathaniel Burwell (1680-1721). He was educated at Eton and Cambridge, and inherited considerable property, living at "Fairfield," Gloucester Coounty. He would be president of the Council in 1750-1751.(<cit><bibl n="B42">Kneebone <hi rend="italics">et al.</hi>,  <title>Dictionary of Virginia Biography.</title> 2:434-5;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 114.</bibl></cit>) </note>

<note id="n12">[12] Mann Page (1718-1778)  was Robert Carter's grandson by his daughter Judith (Carter) Page and her husband Mann Page (1691-1730). He  would inherit "Rosewell," Gloucester County, from his father, and marry first Alice Grymes (1724-1746) in 1743,  and in 1748, Ann Corbin Tayloe. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 212.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n12.5">[12.5]  Fairfax Harrison wrote that in 1726 there was a bill before the House of Burgesses proposing to "divide Stafford [County] at Aquia creek and create above that boundary a county to be named <hi rend="italics">Hartford,</hi> but after debate the proposal was rejected." (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> pp. 311-312, citing the <title> Journals of the House of Burgesses, 1727-1740.</title> pp. 408-414.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n13">[13] A moiety is one of two approximately equal portions.</note>

<note id="n14">[14] Robert Jones was the son of William Jones of Northumberland County; he moved to Prince William County where he was a justice and sheriff, 1731-32. He was a head overseer for Carter in the upper country between 1727 and 1729. (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 339;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="A8">Berkeley. "Robert Carter as Agricultural Administrator: . . .", 273-295.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n15">[15] Old Plantation was in Northumberland County. In Carter's inventory, Dennis Sullivant was the property's overseer of 8 slaves, 36 sheep, 75 hogs, 66 cattle, and "a Mare called Mopsy 10 yers ," etc. The property was bequeathed to Carter's son Landon. (<cit><bibl n="A26">Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . .";</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B30">Greene. <title>The Diary of Colonel Landon Carter. . . .</title> p. 4.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n16">[16] Blough (Bluff) Point plantation was in Northumberland County "on Jarvis Creek about four miles from Kilmarnock in Bluff Point Neck."  As noted in the will, Carter  had purchased the property from "John Sudley, the Farther <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> and the Son . . ."  and bequeathed it to Landon. (<cit><bibl n="B29">Miller. <title>Place-Names . . . . </title>. p. 82.</bibl></cit>; and <cit><bibl n="B30">Greene. <title>The Diary of Colonel Landon Carter. . . .</title>, p. 4.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n17">[17] Thomas West was the overseer at Blough Point Quarter in
Northumberland County when Carter's inventory was prepared in 1732. (<cit><bibl n="A26">Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>.)</note>

<note id="n18">[18]  Simon Sallard (d. 1747) was referred to in the 1732 inventory of Carter's property as "Mr." He was then the manager of the plantations in Richmond and Westmoreland counties, and the overseer of Brick House Quarter in Richmond County. (<cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>; <cit><bibl n="B32">Morton. <title>Robert Robert Carter of Nomini Hall.</title> p. 33;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B30">Greene. <title>The Diary of Colonel Landon Carter. . . .</title> p. 304.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n19">[19]  Elizabeth Burwell (1718- ?) was Carter's grandaughter by his daughter, Elizabeth, and her first husband, Nathaniel Burwell. She would marry in 1738 William Nelson of Yorktown.(<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 143.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n20">[20] Augustine Moore (c. 1685-c.1734) of "Chelsea," King
William County, a justice and prominent leader. (<cit><bibl>J.H.P., "The Gorsuch and Lovelace Families," <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography.</title> 25(1917): 431-444.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n21">[21] Carter Page (1724-?)  was Robert Carter's grandson by his daughter Judith (Carter) Page and her husband Mann Page (1691-1730). He would die unmarried.  (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 252.</bibl></cit>)</note> 

<note id="n22">[22] John Page (1720-1774)  was Robert Carter's grandson by his daughter Judith (Carter) Page and her husband Mann Page (1691-1730). He would live at "North End," Gloucester County, and marry Jane Byrd in 1746. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 221.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n23">[23] Elizabeth (Harrison) Randolph (1724-1745) was called "Betty." She was Carter's granddaughter by his daughter Anne and her husband, Benjamin Harrison IV. Betty would marry Peyton Randolph, and their son, Benjamin Harrison V, would be a signer of the Declaration of Independence, and governor of Virginia. (<cit><bibl>"Harrison of James River," <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography. </title> 32(1924): 97;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 259.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n24">[24]  Anne (Harrison) Randolph (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1722-1745) was Carter's granddaughter by his daughter Anne and her husband, Benjamin Harrison IV.  She would marry William Randolph of "Wilton," Henrico County in 1735. (<cit><bibl>"Harrison of James River," <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography. </title> 32(1924): 97;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 254.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n25">[25] Rippon Hall was Edmund Jening's estate in York County which he had acquired in 1687 from John and Unity West when it was named "Poplar Neck." Jenings's bad financial circumstances forced him to mortgage the property to Carter who eventually acquired title to it. (<cit><bibl>"Notes and Queries." <title>William and Mary Quarterly.</title> 2[Apr. 1894]: 270-278.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n26">[26] The clerk copying the will made a mistake in writing "Clough" for "Blough." No record of a "Clough Point" property has been found. For Blough (Bluff) Point plantation, see # 15 above.</note>

<note id="n28">[28] Thomas Carter (1672-1733) was the second of that name in
Lancaster County, and may have been Carter's first cousin as there is evidence that their fathers were brothers. He lived at "Barford" in the northern part of the county. (<cit><bibl>Catherine Adams Jones, <title>The Early Thomas Carters of Lancaster County, Virginia.</title> Lancaster, Virginia: Mary Ball Washington Museum &amp; Library, 1982.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n29">[29] The name "John Hutchins" appears as a resident of Christ Church Parish in the 1716 Lancaster County tithables list. (<cit><bibl>"Tithables in Lancaster Co., 1716." <title>William and Mary Quarterly</title> 1st. ser., 21[July 1912]: 106-11.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n30">[30]  The <hi rend="italics">Mercury</hi> was a slave ship owned by Bristol merchants Francis Chamberlayne and Francis Sitwell. See Carter's letters of July 1720 to these men and others concerning his participation in a sale of a quantity of slaves that reached the colony in 1720 on board this ship. (<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 40.</bibl></cit> )</note>

<note id="n31">[31] Edward Hill was John Carter's father-in-law through his marriage to Elizabeth Hill; John came into possession of  "Shirley" in Charles City County near Williamsburg from Edward Hill. He  also acquired many of his father-in-law's debts as the will notes.</note>

<note id="n32">[32] Property that is entailed in a will is restricted so that it may pass only to certain types, often male, of descendants.</note>

<note id="n33">[33] "William Forrester had been murdered on November 5, 1723, by Thomas Glascock whose son Gregory was named as an accessory." Carter had noted Glascock's capture in his diary on November 13th: "Collo Barber acquaints me me he had Seizd Glascocks who had fled for Murther his Estate Coll Tarpley in the behalf of Glascocks Heir offers to Enter the Land as Escheat " The lands reverted to the proprietors, and Carter apparently managed them for some years for the benefit of Glascock's heirs; he later acquired title to the properties which are mentioned in his will. (<cit><bibl n="B31">Ryland. <title>Richmond County Virginia. . . . </title> p. 101.</bibl></cit></note>

<note id="n34">[34] John Turbervile (d. 1728) was a justice, burgess, and sheriff of Lancaster County. (<cit><bibl>"Tithables in Lancaster Co., 1716." <title>William and Mary Quarterly</title> 1st. ser., 21[July 1912]: 106-11;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl>"Turberville Family of VA," 
http://members.tripod.com/~Bonestwo/index-6.html,  reviewed and downloaded 10/31/2002 </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n35">[35] "Thos. Edwards, a little petty Fogging Lawyer the Clark of our
County that hath as much Mettle and more cunning for Contention then his predecessor had" Carter wrote to Landon Jones, July 23, 1723. Edwards was clerk of the Lancaster County court from 1720-1746. (<cit><bibl><title>Within the Court House at Lancaster.</title> Lively, VA: Lively Printing Services, Lively, VA: Lively Printing Services, [1976]. p. 15.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n36">[36]  Carter had a clerk named John Harvey, and there are notes on some of his letters, "Harvey to copy." A John Harvey witnessed his will, and some of its codicils, which is logical if Harvey had written it out for Carter. However, on 1729 November 14, Carter wrote to Micajah Perry that Harvey, "whom you sent me from the Hospital," had completed his service, indicated that he did not trust Harvey, and intimated that Harvey may have stolen some accounts of the Burwell estate of which he requested copies from Perry.</note>

<note id="n37">[37] Carter refers to an act  of the Assembly of 1727 February, "1st George II, Chap. XI," entitled "<hi rend="italics">An Act to explain and amend the Act,</hi>" For declaring the Negro, Mulatto, and Indian Slaves, within this Dominion, to be Real Estate. . . ." (<cit><bibl>William Waller Hening. <title>The Statutes at Large; being A Collection of All the Laws of Virginia. . . .</title>  [Richmond: privately printed, 1820. Facsimile reprint, 1969.] 4:222-228.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n38">[38] John Carter (b. <hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1725) was Carter's grandson by his son John and his wife Elizabeth (Hill) Carter whom he married in 1723. Little is known of the grandson who was alive in 1728 when Carter wrote the second codicil to his will.</note>

<note id="n39">[39] Robert Carter (1728-1804) was Carter's grandson by his son Robert  (1704-1732) and his wife Priscilla (Churchill) Carter. The grandson would inherit his father's home at Nomini, and would be known as "Councillor" Carter. He would marry Frances A. Tasker of Maryland in 1754. (<cit><bibl n="B32">Morton. <title>Robert Robert Carter of Nomini Hall;</title></bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 332.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n40">[40] "Viz." is an abbreviation for the Latin word "videlicet" which means "namely."</note>

<note id="n41">[41] The <hi rend="italics">John &amp; Betty</hi> was a Liverpool ship owned by merchant John Pemberton. In 1726 the captain was John Gale, and in the next year, she was commanded by a Captain Denton. (<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 18, n. 23.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n42">[42] Elizabeth (Carter) Willis (1725-<hi rend="italics">post</hi> 1763)was Carter's granddaughter by his son Robert. She would marry Francis Willis (1717-1797) of "'White Hall," Gloucester County in 1742. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 312.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n43">[43] George Nicholas (1726-1771) was Robert Carter's grandson by his daughter Elizabeth (Carter) Burwell and her second husband, Dr. George Nicholas. He would marry Elizabeth Ruffin. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 176.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n44">[44] John Nicholas (1725-1790) was Robert Carter's grandson by his daughter Elizabeth (Carter) Burwell and her second husband, Dr. George Nicholas. He would marry Martha Fry in 1758. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 174.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n45">[45] Matthew Page (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1726- ?)  was Robert Carter's grandson by his daughter Judith (Carter) Page and her husband Mann Page (1691-1730). He would die unmarried. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 252.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n46">[46] Robert Page (<hi rend="italics">ca.</hi> 1722-1768)  was Robert Carter's grandson by his daughter Judith (Carter) Page and her husband Mann Page (1691-1730). He would live at "Broadneck," Hanover County, and marry Sarah Walker in 1750. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 241.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n47">[47] This was probably Barnabas Burch "the boatbuildr" with whom Carter had problems causing him to describe Burch as "an idle Roug ever Since he came here  the work he has don hath not answerd" in his diary entry for 1725 February 2. In June of that year, Carter learned the Burch and several others had stolen a gun and hidden it in the woods. In July Carter won a judgement against Burch for running away, and because Burch confessed "that he is totally ignorant of and unable to perform the trade &amp; misteries of a house carpenter for which he entered into Covenant with his sd Master in Great Britain." The court added time to Burch's indenture, and ordered that he receive no salary during his term.  (<cit><bibl n="B28">Jones, <title>Orders Book Entries . . . Referring to "Robert Carter. . . ."</title> p. 120 abstracting Lancaster County Court Orders Book 7 1721-1729, page 181.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n48">[48] Carter's 1732 inventory listed a John Conner as a "Taylor" at Corotoman.</note>

<note id="n49">[49] Bridge House Quarter was located in Riichmond County and lay close to Hickory Thicket "northeast of Warsaw." In Carter's 1732 inventory, Charles Campbell was the overseer of 9 slaves, 8 horses, 41 hogs, and 31 cattle. (<cit><bibl n="B29">Miller. <title>Place-Names . . . . </title>p. 16;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="A26">"Carter Papers: An Inventory. . . ."</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n50">[50] This note eliminated. See fn 6.</note>

<note id="n51"> [51] John Mercer (1704-1768) emigrated from Ireland where he had been
trained as an attorney. "He settled at Marlboroughtown in 1726 as a practicing attorney and at once allowed a facile pen to get him into trouble with the government." He eventually lost his license to practice law, and turned to the land speculation that he had begun as soon as he reached Virginia. (<cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks of Old Prince William</title> p. 315.</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B24">Copeland and MacMaster. <title>The Five George Masons.</title></bibl></cit>)</note>


<note id="n52">[52] "In 1724, Robert Carter took out patents for, among others: the Licking Run tract of 10,227 acres which lay along and east of Licking Run above Germantown and across Owl and Turkey Runs, to what was then supposed to be the western boundary of the vast Brent Town Tract. Here Carter seated the Lodge Quarter mentioned in his will." (<cit><bibl>Carl F. Cannon, Jr., "Robert ("King") Carter of "Corotoman." Unpublished doctoral dissertation, Duke University, 1956, p. 274.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n53">[53] Robert Carter Nicholas (1728-?) was Robert Carter's grandson by his daughter Elizabeth (Carter) Burwell and her second husband, Dr. George Nicholas. He would marry Ann Cary in 1751. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 176.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n54">[54]  In 1728, Carter, his sons Robert and Charles, and his son-in-law Mann Page,  organized a company to mine for copper on a tract of some 27,000 acres that Louis Morton describes as lying "near the present boundary of Fairfax and Loudoun counties." Fairfax Harrison wrote that the tract was "on the Horsepen of Broad." Horsepen Run joins Broad Run on the northern border of Dulles airport. The company was not successful. (<cit><bibl n="B32">Morton. <title>Robert Robert Carter of Nomini Hall.</title> pp. 18-19;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 342. </bibl></cit>)</note>









</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>