<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C24a28a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, January 28, 1724</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca.11  kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C24a28a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2002</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, January 28, 1724</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1724-01-28</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C24a28aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1724-01-28"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C24a28a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to William Dawkins, January 28, 1724</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant William Dawkins, January 28, 1724, to report the arrival of a number of ships in the colony and his plans for shipping tobacco. He reminds Dawkins of the clothes he has ordered for his son Robin who had returned from England with no hats or shoes, especially winter shoes. He then writes at length about the text books that he wishes his son Landon to study while at Mr. Low's school, praising "Lillie's grammer" and Comenius'  <hi rend="italics">Jannua Linguarum Trilinguis. </hi> If Mr. Low cannot make Landon "a perfect Master of this Book in all the three Languages," then he will probably remove Landon to Eton where his grandson, Lewis Burwell, is a student. </p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="WD">William Dawkins,</note> January 28, 1724</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;per Fowler<lb/> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Copy per Keiling<lb/>
Mr. Wm. Dawkins

<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name>
<date value="1724-01-28">Janr. 28th. 1723/24&mdash;</date><lb/>

</dateline>
<salute>Sir</salute>

</opener>

<p><note target="n1">Adam Graves</note> <sic corr="arrived ">arrivd</sic> <sic corr="HERE ">hither</sic> the 8th. Instant I have <lb/>Seen him but twice Suppose he writes to You himself, <note target="n2">Cant</note> had the <lb/>luck to get the Start of him three <sic corr="weeks, ">weekes,</sic> had he been as fortunate <lb/>his business would have been Easily <sic corr="compassed ">compassd</sic> what it will be now <lb/>no doubt he will Inform You, I have not seen him this fortnight <lb/>When he came first on <sic corr="shore ">Shoar</sic> I told him I had not a hhd for him <lb/>believe I may now find him a little, he speaks pretty peremptorily <lb/>that the <name type="ship">Carter</name> will not be here this Year, that You were upon <lb/>thoughts of Sending <note target="n3">Holliday</note> into this river, I shall be glad if <lb/>it prove So, These forward Ships will very much drain us, those <lb/>that are to come will meet with but poor <sic corr="gleanings, ">Glennings,</sic> for my <lb/>part I cannot promise my Self above thirty or forty hhds. of <lb/>leaf Tobo. that will be left out of all my Crops &amp; to Ship <note target="n4"><sic corr="oronocco ">Arronoko</sic></note> <lb/>to <sic corr="London ">Londo.</sic> is one way of giving it away, you will have by <lb/><note target="n5">Keiling</note> the fifty hhds. You <sic corr="chartered ">charterd</sic> for me, &amp; I suppose all Yor. <lb/>Friends Comply with <sic corr="thiers, ">their's,</sic> <note target="n6"><sic corr="Wills">Will's</sic></note> <sic corr="Arrived ">Arriv'd</sic> about the same <lb/>time the <name type="ship">Baily</name> did, &amp; if my If my Intelligence be true will get his <lb/>business done in time, I am not without hopes Adam will <lb/>do so too, I <sic corr="stayed ">Staid</sic> hovering as long as I <sic corr="dared ">dar'st</sic> before I closed <lb/>with Cant for Some Freight, &amp; had bin Shut out but for <note n="MP1"><abbr expan="Colonel ">Collo.</abbr> <lb/>Page's</note> care of me, Cant <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> my <sic corr="notes ">Noats</sic> &amp; the Tobo. <sic corr="lies '">lyes</sic> ready <lb/>but whether he will fetch it I am not certain, I should not <lb/>be at all <sic corr="uneasy ">uneasie</sic> if I can help <del>Adam with</del> The Baily wth it <lb/>I shall be very glad You have an Opportunity of Sending <lb/>my Son <note target="n7">Robin</note> the supply of some <sic corr="clothes ">cloths</sic> &amp;c which I <sic corr="wrote ">writ</sic> for <lb/><gap reason="damage"/><add resp="editor">[soo]</add>n after his Arrival for indeed he is very bare, &amp; most 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
Especially of <sic corr="shoes ">Shoos</sic> &amp; <sic corr="hats ">Hatts</sic> having brought nothing home with <lb/>him, but the things he had new just at his coming away <lb/>&amp; <sic corr="has ">hath </sic> not a <abbr expan="pair ">pr</abbr> of Winter <sic corr="shoes ">Shoos</sic> to his Feet which is some=<lb/>=thing Extraordinary,</p>

<p><note n="CC1">Charles</note> I am in no doubt of seeing within this <lb/>Month or two. You tell me <note target="n8">Landon</note> is a <sic corr="hopeful ">hopefull</sic> boy, I <lb/>could wish <note target="n9">Mr. Low</note> had kept in the old way of teaching the <lb/><sic corr="Latin ">Lattin</sic> Tongue &amp; had made my Boys perfect in their un=<lb/>=derstanding of <note target="n10">Lillie's Grammer</note> and of the Old School books <lb/>that We and Our forefathers learned, There is one Book <lb/>which did me the most service of any that I was Acquainted <lb/>with, to <sic corr="wit ">Witt</sic>, the <note target="n11">Jannua Linguarum Trilinguis</note> in Latin <lb/>English &amp; Greek <sic corr="written ">Writ</sic> by John Comenius, the best Stock of <lb/>Latin Words and in the best sense to Suit the Genius of Boys <lb/>Even to their Manhood, of any Book that Ever I met with <lb/>In my life, It is so very much in my Esteem that I would <lb/>desire You to give Positive directions to Mr. Low that My <lb/>Son Landon be made a perfect Master of this Book in <lb/>all the three Languages, that he may be so perfect to be able <lb/>with his Eye upon one of the Languages to repeat the other <lb/><abbr expan="it is ">tis </abbr> so pretty a compendium of all the arts &amp; Sciences &amp; <sic corr="written ">Writ</sic> <lb/>in so handsome a <sic corr="style ">stile</sic> to captivate the Genious of Youth, that <lb/>I resolve to be <sic corr="pleased ">pleasd</sic> in this matter, &amp; am so much <sic corr="fixed ">fixd</sic> in <lb/>it that if Mr. Low will not Answer my desire, I will have <lb/>my Boy <sic corr="removed ">removd</sic> to another School &amp; I think if he is, the <lb/>next place Shall be to <note target="n12"><sic corr="Eton ">Eaton</sic></note> <sic corr="where ">whither</sic> <note target="n13">Lewis Burwell</note> is <sic corr="gone ">gon</sic>  <lb/>Mr. Low's School is valueable upon the good &amp; orderly Government <lb/>of it, the care he takes of the Boys Moral's but if they do not <lb/>meet with a thorough Improvement in their Learning such <lb/>as will Stick by them &amp; be <sic corr="useful ">usefull</sic> to them in their riper <lb/>Years all our cost is thrown away, &amp; the greatest part of <lb/>their work is to do after they have left the School, it is not <lb/>reading a few scraps in the Poets &amp; other <sic corr="classics ">Classicks</sic> that <lb/>makes boys understand the Scope &amp; <sic corr="design ">designe</sic> of the Authors, I <lb/>have had so good a Character of the Genius of Landon in his <lb/>Aptness to take learning as well as of the Stength of his <lb/>Memory that I have reason to think if he falls into good <lb/>hands he may be an Absolute Master of the Languages <lb/>before he Arrives to Eighteen Years of Age, He is a Younger <lb/>Brother I would make Learning a part of his Portion <lb/>which is all I shall say concerning him at present leaving <lb/>the rest to Your kind care &amp; consideration.</p>

<closer>I am, <lb/>Sir  Yor. very humble Servt. 
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/><abbr expan="Colonel ">Colo:</abbr>
 Page &amp; myself have drawn upon <lb/>You for 50&pound; payble to Peter Richeson the <lb/><abbr expan="general overseer ">Genl. Oversr. </abbr> which I desire You to Answer upon the Accot. of Mr. Burw<add resp="editor">[ell's]</add> <lb/>Estate.</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1723 July 4 -1724 June 11, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. There is a nineteenth-century transcript of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia. </note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Adam Graves was a son of Captain Thomas Graves [d. <hi rend="italics">ante</hi> 1720], long a captain of vessels trading to Virginia, and a special friend of Robert Carter's. Adam Graves commanded the <hi rend="italics">Bailey</hi> in 1725-1727, a ship that belonged to London merchant William Dawkins. (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800, for Adm. 68/194-196 found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert  and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Constantine Cant was the captain of the <hi rend="italics">Burwell.</hi> (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800 for Adm. 68/195, ff. 76v, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] William Holladay commanded a ship named the <hi rend="italics">Princess Carolina.</hi> (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small  Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4]  Oronocco tobacco was one of two major types grown in Carter's day. It was "bulkier and coarser than sweetscented . . .  had a sharper leaf  'like a fox's ear,'" and was stronger in flavor "than sweetscented."  (<cit><bibl>Arthur Pierce Middleton. <title>Tobacco Coast:  A Maritime History of the Chesapeake Bay in the Colonial Era.</title> Newport News, VA: Mariners' Museum, 1953.  p. 97</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] Captain William Keiling commanded the <hi rend="italics">Betty.
</hi> (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley  Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n6">[6] Captain Peter Wills commanded the  <hi rend="italics">Booth</hi> in 1723 and the <hi rend="italics">Amity</hi> in 1727. (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6800, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small  Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n7">[7] Robert Carter (1704-1732) was Carter's seventh child by his
second wife, Elizabeth Landon (Willis) Carter. Robert was sent to England to school in 1718; see Carter's letter to William Dawkins, July 9, 1718. Robert married Priscilla Churchill in 1725 and had two children, one of whom, Robert Carter III, would be known as "Councillor" Carter of "Nomini Hall." Robert Carter II died a few months before his father. (<cit><bibl n="B32">Morton. <title>Robert Robert Carter of Nomini Hall.</title></bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n7">[7] Charles Carter (1707-1764), Robert Carter's tenth child with his second wife, Elizabeth (Landon) Willis Carter. He would live at "Cleve," King George County, and inherit a number of properties in that area from his father.</note>

<note id="n8">[8] Landon Carter (1710-1778) was Carter's seventh child by his second wife, Elizabeth (Landon) Willis, and was the second child to bear the name Landon, the first having died shortly after his birth in 1708. Landon would live at "Sabine Hall," Richmond County, and marry three times, leaving many descendants, some of whom own "Sabine Hall" today. As an adult, he would keep a very interesting and useful diary. (<cit><bibl n="B30">Greene. <title>The Diary of Colonel Landon Carter. . . .</title></bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n9">[9] Mr. Low was Carter's sons' schoolmaster.</note>

<note id="n10">[10] Carter refers to William Lilly (1468?-1522) who "contributed a short Latin syntax, with the rules in English, to the Latin grammar by Colet and Erasmus, c. 1509. This, with another grammar, was the basis of the work known as Lily's Grammar which was long familiar to English schoolboys." It was, by Henry VIII, in 1540 imposed throughout the kingdom as the standard Latin text book. No copy of Lilly is listed in Carter's inventory, but there is a general entry for "7 grammers" that might have included Lilly. (<hi rend="italics">The Oxford Companion to English Literature.</hi> Oxford University Press, 1995, excerpted online at http://www.xrefer.com/entry/372360 as of 6/18/02; <cit><bibl n="A28">Wright. "The Literary Interests of the First Carters." </bibl></cit> p. 60.)</note>

<note id="n11">[11] No copy of Comenius's work appears in the inventory of Carter's library. A typical edition that Carter might have used would be: Johann Amos  Comenius (1592-1670), <hi rend="italics">Janua Linguarum Trilinguis, Sive, Johannis-Amos-Comenii Janua  Linguarum: Novissime ab Ipso Authore Recognita, Aucta, Emendata: Adjunctis Metaphrasi Graeca et Anglicana Versione.</hi>London, 1670.</note>

<note id="n12">[12] "Eton College, near Windsor, Berkshire, one of England's largest independent secondary schools and one of the highest in prestige. It was founded by Henry VI in 1440-41 for 70 highly qualified boys who received scholarships from a fund endowed by the king. Simultaneously, Henry founded King's College, Cambridge, to which scholars from Eton were to proceed. That connection is no longer in place." ("Eton College," from the <hi rend="italics">Encyclopedia Brittanica</hi> online, http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/194547/Eton-College. 1/10/2011)</note><lb/>

<note id="n13">[13] Lewis Burwell (1711 or 1712-1756), Carter's grandson by Elizabeth Carter Burwell and her first husband, Nathaniel Burwell (1680-1721). He was educated at Eton and Cambridge, and inherited considerable property, living at "Fairfield," Gloucester Coounty. He would be president of the Council in 1750-1751.(<cit><bibl n="B42">Kneebone <hi rend="italics">et al.</hi>,  <title>Dictionary of Virginia Biography.</title></bibl></cit>) 2:434-5.</note>

<lb/><lb/><note><hi rend="italics">This text, originally posted in 2002, was revised January 11, 2011, to add footnotes, and to strengthen the modern language version text.</hi></note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>