<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27h22b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Benedict Leonard Calvert to Robert Carter, August 22, 1727
</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 13 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27h22b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2003</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Benedict Leonard Calvert to Robert Carter, August 22, 1727
</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-08-22</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27h22bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1727-08-22"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Benedict Leonard Calvert to Robert Carter, August 22, 1727
</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Benedict Leonard Calvert, new governor of the province of Maryland, writes to Robert Carter, August 22, 1727, concerning the steps taken within that colony to ensure that persons accused of robbery of William Thacker in Virginia will appear at their Virginia trial. He notes that Thackers appears to have fled from debts he owned in Maryland, and his debtors rashly pursued him into Virginia.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from <note target="n1">Benedict Leonard Calvert</note> to Robert Carter, August 22, 1727
</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Annapolis, <add resp="editor">[Maryland]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-08-22">Augst. 22d. 1727</date><lb/>
To the Honble: Robert Carter Esqr. <lb/>President of his Majtys Council in <lb/>Vrginia and Commander in cheif <lb/>of the Same Colony<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute></salute>

</opener>

<p>Soon after my Arrival here in the last month invest<lb/>ed with <note target="n2">my Brother</note> the Lord <sic corr="Proprietor's">Proprietarys</sic> Command for the Govern<lb/>ment of this Province a Certain Richard Thacker came to me <lb/>with an hue and cry under the Seal of your province as also a <lb/>Letter from your Self to my predecessor here in the <abbr expan="Government">Governmt.</abbr> <lb/>both <sic corr="relating">relateing</sic> to a robbery <sic corr="alleged">alledged</sic> by the Said Thacker to have <lb/>bin on him Committed within your province by Philip Hammond <lb/>and other <sic corr="inhabitants">inhabitents</sic> of this province therefore <sic corr="desiring">desireing</sic> <lb/>the Seizure of the Said persons as fellons and their Conveyance in <lb/>to Virginia in order their further prosecution at law for the <lb/>Offence&mdash;</p>

<p>As I was then newly <sic corr="Enterred">Enterd</sic> into the Administration <lb/>and the Case in its Circumstances appearing very Extraordinary <lb/>to me I could not avoid taking Some time to Consider and Advise <lb/>the proper method of proceeding in Such a Case in the which the <lb/>variety of Opinions here I could not Easily and readily be Sat<lb/><sic corr="isfied">isfyd</sic> for in our Enquirys <sic corr="we">wee</sic> found not any Certain rule of <lb/>proceeding in Such a Case <sic corr="Established">Establishd</sic> <sic corr="Either">Eithr</sic> by Law or Practice <lb/>but I hope what has here bin done in Prosecution of the request <lb/>will Entirely answer the Intent of it by proving against a <lb/>a <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> failure of Justice. Warrants, were <sic corr="Issued">Issd</sic> for the <sic corr="Apprehension">Apprhensign</sic> <lb/>of the Said <sic corr="Accused">Accusd</sic> Persons upon which they have Surrended them<lb/>selves and their Case by many Depositions taken both here 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
and in Virginia appearing more like a trespass than a robbery <lb/>they were Admitted to bail they are Severally bound in two re<lb/>cognizances one to his Majesty to appear at the next General Court <lb/>in Virginia if so required by the Commander in <sic corr="Chief">Cheif</sic> of Virginia <lb/>or by the Commander in <sic corr="Chief">Cheif</sic> of this province the other to <abbr expan="our">or.</abbr> Lord <lb/><sic corr="Proprietor">Proprietary</sic> to appear here at our next Assizes in Prince Georges <lb/>County where the Continuations for the Violence <sic corr="Offered">Offerd</sic> to Thacker <lb/>was alledged to be so that Thacker will have full Scope to Pro<lb/>secute if he pleases and I am <sic corr="Satisfied">Satisfyed</sic> the Gentlemen would no <lb/>ways decline Appearing at your Court if so required were <lb/>they not bound by recognizances so to do and on the least Intim<lb/>ation from your self or Order that their Appearance is required <lb/>According to their recognizances you may be Assured they <lb/>Shall be forthcoming at your <abbr expan="Generalk">Gen:</abbr> Court I must only desire <lb/>timely notice Adequate to the Distance between us I have <lb/>made diligent Enquiry after Thacker to inform him of these <lb/>Proceedings but as he Absconds I <sic corr="believe">beleive </sic>for Debt have not <lb/>yet heard of him <sic corr="though">tho</sic> I hope a Letter which I gave to a frient <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> of <lb/>his may have r<add resp="editor">[e]</add>achd his hands however indiscreet the Car<lb/>riage of these Gentlemen may Appear yet it is very Evident <lb/>that as they are Merchants and traders here both of Substance <lb/>and reputation the Said Thacker was Considerably Indebted <lb/>to them on which Account he was flying the province where<lb/>fore they persued him and that when he <sic corr="delivered">deliverd</sic> them his <lb/>money he Seemd <sic corr="Satisfied">Satisfyd</sic> on their promise he should not go <lb/>to <sic corr="Gaol">Goal</sic> it likewise appears on their Carrying him before Colonel <lb/>Addison a Provincial Justice Since deceased to <sic corr="Acknowledge">Acknoledge </sic><lb/>a Deed made to the Said Hammond by the Said Thacke he the <abbr expan="Said">Sd.</abbr> <lb/>Thacker did it very freely without ever declaring any <lb/>Violence to have bin <sic corr="Offered">Offerd</sic> to him by the Said Gentlemen <lb/><sic corr="though">tho</sic> being in a Majestrates house he might <sic corr="Safely">Safly</sic> have done <lb/>it these and many Other Circumstances will Appear on 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
Tryal in <sic corr="Extenuation">Extinuation</sic> of the Crime imputed to them which ca<add resp="editor">[n]</add> <lb/>never carry the face of felonius intent to <sic corr="rob">robb</sic> it was but an <lb/>hasty and indiscreet demanding of their own however let <lb/>Justice decide that in due course of Law and I hope what <lb/>has bin here done Conducive to it will Show that <sic corr="we">wee</sic> desire <lb/>not <add resp="editor">[to]</add> Obstruct it,</p>

<p>I have nothing more to offer at Present but the Sincere <lb/>tender of my respects and Services to your Self and Colony <lb/>and I hope there will ever be that freindly Correspondence <lb/>between the two <abbr expan="Governmets">Governmts.</abbr> as becomes Persons so nearly <abbr expan="Allied">All'd</abbr> <lb/>in nationel types of Affinity as the Inhabitants of the two <lb/>Provinces are to Each other I must also <sic corr="beg">begg</sic> that whenever <lb/>this or any thing Else Shall bring me to your remembrence <lb/>You will be so good as to consider me in the Quality of </p>

<closer>Honble Sir <lb/>Yor. most Obedient <lb/>&amp; most humble Servt. <lb/>to Command <lb/>Bentt: Leond: Calvert<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>To <lb/>the Honble: Robert Carter Esqr. <lb/>President of his Majtys Council in <lb/>Virginia and Commander in <sic corr="chief">cheif</sic> <lb/>of the Same Colony
<lb/>Present</seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. Carter probably had the letter copied for his reference because it was an official one that would have to be placed among the records at the capital in Williamsburg. The address has been copied from the foot of the letter into the address line at the head of the letter.</note>

<note>See also Carter's letters of 1727 June 21 to John Randolph and William Robertson, and of 1727 June 24 to the governor of Maryland concerning the case.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Benedict Leonard Calvert (1700-1732) was governor, 1727-1731, under the "Restored Proprietary Government" of Maryland. ("Governors under Restored Proprietary Government, 1715-1776." Archives of Maryland Historical List Governors of Maryland, 1715-1776. Posted on the web by the Maryland State Archives at http://www.mdarchives.state.md.us/msa/speccol/sc2600/sc2685/html/govintro.html.) </note>

<note id="n2">[2] Charles Calvert (1699-1751), fifth Lord Baltimore, the colony's fourth proprietor, served as govenor 1732-1733. ("Calvert Family Tree." Posted by the Maryland Office of the Secretary of State. http://www.mdkidspage.org/calvertfam.html)</note>







</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>