<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27l07a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Colonel Thomas Lee, December 7, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 12 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27l07a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Colonel Thomas Lee, December 7, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>2 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-12-07</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27l07aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>2 p.</extent>
<date value="1727-12-07"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27l07a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Colonel Thomas Lee, December 7, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Colonel Thomas Lee, December 7, 1727, concerning land desired by Lee, and expressing his low opinion of surveyor John Savage.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Colonel <note target="n1">Thomas Lee,</note> December 7, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-12-07">Decr: 7. 1727</date><lb/>
Collo: Lee<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>I will allow You are better acquainted than I am with<lb/> the geography of the <sic corr="forest">forrest</sic> lands of <abbr expan="Stafford">Staffd</abbr> but I have another view in desiring <lb/>an interest in a landing place that Affords a good Carriage to it <lb/>near the falls of the river than you think <del>fit</del> of <note n="GT"><abbr expan="George">G.</abbr> <sic corr="Turberville">Tubervile</sic></note> is more cha<lb/><sic corr="grined">green'd</sic> at <sic corr="your">yr</sic> late Entry there than my self had his father not kept 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
his letter too long he would have been before <sic corr="you">yo:</sic> in that Entry when <sic corr="you">yo:</sic> <lb/>are pleased to pursue the inclinations of service to me with suitable <lb/>performances I shall always account myself indebted to <sic corr="endeavor">endeavour</sic> <lb/>proper retaliations</p>

<p>If <sic corr="your">yr</sic> judgement &amp; mine happens to differ in the <lb/>rules of my proceeding I can't help that my own reason must be my <lb/>Dictator &amp; not another mans when <sic corr="you">yo:</sic> fall into Exclamations <abbr expan="against">agt:</abbr> <lb/><note target="n2">Savage</note> I am very forward to <sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> them having found him out in so <lb/>many of his tricks indeed no mortal that I hear of with whom he <lb/>hath been concerned with give him a good word &amp; yet from an Epis-<lb/>tle came to my hands <del>[illegible]</del> <add place="supralinear">just now</add> if <sic corr="you">yo:</sic> would allow him to be the painter of <lb/>his own Character <sic corr="you">yo:</sic> must take him to be a Saint &amp; that all the <sic corr="Stories">Storys</sic> <lb/>which are reported of him are the Effects of malice <sic corr="falsehood,">falshood,</sic> &amp; injustice; bidding <lb/><sic corr="defiance">defyance</sic> to <del>[illegible]</del> <add place="supralinear">all</add> his <sic corr="enemies">enemys</sic> to prove the least of them before an im=<lb/>partial judicature I do not remember to have said I should have no re=<lb/>gard to Hoops warrant which is this day <abbr expan="returned">return'd</abbr> to me by Savage with <lb/>the plat for three hundred ninety five acres <del>[illegible]</del> <add place="supralinear">in order to have a deed</add> <lb/>the Enclosed paper will let <sic corr="you">yo:</sic> into the Affair more particularly</p>

<p>You Urge to have the surplus above the warrant <lb/>and in such place as will best answer to <sic corr="your">yr.</sic> <sic corr="convenience">conveniancy</sic> Certainly <lb/>upon reflection <sic corr="you">yo:</sic> will think this by no means to be right if the quantity <lb/>expressed in the warrant Were nicely to be kept to the <abbr expan="proprietors">proprs:</abbr> ought to turn out <lb/>the land in such place as they should <sic corr="choose">chuse</sic> &amp; not where the pretending pers<lb/>on desires it this is the strictest equity but <sic corr="you">yo:</sic> know we never <sic corr="tie">tye</sic> men down <lb/>exactly to the quantity of their warrants sometimes the <sic corr="surveyor">surveyr</sic> gives <lb/>them more sometimes less</p>

<p>Upon the whole if <sic corr="you">yo:</sic> can propose away how I may <lb/>with justice do <sic corr="you">yo:</sic> service in stopping this Deed to Hoops Assignees I <lb/>shall be <sic corr="inclined">enclinable</sic> to come into it</p>

<p>Savage hath often sent me warrants with <lb/>Assignments on the backsides &amp; seldom fails to be a witness somet=<lb/>imes warrants that have issued in other mens names he hath <lb/>assigned to himself in this practice I have often suspected he hath <lb/>imposed Upon me I am </p>

<closer>Sir Yor most humble servt.</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. </note>

<note>The name of Carter's home, "Corotoman," the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Thomas Lee (1690-1750) was the son of Richard Lee II, and nephew of Edmund Jenings under whom he had served as the assistant Virginia agent of the Northern Neck proprietors. He would build "Stratford," and succeed Carter on the Council. (<cit><bibl>Burton J. Hendrick. <title>The Lees of Virginia: Biography of a Family.</title> [Boston: Little Brown, 1935]. pp. 48, 51, etc.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2]  John Savage was a surveyor, later (1734) to be employed by Lord Fairfax in his  attempt to establish the boundaries of the proprietary. (<bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 619.</bibl>)</note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>