<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C27l22a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Colonel Mann Page, December 22, 1727</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 13 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C27l22a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Colonel Mann Page, December 22, 1727</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>3 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1727-12-22</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C27l22aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1727-12-22"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C27l22a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Colonel Mann Page, December 22, 1727</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to his son-in-law Colonel Mann Page, December 22, 1727, thanking him for his long letter the writing of which must have tired Page who may wish to use a clerk as he does. He was surprised that the English opinions concerning the rights of the proprietors of the Northern Neck to certian fees had yielded rights that Carter had never considered part of the grant. His son Charles has visited Page's settlement and found that it was ready for occupancy. Charles had planned to cross the Shenandoah but the waters were too high. He comments on the governor's position concerning the vacant auditor's place, the bad news concerning his grandson, Lewis Burwell, and that he has directed Micajah Perry to send Burwell to Cambridge in the spring. He concludes that he is sending his daughter all the chocolate nuts he can spare, and hopes that she will have a successful childbirth.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Colonel <note n="MP1">Mann Page,</note> December 22, 1727</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place"><add resp="editor">[Corotoman, Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1727-12-22">Decemr 22d: 1727</date><lb/>
Collo Page<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Honble: Sir</salute>

</opener>



<p>I am <sic corr="thankfu;">thank full</sic> to you for your news and <lb/><sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> it tired you <sic corr="heartily">hartily</sic> <add place="supralinear">to write so much</add> your refuge must be to do as I am <sic corr="forced">forct</sic> <lb/>to write by another hand</p>

<p>I shall make no reflections on the proceed<lb/>ings of the Council only that they <add place="supralinear">were</add> very extraordinary and none knows <lb/>how far the consequence will sting but <add place="supralinear">as</add> the hands of Governours are <lb/>tyed up by their instructions from receiving presents from the Country 

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>
its probable the Councils will too in time</p>

<p>My suspicious humor made me expect <lb/>greater alterations in the Attorney generals Opinion than I find <lb/>the fines by Act of Assembly I never pretended to and the <note target="n1">felo<lb/>deses</note> I had his Opinion before were not Granted but by ex<lb/>press words so that the crown <add place="supralinear">have</add> got nothing but <add place="supralinear">what</add> I would readily <lb/>have <note target="n2">yielded</note></p>

<p><note target="n3">Charles</note> was at Your settlement both <lb/>he and <note n="RJ">Jones</note> who was with me last week agree that your Over<lb/>seers house &amp; quarter would both be finished by last Saturd<lb/>ay so that you may plant Your people there as soon as <lb/>you think fit <del>Charles had</del> for the Other buildings that <lb/>w<del>ould</del><add place="supralinear">ill </add>be necessary for the plan: I think I shall be able to <lb/>do <del>them</del> for you before they will be wanted</p>

<p>Charles had the courage to see <sic corr="Shenan">chenan</sic><lb/>doah but the waters were too high for him to pass it to the <lb/>other side where the greatest body of good land <sic corr="lies">lyes</sic> he is very <lb/>particular in the relation of his travels but that must be <lb/>the <del>work</del> <add place="supralinear">entertainment</add> of Another time Charles will best divert you with <lb/>it himself</p>

<p>Certainly the <abbr expan="Governor">Govr:</abbr> hath taken the most<lb/>prudent way in respect to the auditors place to disabli=<lb/>ge none I am Sorry the Assembly is to be held in the winter se=<lb/>ason The very bad story you tell me of <note target="n4">Lewis Burwell</note> is a very gre<lb/>at Affliction to me If I knew how to help it I have ordered <note n="MP2">Mr. <lb/>Perry</note> by this <sic corr="Liverpool">Leverpool</sic> ship to send him to Cambridge in the <lb/>spring which hath been your advice All along and have pre<lb/>st him with great earnestness to be <sic corr="careful">carefull</sic> in his choice of <lb/>a proper tutor</p>

<p>I have sent <note n="JCP">my Daughter</note> 20 pounds <lb/>of chocolate nuts which is all I can well spare <sic corr="allthough">altho</sic> if <lb/>these will not do before you can recruit I will let you have <lb/>some more <note target="n5">Mrs Wormeley</note> lately had as much from me</p>

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
<p>Pray god Grant my daughter a happy <note target="n6">minuit</note> this <lb/>family salutes you with their proper <sic corr="compliments">complyments</sic> all <lb/><sic corr="join">joyn</sic> in our wishes for a Merry Christmass to you my <lb/>kind love &amp; respects to my Daughter &amp; children I am <lb/>glad to hear they are got well again my eyes continue <lb/>as bad as ever &amp; my Other Maladies persecute me every <lb/>night this cold weather hath kept me in the house that I <lb/>could not ride out these many days I am</p>

<closer><seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/></seg></closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a 19th-century transcript of the letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note>

<note>The name of Carter's home, "Corotoman," the county, and colony have been added for clarity to this unheaded draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] Felodese is the legal term for a suicide.</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Carter writes of the opinions just received in the colony with its attorney general's return from England concerning the rights of the proprietors to certain fees in their lands in the Northern Neck.</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Charles Carter (1707-1764) was Robert Carter's tenth child; his mother was Carter's second wife, Elizabeth (Landon) Willis Carter. Charles would live at "Cleve," King George County, and inherit a number of properties in that area from his father. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 340;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B32">Morton. <title>Robert Robert Carter of Nomini Hall.</title></bibl></cit> Numerous references.)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] Lewis Burwell (1711 or 1712-1756), Carter's grandson by Elizabeth Carter Burwell and her first husband, Nathaniel Burwell (1680-1721) for whom Carter was guardian. He was educated at Eton and Cambridge, and inherited considerable property, living at "Fairfield," Gloucester County. He would be president of the Council in 1750-1751. (<cit><bibl n="B42">Kneebone <hi rend="italics">et al.</hi>,  <title>Dictionary of Virginia Biography.</title>  2:434-5.</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 114.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] Carter probably refers to the widow of John Wormeley.</note>

<note id="n6">[6] The transcription of this word is questionable, and it seems likely Carter dictated a word unfamiliar to the clerk. No other possible word has been discovered, however. Carter may refer to the impending birth of Judith (Carter) Page's last child, a daughter who apparently died soon after her birth in 1728. (<cit><bibl n="B3">Carleton. <title>A Genealogy. . .  of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 252.</bibl></cit>)</note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>