<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C28f01b">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, June 1, and July 9 and 19, 1728</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 15 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C28f01b.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2004</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, June 1, and July 9 and 19, 1728</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>5 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:  Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1728-06-01</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C28f01bT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent> p.</extent>
<date value="1728-06-01"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C28f01b.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to John Pemberton, June 1, and July 9 and 19, 1728</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to Liverpool merchant John Pemberton, June 1, and July 9 and 19, 1728, to cover a bill of lading of his own tobacco, report a bill of exchange, and give orders for payments. In a lengthy post script dated July 1st, Carter discusses some protested bills of exchange, methods of payment for his services in selling slaves, some goods he had attempted to sell for Pemberton, and tobacco he is shipping. In a second post script dated July 19th Carter sends some bills of exchange and deals with further matters relating to the sale of the  slaves on the ship <hi rend="italics">Rose.</hi></p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to <note n="JP">John Pemberton,</note> June 1, and July 9 and 19, 1728</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1728-06-01">June the 1st: 1728</date><lb/>
Mr. John Pemberton<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir&mdash;</salute>

</opener>

<p>This Shall relate to my own affairs. herein <lb/>Send you a bill of Lading for 18 hogsheads of Sweet Scented <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> <lb/>made at my own Plantations on board the <note target="n1"><abbr expan="John">Jno</abbr> &amp; Betty</note> <abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Denton <lb/>I promise my Self it is good but you must be the Judge when it <lb/>comes to your view,</p>

<p>I have already advised you of a bill of Exchange <lb/>I drew upon you for &pound;10 to <note target="n2">Mrs. Young</note> I now desire you to <lb/>pay unto the <abbr expan="Owners">Ownrs:</abbr> of the <name type="ship">John and Betty</name> &pound;16"10"9 the <lb/>ballance of their <add place="supralinear">money</add> Accot. Also to the Freighters of the Ship <name type="ship">rose</name> &pound;18- <lb/><abbr expan="Doctor">Doctr.</abbr> Edgars Debt these Sums to be Carried to my Accot.</p>

<p>It is a little to Early to Send an Invoice <lb/>for <del>Some</del> Goods Shall refer that work to another&mdash;<lb/>Opportunity I am </p>

<closer>Sir, Yor. very humble Servt.
<seg type="postscript"><lb/><lb/>herein I Send you <abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Dentons <lb/>Exchange on your Self for &pound;22"18 <lb/>which I desire Credit for&mdash;<lb/>
per Denton<lb/>
<del>Copy per Brackhill<lb/></del>
per <note target="n3">Price</note></seg>

<seg type="postscript">

<pb n="2"/><lb/><lb/>

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;To be Added to Mr. Pembertons Letter June 1st:<lb/><lb/>
Sir&mdash;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Rappahannock July the 9th: 1728<lb/><lb/>

	&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;to be Copyd&mdash;<lb/><lb/>

	&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Since the Above I <abbr expan="Received">Rec'd</abbr> your Packet by <note target="n4"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt:</abbr> Tarleton</note> <lb/>the protested bills Killbys, Coopers, and Cockburns, are come to hand <lb/>when I Shall get the money will be a Question, The whole amount of <lb/>theirs with their protests amounts to &pound;112:4:10 which I desire you <lb/>to accot: for to the Freighters of the John and Betty and the rose and <lb/>Charge my Accot. with it. You tell me the <abbr expan="Gentlemen">Gent.</abbr> <sic corr="Concerned">Concernd</sic> think it <lb/>hard to Stay so long for their Considering I have 10 <sic corr="per Cent">perCt:</sic> and others 

<pb n="3"/><lb/><lb/>
have but 8 In all the business of this nature that I have transacted <lb/>this hath bin my method and gave no uneasieness if I had thought <lb/>it would now I shall have <sic corr="ordered">orderd</sic> the Payment of the money upon <lb/>your receipt of the protested bills and As to your own Part you will <lb/>allow me to think under the Circumstances of Affairs that are be=<lb/>tween us it amounts to the Same thing<lb/><lb/>

	&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;I have made Enquiry into the methods of <abbr expan="our">or.</abbr> Bristol <lb/>Factors and am <sic corr="informed">informd</sic> their Contracts are to return half the <lb/>produce of the Cargo by the Ship the rest they are allowd a Twelve <lb/>month to pay it in and what bills are protested they have three<lb/>months after the protest to pay them in now whether <add place="supralinear">theirs or mine</add> is the most <lb/>Satisfactory way to you <abbr expan="Gentlemen">Gent.</abbr> <sic corr="Concerned">Concernd</sic> I must Submit to yor. <lb/><abbr expan="Judgement">Judgemt.</abbr> indeed I charge 2 <sic corr="per Cent">perCt:</sic>: more then they do and less I will <lb/>never do Such business for but I flatter my Self that this 2 <sic corr="per Cent">perCt:</sic> hath <lb/>bin no loss to the Owners. You can best tell from yor. own Experi-<lb/>ence whether I am right in this Conjecture or no,<lb/><lb/>

	&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;When I took from <note target="n5">Christian</note> your return goods <lb/>I Expected to put them <sic corr="off">of</sic> in a Lump fee at the prices they were charged <lb/>at and in doing so I thought I Should do you Service but it hath <lb/><sic corr="happened">happend</sic> otherwise they are all unsold Except a little of the Tallow <lb/>and I am afraid I must Sell them for <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> at last,<lb/><lb/>

	&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;I have now <sic corr="Shiped">Shipt</sic> of the <corr resp="editor">[tobacco mark]</corr> 32 hogsheads on board the <lb/><note n="CS"><name type="ship">Carter</name></note> for London which I Shall Consign to you there will be 7 <lb/>or 8 prized hogsheads more got in this year if I can get them into <lb/>Tarleton <del>I Shall have rather</del> <sic corr="believe">beleive</sic> I shall please you better <sic corr="than">then</sic> <lb/>to Send them to any other Port, I Shall Conclude at Present <lb/>
Sir <lb/><lb/>Yor. humble Servt:&mdash;
<lb/><lb/>Trice
<lb/>here is a Small Bill <abbr expan="Daniel">Danl.</abbr> <lb/>Hornbys for 6&pound; on yor. Self
<lb/>Copy per <note target="n6">Hopkins</note>
</seg>



<seg type="postscript">

<pb n="4"/><lb/><lb/>

PS:			&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;July the 19th: 1728<lb/>
		&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Now Send you three bills of Exchange two of them <lb/>on the Accot. of the Ship rose to wit Tom Osborne on <sic corr="Lionel">Lyonel</sic> Lyde for &pound;13 <lb/><note target="n7"><abbr expan="Charles">Ch:</abbr> <sic corr="Grymes">Grimes</sic></note> on your Self for &pound;15"5 the other bill is on my own Accot. <lb/>Tom Osborn on your Self for &pound;12"-"- <note n="GE"><abbr expan="Major">Majr.</abbr> Eskridges</note> debt Still unpad <lb/>for &pound;19 which I desire you to Accot. for to the <abbr expan="Freighters">Frs.</abbr> of the rose &amp; place to my Accot. <lb/><lb/>

<pb n="5"/><lb/><lb/>
Part of Mr. Pembertons Letter. and thus reckon the money Accot. of that Concern <lb/>will be pretty near ballanced, when the <abbr expan="receiver">recr.</abbr> is paid for the <abbr expan="Tobacco">Tobbo:</abbr> that are yet <lb/>due to that Concern and Some other Small <lb/>Charges
<lb/>Copy per Carter



</seg>
</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Robert Carter Letter Book, 1727 April 13-1728 July 23, Carter Family Papers, Virginia Historical Society, Richmond. The first post script (of 1727 July 9) is from Robert Carter letter book, 1727 May-1728 July, Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity to the  heading on the draft.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] The <hi rend="italics">John &amp; Betty</hi> was a Liverpool ship owned by merchant John Pemberton; she often carryied slaves into the colony. In 1726 the captain was John Gale, and in the next year, she was commanded by a Captain William Denton. The ship would be lost in 1729. (<cit><bibl n="B12">Wright. <title>Letters of Robert Carter. . . .</title> p. 18, n. 23</bibl></cit>; Carter to Pemberton, 1730 April 15; and Carter to William Dawkins, June 28, July 26, and August 22, 1727, for Denton's first name.)</note>

<note id="n2">[2] Mrs. Elizabeth Young was Carter's housekeeper. He had agreed  with her for one year's service in 1724 but found her satisfactory for a longer term. She went to England in May 1728. (Diary 1727 June 2, and Carter to William Dawkins, June 28, July 26, and August 22, 1727, for her first name. Carter to Pemberton 1728 May 8, for her sailing to England.)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] The 140 ton <hi rend="italics">Welcome</hi> was owned by London merchant James Bradley to whom Carter would write about her on 1727 May 17.  John Trice (Frice) was her captain, 1723-1728. (<cit><bibl>Survey Report 6801 summarizing Adm 68/195, 154r, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n4">[4] This may have been James Tarleton who in 1731 cammanded the <hi rend="italics">The Loyalty</hi>. Several vessels with this name sailed to Virginia. One commanded by Francis Wallis cleared from Poole for Virginia in 1726. Captain Loxom commanded  a vessel of this name in 1730.. (Survey Report 9727, Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. See Carter's letters to John Pemberton 1730 April 15 and 1731 August 4.)</note>

<note id="n5">[5] James Christian was captain of the <hi rend="italics">Rose,</hi> a vessel owned by merchant John Pemberton of Liverpool. (See Carter to Pemberton, 1730 April 15.) </note>


<note id="n6">[6] Captain James Hopkins commanded the <hi rend="italics">Mary</hi> in 1727-1728. He was then working for London merchant Robert Cary. He is mentioned in Carter's diary. (<cit><bibl>Adm. 68/194, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n7">[7] Charles Grymes (c. 1692-1743) was the son of John Grymes of Middlesex County, but lived at "Morratico," Richmond County where he was sheriff, burgess, etc. (<cit><bibl>"The Grymes Family." <title>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography</title>. 28[1920]: 90-96, 187-94, 283-85, 374-75.</bibl></cit> and <bibl n="B31">Ryland. <title>Richmond County Virginia. . . . </title> pp. 500, 504, 514.</bibl></note>




</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>