<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?xml-stylesheet href="carter.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM 'teixlite.dtd'[
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">   
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>  

<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "ISOlat1.pen"> %ISOlat1;  
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "ISOlat2.pen"> %ISOlat2;  
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "ISOnum.pen"> %ISOnum;  
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "ISOpub.pen"> %ISOpub;  
<!ENTITY % ISOtech SYSTEM "ISOtech.pen"> %ISOtech; ]>
<TEI.2 id="C32b28a">


<teiHeader type="aacr2">
             
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
     <title type="245">Letter from Robert Carter to Edward Athawes, February 28, 1732</title>
   <title type="gmd">[electronic resource]</title>
     <author>Carter, Robert</author>
   <respStmt>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
     <name id="editor">Edmund Berkeley, Jr.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup</resp>
     <name>Edmund Berkeley, Jr. and the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<extent>ca. 9 kilobytes </extent>

<publicationStmt>
     <publisher>University of Virginia Library.</publisher>
     <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
     <idno type="ETC">C32b28a.xml</idno>
     <availability>
     <p>Publicly accessible</p>
     <p n="public">URL: http://carter.lib.virginia.edu/</p>
         </availability>
     <date>2006</date>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
     <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
     <title>Letter from Robert Carter to Edward Athawes, February 28, 1732</title>
     <author>Robert Carter</author>
</titleStmt>
    <extent>1 p.</extent>
<publicationStmt>
     <date></date>
   <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Letter book, 1731 July 9-1732 July 13 , Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
     <projectDesc>
     <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
     </projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
     <p>Some keywords in the header are a local electronic Text Center scheme to aid in  establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>

<classDecl>
     <taxonomy id="LCSH"><bibl><title>Library of Congress Subject Headings</title></bibl></taxonomy>
</classDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
     <creation><date>1732-02-28</date></creation>
     <langUsage><language id="eng"></language></langUsage>
     <textClass>
     <keywords><term>non-fiction</term><term>prose</term></keywords>
     <keywords scheme="LCSH"><term type="Field650">LCSH</term></keywords>
     </textClass>
</profileDesc>

</teiHeader>

<text id="C32b28aT">

<front>
<div1 type="summary" n="1">
<head>
<bibl>
<abbr>AL</abbr>
<extent>1 p.</extent>
<date value="1732-02-28"></date>
<idno rend="suppress">C32b28a.xml</idno>
<title>Letter from Robert Carter to Edward Athawes, February 28, 1732</title>
</bibl>
</head>
<p>Robert Carter writes to London merchant Edward Athawes, February 28, 1732, on behalf of the Frying Pan copper mining company to report the arrival of a ship carrying  goods for the company, and that the miners from Bristol, to whom Lord Fairfax had given a lease, are having no better luck in finding good ore than the company's miners. He responds to criticism about lack of candor in the company's affairs by pointing out that Micajah Perry has been closest to Lord Fairfax, and the company has accordingly used his offices. He reminds Athawes of two shipments of copper ore.</p>
</div1>                 
</front>



<body>
<div1 type="letter" n="1">
<head>Letter from Robert Carter to Edward Athawes, February 28, 1732</head>
<opener>
<dateline>
<pb n="1"/>
<name type="place">Rappahannock, <add resp="editor">[Lancaster County, Virginia]</add></name><lb/>
<date value="1732-02-28">Feb: 28. 1731/2</date><lb/>
Mr. Edward Athawes<lb/>
</dateline>
<salute>Sir</salute>

</opener>



<p>his accompanys a <name type="city"><sic corr="Liverpool">Leverpool</sic></name> Ship and is the<lb/>
first Opportunity has offered from this place this Season <note target="n1"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr>Malbon</note><lb/>
Met with a long passage from <sic corr="Maderia">Maderas</sic> <abbr expan="Arrived">Arriv'd</abbr> here but ten days agoe<lb/>
your goods to the <note target="n2">Frying Pan Company</note> are not yet brought on <sic corr="shore">shoar</sic> I have<lb/>
many letters from you to the Company none of them afford us much comfo=<lb/>
=rt and what is the worst of all our hopes of Success are quite blown up we<lb/>
have been able to meet with no vein of Ore worth raising since last summer<lb/>
and begin to be very near the  erms of dispair however we still keep pushi=<lb/>
=ing <add resp="editor"> [<hi rend="italics">sic</hi>]</add> on and must continue making further <sic corr="searches">serches</sic> till our<lb/>
miners times expire</p>

<p>The <note target="n3">Bristol mens</note> Undertaking <sic corr="has">hath</sic> been much<lb/>
at the same pass <abbr expan="until">'till</abbr> very lately I met with a story the other day how true<lb/>
I know not that they had just fallen upon a large vein of very rich Ore  this<lb/>
wants confirmation. If <sic corr="we">wee</sic> meet with any good news no Opportunity<lb/>
shall slip of Communicating it to you</p>

<p>In your letter of the 20th of <abbr expan="October">Octobr.</abbr> you are <sic corr="pleased">pleasd</sic><lb/>
to complain you think you have not been treated with so much Candour<lb/>
as you ought to have expected in this Affair I must assure you you have<lb/>
no foundation for this Charge <note n="MP2">Aldderman Perry</note> <sic corr="has">hath</sic> a great deal of<lb/>
intimacy with <note n="TF">my Lord</note> and wee took him to be the most proper person<lb/>
to treat with him about a <sic corr="lease">leas</sic> for our mine in Case it Succeeded and <add place="supralinear">he</add> <sic corr="has">hath</sic><lb/>
been the only person <add place="supralinear">that</add> <sic corr="has">hath</sic> negotiated my affairs with his Lordship and<lb/>
I must own <sic corr="has">hath</sic> always been very Zealous in doing me all friendly servi <lb/>
ces and we could pitch upon no person in our opinion so proper to bring<lb/>
about this matter but it was not without giving him the liberty to make<lb/>
use of You in carrying it on as he should find Occasion and we were not<lb/>
wanting in expressing how much You had exerted Your self in serving<lb/>
us in this adventure</p>

<p>We sent you 16 barrels of rich ore as we thought<lb/>
in Your <sic corr="brig">brigg</sic> <note target="n4"><abbr expan="Captain">Capt.</abbr> Becher</note> our bill of Loading bears date the 13th of <abbr expan="September">Sepr.</abbr><lb/>
we have no accot Yet of his Arrival We also sent you 11 Barrels<lb/>
by <abbr expan="Captain">Cap.</abbr> Reid in the <note target="n5"><name type="ship">Thistle</name></note> that bill of Loading dated <abbr expan="November">Novembr</abbr> 14. <lb/>
of this we have no reason to expect an Accot yet I am for self &amp; <abbr expan="Company">Compa</abbr><lb/>
</p>

<closer>Sir  <abbr expan="Your">Yr</abbr> most humble Servt.&mdash;</closer>


</div1>

</body>



<back>

<div1 type="back matter">
<head>NOTES</head>

<note><hi rend="italics"><hi rend="bold">Source copy consulted:</hi></hi> Letter book, 1731 July 9-1732 July 13 , Robert Carter Papers (acc. no. 3807), Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia. There is a nineteenth-century copy of this letter in the Minor-Blackford Papers, James Monroe Law Office and Museum, Fredericksburg, Virginia.</note>

<note>Robert Carter generally used a return address of "Rappahannock" for the river on which he lived rather than "Corotoman," the name of his home, on his correspondence, especially to merchants abroad. The county and colony have been added for clarity.</note>

<note id="n1">[1] The <hi rend="italics">Rebecca </hi> was probably a London ship; she was of 300 tons, had a crew of 11, and was commanded by Samuel Malbon in 1731-32. (<cit><bibl>Adm. 65/195, found in the microfilms of the Virginia Colonial Records Project, Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia.</bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n2">[2]  In 1728, Carter, his sons Robert and Charles, and his son-in-law Mann Page,  organized a company to mine for copper on a tract of some 27,000 acres that Louis Morton describes as lying "near the present boundary of Fairfax and Loudoun counties." Fairfax Harrison wrote that the tract was "on the  Horsepen of Broad." Today, there is a Frying Pan Park just east of the border of the Dulles Airport reservation, and there are other things with the name in the area. The company was not successful. (<cit><bibl n="B32">Morton. <title>Robert Robert Carter of Nomini Hall.</title> pp. 18-19;</bibl></cit> and <cit><bibl n="B4">Harrison. <title>Landmarks. . . .</title> p. 342. </bibl></cit>)</note>

<note id="n3">[3] Lord Fairfax had given a lease to miners from Bristol to dig on his land. See Carter's letter to Fairfax, 1730 July 16. </note>

<note id="n4">[4] The clerk probably misunderstood Carter and wrote "Beecher" when "Belcher" was correct. There are several references in letters to Athawes the previous year to Captain Belcher of Athawes' brig <hi rend="italics">Mary.</hi></note>

<note id="n5">[5] The <hi rend="italics">Thistle</hi> was a London ship commanded by a Captain Reid and owned by merchant James Buchanan. (See <cit><bibl>Carter to Edward Athawes, 1731 September 10, and Carter to James Buchanan, 1731 November 19.</bibl></cit>)</note>


</div1>
</back>

</text>

</TEI.2>